hello everyone I'm Tim Hatcher good
morning thanks for coming
so I'm going to talk to you about web
inspector and modern JavaScript but
first I'm going to just talk about
modern JavaScript so what exactly is
modern JavaScript well let's go through
some of the history of JavaScript which
is also known as ECMO script as some of
you may know but it's had a long history
it's been around since the 90s and it
had a lot of momentum back in the 90s
when it was first part of the browser
Wars but it kind of sputtered installed
but javascript is alive and well
nowadays everyone's using it for web
apps to server applications and some of
the standards bodies have been battling
over some of what should be included in
the next version of JavaScript and I'm
happy to say that they finally started
coming together and started releasing
what is known as ECMO script 6 and this
sixth edition brings a lot of cool
things and it's really just JavaScript
and that's how I'm going to refer to it
in in this modern JavaScript world
there's a lot of great things and this
is just some of them there's some
destructuring Maps promises and let's go
over some of these new features that are
also now available on iOS 8 and OS 10
Yosemite so when they're available I
mean you can use them in Safari or your
iOS applications or Mac applications and
not just in web views but also
javascriptcore context so let's talk
over some of these let's first talk
about some math additions javascript has
had a math object pretty much since day
one
but javascript nowadays is super fast
with the modern llvm jit that we have in
iOS 8 and OS 10 year siboney you need
these super fast math functions to do
complex things like WebGL or complex
scientific calculations and most of you
will recognize a lot of things in this
list that you've used in the past for
your your own applications and they're
now available in modern JavaScript so
that's the math editions now let's talk
about maps and sets so what do I mean by
maps and sets well in JavaScript you
might think of this as a map this is
something that you create as a generic
object and it's really just a property
bag you can throw whatever you want on
this object you can set simple strings
and any object can be the value and you
can remove things from that map well
these maps have some limitations there's
string coercion when you're when it
comes to the key everything that is the
key needs to be coerced into a string so
it's not going to give you exactly what
you want if you want to use it for a
property bag that's tracking some node
it won't work well in modern JavaScript
there's now a map object and it does
pretty much the same thing that you
would do with an object it has a little
bit different syntax and API but it's
pretty much all the same the most
powerful thing you can do with the map
object is you can use any value as the
key and a lot of people will use this to
track Dom nodes that they have in the
page adding some additional data on the
side instead of tacking it on to the Dom
node itself so it really allows you to
can compartmentalize data that you're
tracking on the page but there's some
issues with that if you add it to the
map that map is going to hold a hard
reference to it and that's why modern
JavaScript has a weak map and that means
whenever the the the key disappears or
gets garbage collected it's also removed
from the map so in this case I have a
node in my week map and when that node
is removed by doing a remove call or
remove child in that page it will no
longer be in the map and the data that's
associated with it will also get garbage
collected so that's maps and sets and
there's also a set object that I didn't
cover but it's pretty straightforward it
only allows the key to be added to the
set so now let's talk about
destructuring if you got excited about
some of the new features in Swift this
will be right up your alley as far as
JavaScript goes it allows you to return
like multiple objects in in an array in
this case I have an array of 22 numbers
here and traditionally I would have to
collect that in a result object and I
would have to break each piece off from
from that array to use it in a separate
variable that made more sense in the
scope I was using it in but with D
structuring we can break that down into
one line now my function that's
returning to two results that maybe
didn't make sense as array but it was
what I could use to return multiple
things at once I can now save those into
the Alpha and Beta variables right there
in one line and this might look like an
array but when it's on when it's on the
left side we're dealing with the
destructuring syntax and it's not just
for a raise you can destruct your
objects and this is when it becomes more
of a pattern matching so in my example
here say I have a point
and normally I would have to save it off
into a result and break each piece out
if I wanted to use some more concise
syntax for those those variables but now
I have object destructuring in this case
in if I want a different variable name
than the property I can separate them by
colons so X is the value that's coming
out of the object pattern matching and
my X is the variable name in the local
scope in this case but if I want to use
the same name I can omit the second
piece and just use Y and Y is now a
local variable in the scope and you can
do some really fancy things that I don't
have examples for but you can deeply
nesties pattern matches and objects with
arrays and vice versa so you can really
break apart your object if that if
that's what works for your application
so that's d structuring now let's talk
about what we call the spread operator
and this is something that is barred
from many languages but it comes in very
very handy and I love using it and it's
it really takes away some of the common
idioms that you would do before if
you're building up arguments that you
want to call on a function as an array
before you would have to resort to call
or dot apply and pass in those arguments
but now with the spread operator which
is represented by three dots prefixing
an object and in this case it's a it's
an array but secretly the spread
operator works on anything it even works
on maps and it will break it out in key
value sequences so anything that has
support for iteration which I'll talk
about in a bit can be spread and this
will spread it out and call my function
foo with the three arguments that are in
the array
one thing that you could never do in
javascript and you can only do now with
the spread operator is called a
constructor with an array input or a map
input you can now take your parts of a
date and spread them across the date
constructor instead of having to
manually do 012 and break it out like
that the spread operator is also useful
in construction of array literals say
you have something that's pretty
repetitious you want to have a separate
form and a combined form normally you
would have to either repeat the data or
push and pop and and add add everything
concatenate everything together but with
the spread operator you can just spread
those other arrays right out into the
new array that you're constructing so
this is a handy way to do pretty complex
concatenation and you can understand
what it's doing without having to parse
different calls to different array
functions so that's the spread operator
now let's talk about something new a new
for loop that's available in javascript
javascript has traditional loops which
you can iterate over an array by doing
an index and a length and you still
might need to use this if you care about
the index or the length and you're doing
some complex operation based on those
some people have avoided the syntax
because it's it's ugly and they use
something for called for each on an
array that lets you iterate over
individual items and you handily get the
item right there that you can work with
but this creates a closure it does a lot
of complex things that you might not
want to deal with overhead wise well
with the the new for loop
it's in modern JavaScript this is all
you have to write to iterate over an
array and this will iterate over every
item in the array if you break early
it'll stop but it starts at the the
first item but it's not just for raise
say you have a set you can iterate over
that set and if you have a map you can
iterate over the key and value very
similar to what you can do and Swift so
now you have the key and value right
there to process both at the same time
instead of doing extra lines of code
using the for in loop which is available
in JavaScript now you can do it right
here with four of and for of is the only
way to iterate over the keys and values
in maps for n will not do what you
expect and for reasons I'm not going to
go into but maybe you want to iterate
over a week map that's not supported for
reasons that involve the garbage
collection you cannot iterate over the
keys and values of a week map and this
is part of the spec so that's four of
loops now one of the new things in
modern JavaScript that I'm really
excited about is promises and it solves
a long-standing problem of JavaScript
now that javascript is moving more and
more asynchronous everything's
asynchronous you you don't want to be
blocking your application and say you
have a function that you've written that
loads of URL maybe it does an xhr behind
the scenes for you to wrap up all the
different browser and compatibilities
that are out there so this will load a
URL and that's all what I'll do you
can't get the data to get the data you
might be inclined to do a return result
that gives you the data that that was
loaded but this this is synchronous you
can't get away with this in a in a
shipping product without blocking your
user interface so you have to resort to
a callback function and JavaScript makes
this really easy I do this every day
when javascript pass in a callback
function and it works and it's very
usable and it's very handy but when it
gets deeply nested and you're passing in
multiple information and it just gets
confusing and hard to follow you have
all these load calls in this case what
which one is handling which information
well this is what promises solve with
promises you can write something like
this where the first load returns a
promise and immediately on returning
that promise I can call the then
function and that's pretty much the only
API you need to be concerned about with
promises and you can pass a call back to
that Venn function which will get called
when that promise is fulfilled and that
callback can return another promise and
this is where it's magical you can chain
keep chaining along that so these
callbacks are in line here just for
clarity for you but they might be they
might be named functions that you have
somewhere else and it makes it very
clear that this is the order of
operations so that's promises and taking
it to the next level you can then use
another API a global API promised at all
and what this does is you can pass in an
array of promises and it will return a
new promise and that new promise that it
returns is dependent on all of those
promises finishing if any of them error
out your then object can get past a
callback that gets called for errors but
in this case done will get called when
only all of those promises succeed
or fulfilled but maybe you only care
about the first one you're loading a
bunch of images and once you got one
image you're ready to go that's where
promise that race comes in it will call
your call back when the first one of
those promises is fulfilled so that's a
quick glance of promises so that pretty
much wraps it up with modern JavaScript
at least the parts that we've already
implemented and decided we're ready for
consumption there's a lot that's being
done in ECMO script 6 that is not ready
and it's going to be coming down the
pipeline but these pieces we feel you're
ready to use in your application in
browsers that support them so now let's
talk about the web inspector so if
you're not familiar with the web
inspector this is what it looks like and
we've had this UI for a while but we've
done a lot we've fixed a lot of bugs
we've added a lot of features but the
main thing we've done this year is made
the web inspector available in more
places we've listened to your feedback
and you want to be able to inspect your
map Mac application you want to be able
to inspect your javascriptcore context
and that's exactly what you can do with
iOS 8 and OS 10 Yosemite so with Safari
you've been able to inspect your iOS
apps and iOS safari by tethering up to
your computer but now you can inspect
your Mac application and right there
from Safari see a list of your Mac
applications so what's that look like
but first like I said you want to
inspect your JavaScript court context
but web inspector is all about the web
and it's only been able to work with
WebKit up until this point but now web
inspector can
connect to your JavaScript core based
applications so even if you're not using
a web view but you're using javascript
core for some logic in your game you can
now de bug that JavaScript right in the
web inspector and it's really great so
let's let's show you what it looks like
so Mac App inspection like I said will
show up right next to your iOS devices
in the development you in this case I
have two mac apps and the second one
here j/s pong is a JavaScript corps app
the first one is a webview but they're
right there side by side their
first-class citizens and like I said you
can also still connect to your iOS
applications in iOS Safari from the same
development you but for Mac App
inspection we require you to add an
entitlement to your app we you don't
want anyone else debugging your
JavaScript context or stealing your
JavaScript code from your Mac
application that you've worked so hard
on so we require you to have this
entitlement on your applications that
you're developing locally and it's very
simple to do and I'll give you a demo of
it here in a little bit but what about
javascriptcore inspection what's that
look like well it looks just like the
web inspector this is the same web
inspector that you saw a little bit ago
the other one was for the webview this
one's for javascriptcore context there's
a couple buttons that are missing that
don't apply to JavaScript for context
like styles in the DOM and things like
that but for the most part it's
everything you need to debug your
JavaScript core application and you have
the full console you can do a ripple
evaluate JavaScript or see console logs
console dot log is now available in your
JavaScript per application so if you
have your own log function you can now
abandon it and start using console dot
log and get all the great benefits of
the web inspectors log functions
but if you don't do anything the
consul's pretty much all you'll have
available and i'll tell you why we don't
know what you're evaluating in your
JavaScript court context if you're
evaluating large scripts those are
something you probably want to debug but
you could be evaluating something every
200 milliseconds and that would quickly
pollute the sidebar here so you any
script that you want to debug in the web
inspector we will need you to supply a
URL or just a plain name for that script
and we've given you a couple new AP is
for this there has always been the
evaluate script functions we now have a
new objective c one that takes a source
URL and this URL can be a file URL it
can be any URL that the web instructor
really doesn't take it take it other
than to get the name at this point but
if it's a file URL it'll have a little
bit extra benefits and i'll talk to you
about that in a little bit but jas
evaluate script has always supported the
source URL but a lot of people just pass
the null to it so if you're using the
old capi make sure to start passing a
source URL for things that you want to
debug that way they will show up in the
web inspector and that's for scripts but
what about your context identifying a
context is pretty difficult with
JavaScript we don't know what it is the
by default it'll just say je s context
in the development you but if you have
multiple contacts you don't want to see
a list that says j/s contacts j has
contacts JS context you want to identify
those and as the developer you should
know what you're using that context for
and we provide these new AP is that lie
you to name your context and the name is
only used for debugging it'll only show
up in safaris development you so let's
just give a demo of this so I have a
sample application that we released a
while ago at a previous WWDC jazz pong
and it's a simple pong game but I have
some things I need to do to it to make
it work with jas context inspection
the first thing I need to do is make
sure the entitlement is there and if
you're in the App Store you probably
already have an entitlements file in
this case I already have an appt sandbox
and that will give me an entitlement and
I have it right here in the sidebar j/s
pong entitlements so let's go in and add
the entitlement that we need and I said
it was calm dot Apple that security
judge gets task Wow and it's a boolean
and we'll go ahead and say yes so that's
all I need to do to allow jazz context
inspection in my application and i'll go
ahead and save that and i'll go ahead
and build and run it and it's a very
simple pong game the AI is controlled by
a javascript that you can modify here in
the app i'm not going to talk about that
but now i can go to safari and in the
development you i will see mac pro and i
will see j/s pong and my j/s context and
I didn't name the context yet so it's
getting the default name and i'll go
ahead and inspect that and you'll see
the resources are empty I'm not seeing
that art that AI scripts that i've
loaded but I'm if I want to debug that
I'll need to give that a name but at
this point I have access to the console
if you don't do anything you can do
evaluations here in the console you can
get access to any Global's that you
might have available in your context and
you will see exceptions and logs and
errors and in this case we have an
example exception and this will give you
a back trace not just of your JavaScript
but of your native code so you can see
exactly where that function or script
was evaluated all the way to your native
code so you can trace it back to the
exists the origin
so let's go back into Xcode and name
some of these so it's pretty simple I'll
just comment this out this is this will
name my contacts pong context I only
have one context but if I had multiple
ones it would be imperative for me to
name them and when I'm evaluating the AI
script all I have to do is construct a
URL in this case I'm just making a URL
with a string and it really doesn't have
a location and i'll just use the new
with source URL method and pass in that
URL now let's build and run and see what
happens in the web inspector will go
ahead and reconnect to the pong game and
in the resource sidebar we now have that
AI script and in the in the app we
didn't syntax highlight it but the web
inspector knows exactly how to syntax
highlight JavaScript so we can set
breakpoints right here and since the
script is called every iteration of the
movement it should break right away and
now I'm in the debugger I have access to
the call stack there's nothing other
than this function being called but if
there was a deeply nested call stack you
would see it right there in the sidebar
and I can also bring open the scope
chain and we can just like you would any
JavaScript context you can now inspect
the objects that you're getting passed
around or your global scope in this case
and we can do what any debugger does and
step through and do anything you would
do in a normal debugger in addition to
hovering over variables to see their
current value or evaluate things in this
current scope in the console so in this
case let's try modifying the ball here
maybe we want to to modify the rules
upon here and make something really easy
to hit so I've gone ahead and modified
that and I have a update function here
that will redraw my my scene and you can
see the ball increased in size as I met
after I made that change and this is
working with Objective C bridged objects
the ball object here is a bridge
objective-c object that you can use as
you would a normal JavaScript object so
that's j/s context inspection and we'll
go ahead and play it and the ball stays
the same size and keeps on going so
again any web view any JavaScript
context that you have in your
application can be debugged now as long
as you have the right entitlement and
then this also applies for iOS so only
builds that you build and run onto your
device or into the iOS simulator will be
inspected all any app from the App Store
will not be allowed to be inspected by
anyone else so that's all you need and
again name your contacts and name your
scripts so you can easily identify them
when you're debugging so now let's talk
about something that we've had in the
web instructor for a while the timeline
and something new this year is the
source code timeline so what do I mean
by that what sorts of problems does it
solve so source code timelines help you
answer this question what happened when
i clicked on something on the page maybe
it's a new project that you're working
on maybe it's something you wrote years
ago and you don't remember how it worked
and you want to find that line of code
that handles this click so you can fix a
bug or so you can just modify it for
some new behavior that you're your
client is asking you to add so when this
click happens there's a lot of stuff
that's probably going on but you really
only care about code that you wrote
maybe you have some analytics code or a
lot of other code that it might be hard
to decipher or
see the inner liner interleaved
functions and event calls and all these
things that happen in a big modern web
application so when I click on that you
start wondering what okay what script is
handling this this button and it turns
out it's this one but with the new web
inspector we can dig deeper in this
script I can now see a timeline
representation of what the script is
doing so I can see over time where the
mouse events are coming in where the
clicks events where the timer was added
where the timers are firing where I
might be doing forced layout which is a
pretty evil thing to do in a modern web
and web app so what's it look like in
the web inspector well here's the new
web inspector timeline and you can see
in the sidebar here we have all of our
scripts and resources from the page
broken out in their hierarchy of how
they're included by you the developer in
the page and you can expand each script
to see what that script is doing and
where the line of code was and in this
case you'll see a whole timeline where
things are happening repeatedly you'll
start seeing patterns and allow you to
identify problem areas if something's
firing too much too little not at all if
you don't see it in the list and if you
want to dig deeper into the code all you
have to do is click right there on the
sidebar and it'll take you right to that
location and you can mouse up and down
through this sidebar and have your code
on one side and your timeline data in
the sidebar so you can get a good
overview of what this script is doing
really quick so that's the source code
timelines and I'll give you a demo here
in a little minute so something else
that's new in the web instructor is
breakpoint probes so
you might have some information that you
want to know when you when that mouse is
clicked or when your mouse is moving and
those things are kind of hard to debug
in the debugger you often have to resort
to printf debugging because you don't
want to constantly be switching context
between your app and the page and the
web inspector so you often resort to
printf debugging in you're cluttering up
your console with thousands of lines and
it's hard to decipher especially if
you're debugging multiple areas that are
not related and you don't care if
they're in the about the interleaved
data so that's this is where breakpoint
probes come isn't it lets you see these
properties that you might care about
without having to break out into the web
inspector so let's just go ahead and
give a demo of this so let's go to
Safari here and I have a simple stack
the block game that I want to too it's
been a while since this was written so I
want to see what's going on let's let's
go ahead and use the timeline panel for
this I'll go ahead and bring up the web
inspector in the development you show
web inspector and we'll go to the
timeline panel and by default the
timelines empty it it's not recording
all the time and it only automatically
records when you reload the page or when
you press the record button up here in
the corner and this can record any
length of time that you would like to
record but when you when I reload the
page it'll only record a little bit so
I'm just going to go ahead and start
recording here and see what this page is
doing as I interact with this game and
you'll see the events and all the the
work that the engine is doing in
response to these events start filling
up on the timeline and I'll go ahead and
stop this and my application has three
scripts but the logic is all in blocks
jas all the other stuff is stuff I
didn't even write I don't even know
what's going on there so I can
nor those but they're doing some work
and normally that would that would
clutter up my UI but their collapse here
so they're not taking up any space i'll
go ahead and expand the script that I
care about here and I can see that
timers are firing pretty pretty at a
pretty good clip as I'm interacting with
the page and there's key key events that
are firing every time I press a key some
of the other features of the timeline
here we can now soom and scale the the
overview panel so if you want to dig in
to see where things are happening across
domains in this case we have three
timelines the network requests layout
and rendering and JavaScript and all
three play a key role in the performance
of your page so if you see anything
interesting happening in a specific time
range you can zoom in on it make it make
a selection and that information will
show up below in the timeline and you
can also drag this around to scroll and
scrub through your time as things are
happening on the on the page so in this
case let me reload and I'll show you the
networks and in this case it's a local
file but we now have network load
information and you see those on the
network timeline and you'll notice that
the timeline just automatically stopped
recording there it records up to a
certain amount of time unless you
manually hit the record button again to
record more information so let's look
into the network timeline here and we
can see all of the network details that
you might be familiar with in the
previous network timeline they're all
there and you can sort sort these
columns by whatever information you find
most interesting if you're looking for a
large script you can sort by transfer
size and see the biggest script show up
right there let's go back to start time
you can also do click on the other
timelines and get detailed tab linear
data of what was happening in
time range and again this is all time
range based so you can see as these
layout and rendering events filter out
they disappear from the the display
below JavaScript and events is a special
view and if you're looking for the old
profile data this is where it's moved to
so as you're recording timeline we will
now capture profiles of all those entry
points into your JavaScript so whenever
script is evaluated you can expand these
to see all of the functions that were
called in your script and how much time
each individual function took to make up
that piece of that entry point so that's
a brief glance at the timeline but there
is one cool thing that people always
forget about when they're talking about
the timeline and that's the filter the
filter bar is vastly underappreciated in
the web inspector and even Xcode where
it comes from where you can filter down
this list to find what exactly you want
so in this case i looked i did a filter
for a vent and it found add event
listener right there and it brought it
to the front expanded those profiles and
showed me that exact function i was
looking for so that's the filter bar and
i encourage you to start using filtering
more often in the web inspector and even
Xcode will go back to my block
application and bring up the web
inspector and let's go ahead and go to
the resource sidebar here and I really
want to improve this key function
listener this key key listener it's
using key code which is pretty arcane
and there's some new API key identifier
that's been out for four years that I
could use that would give string
representations of these for my cases
instead of the numbers so what I'll do
like I said when when we set a
breakpoint any time that key is pressed
it's going to interrupt my process so
now to do another key I have to hit
continue and log what I wanted
and press another key figure out what
i'm doing here but with this breakpoint
we can add a breakpoint action and i'll
go ahead and edit this breakpoint which
will bring up the breakpoint action pop
over and let's go ahead and add a probe
so we have a few actions available I'm
not going to cover them but they're
pretty self-explanatory probe expression
in this case is is brand new and we'll
go ahead and evaluate an expression that
we're interested in and we have an event
object here and I want to know what that
key identifier is and that's all I need
to type and I want to automatically
continue after evaluating so it doesn't
pause in the debugger so we'll go ahead
and break out of here and when I added
that probe it added a new sidebar item
called probes and this is where that
data will show up in the table so I'm
going to go back to my game and interact
with it and now it's logging that key
identifier every time I press the key
and showing me the values that I can now
take an input into my code and improve
my code and I didn't this would have
been a back-and-forth process or a lot
of assumption of what these identifiers
were now I can see them all and a table
and go back to my case and modify them
so that's probes so that's a little bit
about breakpoint probes and source code
timelines and I encourage you to play
around with them and see how they can
fit into your debugging workflow so now
let's talk about accessibility new in
the web inspector we have an
accessibility details view and this is
pretty pretty important if you're
working on a major web site you want to
be accessible to everyone Apple cares a
lot about accessibility and we do a lot
of work to make accessibility matter but
it only goes so far as to how much you
put into it when you're developing your
own applications and that goes for iOS
applications and web applications and on
the web we have something called aria
and it's recently hit a milestone Aria
one or is about to and that allows you
to define for a dom node what that dom
node does as a role and those roles are
translated into things that the pert
that the person using the computer with
voiceover can hear or see with with your
with your web application and in this
case I have a web page that has an alert
an HTML alert and those are notoriously
hard to debug or hard for a sighted a
non sighted person to see when they pop
up in a web page because they're not
going to be able to see that content
unless you annotate it with Aria roles
and in this case the voice-over
machinery and accessibility machinery in
webview exposes a lot of details like
child relationships and these
relationships are not necessarily the
same as a normal Dom node relationship
where where your parent could be someone
that's deeply a deep ancestor of you and
we show those in the sidebar here as a
parent-child relationship and they're
all linkable so I can click on them and
go directly to these other child nodes
that are part of my alert and see that
this button has the right role for a
button and it will allow people it won't
allow people to focus it but it allows
people to click it and that's a brief
summary of what you can do with the web
inspector and accessibility there's a
session tomorrow morning that covers
accessibility and the web and I
encourage you to go check it out if you
if you have a website or a web view in
your iOS or Mac application
please do make it accessible so that's
accessibility details now let's talk
about something that's that's really fun
which is color color is one of those
things we as people can understand
numbers but colors there's millions of
them and it's a very visual and a very
personal process of picking the right
color and if you're like me and you're
working on a web page you might have a
client come in and say I want this color
salmon or this color taupe it's hard to
for them to take those words and you can
translate that into the right color
wouldn't it be great if you could just
bring up a color picker right there in
the web page and modify it right there
in front of them so that's what we've
added in the web inspector and I'll give
you a demo so I have an icon that I've
been mocking up and often I do these
things in the web because that's
something I understand i can I can play
around with it a lot easier than maybe I
could do in Photoshop and this icon is a
little small so I'll just go ahead and
bring up the web inspector here and i
have a class that i can add to make it a
little bigger for you so now i have my
icon it has a couple colors it's got
this color for the glyph and it's got a
gradient in the background i can bring
up the style sidebar and see those
colors and in this case i'm using some
named colors CSS has hundreds of named
colors but maybe it's not the right teal
that's a little more green than i
expected or the light blue is is not
enough seafoam or whatever your clients
telling you to to make this color so i
can click on these color swatches and
get a color editor or i can switch over
to the CSS resource
and get the exact same experience but in
this case we want your source code to be
front and center so we don't even add
those color swatches but we have a new
feature that lets you get a data
detector like experience when we detect
that it's a color we will show a color
wheel next to it as you hover it and
when you click on that wheel we bring up
the color pop over and in this case we
can just click around and you can see
the color updating live right there on
the web page and I can find the right
color that I'm looking for for this
glyph and if it's a named color it will
default back to the name color syntax
but if it's not something that's named
it will just give you the the RGB syntax
or rgba if you picked an alpha but we
didn't stop there we now let you do
gradients and gradients are even more
hard to visualize than color because you
have that interplay of the colors
transitioning from one to another and
it's hard to see those in your mind but
we can go ahead and edit this gradient
and it gives you a simple slider that
you might be familiar with in from other
you eyes and I can drag these around and
you'll see it's updating the source code
as I drag this the percentage is
changing and when I let go it updates
the page live so I can see exactly what
is applying to this page but you can't
just edit the color stops you can edit
the type of gradient or you can pick
linear radial so it's coming out from
the center and I can click on these
colors and get the color wheel and start
editing each of these color stops
directly so I can find the the exact
look I'm looking for drag this around
maybe we want it to be more of a
starburst look
a little bit more yellow or the client
might say oh I want a linear gradient in
this case so let's go back to the
traditional iOS look for four gradients
and start picking some pretty wild
colors here so that's the gradient
editor in the the new web inspector and
what I didn't show you here let's go
back and reload here if I make any of
these changes say I want to go back and
save it let's make this a red and that
looks good that looks like a sunset in
the web inspector I can just go ahead
and hit command s that will bring up the
traditional save dialog go ahead and
replace it and now if I close the web
inspector reload the page I have that
gradient color right there the icon is a
different size because I was modifying
the DOM and it that doesn't save but if
you're editing a CSS resource or any
other local file resource you can save
those right back to disk from the web
inspector so that's color and great in
editing and I hope you play around with
it and try it out it's really fun to
just get down and dirty with those those
colors and the gradient syntax is
something that I still have trouble
remembering but the web inspector will
just help you right there I get the
right syntax and and let you go on to do
more important things in your code so
that's a summary of all the new features
and just a brief introduction of all the
new features in the web inspector so I
encourage you to take advantage of the
new JavaScript language features as
you're able to release and use the new
broad on browsers or use iOS 8
exclusively or mac OS yosemite
exclusively you can start using some of
these new language and syntax features
the web instructor is now available
again from your Mac applications if you
have a web view that you've always
wanted to see what it's doing in your
application there's been a few ways to
do it but you can now officially use the
web inspector in your Mac application
and I want you to enjoy debugging your
JavaScript context this is something
that may seem simple oh yeah there's now
a debugger but yeah now there's a
debugger you can now de bug this
JavaScript that's been plugging you or
giving you these weird errors or it's
always been hard to debug these contacts
because there's been no debugger that's
been able to give you that information
and again it's really important to make
your web applications accessible and
your iOS applications accessible and be
a colorful person enjoy color editing in
the web inspector and great in editing
and again for more information you can
contact evangelism at this email address
or the developer technol support and
even the Apple forums I'm on the Apple
forums if you have a question about the
web inspector or anything web related or
one of our team will be able to answer
it or i would there again there's a
couple more sessions that might interest
you as web developers or iOS developers
that have web or JavaScript context you
can go to the session tomorrow morning
and learn all you need to know about
accessibility in your web application
and then stay in that same room and
learn about responsive web design for
you're making your web apps scale from
desktop size to iPhone sighs and that's
it thanks a lot