With the introduction of
the revolutionary iPhone X
and AppleTV 4K,
the video playback experience
is taken to a whole new level
with the addition for support
for high dynamic range
and 4K video.
4K typically refers to
frame sizes up to 3840 by 2160,
offering an exceptionally
detailed
and high resolution image
when compared to HD.
Wide color is supported across
iOS, macOS, and tvOS,
and the media frameworks support
up to the rec 2020 color space,
which covers about 75 percent of
the visible spectrum.
The addition of support for HEVC
enables the delivery of
higher quality video
at about a 40 percent lower
bit rate compared to H.264.
HDR video must be
delivered using HEVC.
There are two HDR formats
that we support:
Dolby Vision and HDR10.
HDR10 utilizes static metadata
that is applied to
the entire program.
This metadata should be in
the HEVC configuration box
and not stored in
individual sample data.
For Dolby Vision content,
we support Profile 5,
which is single-layer,
10-bit HEVC,
and up to level 7.
For both HDR formats,
the content must be encoded
using HEVC.
You should include HDR variants
of less than or equal to
30 frames per second.
And you must always provide
SDR variants
for both your
primary media content
as well as your
I-frame playlists.
In order to help devices
select compatible variants,
we have added
a new video range tag
to the HLS specification.
If you include any
HDR variants in your playlist,
you must include this tag.
Declare SDR for any
standard dynamic range variants
and PQ for HDR10
or Dolby Vision variants.
This tag is an advisory
to the client
so that it will not attempt
to play streams
that it cannot support.
In order to support
HDCP TYPE-1 content protection,
the new TYPE-1 value has been
added to the HDCP level tag.
This value is typically
applied to content
with a resolution of
greater than 1920 by 1080.
This tag is also
advisory in nature
and prevents the client from
attempting to playback content
that can't be supported by
the currently attached display.
To finish up, let's take
a quick look at a few examples
of how a playlist differentiates
the different types of content
and how the tags we just
discussed are applied.
This is an example of a standard
dynamic range HEVC stream
that does not require HDCP.
This second example
describes a 4K HDR stream
as indicated by the PQ value
of the "VIDEO-RANGE" tag.
The "CODECS" tag describes it
as a Dolby Vision stream,
and the "HDCP-LEVEL" tag
indicates that TYPE-1
will be required in order to
successfully
playback the stream.
This 4K HDR10 example
only differs from
the Dolby Vision example
by the "CODECS" tag.
The "VIDEO-RANGE" and
"HDCP-LEVEL" tags are the same.
For more information on
HTTP live streaming,
please visit
devleoper.apple.com/streaming
for access to
the HLS authoring guide,
HTTP live streaming tools
including the stream validator,