Linking your app
against the iOS 11 SDK
is the only thing you need to do
in order to take advantage
of the super Retina display
on iPhone X.
If your app is largely based
on standard UIKit controls
and you use Auto Layout,
then you're in good shape
since most of the work
will be done for you by UIKit.
If you use custom controls,
or you're not using Auto Layout,
or if you're a custom
full screen app
like many games are,
don't worry.
While there may be
some work for you to do,
it's not difficult and there is
lots of support built in
with tools like the new
Safe Area layout guides.
In either case, you will want
to thoroughly test your app,
especially in landscape, to make
sure everything looks right.
The latest version of Xcode
includes simulator support
for iPhone X, allowing you
to make most layout changes,
especially any adjustments
relating to respecting
the Safe Area.
For some apps,
like ones that use Metal,
or hardware features
like the front-facing camera,
you may need to use
an actual device.
Let's take a quick look
at the new iPhone X simulator.
Just like other
iPhone or iPad simulators,
you'll have access to many
of the built-in system apps.
This is a great way
to see examples
of how different UIKit
components behave on iPhone X.
For example, the Files app
shows many of the latest
iOS 11 APIs in action,
like the integrated search bar
or large navigation bar titles.
And don't forget, you can
sign into your iCloud account
in the simulator, which gives
you access to iCloud Drive.
This makes it really easy
to transfer files
or test content like photos
into the simulator.
Another good example
is the Contacts app,
which shows how table views
behave on iPhone X.
Be sure to rotate
the simulator to landscape
where you can see behaviors
like the section headers
going edge to edge,
but the table contents
remain indented
according to the Safe Area.
We'll talk more about
table views a bit later.
Let's move on to
an app that I work on,
the WWDC app.
I've spent a little time
moving it over to iPhone X
and I'd like to share
some layout issues
that I encountered,
and how I fixed them.
The WWDC app is actually
a pretty typical real-world app.
It's been around
for a number of years
and it's been worked on
by various engineers
from year to year.
While it uses lots of standard
controls and Auto Layout,
it also has custom views,
and older parts of the app
do manual layout instead.
I'll use it to highlight
three different areas
that needed to be updated
for iPhone X.
I've started by opening
the project in Xcode 9
and set the Base SDK to iOS 11.
So we're all set to run
at the native resolution.
When you do this with your app,
if you don't see it running at
the full iPhone X resolution,
double check that you've
configured a Launch Storyboard,
as that's also needed.
OK, our initial view
is the Videos tab,
and this looks pretty good.
This was all new code this year
using UICollectionView
with Auto Layout,
along with standard navigation
bar and toolbar controls.
So I'm not really surprised
that most of the interface
lays out correctly,
because UIKit is doing
most of the work for me.
One place where
we don't use Auto Layout
is on the News tab.
Let's have a look at that.
This view actually
looks pretty good,
even though it's doing
manual layout of the UI.
While we're not using
Auto Layout directly,
the code doing the layout
is paying attention
to the layout margin insets,
and UIKit is automatically
adjusting those
to respect the Safe Area.
The first problem
that I encountered
is here on the News tab,
and it's in
the fullscreen photo viewer.
Even though this particular view
uses Auto Layout,
the page control is too far down
at the bottom of the screen.
It's running into
the Home indicator.
The problem here is that the
page control's bottom constraint
is relative to the superview,
which is full screen and goes
behind the Home indicator.
Instead of constraining
to the superview,
what we should do
is constrain the page control
to the Safe Area layout guide
at the bottom.
Let's make that change now.
I've opened this interface
in Xcode,
but before I can
adjust the constraint
I need to enable Safe Area
layout guides in this xib file.
Storyboards and xibs
created prior to Xcode 9
will not automatically have
Safe Area layout guides
turned on.
Go to the Document inspector
and select the Use Safe Area
Layout Guides checkbox.
One thing to note here
is that for iOS storyboards,
turning this on
will automatically upgrade
constraints tied to the scene's
top and bottom layout guides,
as well as leading
and trailing edges.
So be sure to review and test
your Auto Layout constraints
after turning this on.
Now I can select the bottom
constraint of the page control.
And look at the Attributes
inspector for this constraint.
Here we see that
the constraint is connected
to the superview's bottom edge
and that's what is keeping
the control too far down.
Instead of the Superview,
if we change this to be
connected to the Safe Area,
then on iPhone X
the page indicator
will automatically move up
above the Home indicator.
When I build and run now,
the page control
is at the right place,
and this works for both
portrait and landscape.
Let's move on to
the second issue that I found,
which is over in the Videos tab.
Once again,
things look pretty good,
but if I bring up
the search field,
well, that doesn't
look quite right.
Let's compare this
to the Contacts app looks.
A couple things look wrong here.
The color of the search bar
background isn't quite right,
and the sizing is a bit off.
And if I rotate to landscape,
I can see things
don't look right here either.
The search field and Cancel
buttons are both being clipped
by the rounded corners
of the screen.
This is a typical example
where paying attention
to the Safe Area
is really important.
For this search field,
what the WWDC app is doing
is explicitly presenting
a UI search controller.
Now in iOS 11,
the search bar can be integrated
with the navigation bar,
which will give
the right presentation
like we saw in Contacts.
Let's look at the code
and make that change.
Here's the code that presents
our search controller.
I'm going to make two changes.
First, instead of presenting
the search controller,
we'll hand it to
the UINavigationItem
for this view controller.
And second,
I'll set the search controller's
isActive property to true.
This will cause
the navigation bar
to activate it
and start editing.
Notice that we can use
the availability support
to only do this for iOS 11,
while preserving
the existing behavior
for older versions of iOS.
Let's build and run
to see how that looks.
Much better.
This looks like
the correct presentation
of the search field for iOS 11.
And in landscape?
Terrific.
Now the search bar is fitting
into the Safe Area nicely,
and this is all being
automatically managed for us
by the navigation bar.
If you have search bars
in your UI with navigation bars,
you definitely want to make
a similar change on iOS 11.
Now let's take a look
at the third part of the app
that I needed to work on.
Here in the Schedule tab,
we are using a UITableView.
The layout in portrait
looks pretty good,
although we've got
another case of a search bar
that doesn't look right.
This one happens
to be getting inserted
in the table view
as a header view,
but we can apply
the same change as before
to integrate it
with the navigation bar instead.
I'll set the search controller
on the view controller's
navigation item,
and set the active state
appropriately.
Let's build and run.
This looks great.
If I rotate to landscape,
the search field looks fine
and most of the UI looks like
it's respecting the safe areas.
But if you look closely,
we use a custom
background color
for the table section header,
and that looks wrong.
The color should be extending
to the edge of the screen,
like they do
in the Contacts app.
If we look at the code,
we can see that the app
is setting the background color
on the contentView
of the header view.
That seems like
a reasonable thing to do,
and in fact, it works fine
on iPhones other than iPhone X.
So what is the problem here?
To understand what's happening,
we need to look at the details
of how a table view
lays things out on iPhone X.
To help illustrate this, let's
start with the really useful
View Hierarchy Debugger
in Xcode.
Here's that view
we were looking at.
Down in the bottom right,
I can adjust
the visible view range
to hide all the views
except the table view itself.
The table view will be
the full size of the screen.
Now I'll adjust
the visible range
to include the cells
of the table view.
Notice how the cells extend
from edge to edge.
I'll select one to highlight it,
and overlay the Safe Area
on top of this view
to illustrate where it would be.
Now I'll keep extending
the visible range
to pull more views
into the picture.
What we're seeing now is that
the content view of the cells
have been automatically
inset to the Safe Area.
So this causes a discrepancy
between the size
of the table cell,
the one that goes
from edge to edge,
and the content view
of the cell,
which has been inset.
I'll highlight
a few of the views
that are involved here.
But now this picture
is getting a bit busy,
so let's simplify this
and label these views.
By default, table cells
will inset their content views
so that they are
inside the Safe Area.
That insetting behavior is
something that you can control.
In Xcode, you can use
the Content View
Insets to Safe Area checkbox.
There's a corresponding property
you can set in code as well.
If you uncheck the checkbox,
then the content view
will not be inset,
and the content view
will now go from edge to edge.
One final point here
is that regardless
of the content view's insetting,
the layout margins
in the content view
will continue to be relative
to the Safe Area by default.
Similar to
the content view insetting,
there are properties
that give you control
over the behavior
of these layout margins.
You can get
more details about this
and other margin-related options
in the documentation
and WWDC videos which
I'll mention at the end.
OK, now that we've seen how
table views position their cells
with regard to the Safe Area,
let's go back to the code
where we were setting
the background color
on the header view.
We can see that we're setting it
only on the content view,
which is being inset
to the Safe Area.
At this point, there are
a couple different ways
we could fix this problem.
One of them would be
to disable the table view's
default behavior
of insetting content views
to the Safe Area,
but doing that
will affect everything else
in our content view as well,
and we'd lose this helpful
default behavior.
Instead, the best solution here
is to set the background color
of the background view,
which, unlike the
inset content view,
spans the full width of the cell
regardless of any
Safe Area insets.
With that change,
when we build and run,
we go from this,
where the header background
color doesn't go edge to edge,
to this, where the colors
span the entire table
but the content view
isn't changed at all.
That looks much better.
Those are three examples
of issues I encountered
while updating the WWDC app
for iPhone X.
They weren't difficult to fix,
and mostly had to do
with landscape view.
A few quick reminders.
Linking against the iOS 11 SDK
and including
a Launch Storyboard
will enable the fullscreen
native resolution for your app.
And while you may see
some issues in portrait,
the majority will very likely
be in landscape
so be sure to test all your UI
with the interface rotated,
both to the left
and to the right.
You'll avoid most issues
by respecting the Safe Areas.
Auto Layout
and the safeAreaLayoutGuides
will handle a lot of the layout
challenges automatically,
but if you're doing
manual layout
you do have access
to the Safe Area insets
and can do whatever
calculations you need.
This information is available
via the UIView class.
It's also important
to not interfere with
the Home indicator
at the bottom of the screen.
For details about
the Home indicator
and many of the other aspects
of designing for iPhone X,
be sure to watch
the Designing for iPhone X video
which has lots
of important details
for bringing your app
to this new screen.
There were also
a few key videos at WWDC 2017
where we introduced
the Safe Area layout guides,
talked about important
gesture handling changes,
and how to take advantage
of new iOS 11 features
like the integrated search bar
support, and much more.
And of course, you can always
get more information
at developer.apple.com
or on our Developer Forums.