iOS 11 introduced ARKit:
a new framework for creating
augmented reality apps
for iPhone and iPad.
ARKit takes apps
beyond the screen
by placing digital objects
into the environment around you,
enabling you to interact
with the real world
in entirely new ways.
At WWDC we introduced
three primary capabilities
for ARKit.
Positional tracking
detects the pose of your device,
letting you use
your iPhone or iPad
as a window into a digital world
all around you.
Scene understanding
detects horizontal surfaces
like tabletops,
finds stable anchor points,
and provides an estimate
of ambient lighting conditions,
and integration with rendering
technologies like SpriteKit,
SceneKit, and Metal, as well as
with popular game engines
such as Unity and Unreal.
Now with iPhone X,
ARKit turns its focus to you,
providing face tracking
using the front-facing camera.
This new ability
enables robust face detection
and positional tracking
in six degrees of freedom.
Facial expressions are also
tracked in real-time,
and your apps provided
with a fitted triangle mesh
and weighted parameters
representing
over 50 specific muscle
movements of the detected face.
For AR, we provide
the front-facing color image
from the camera,
as well as a front-depth image.
And ARKit uses your face
as a light probe to estimate
lighting conditions,
and generates
spherical harmonics coefficients
that you can apply
to your rendering.
And as I mentioned,
all of this is exclusively
supported on iPhone X.
There's some really fun things
that you can do
with Face Tracking.
The first is selfie effects,
where you're rendering
a semitransparent texture
onto the face mesh for effects
like a virtual tattoo,
or face paint,
or to apply makeup,
growing a beard or a mustache,
or overlaying the mesh
with jewelry, masks, hats,
and glasses.
The second is face capture,
where you are capturing
the facial expression
in real time
and using that as rigging
to project expressions
onto an avatar,
or for a character in a game.
So let's dive into the details
and see how to get started
with face tracking.
The first thing you'll need
to do is to create an ARSession.
ARSession is the object
that handles
all the processing
done for ARKit,
everything from
configuring the device
to running
different AR techniques.
To run a session,
we first need to describe
what kind of tracking
we want for this app.
So to do this, you'll create
a particular ARConfiguration
for face tracking and set it up.
Now to begin processing,
you simply call the "run" method
on the session
and provide the configuration
you want to run.
Internally, ARKit will configure
an AVCaptureSession
and CMMotionManager to begin
receiving camera images
and the sensor data.
And after processing, results
will be outputted as ARFrames.
Each ARFrame
is a snapshot in time,
providing camera images,
tracking data,
and anchor points -- basically
everything that's needed
to render your scene.
Now let's take a closer look
at the ARConfiguration
for face tracking.
We've added a new subclass
called
ARFaceTrackingConfiguration.
This is a simple
configuration subclass
that tells the ARSession
to enable face tracking
through the front-facing camera.
There's a few basic properties
to check for the availability
of face tracking on your device,
and whether or not
to enable lighting estimation.
Then once you call "run,"
you'll start the tracking and
begin receiving ARFrames.
Once a face is detected,
the session will generate
an ARFaceAnchor.
This represents
the primary face --
the single biggest, closest face
in view of the camera.
An ARFaceAnchor
provides you with the face pose
in world coordinates,
through the transform property
of its superclass.
It also provides
the 3D topology and parameters
of the current
facial expression.
And as you can see,
it's all tracked,
and the mesh
and parameters updated,
in real time,
60 times per second.
Now, focusing in
on the topology,
ARKit provides you with
a detailed 3D mesh of the face
fitted in real time
to the dimensions, the shape,
and matching the facial
expression of the user.
This data is available in
a couple different forms;
the first is
the ARFaceGeometry class.
This is essentially
a triangle mesh,
so an array of vertices,
triangle indices,
and texture coordinates,
which you can take
to visualize in your renderer.
ARKit also provides
an easy way to visualize
the mesh in SceneKit through
the ARSCNFaceGeometry class,
which defines a geometry object
that can be attached
to any SceneKit node.
Now aside from
the geometry mesh,
we also have something
that we call blend shapes.
Blend shapes provide
a high-level model
of the current
facial expression.
They're a dictionary
of named coefficients
representing the pose
of specific features --
your eyelids, eyebrows, jaw,
nose, etcetera --
all relative
to their neutral position.
They're expressed
as floating point values
from zero to one,
and they're all updated live.
So you can use these
blend shape coefficients
to animate or rig,
a 2D or 3D character
in a way that directly mirrors
the user's facial movements.
Just to give you an idea
of what's available,
here's the list
of blend shape coefficients.
So each of these is tracked
and updated independently --
the right and left eyebrows,
the position of your eyes,
your jaw, the shape
of your smile, etcetera.
Something that goes
hand-in-hand
with rendering the face geometry
or animating a 3D character
is realistic lighting.
And by using your face
as a light probe,
an ARSession
that's running face detection
can provide you with
a directional light estimate,
representing the light intensity
and its direction
in world space.
For most apps,
this lighting vector
and intensity
are more than enough.
But ARKit also provides
second-degree spherical
harmonics coefficients,
representing the intensity
of light detected in the scene.
So for apps with more
advanced requirements,
you can take advantage
of this as well.
And a couple more features
to mention.
In addition to the front-facing
camera image with color data,
ARKit can also
provide your app with
the front-facing depth image
as well.
And I'm showing this here
as a greyscale image.
The data itself is provided
as an AVDepthData object,
along with a timestamp.
But it's important to note,
this is being captured at 15Hz,
which is a lower frequency
than the color image
which ARKit captures at 60Hz.
And finally, a feature that can
be used with any ARKit session,
but is particularly interesting
with face tracking is:
Audio Capture.
Now it's disabled by default,
but if enabled,
then while your ARSession
is running,
it will capture audio samples
from the microphone,
and deliver a sequence
of CMSampleBuffers to your app.
So this is useful
if you want to capture
the user's face and their voice
at the same time.
For more information
about face tracking,
and links to the sample code,
please visit
our Developer website
at developer.apple.com/arkit.