Raster Order Groups
is a new feature in Metal 2
and we're further extended it
specifically for
the new A11 GPU.
This video is one of five
that describe
the new GPU capabilities of A11.
To get the most out of it,
you'll want to have
previously watched videos
on Imageblocks and Tile Shaders.
I'll start with a brief review
of Raster Order Groups
as already available in Metal 2,
before moving on
to new A11's new capabilities.
Raster Order Groups
is a feature that requires
that the GPU execute part
of your fragment shader threads
in order with other threads
that overlap it.
This ordering comes
from the submission order
of your draw calls
within a renderpass,
and the order of each triangle
within that draw call.
The overlap is determined
by the Rasterizer.
Two fragment threads
are determined to overlap
if they target the same
framebuffer X and Y location,
the same sample,
and the same layer.
For example, two fragments
would be considered to overlap
if they would both depth test
against the same
depth buffer sample.
This is a typical case
of two triangles,
with the blue triangle first
and the green triangle second.
For access to classic
graphics framebuffers,
blending is always something
the GPU executes in order.
GPUs are not going
to suddenly blend
the green triangle in back,
because of scheduling variations
from frame to frame.
But fragment shaders
are going to execute
concurrently and out of order.
Without raster order groups,
work is only serialized
after fragment shading
completes,
but before blending.
But what if you're not blending
into the framebuffer?
Many recent developments
in graphics algorithms
attempt to build
more interesting data structures
from your fragment shaders.
There are multi-layer encodings
for better post-processing
or order independent
transparency.
There's voxelization,
and special purpose
blend functions.
All of these are built
on the fragment shaders
that are storing data
into custom data structures
in memory,
rather than merely blending
a color into an output texture.
But if direct access to memory
from the body
of your fragment shader
can happen in any order,
at any time, and concurrently,
that's severely limiting.
Dealing with those data races
has caused
existing implementations of
those algorithms
to be far more expensive
than they otherwise
would have been.
What we really want
is to get that blending-like
ordered behavior,
but not after the end
of our fragment shader,
but within it.
We effectively want the illusion
that our memory accesses
are happening serially in order.
That's what
Raster Order Groups does.
It lets you annotate
your pointers to memory
with a Raster Order Group.
Accesses through
those pointers
are then done
in a per-pixel submission order.
The hardware will wait
for any older
Fragment Shader Threads
that overlap
with the current thread
to finish before the current
thread is allowed to proceed.
This effectively
gives you mutual exclusion,
but better.
It provides
ordered mutual exclusion,
where you know
which thread is going to enter
the critical section first,
and which will do so second.
This feature was presented
in greater detail at WWDC 2017
in the session
Introducing Metal 2,
so if you'd like a deeper dive,
you can watch that video.
So with the basics covered,
let's move on to what's new
in the A11 GPU.
Raster Order Groups
are more useful,
more powerful,
and higher performing on A11.
First, A11 exposes
the GPU's internal tile memory.
Just like device
and texture access,
tile memory is
a lot more useful
if you can access it
in a predictable order,
and so Raster Order Groups
can now apply
to tile memory too.
Second,
where Raster Order Groups
on other GPUs
are limited
to only one mutex per pixel,
A11 can go finer-grained
than that,
allowing an even lighter touch,
and minimizing how often
your threads
are waiting for access.
I'd like to show you
a pair of examples
demonstrating how to use
these capabilities
to unlock new performance
in some
common graphics algorithms.
The first example
is classic deferred shading.
On traditional GPUs,
deferred shading is done
in two passes.
First filling a G-Buffer and
outputting multiple textures,
and then a second renderpass
that reads from those textures,
rendering light volumes,
and calculating
the shading results.
But deferred shading
tends to burns
a lot of memory bandwidth.
One great ability
of our A-series GPUs
is keeping as much bandwidth
as possible on chip,
eliminating these
intermediate textures
by coalescing
both passes into one,
keeping the G-Buffer
in tile-sized chunks
entirely with an imageblock
within the GPU.
Both of these tasks become
phases of one renderpass.
You can see
a much deeper dive
of how to build
these coalesced RenderRasses
in the A11 Imageblock
and Tile Shading videos,
while this video
is going to focus on
just the synchronization
aspects.
The performance
of single pass deferred shading
gets even better
by leveraging multiple
Raster Order Groups.
To take look at that,
lets dig into some of the
details of Phase number two:
Lighting.
Our basic lighting process
starts by drawing a volume
that encompasses
a light's influence,
spawning fragment
shader threads.
Each thread
is effectively applying
one light to one pixel.
Our Lighting thread starts
by reading the G-Buffer fields.
On A-series GPUs,
you'll want to read this
directly from an imageblock,
which is
the fastest memory available.
Then you'll execute
your chosen shading model,
which is typically
quite a bit of math,
and can take some time
to execute.
Finally,
you'll sum the contribution
of this light
back into the imageblock.
A very quick step.
Then we have a second light
being applied
by a second thread.
For a single-pass
deferred shading implementation
before A11, it would
look something like this.
You can see the ordering
is imposed
on the very first read
from the imageblock,
forcing the entire execution
of these two lights
to run serially.
This is because a GPU
that supports only
a single Raster Order Group
must wait on all accesses
from prior threads to complete
before any accesses
from later threads can begin.
This applies
even if both accesses are reads
that do not actually conflict
with each other.
A11's support
for multiple Raster Order Groups
eliminates
this over-synchronization.
Multiple groups
allow you to run
these non-conflicting reads
concurrently,
and synchronizing only on
the very brief end of the shader
that accumulates the result.
You can achieve this
by declaring our three G-Buffer
fields to be in one group
and our accumulated lighting
result to be in a second group.
The hardware may now
order them separately.
Outstanding writes
into one group
do not require that reads
in another group have to wait.
Multiple readers
within a single group
do not have to
wait on each other.
This means that more threads
can be eligible to run
at any given time,
allowing for more parallelism
and improved performance,
above and beyond what you get
by keeping your G-Buffers
on-chip in the first place.
The code is just as simple.
My three G-Buffer fields
are read and written together
at the same time,
and so I will annotate them all
to put them into group zero.
The accumulator is read
and written at a different time,
and so I'll annotate it
into group one.
As far as adoption goes,
that's really about it.
Raster Order Groups
is an extremely easy capability
to start using.
On to the second example.
I'm going to make our deferred
shading example more complex
by adding another phase.
After I have a lit version
of my opaque content,
I'm going to add
a transparency phase to the mix,
forward shaded,
and approximating
back-to-front blending order.
One way to do that,
which A11 is really good at,
is to declare our imageblock
to store an array
of color and depth pairs.
Each forward-shading fragment
adds an entry to this array
with some handling
of overflow.
And at the end of my tile,
I'll sort and blend
back to front,
using the saved depths,
enabling back-to-front blending.
So this is a timeline
showing off the life of one tile
and its imageblock
from left to right.
I start with A11's imageblock
laid out for deferred shading,
and I end up
with my shade opaque color.
At the end, I have
my transparency phase,
where I'm building
and then sorting my arrays
of colors and depths.
Within each of these passes,
Raster Order Groups will control
how much parallelism is possible
between fragment threads.
For performance reasons,
I really want
these two operations
to be one renderpass.
I do not want to save anything
out to device memory
just to reload it
at a later pass.
But the imageblock declaration
is wildly different
between the first and second
parts of my scene,
both in data type
and Raster Order Group
assignments.
A11 can do this transition
with one step on your part.
To bridge the gap
between these phases,
you need to put
a tile shader in between.
A tile shader
is a compute threadgroup
that can access the entire
tile memory and imageblock.
Tile shaders have the behavior
that they do not launch
until all fragment shader
threads prior have completed,
regardless of Raster Order Group
declarations.
This lets you be assured
that this tile shading
threadgroup
has exclusive access
to this memory.
With the tile shader,
you can read and write
the entire tile,
reformatting it as you wish,
and in particular,
reading from the imageblock
via its old outgoing type,
and reinitializing
the contents of imageblocks
using its new type.
Just like tile shaders
have a full barrier
before they execute,
they also have a full barrier
after they execute.
No subsequent
fragment shader threads
will access memory
until after the tile shader
has fully completed,
regardless of how you've set up
Raster Order Groups
in the later phase.
This means that you can rely
on this initialization
being completed before
the transparency work begins.
The requirement here
is pretty simple.
If you want to rearrange
your imageblock contents
or change which fields
a Raster Order Group protects,
you need to put a tile shader
in the middle
to make that transition
well-ordered and safe.
Several of the pieces of sample
code we're publishing for A11
shows this sequence in practice.
So that's really all there is
to making use
of Raster Order Groups'
expanded capabilities on A11.
You've seen
how Raster Order Groups
are even more flexible
on A11 than on any other GPU.
The hardware
supports multiple groups,
which can eliminate
over-synchronization
and improve performance.
They work hand-in-hand
with A11's fragment shader's
access to tile memory
and you can use tile shaders
to entirely change
the character of
your imageblocks,
including Raster Order Group
configuration,
right in the middle
of your render pass.
Putting it all together,
this lets you build workloads
on A11
that are incredibly light
on bandwidth,
and very well-performing.
For more information
about Metal 2 and A11,
and links to the sample code,
please visit
the Metal developer website.