In this last presentation
of the series,
we will focus
on threadgroup sharing,
which allows flexible
and efficient sharing of data
between both
threads and threadgroups.
The Metal 2 memory model adds
the following new capabilities.
Threadgroups can now
communicate with each other
through memory,
which makes it possible
to build efficient lock-free
data structures
for producer-consumer
style algorithms
in your compute kernels.
One or more threadgroups
could be producing data
while one or more threadgroups
could be consuming.
Threads within a threadgroup
may now also communicate
without the need for heavier
weight execution barriers.
Previously, the only way
to share data
between threads in a threadgroup
was using an execution barrier.
The execution barrier ensures
that all threads in
a threadgroup reach the barrier
before any threads
starts execution again.
The execution barrier provides
for memory to be synchronized
so that after the barrier,
a thread can read
what other threads
wrote to a given data location.
Forcing all threads to wait
may not be very efficient
and may be error-prone
in the face
of conditional control flow.
With Metal 2,
threads within a threadgroup
can synchronize without
requiring an execution barrier,
making it possible
for much finer grained sharing
between threads.
It also allows sharing of data
even when threads diverge
in their control flow.
This data sharing between
threads and threadgroups
is enabled by ordering
memory operations
around atomic operations or
the new memory fence function.
Let's look at an example
where we need threadgroups
to communicate with each other.
In this example,
we have a kernel
that is summing
an array of floats
but it could be more complex
reduction operation.
We dispatch a kernel
with N threadgroups
from the host.
Each threadgroup reads
a region of the input array
and computes
a per-threadgroup sum,
which gets written to a buffer
called the Threadgroup
Sum Array.
Previously in Metal,
you were forced to dispatch
a final threadgroup
to compute the final sum.
Doing so may not have been
very efficient
because the kernel
launch overhead
may be larger
than the summing operation,
and the single threadgroup
may not fully utilize the GPU.
With Metal 2,
we need only a single kernel.
Once all the threadgroups
have computed
their per-threadgroup sums,
the last executing threadgroup
computes the final sum.
The atomic functions
in Metal 2 shading language
not only allow mutually
exclusive access
to a memory location,
but also allow you to specify
how memory is ordered
between threads
within or across threadgroups.
These atomic functions
now take two new arguments,
a memory order
and a memory scope,
to control behavior
of ordering operations.
Metal 2 also adds
a new thread fence function
that can be used
for ordering memory
without atomic operations.
The updated atomic functions and
the new thread fence function
behave similarly
to functions available in C++,
so should be
quite familiar to you.
Let's take a closer look
at the memory orderings
that can be used with the atomic
and thread fence functions.
The new argument specifies
how memory operations
are to be ordered around these
synchronization primitives.
First, we have
the relaxed memory order.
This is the fastest mode,
and only provides a guarantee
of mutually exclusive access
to an atomic operation.
If you do not need
to synchronize data
between threads,
you should use
the relaxed memory order.
It is the only ordering
previously supported in Metal.
Next we have the acquire-release
memory order,
which can be used
to share data between threads.
Writes from one thread become
visible to consuming threads
after issuing
a release operation.
Likewise, consuming threads
will see that data
after performing a corresponding
acquire operation.
The memory scope specifies
whether data
needs to be synchronized
between threads in a SIMD group,
threads in a threadgroup,
or across threadgroups
executing on the device.
The larger the scope,
the higher
the synchronization cost.
Let's return to the example
where we showed
the benefit of thread groups
directly communicating
and take a look at
how we can implement this
using the Metal 2 memory model.
In this example,
each threadgroup
first computes
its per-threadgroup sum.
One of the threads
in the threadgroup
will write that sum to a buffer
holding all threadgroup sums.
We then atomically
increment a counter
to indicate that the threadgroup
has finished execution.
We use the acquire-release
memory order
to atomically increment
a counter,
ensuring that all threads
have the most up-to-date count.
The atomic add operation
also returns the previous value
of the counter,
which we use to determine
the last executing threadgroup.
Barriers are still necessary
for ensuring all threads
of a threadgroup
reach the same point
in their execution.
In this case, all threads
need to barrier
before the last threadgroup
is repurposed
to compute the final sum.
Once the last threadgroup
has been determined,
it can compute the sum
of per-threadgroup sums.
The last executing threadgroup
computes the final sum
and writes it
to the appropriate buffer.
It also resets the counter
to zero for future operations.
It does so using
the relaxed memory order
because there is no need to
synchronize with other threads.
To close, I've shown you
how the Metal 2 memory model
allows for flexible
and fine-grained sharing of data
between threads
without execution barriers.
Threadgroups can now
communicate with each other,
making it possible to build
lock-free data structures
for producer-consumer style
algorithms
in compute kernels.
For more information
about Metal 2
and links to the sample code,
please visit
the developer website
at developer.apple.com/metal.
Thank you for watching!