Building upon Imageblocks
and tile shading,
Imageblock Sample
Coverage Control gives you
new opportunities to optimize
your multisampled render passes
and is designed for the enhanced
multisampling hardware
in the A11's GPU.
Imageblock Sample Coverage
is the third in a series
of presentations
focused on new Metal 2
features on A11.
Before we dive into the enhanced
multisampling features
in Metal 2,
let's have a quick refresher
on Multisample Antialiasing.
Multisample Antialiasing,
or MSAA,
is a technique used to improve
the appearance
of primitive edges
by representing each pixel
with multiple depth
and color samples.
First let's take a look
at how a GPU renders a triangle
without multisampling.
Here's a four by four grid
of pixels
representing your
color attachment.
The GPU's rasterizer
samples the center of a pixel
to determine if it is covered
by a primitive.
Let's bring in a triangle.
All the pixel centers
covered by the primitive
are colored red.
If each pixel only has
a single sample position,
a pixel is classified
as covered or not covered
based only
on the pixel center.
You can see
in the resulting image
the classic symptom
of edge aliasing:
the staircase artifacts
also known as jaggies.
Let's see the same triangle
rendered
with multisample antialiasing.
For this example,
each pixel
has four evenly distributed
sampling positions.
With four samples per pixel,
the GPU's rasterizer can
determine finer grained coverage
for the primitive.
When a multisampled attachment
is resolved,
the GPU will average
the values of the samples
to determine the final color
of each pixel.
This results in a smoother edge
and reduces the appearance
of the staircase effect.
In traditional
multisampling implementations,
the tradeoffs for
the improved edge appearance
are the computational overhead
of blending each sample,
the larger memory footprint
of multisampled
attachments textures,
and the higher memory bandwidth
to store and resolve
multiple samples per pixel.
Apple's A-Series GPUs
have a very efficient
MSAA implementation
that directly addresses
these tradeoffs.
The hardware tracks
whether each pixel
contains a primitive edge
so that your blending
executes per sample
only for the pixels that have
difference sample values.
With Metal on A-series GPUs,
you can eliminate
the extra memory
storage requirements
by using memoryless
render targets
for the multisampled
attachments.
The full sample data
only exists temporarily
in tile memory.
By using Metal's multisample
resolve store action,
you avoid incurring
any additional
system memory bandwidth
by directly resolving
from tile memory
to the resolve attachment.
In addition, Metal 2 introduced
Programmable Sample Positions
to allow you to choose
the sample locations
and control
your sampling pattern.
With Metal 2 on A11,
we made multisampling
even more efficient at blending.
While current A-series GPUs
already track whether edges
intersect each pixel,
the A11 GPU
extends this tracking
to an even finer granularity
by tracking
the number of unique samples
within each pixel.
Even without using
any other Metal 2 features,
your existing
multisampled applications
will blend more efficiently
with A11's GPU's
enhanced multisampling hardware.
Leveraging the flexibility
of other Metal 2 features
such as Imageblocks
and tile shading,
Imageblock Sample Coverage
Control gives you access
to each pixel's sample
coverage tracking data
for even more control
of your multisampled
render passes.
With Imageblock Sample
Coverage Control,
your tile pipelines
can resolve sample data
at any time in a render pass
using your own
custom resolve algorithms.
To understand
the additional flexibility
provided by Imageblock Sample
Coverage Control,
you first need to understand
how edge tracking works
in the A-Series GPUs.
Current A-series GPUs
rasterize your scene in tiles,
and each tile contains metadata
that tracks whether a pixel
contains a primitive edge.
In this image, the red pixels
contains primitive edges,
and the white pixels do not.
The number of edge-containing
pixels increases
relative to the density
of your scene's geometry.
When a pixel contains
a primitive edge,
that means it has
multiple unique sample values.
For this reason, the blend
equation executes per sample
for edge-containing pixels.
Pixels that do not contain
an edge need to blend only once.
The A11 GPU tracks edges
with a finer granularity.
Pixels that contain edges
often only have
a few unique samples.
The A11 GPU's
enhanced multisampling
tracks and blends
only the unique samples.
In the Metal Shading Language,
we give a name
to these unique samples:
colors.
So let's take a look
at how the A11 GPU
improves multisampled
blending performance.
For pixels that contain
a primitive edge,
the A11 GPU will track
the number of unique colors
in that pixel.
As primitives intersect
or completely cover a pixel,
the number of colors contained
in that pixel
will grow and shrink.
The A11 GPU tracks these
transitions automatically.
In the diagram on the right,
the pixel contains four samples,
but only two colors.
When the A11 GPU
needs to blend the next
primitive with this pixel,
there are only two
unique samples to blend.
And for advanced
rendering algorithms
that use programmable blending,
the savings will be significant.
So let's take a fragment
through a few of these color
tracking transitions.
Initially, each fragment
contains a single color,
representing all samples.
This would be your clear color
when a render pass begins.
If a primitive edge
cuts through a pixel,
the A11 GPU will create
a new unique color
and assign the covered samples
to the new color.
The two samples covered
by this green triangle
are assigned
to the new color one.
The samples that are not covered
are still assigned
to the color zero.
Let's say the next primitive
that intersects this pixel
is a red translucent triangle.
The red triangle
covers three samples.
Current A-Series GPUs
would blend each
of the three covered samples.
The A11 GPU, blends only twice
because two
of the covered samples
share the same color index.
In this case, color one
is a blend of green and red,
and the GPU creates
a new color at index two
since that is a new,
unique color.
The number of unique colors
in a pixel can grow
when a primitive
cuts through a pixel.
But there are times
when the hardware will reduce
the number
of unique colors.
Here, an opaque,
non-blending triangle
entirely covers the pixel.
All four samples
are completely replaced by blue,
so the A11 GPU will merge
the three colors back to one,
since all the blue samples
can be represented
by a single color again.
The enhanced mutlisampling
hardware in the A11 GPU
is so powerful
that we extended
the Metal shading language
to give you explicit control
over sample coverage
with Imageblock Sample
Coverage Control.
With this new feature,
tile pipelines
have the capability
to resolve sample data in place
in the middle of a render pass
by changing the color coverage
of the pixel.
And since you write the kernel
in Metal Shading Language,
that means you can write
your own custom resolve filters.
Let's go through
a simple example.
First, we have a kernel
that has
an imageblock argument.
Next, we query
the number of colors
at a given coordinate
in the imageblock.
For a render pass
with four samples per pixel,
the value returned can be
one, two, three, or four,
depending on how many
unique colors are at that pixel.
A multisampled imageblock
can return an imageblock data
for each sample or color.
In this example, we will get
the imageblock data for color c.
Since this example
is looping over
the number of unique colors,
we also need to consider
the number of samples
that are covered by each color.
We do this by getting
the coverage mask
for this color index
and calling pop count
to get the number of set bits
in the mask.
Next, we finish resolving
our color
by dividing by the number
of samples per pixel
and writing the resolved value
back to the imageblock
with a full sample mask.
By writing a single value
with a full sample mask,
the A11 GPU will merge
all the sample data
back to a single color.
Now this is an example
of a basic resolve,
but since it is a tile pipeline,
you can write a kernel
to resolve your sample data
in a way that best fits
your application.
So you just saw an example of
writing a custom resolve filter.
Let's discuss another
reason to use tile shading
to resolve sample data.
Now, some applications render
complex scenes
with lots of opaque geometry
and lots of translucent geometry
like particles.
While the A11 GPU
will do its best
to blend only the unique colors
for each pixel,
if you know that your scene
has a lot of blended geometry,
with large amount of overdraw,
you may want to resolve
your sample data
with a tile pipeline
before the heavy blending phase.
With Imageblock Sample
Coverage Control,
you can resolve the
sample data with a tile pipeline
after rendering
your opaque geometry
to ensure that all pixels
contain a single unique color
prior to blending.
Let's look at a more
advanced example
of using a tile pipeline
to change the coverage
of the sample data.
Since the tile pipeline
can be implemented
with the compute function,
you can do much more than
simply average values together.
Our Surface Aggregation
sample app starts
with a multisampled single-pass
deferred shading algorithm
and uses a tile-based
kernel dispatch
to reduce the number
of shaded samples
in the deferred pass.
The goal of this algorithm
is to shade fewer samples
in the expensive
deferred pass
while retaining
the edge-smoothing benefits
of multisample antialiasing.
We won't dive into all
the details of the algorithm,
so be sure
to download and explore
our Surface Aggregation
sample app.
But now let's visualize
how this technique
reduces the cost of shading.
The two images
visualize the pixels
containing more than one sample
per pixel in the g-buffer.
The image on the left
shows the g-buffer
before merging surfaces,
and the image on the right
shows the g-buffer
after merging surfaces.
The surface aggregation kernel
is able to reduce
the number of
g-buffer samples
that need to be shaded.
As you can see
on the right image,
the only pixels containing
multiple unique samples
are on true creases
and depth boundaries.
Before Metal 2
on the A11 GPU,
this algorithm would require
a separate render pass
for each phase of the algorithm,
incurring multiple round trips
to system memory.
But with Imageblock
Sample Coverage Control,
all three phases
of the algorithm
can be merged
into one render pass,
saving your app
a ton of memory bandwidth.
As you can see in the diagram,
all three phases operate
on the imageblock
keeping all the working data
inside tile memory.
First, you will
render the g-buffer
to the imageblock
in tile memory.
And next, you will dispatch
the surface aggregation
tile pipeline
to reduce the number
of g-buffer samples
into fewer aggregate
g-buffer samples.
Finally, the deferred
shading pass
will only shade
each aggregate sample.
If you're interested in learning
more about this technique,
please visit the link
at the end of this presentation
to download the sample app.
To recap, we first talked
about the hardware enhancements
made to multisampling
in the A11 GPU.
The A11 GPU tracks
the number of unique samples
in every pixel to reduce
the cost of blending.
This optimization applies
to both API blending
as well as
programmable blending.
We then discussed
the enhancements
in Metal 2 for the A11 GPU
that expose this powerful
hardware feature
to kernels used in tile shading.
With Imageblock Sample
Coverage Control,
you can write your own
custom resolve kernels
and dispatch them at any time
in a render pass
to implement
powerful new optimizations.
Together, the enhanced
multisampling in the A11 GPU
and the new shading language
features in Metal 2
enable new techniques to keep
your data on-chip longer.
You can use this feature
to implement algorithms
like Surface Aggregation
in a single render pass.
For more information
about Metal 2
and links to the sample code,
please visit
the developer website
at developer.apple.com/metal.
Thank you for watching.