Metal 2 introduces
a new set of APIs
and shading language changes
to take advantage of
the architecture
and new features
of the A11 GPU.
Let us review what is new
with Metal 2 on A11.
Apple designed Metal
to enable rapid innovations
in GPU architecture.
And in turn,
the Apple GPU architecture
has informed
the design of Metal.
This deep and seamless
integration of hardware
and software
enables exciting new
possibilities for your graphics,
compute, machine learning apps,
and games.
Just three years after
the introduction of Metal,
we introduced Metal 2,
the next generation of Metal,
at WWDC 2017.
Building on a clean
and well-factored design,
Metal 2 expands to include
even more cutting edge ways
to access the capabilities
of the GPU,
such as GPU-driven rendering,
which allows the GPU to dispatch
graphics workloads to itself,
further increasing efficiency
and decrease the draw call
cost by up to 10X.
In 2015, Metal expanded
to support the Mac
and desktop GPUs.
Now, Metal 2 aligns the API to
expose key features uniformly,
regardless of the underlying
GPU architecture.
With the rise of
machine learning
across a wide variety
of domains,
Metal 2 brings a wider and more
sophisticated set of functions
that are aimed at accelerating
inference operations
for improved performance
and efficiency.
Metal 2 also brings a new
set of optimization tools
that make it far easier for you
to expertly tap into
the power of the GPUs
on Apple platforms.
And now, we can reveal
more Metal 2 capabilities
that we didn't announce at WWDC.
Metal 2 includes a set of
powerful new features
that expose the unique
capabilities
of Apple-designed GPU
in our latest A-series chip,
the A11.
Before we go into the details
of A11 GPU architecture
and features,
let us review the architecture
of a classical GPU
and tile-based deferred
rendering architecture.
This is a simplified diagram of
a classical GPU architecture.
GPUs are massively
parallel machines.
The vertex and fragment stages
that are shown in this diagram
are replicated many times,
and they run in parallel.
There are also many
optimizations
such as cache hierarchies,
FIFOs,
early coarse depth test,
and so on,
that are not shown
in this diagram.
Fundamentally,
GPUs with classical architecture
take primitives
and generate depth, color,
data buffers,
and textures.
One of the defining
characteristics
of this architecture
is that the output
of the vertex stage
feeds directly into
the fragment stage.
Let us look at the tile-based
deferred rendering architecture,
which is also known as TBDR.
All A-series GPUs are based on
TBDR architecture.
TBDR makes some
significant changes
to the classical GPU
architecture.
The first major difference
is that the vertex stage
is not fed directly into
the fragment stage.
Instead, as they come out
of the vertex stage,
the primitives are binned into
screen-aligned small tiles
and stored into the memory.
This change allows
the vertex stage
to run asynchronously
relative to fragment stage.
While running the fragment stage
of a renderpass, in parallel,
the hardware executes the vertex
stage of a future renderpass.
Running vertex stage
asynchronously
provides significant
performance improvements.
The vertex stage is usually
making heavy use
of fixed-function hardware,
whereas the fragment stage
is a heavy user of math
and bandwidth.
Completely overlapping them
allows us to use
all the hardware blocks
on the GPU simultaneously.
Having primitives binned
to tiles allows us
to process all primitives
in a tile all together.
Let us see how we can
take advantage of that.
We put tile-sized,
full resolution,
depth, stencil,
and frame buffers on the chip
next to our shader cores.
We call this memory
tile memory.
There are three important
characteristics
of the tile memory.
First, the bandwidth between
the shader core and tile memory
is many times higher
than the bandwidth
between the GPU
and the external memory,
and scales proportionally
with the number of shader cores.
Second, the memory access
latency to the tile memory
is many times lower than
the latency for the accesses
to the external memory.
Finally, tile memory consumes
significantly lower power
than the external memory.
TBDR uses this low-latency,
low-power-consumption,
high-bandwidth memory
for two major optimizations.
First, the tile depth/stencil
memory allows the hardware
to generate full depth
and stencil buffer information
for opaque objects
before the shading core
starts to process them,
which enables the hardware
to perfectly cull fragments
that are occluded before
sending to the shader core.
If the depth buffer
is not needed
for the subsequent renderpasses,
the full-size depth buffer
can be entirely eliminated
through the use of
memoryless render targets,
saving a large amount of memory
bandwidth, storage, and power.
Second, tile memory is used
for storing the color buffers
on the chip.
Blending operations are fast
because they do not
need to access
the full-sized frame buffer
on the external memory.
Tile memory is written
only once,
after the entire tile
is processed,
and saves significant
amounts of power,
performance, and bandwidth.
Higher occupancy is achieved
thanks to this faster memory.
The framebuffer fetch feature
allows you to implement
custom blending
and enables several
advanced techniques.
Combined with
memoryless frame buffers,
many of these techniques
do not need to consume
external memory either.
As a result, TBDR brings
great performance
even when bandwidth is limited.
TBDR consumes
much lower power,
which is essential for
battery-powered devices.
Let us now switch gears
to A11 GPU.
On A11, the first major change
we made to the GPU architecture
is to give you direct control of
data residing in tile memory
from your fragment functions.
Imageblocks provide
optimized access to image data
residing in tile memory.
You'll be able to lay out pixels
in the way that makes sense
to your application,
yet can still be rendered to
efficiently.
An imageblock is a 2D data
structure in tile memory.
You can specify its width,
height, depth, and format.
Metal 2 adds
texture pixel formats
to the shading language
to give you full control
over the pixel layout
through the packed data types.
The second major
architectural change
gives you access to all pixels
that are stored in tile memory
at the same time.
Tile shading is the new
programmable stage
in Apple's A11 GPU that
provides compute capabilities
inline within render passes.
Tile shading enables a whole new
level of performance
and efficiency in Metal 2.
Rendering and compute operations
can now share the data
through the higher bandwidth,
lower latency,
and lower power tile memory.
Tile shading is deeply
integrated with imageblocks.
You will be able to analyze
imageblock contents,
summarize that content,
store imageblocks mid-scene,
and even change
imageblock layouts.
You can also use
threadgroup memory
just like a regular
compute kernel would.
For tile shaders,
the threadgroup memory
is persistent.
Each successive invocation
of tile shader
can operate on
the threadgroup memory,
starting with the values
that are left
from the previous tile shader.
This is true for imageblock
memory as well.
They are persistent
between invocations of
tile and fragment shaders.
Additionally, we are introducing
an advanced version of
raster order groups
that supports imageblock
and tile shading.
And finally, we are extending
the Metal shading language
to give you full control over
sample coverage
for multi-sampled imageblocks.
Let us see a set of
rendering techniques
that can take great advantage
of the new architecture
and the new Metal 2 features.
Tile shaders, imageblocks,
and raster order groups
are a great way to combine
interleaved,
render, and compute passes
into a single combined pass.
Deferred rendering
and tiled forward rendering
could be accelerated
this way.
Let us look at the tiled forward
implementation as an example.
You can pass geometry to create
on-chip depth information first,
then run a tile shader
to create per tile min-max
depth information,
run another tile shader
to create a culled light list
in threadgroup memory,
and then run
your material shaders.
All of these operations can
be done in one combined pass,
increasing performance
by eliminating
large amounts of bandwidth,
storage, and power.
These features also enable
efficient implementations
of order-independent
transparency,
multi-layer alpha blending,
and sub-surface scattering.
Sample coverage control,
tile shaders, and imageblock
enable much more efficient ways
of doing custom MSAA resolves,
MSAA tone mapping,
and surface aggregation.
To show how some of these
use cases can be accelerated,
we are releasing sample code
for deferred rendering,
tiled forward,
multi-layer alpha blending,
and surface aggregation.
Metal 2 on A11 advances
the TBDR architecture
by introducing imageblocks,
tile shaders,
imageblock sample
coverage control,
and raster order groups.
Additionally, we introduced new
Metal shading language changes
to give you new and efficient
mechanisms to share data
between your compute threads
and threadgroups.
Let us briefly review these
and other additional features
and performance
improvements on A11.
Let us start with imageblocks.
An imageblock is a 2D data
structure in tile memory.
Fragment functions
can only access a single pixel
that corresponds
to its location,
whereas kernels can access
the entire imageblock.
Each pixel can be quite complex,
consisting of
multiple components,
and each component
can be addressed
as its own image plane.
Imageblocks also provide
bulk access
to the GPU's format
conversion hardware.
Floating point pixels
will be converted to
the destination texture format
when stored to device memory.
Tile shaders provide
compute capabilities
inline within render passes.
Tile shaders can access
the entire imageblock,
and just like regular
compute kernels,
they have support
for threadgroup memory.
Unlike a threadgroup memory
of a compute kernel,
the threadgroup memory
of a tile shader
persists across
the lifetime of a tile,
just like color data
persists across draws.
So where before
you were limited
to communicating across draws
within the scope of a pixel
using the framebuffer
fetch feature,
you can now communicate
between the tile dispatches
and fragment draw calls
using the wider tile scope.
Let us now look into how A11
improves MSAA
over previous generations.
Apple's A-series GPUs
have a very efficient
MSAA implementation.
When the fragment
is not an edge fragment,
the hardware blending
executes once per fragment,
not once per sample.
Additionally, you can resolve
directly from tile memory
to the resolve attachment
and avoid incurring
additional memory bandwidth.
Through the use of Metal's
memoryless render
target feature,
you can also eliminate
MSAA rendertarget memory
storage entirely.
With Metal 2 on A11,
we took MSAA even further.
While our current A-series GPUs
already track edges in a pixel,
the A11 GPU
extends this tracking
to an even finer granularity
by tracking the number of unique
samples within each pixel.
This hardware change makes your
multisample applications faster
without requiring
any changes to your application.
With A11,
Metal 2 also gives you
full control of this
tracking metadata
with imageblock sample
coverage control.
You can also leverage
this feature in combination with
threadgroup imageblocks
and tile shaders.
With imageblock sample
coverage control,
your tile pipeline can modify
the GPU's sample
coverage tracking data,
allowing you to resolve
sample data
at any time in a render pass
with your own
custom resolve algorithm.
Raster order groups enable
you to access memory
from overlapping fragment
functions in submission order,
and allows fragment functions
to communicate.
A11 extends the raster order
groups' functionality.
First, A11 exposes the GPU's
internal tile memory.
Raster order groups
make tile memory more useful
by giving you access to it
in a predictable order.
Second, where raster order
groups on other GPUs
are limited to only
one mutex per pixel,
A11 can go finer-grained
than that,
allowing an even lighter touch
and minimizing how often your
threads are waiting for access.
Now let us look at how
Metal 2 accelerates data sharing
between threads
and threadgroups.
Metal 2 shading language
extends atomic functions
with memory order
and scope attributes.
These new additions enable
new ways of flexible
and efficient sharing of data
between threads.
Before Metal 2, to communicate
between threadgroups
required completing
the kernel execution
and issuing a new kernel
to consume the outputs
of the threadgroups
of the first kernel.
On Metal 2, threadgroups can
communicate directly
with each other.
Additionally, with the addition
of these new features,
threads within a threadgroup
can communicate
without using a barrier
resulting in improved
performance.
We also added some other
significant features
and capabilities to
Metal 2 on A11.
On A11, f16 math has overall
better accuracy
through the improvements
to rounding
and the maximum value
handling.
A11 adds support
for texture cube arrays,
and introduces read-write
texture functionality.
With A11, an array of
sampler coverage
comes to A-series GPUs.
A11 adds post-depth
coverage feature
and provides a more flexible way
of dispatching compute kernels.
A11 adds support for quad scoped
permute operations as well.
For further details about
these features,
please check the Metal 2
documentation.
A11 makes many significant
performance improvements
to the GPU.
It has up to 2X math performance
when it comes to tasks
for computer vision,
image processing,
and machine learning.
But that is not the only area of
improvement for performance.
Let us review
the improved performance
and capabilities of A11 GPU.
We doubled F16 math
and texture filtering rate
per clock cycle
when compared to A10 GPU.
Please note: On A11,
using F16 data types
in your shaders when possible
makes a much larger
performance difference.
We doubled the maximum
threadgroup size
from 512 to 1K on A11.
Maximum multiple render
target size increased
from 256 bits to 512 bits.
Maximum threadgroup memory
size doubled from 16K to 32K.
We also made significant
improvement
over the performance of
feedback operations.
They're also known as
alpha-test and discard.
For more information
about Metal 2
and links to the sample code,
please visit the developer
website at
developer.apple.com/metal.