In this presentation
we will focus on imageblocks,
which allow you to describe
image data in tile memory
that the GPU
can manipulate efficiently.
Imageblocks provide
optimized access to image data
residing in tile memory.
And with the A11 GPU,
we're giving you
direct control of it.
You will be able
to lay out pixels
in the way that makes sense
to your application,
as well as move data explicitly
to and from it.
Imageblocks are deeply
integrated
with fragment processing
and the new tile shading stage.
They are also available
to traditional compute.
No matter which stage you're in,
imageblocks are recommended
for representing your images
because they optimize access
to grids of 2D data.
Imageblocks are
a key building block
for several of
the other features we'll discuss
in this presentation series.
Let's start by defining
imageblocks more precisely.
An Imageblock is a 2D
data structure in tile memory.
It has width, height,
and a pixel depth.
Fragment functions
can only access a single pixel
that corresponds to
its location.
Compute kernels,
on the other hand,
have access to
the entire imageblock.
Each pixel can be quite complex,
consisting of multiple
components,
and each component
can be addressed
as its own image plane.
This allows adjacent components
to be efficiently stored
to one or more textures
in device memory
as bulk operations.
Imageblocks also provide
bulk access
to the GPU's format
conversion hardware.
Floating point pixels
will be converted to
the destination texture format
when stored to device memory.
Let's now take a closer look at
one of the benefits of
using imageblocks,
accelerating image data movement
out of tile memory.
Prior to imageblocks,
you probably moved
portions of your textures
into threadgroup memory
before operating on them,
one pixel at a time.
But the GPU didn't understand
that you were
operating on image data,
so you also had to
store those pixels back out to
device memory textures,
one pixel at a time.
With imageblocks, you can
instead store the image data
using a single operation,
which is much more efficient.
Now let's turn to
how you describe
imageblock properties
to Metal.
In a compute pass,
you describe the imageblock's
width and height
using the API shown here.
The dimensions can be
different for each dispatch.
The imageblock's pixel depth
is described in the shading
language as a structure.
The entire imageblock
is made available as an argument
whose type is templated
by that struct.
Let's take a closer look
at the shading language syntax.
In this example,
we are describing a pixel
consisting of three elements,
each with a varying number of
components.
The imageblock is made available
to the kernel as an argument.
Kernels access any location
within the imageblock
by reference
using the data method,
which takes the location
as its argument
and returns a pointer to
a new address space
called threadgroup_imageblock.
With a reference
to a particular location,
we can read and write
to elements at that location.
I mentioned earlier that
imageblocks are laid out
in planes that can be
stored efficiently
to device memory textures.
In the shading language,
we call adjacent planes that
can be stored together a slice.
Let's take a look at
an example kernel.
In this example,
we've loaded a source texture
into an imageblock,
performed some image processing
on that block,
and are ready to store
the color elements
out to a destination texture.
We only need one thread
of our threadgroup
to perform the write,
so we must first barrier
to ensure all threads
have finished processing
the imageblock.
Notice that Metal adds a new
memory target for the barrier,
declaring that we only
need to wait for writes
on the imageblock to complete.
We then acquire our desired
slice from the imageblock
using the slice method.
The slice method
takes a reference
to any pixel element
that's part of the slice.
Finally, we write the slice
to the destination texture.
Each imageblock
probably represents
only a region of your texture,
so we specify the texture offset
at which to write
the imageblock.
Let's now turn to
how imageblocks in fragment
functions are specified.
Unlike imageblocks
in compute passes,
imageblock dimensions
in a render pass
are constant for the entire pass
and set using the properties
shown here.
Imageblock pixel depth
can be declared
in the shading language
as a struct,
just as I've already shown
for kernels.
Fragment functions, however,
also support declaring
the pixel depth
using render pass attachments.
Let's take a look at the syntax.
In this example, we've declared
the pixel structure
explicitly in
the shading language.
Since fragment functions
only have access
to their implied location
within the imageblock,
the argument type
is the struct itself,
but tagged with the
imageblock_data attribute.
We also need to
tag the return value
with the same attribute.
Doing so allows Metal
to generate the correct access
instructions.
Now let's see what this
same example looks like
when we declare
the pixel structure
using traditional
render pass attachments.
This form is identical to
the syntax you already know.
In fact, you've always used
imageblocks in render passes
because tile memory
has always been
a key aspect of A-series GPUs.
What's new is that Metal 2
now makes tile memory
generally accessible.
This form abstracts
the underlying
imageblock storage format,
which is derived from
the textures
attached to the render pass.
Regardless of
texture storage type,
the data is presented as
floating point or integer
in the fragment function.
Another difference between
A11 and earlier architectures
is where those implicit
imageblock format conversions
occur.
On A7 through A10 GPUs,
the storage formats
were expanded to floating point
in tile memory.
This is why Metal documents two
sizes for every pixel format:
one when stored in device memory
and one when stored
in tile memory
as render pass attachments.
On A11, format conversion
occurs on each load and store
from tile memory
to temporary registers
in the shader core.
Doing so allows you
to squeeze even more use
out of tile memory.
You now have a choice in how to
declare your pixel structure,
so let's review best practices
that can help you decide.
Implicit imageblocks are great
when your fragment function
must support multiple
render pass attachment layouts
because they abstract
the underlying storage formats.
Implicit imageblocks
are also compatible
with load and store actions
because the structure
is known by the API.
Explicit imageblocks
on the other hand
allow you to express
more complex pixel structure.
Explicit imageblocks also don't
require main memory backing,
so they're a great fit
for temporary data
produced and consumed
entirely within
the scope of a render pass.
Now let's take a closer look at
what we mean by
complex pixel structure.
In this example,
we're going to store
multiple translucent colors
and their depths per pixel
so that we can later
sort and composite
for more accurate
transparency effects.
We start with a single
fragment declaration,
declare an array of them,
and then nest it in
a top-level struct
that we can pass
to and from our shader.
Expressing this structure
using render pass attachments
would be awkward and would
obscure the author's intent.
Of course,
you don't have to choose between
implicit and explicit forms
because Metal allows you to
pick the right tool for the job.
Mixing also allows you
to incrementally
adopt imageblocks
into your code base
and easily integrate
new features
into existing shaders that
benefit from the explicit form.
Using both forms together
is easy,
just provide
two imageblock arguments.
Let's take a look at an example.
As you can see, we can
supply two imageblocks
as both inputs and outputs.
The color and imageblock_data
attributes
make it clear to Metal
which slices derive from
render pass attachments
and which do not.
Up to two imageblocks
per input and output
can be declared
for each function.
Explicit imageblocks allow you
to control pixel layout exactly
using packed types.
The Metal shading language
already provides
packed floating point
vector types,
which have traditionally
described vertex
and constant data layouts.
But now we need packed types
that match what could have
previously been described
using implicit imageblocks
and texture pixel formats.
Metal 2 adds such types
to the shading language.
These formats are converted
to and from floating point
using the load/store hardware
we discussed earlier.
What's more is that
these new packed formats
can be used to describe vertex
and constant data layouts, too.
Let's take a look at
how you declare these new types
in the shading language.
In this example we see
a few of the new packed types
used to describe both
imageblocks and vertex data.
These types require
that you declare
both the storage format
and unpack format
used within the shader core.
Now let's glance at
all the new packed data types
that have been added.
As you can see, the Metal
shading language adds
one, two, and four
component normalized types,
each supporting eight
or 16-bit components.
We've also added both signed
and unsigned variants
as well as support for more
specialized 32-bit formats
such as 10a2, mini floats,
shared exponent, and sRGB.
Finally, the GPU debugger
in Xcode directly supports
the visualization and
inspection of imageblocks.
Each slice can be inspected
as if it were a texture.
Here we see on the top
an example G-Buffer layout
from our sample code.
And on the bottom we have
the same imageblock
show in Xcode's GPU Debugger.
The tile section of
the bound resources view
shows the imageblock slices
as a set of textures.
From here you can
inspect each of the slices
just like any other texture.
In this presentation,
we saw how imageblocks
enable you to efficiently
move multiple pixels
from tile memory
to device memory
and control the layout
of image data in tile memory
precisely to improve
storage density.
We also saw how we could
also leverage
the A11 GPU's new
pack/unpack hardware
in both imageblocks
and other address spaces.
For more information
about Metal 2
and links to the sample code,
please visit
the Developer website
at developer.apple.com/metal.