Apple TV 4K takes
the living room experience
to a whole new level,
with support for 4K resolution,
P3 color, HDR video playback,
the incredible
A10X Fusion processor,
and the updated and improved
Siri Remote.
Updating your app to
support these new features
is very straightforward.
The first step is to
add a 2x launch image.
Until you do so, tvOS
is going to run your app
in compatibility mode.
While you're at it, you'll also
want to add 2x app icons
and top shelf images.
When attached to
a 4K television,
UIKit will now automatically
select retina assets
from your asset catalogue.
You can inspect what screen
scale the device is running in
by inspecting the scale property
of the main UIScreen.
You can also determine
the pixel resolution
of the attached display by using
the nativeBounds property.
Just like the latest iOS
and macOS devices,
we're really excited
that Apple TV 4K
now supports P3 color.
When providing retina assets,
you may also want to
update your assets
to take advantage of
this wider color space,
allowing your graphics
and images to contain
even richer and more saturated
colors than before.
This isn't just for flat images
but is supported for
layered images as well.
Media apps will also want to
look at updating their streams
to include 4K and HDR variants
for any content that was
produced in these formats.
Apple TV 4K supports
both Dolby Vision and HDR10
for HDR content,
and the addition of support
for HEVC
enables these higher fidelity
and resolution streams
while consuming up to
40 percent less bandwidth
than comparable streams
encoded using H.264.
The updated and improved
Siri Remote
now provides motion data
for attitude and rotation rate,
in addition to the values
for acceleration and gravity
that the prior version offered.
To determine if
the paired remote
supports these new features,
you can inspect the new GCMotion
"hasAttitudeAndRotationRate"
property.
The values for attitude
and rotation rate
are then provided by the
respective GCMotion properties.
And with those few changes,
you're going to be able to
take advantage
of all of the new capabilities
and performance of Apple TV 4K.
For more information on updating
your app for Apple TV 4K,