[ Silence ]
I think a developer
would look like a geek.
Nerdy, plaid.
Unshaven, glasses.
Spikey hair, beard.
A guy behind a
door, that's got enough
of a crack they can
slide a pizza underneath.
I think you won't even
know who a developer is.
I think you'd be surprised.
I really don't know what
a developer looks like,
but the apps they make
let us do amazing things.
[Background Music] You
can talk about a project,
you can articulate
it rationally,
but you cannot communicate
architectural ideas
without a drawing.
I use an App called
Paper by FiftyThree.
It really provides
a sense of freedom,
a sense of being
emancipated from technology.
It allows you to
communicate as if directly
from your heart, from your soul.
It's just part of you.
And I think that that magic
is part of the app world.
The app I cannot live without
is a banking app named the Zhi
Fu Bao.
Airbnb saved my life.
I talk to my friends.
Instagram, Tumblr.
Like blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah.
Evernote.
That's the one.
I'm addicted to Pinterest
because it is amazing.
There's so much
entertainment.
Duck face.
It's limitless
what you can do.
[Background Music]
The ocean, for me,
is the lungs of our planet.
The health of the ocean
is absolutely essential
to the health of
us as human beings.
Pangaea runs a
sailing expedition vessel
to help scientists collect data
on marine debris all
around the world.
There's a variety of apps that I
use everyday, iNavX is essential
for us to be able to
navigate the vessel.
Marine Debris Tracker allows
you to enter the marine debris
that you find into a global
database, so we can start
to build up a bigger picture of
this problem around the world.
I think these apps are
essential for us to be able
to bring change to what's
going on in the ocean.
The best app of all
time has to be Tinder.
I'm most probably
like the millions
of people that's got
sucked into Candy Crush.
Robot Unicorn Attack 2.
Crazy girl looking to
meet new people in London.
Interesting.
Words With Friends, Scrabble.
I play Solitaire and
of course I always win.
[Background Music]
We are stewards
of dreams and hope for hitters.
They come in and they want
to achieve amazing
things and that's my job.
Dartfish has just made
my life so much easier.
I'm able to break down the swing
into parts, so that you can see,
OK, here's the mistake
and here's the adjustment
that I need to make.
So, what you have is a kid
that can not only do it right,
but then you can train him on
doing it over and over and over.
Now they're able
to look and say,
"You know what, I'm
getting better."
And that's one of the things
that you need for life
in general, but in
sports you want hope.
And so now it's easy for
them to focus on dreaming.
[ Noise ]
We need like a
silence finder app.
Pop, pop, pop, pop.
Pop, pop, pop.
I gravitate towards very
melancholy and painful songs.
[Singing] Ahhh.
And then it's time
to turn the page, whoop.
This has become as
essential as my guitar.
There are apps that
help people, that like,
really improve people's lives.
[Background Music] Every
now and then I'll sort of stare
at the hand, with the sense of
sort of wonder going, "Wow."
It is like magic, it really is.
In combination with the
hand the app has allowed me
to gain functionality
and independence.
I enjoy being known as the
kid with the bionic arm.
You know, it's something
interesting,
and it's something different,
and I'm a big fan
of being different.
[ Music ]
You open up an app and
you open up a possibility
and a whole world is being born.
What we really have
is an intersection
between technology and art.
You see the world in a different
way and I think an app can do
that because it really does
open something you didn't
know beforehand.
Developers are doing
extraordinary things.
I can't believe what they're
creating today, it's genius.
If I met the person
that made Sky Go,
I'd probably give
him a massive hug.
You inspire me so much.
They make our lives better
and they think of things that,
obviously, regular
people can't think of.
I don't know how
the technology works,
it's just magic to me.
There's no question they
are changing the world.
So, to everyone
who's made any apps
that I've ever enjoyed
I say, "Thank you."
[ Applause ]
Good morning.
Welcome to San Francisco.
We're here today and all week
to celebrate the
developer community and all
of the amazing apps
that they've created.
I hope that video
did a great job
of capturing just
how deeply we feel
about out developer community
and more importantly the number
of lives they've enriched.
So from all of Apple,
thank you very much.
[ Applause ]
This is a milestone year
for this conference.
It's the 25th anniversary
of the conference.
It started in 1990 with just
1,300 developers, who gathered
to talk about the System 7.
And there was one lab in
that developer conference.
Now, WWDC is a huge conference
for Apple and a huge conference
for all of our developers.
We have over a thousand
of our best
and brightest engineers here
today to talk with you directly
in labs, about how
to improve your code.
We've got people from more
countries than ever before,
and two-thirds of the
attendees today are here
at a developer's conference
for the very first time.
[ Applause ]
A special shout-out this morning
to the student scholarship
winners.
They worked really
hard to get here.
[ Applause ]
Our youngest developer in
the audience today is 13.
[ Applause ]
We're going to be seeing apps
from them for a long time.
The developer community
is incredibly vibrant.
We now have 9 million
registered developers.
That's up almost 50
percent since last year.
That's the most developers we've
ever added in a single year.
Now, this morning,
we're gathered to talk
about two powerful
platforms, OS X and iOS.
And you are going to see some
great new features for both,
and some great updates.
But even more importantly,
you're going
to see how they've
been engineered
to work seamlessly together.
Now, you're also going
to see the mother
of all releases for developers.
It's a huge release
and it's so huge
that we've dedicated
an entire section
of the presentation
just for this.
[ Applause ]
So, let's get started
with OS X and the Mac.
We're shipping the best
Macs in our history.
If you look just in
this last fiscal year,
while the industry declined by 5
percent Macs grew by 12 percent,
that's swelled our installed
base of Macs to over 80 million,
which is a record for us.
We're really proud of this.
And of course our latest release
of OS X Mavericks has
done really great.
It had great features for power
users like power tabs, and tags,
and enhanced support
for multiple displays.
Advanced technologies
for longer battery life
and greater performance.
And of course, new
and improved apps.
Just since its release in
October we've installed
over 40 million copies
of Mavericks.
This is the most of a single
release ever in Apple's history.
Also, that makes over 50 percent
of our installed base working
on our latest operating system.
This is the fastest
adoption ever
of any PC operating
system in history.
Now, you may wonder how
that compares to Windows.
[ Laughter ]
I knew somebody was going to ask
so I decided to make a chart.
[ Laughter ]
Well, as it turns
out Windows 8 shipped
about a year before Mavericks
and it's at 14 percent.
[ Laughter ]
Need I say more?
[ Applause ]
So, we could not be happier
with Mavericks and the momentum
of the Mac, but of course
we're always future focused.
And today, to talk about
the future of OS X,
I'd like to invite my
colleague up, Craig Federighi,
to tell us all about it.
Craig.
[ Applause ]
Good morning.
Wow.
[ Applause ]
Well, it's wonderful to be here
presenting among the greatest
developers collected
in the world.
You guys are fantastic.
You know, it was just a
year ago, here at WWDC,
when we narrowly averted a
major OS X naming crisis.
[ Laughter ]
You may remember that we're able
to deftly shift from names based
on big cats to names based on
beautiful places in California,
starting of course
with OS X Mavericks.
Well, it's another year
and time for another name
and so we collected our
crack product marketing team,
shoved them in their VW Minibus
and set them out on the road.
Now, they first ventured south
discovering OS X, Oxnard.
[ Laughter ]
This wasn't quite right.
But undeterred, they
headed east,
landed in OS X Rancho Cucamonga.
[ Laughter ]
Still, we hadn't
quite hit the mark.
So, they boldly ventured
north landing at OS X Weed.
[ Laughter ]
Now--
[ Applause ]
Strangely, this one had
large pockets of support
within the product
marketing organization,
but saner heads did
prevail and they set off
on what then was somewhat
more circuitous path.
It took them ultimately
to a place
that embodies the
beauty and power of OS X.
We discovered OS X Yosemite.
[ Applause ]
Now, Yosemite is a fantastic new
release with a new interface,
big enhancements to
our most popular apps
and something all knew,
we call Continuity.
Now, I want to start
with design.
OS X, of course started with
the bold design of Aqua.
And over the years, it's evolved
to the refined look we all
loved today in Mavericks.
Well, with Yosemite, we
continue this evolution and I'd
like to give you a look
at where we're headed.
[ Music ]
How about that?
[ Applause ]
I think the team has done
some remarkable work.
You know, we started with the
most fundamental controls,
focused always on clarity,
as well as utility.
We refined the tool bars
and the window materials
and the window constructions.
If you look at the window title
bar, you'll see how the use
of translucent materials
gives you a sense of place
as you scroll your content.
Now, these same carefully
crafted translucent materials
are used in the sidebars.
So now, your windows take on
the personality of your desktop.
As you change your desktop
picture, your window adapts
to reflect that personality
and that temperature.
And the translucency also
helps maintain a sense of depth
and place as you move your
windows over one another.
Now, we also use the same
gorgeous translucent material
for the dock and check out these
beautifully crafted new icons.
So clean and yet so
fundamentally still Mac.
And check out the trash can,
that is a gorgeous trash can.
You wouldn't believe how
much time we spent crafting a
trash can.
[ Laughter ]
So, we also focused on precise
and consistent typography
throughout.
So, from the menus
to the window chrome
to application control is
consistent and clear type.
Now, we know, for our pro users,
often, they really want to focus
on the center on the
screen and not be distracted
by bright menus and
bright docks,
so we also introduced
a dark mode.
[ Applause ]
Lovers of dark.
Yes. So, of course
these changes extend
through to the applications.
You notice here, with
Calendar, this construction
with a common toolbar
and title bar area
that makes the window both
more distinctly recognizable,
but more importantly maximizes
the space available for content.
And we carry this
over throughout the
system to apps like Maps.
Now, we also have a new look
for sidebar apps, like Messages,
you can see it here with the
beautiful translucent material
running top to bottom.
And we extend that look
to apps like FaceTime,
Contacts, and Reminders.
All in all they come
together for a gorgeous
and more usable version
of OS X, the best ever.
[ Applause ]
Next, let's talk about
Notification Center.
Notification Center
on OS X, of course,
adopts the dark translucent
material
and precise type of Yosemite.
It also now, most importantly,
has a new Today view.
So, you get an at-a-glance
look at your Calendar,
your Reminders, Weather, and
more, but most importantly,
you can extend the contents of
Today view with the contents
of widgets and apps that you've
downloaded from the App Store.
Just add them right in and set
up the Today view, that you want
for at-a-glance access
to information.
And that is Notification Center.
[ Applause ]
Next up. Spotlight.
So Spotlight has always
been a superfast way
to launch applications and
find content local on your Mac.
And Yosemite is a
great new interface.
So when you click on
the magnifying glass
on the toolbar you'll
get a big field right
in the middle of the display.
And if you just type
a few characters,
you can launch an app just
like that, or type the name
of a document and you
get great search results
and an inline preview,
it's really awesome.
Now, in addition to these
sources, local to your Mac,
we also tap into sources of
information on the internet.
So for instance, type a few
characters in like Yosemite,
you can get news feed,
information from Wikipedia,
and even maps all
at your finger tips.
I'd like to give
you a quick demo
of the new UI in Yosemite now.
[ Applause ]
All right.
So here is our first
look at Yosemite live.
So we see our beautiful new
typography in our menus,
this gorgeous new dock
and these beautiful icons.
Let's launch an app.
I'm going to start here with
Maps and I want you to observe
that as I scroll the
content of the map,
the way that the title bar
actually reacts its translucency
and color to the content
beneath is just really gorgeous.
I'm going to launch
now another app.
Calendar. So Calendar has
a new look for a week view
but also an all new day view.
And you notice here on day
view, I have all of my meetings
in the day right
here on the left,
and on the right I got
details about my appointments.
So for instance,
here at 2 o'clock,
we have our executive
karaoke outing,
that's going to be big blast.
It's right there.
You want to probably drop in
on that if you get the chance.
So let's take a look
now at Messages.
So Messages, you see this use
of the translucent sidebar
material, how it reacts subtly
to the background is really
nice, and how the contents
of the title bar react as I
scroll content underneath.
It's really cool.
Let's take a look at
Notification Center.
So of course, I have
my notifications here,
but I also have Today view
so I can see my Calendar
at a glance, my Weather.
These are interactive so I
can click, get hourly weather,
clock, interact with stocks for
instance, or even Reminders.
So here I'm supposed to practice
for the demo and I forgot to do
that but it's too late now.
So, we'll send out
one on its way.
Now, of course, I can edit
these widgets as well,
just click the Edit
button down here
and you see widgets available
to me right here on the side.
These are all from apps
that can export widgets.
So I'm just going to
drag out Calculator,
add that in here just like that
or even a third party widget.
Let's drag one of those
in, ESPN SportsCenter.
So right there, I get all my
information right at a glance.
It's really awesome.
[ Applause ]
So next. Spotlight.
So I'm going to click here on
the magnifying glass and, boom,
got a search field right in
the middle of the screen.
I can type just a couple of
characters to launch an app
like our new reminders.
There it is.
It's that easy.
But of course, Spotlight is
great for looking up people too.
So I'm going to look
up Phil Schiller here.
There's Phil.
And you see I have all of
his contact information here,
but I also have matches
on mail from Phil.
Phil and I are planning
a camping trip.
He's a bit of a gear nut
and has something he wants
to try out on our trip.
We also have Events
and Reminders.
So we have here that our Meeting
at the Campsite and-- oh, good.
I see that Jeff and Johnny are
both in on the trip as well.
And I'll tell you, you just have
not had chili by the campfire
until you've eaten it with one
of Johnny's custom
crafted aluminium spoons.
[ Laughter ]
It's a-- it's the diamond
cut chamfered edges
that really make the experience.
So, I'm working on a document
as well to help plan our trip.
Now, there are a lot of ways
of course to find documents,
but one way now is by app.
So this is a numbers document.
I typed numbers and you
see in addition to the app,
I get all my recent documents
that I've opened with that app
and I can access
them right here.
So let's open up my hiking trip.
And here we see that the trip
has planned involved a 16.4 mile
hike and you're being an
operations professional.
Jeff is a big stickler
for the metric system.
And so, fortunately,
Spotlight has my back.
I can just type in
16.4 miles here
and I get an instant
conversion to kilometers.
So that's awfully handy.
We do all kinds of conversion.
They drop that in, fix
that document right up.
[ Applause ]
All right.
Well, that's enough
for my document.
I can also do great searches
like just type a few characters,
bang, I've got Yosemite
entry from Wikipedia.
I've got news from
various sources.
I even have maps right here.
Well, you know, I'm looking to
plan a dinner and maybe a movie
out and now without
even launching an app,
I can just do a look up
for sushi for instance.
And we see I have maps
results right here,
right inside of Spotlight.
And of course, in addition
to map information,
we've got pictures,
great information
from Yelp, it's all right there.
And to wrap it up, I want
to go out to a movie.
You can just type
in Godzilla here.
Oh, there we go, Godzilla.
And you see, I have show times
where it's playing near me
right here in Spotlight as well
as content I can stream from the
iTunes Store, all in Spotlight.
That's a quick look at
the new UI of Yosemite.
[ Applause ]
So next, iCloud Drive.
Now-- OK, intriguing.
So, we all know that
documents in the Cloud,
provides a really convenient
way for working with an app
that works across all platforms
working on the same document.
But now with iCloud Drive,
your Mac in addition will
let you work on those
within the document has,
all of those folders right
accessible inside of Finder.
And in addition to those
apps that are local
to your Mac you can
get a content from apps
that you don't have on your Mac,
so get a contents
from iOS documents.
But even better, you can
store all of your own files
of any sort and organize them
however you wish with folders
and tags and they're
synchronized automatically
across all your Macs.
[ Applause ]
And all of this content
is also accessible
from your iOS devices via the
iCloud document picker right
in app.
And what the heck we're
throwing in Windows, too.
[ Laughter & Applause ]
Next up. Mail.
So, Mail in Yosemite has an
elegant new Yosemite style UI.
But we really focused
on the basics,
reliable synching fast switching
between mailboxes, quick fetches
of your new mail, the basics.
But in addition to that, we want
to address a fundamental problem
with email, which is these
days we so often want
to send large attachments
whether it's videos
or large sets of photos and
we're underpinning one of these,
a message saying that our
recipient's mail server can't
take those large attachments.
Well, we're solving that problem
with the technology
we call Mail Drop.
With Mail Drop, instead of
your message bouncing off your
recipient's mail
server, you can elect
to have the attachment
sent encrypted
and securely via iCloud
separate from the message
and it rendezvous on
the receiving end.
So, if your recipient has a Mac,
they get it just like before.
And if they have another
client, they get a link
to securely download
those attachments.
And those attachments can
be up to 5 gigs in size.
That's Mail Drop
[ Applause ]
So next. Markup.
Have you ever been working on an
email message and you realized
that if you could just
maybe circle something
or write something
on the message,
maybe do a little something,
you can get your point
across so much more clearly,
well, now with Markup you can.
It burns right back in
to your mail message,
and it even works with PDFs.
So if you needed, for instance,
sign a PDF, you can now do
that with your iSight camera
or even drawing your
signature right on the trackpad
and it goes right
into the email message
and you can send on its way.
It's going to be super handy.
Next. Great.
I love it.
Next up. Safari.
We've in Yosemite been
able to pack all the power
of the Safari UI
into this single bar,
and that means you have
more space for your content.
Now, of course, you may
wonder what happened
on my Favorites bar.
Well, of course, you can bring
that back if you want to.
But in Yosemite you
don't really need
to because now your
Smart Search Field
when you click it shows you all
of your favorites right there.
And it's also really
great for search.
So in addition, when
you type to get
in your smart search
suggestions,
you also get spotlight
suggestions right there
in your completion menu.
And this means, you can get
things faster than ever before.
Now, Safari is also more
powerful than ever with sharing.
So now, if you want to subscribe
to an RSS feed on the site,
you can do that right here
and those RSS feed
articles will show up right
in your Safari sidebar
under Shared Links.
And you can also share to
people more quickly than ever,
because Safari lists the
people you've message
with most recently, and with
just one click you can share
a webpage.
Now, Safari is better than
ever as well with tabs.
We now have a tab view that
gives you a bird's-eye glance
of all of your tabs and it
stacks tabs from sites just
like this so you get
individual stacks
for each site that
you're browsing.
Safari is also great
when it comes to privacy.
Safari was the first browser
to introduce private browsing
and now it's easier than ever,
because you can create
a new private window.
And when you do, all the
content within that window
and all its tabs
stay private and all
of your other windows
are unaffected.
It's really handy.
Now, Safari is great when
it comes to standards.
It has WebGL now for
superfast 3D graphics,
SPDY for efficient networking,
and HTML Premium Video.
Now, this enables modern Macs
to efficiently stream video
from site like Netflix
without a plug-in
and the results are awesome.
You get up to two hours
longer battery life
on a MacBook Air
streaming Netflix.
And that's for 1080P video.
Now, Safari has been
set the benchmark really
for energy efficiency
since Mavericks
and its lead here continues.
When it comes to multi-tab
browser energy efficiency,
Safari is without equal.
And when it comes to the
kind of UI manipulations
that are typical in web apps,
Safari is faster than ever.
And how about JavaScript?
Well, take the most complex kind
of JavaScript that's typical
of very rich web applications.
Well, Safari now has a Fourth
Tier LLVM-based optimized
JavaScript Compiler that is the
fastest of any major browser.
And when it comes to
typical website JavaScript,
Safari is in a league
of its own.
So of that is Safari.
And to give you a quick
demo, I'd like to bring
up Brian Crowe to the stage.
Let's give him a big welcome.
Brian.
[ Applause ]
&gt; Thanks Craig.
I'm really happy
to be here today.
So, I'm just going to
dive right into Safari.
Here we go.
It's really great.
And when you go to a website,
you can really appreciate
the new design.
It's simpler and it's
even more powerful.
I can open up the sidebar really
easily to get at my Bookmarks,
my Reading List as well
as my Shared Links.
And when I click into the Search
field, I get instant access
to all my favorite sites.
It's really nice.
So, I'm going to
go ahead and type
in a search for Ansel Adams.
There we go.
And if I hit return,
I can just go
to a regular old Google search.
But, since Ansel Adams
is a common search term,
I get this new Spotlight
suggestion there at the top.
It has a snippet of
information from Wikipedia.
I can read it there, or
if I'd like I can go ahead
and see the entire article
right on the Wikipedia site.
It's super convenient.
Now, if you use tabs,
you're going to love this.
Now, no matter how many
tabs I have opened,
I can smoothly scroll
through them to get at any
of that tab I'm looking for.
It's really nice.
[ Applause ]
So now, sometimes I want to
see my tabs so I can go ahead
and do this and I'll click
on the new Tab View button.
And there you go, a
beautiful bird's eye view
of all my open tabs.
So, I'm going to go ahead
and select this one here.
It's a photoblog with a
bunch of pictures of Yosemite
and there's a couple of good
ones of El Capitan down below.
So, I'll find in
there El Capitan.
And then I'm going
to choose this one.
Now, I want to share it
with Craig so I'm going
to get the high-res image.
Now, sharing couldn't
be easier in Safari.
I just simply click on
the Share button here,
and now I can use the new
recent recipients feature
to address it to Craig.
And here we go.
And with just one click, I'm
ready to send that image.
It's that easy.
So-- But before I send it,
I'm going to add my
two cents to this.
So, I can go here and we
have just the right feature
called Markup.
Now with Markup, I
can edit this image
without ever even leaving Mail.
It's really great.
So, what I'm going to do
is annotate this image
with a nice magnifying
glass a loop.
So, you move it around
you can say
that it magnifies
everything underneath it.
So, I'm going to
place it right here.
And it turns out
that those two specs
on the big granite face there,
they're actually climbers.
It's kind of crazy.
So, I'm going to
zoom it a little more
so you can see it better.
There we go.
So, I can zoom nicely
and place it here.
Now, I want to point this
out to Craig in the mail.
And I can use my trackpad
to draw on the image.
So, I'm going to go ahead
and draw an arrow here.
There we go.
And you notice Markup's smart
enough to recognize the arrow
and make it really pretty.
So now-- now, it's really
easy to add a comment.
And so, check out the climbers.
There we go.
Now, I can have a little
fun with this, so I'm going
to go ahead and create
a cartoon bubble, OK?
I'm not so good at drawing
but Markup's going to help me.
There we go.
So, luckily you can
clean that up [phonetic],
it's better than I am.
So now I can add a caption.
And so, I think I'm
going to appeal
to the inner developer
and all of us.
I'm going to type in
"I hope the rope is,"
wait for it, "multithreaded."
Yeah.
[ Laughter ]
OK. So, I think I've done
enough to this picture.
Time to go.
So, now it's ready
for me to mail
and I can just click like that.
So that's how easy it is
to Markup an image in Mail.
So, those are just a couple
of great new features
in Safari in Mail.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
How about that
parallel programming joke.
You did not see that coming.
Next, something entirely
different.
It's called the Continuity.
So now at Apple, we
believe you should be able
to use the right
device for the moment.
Maybe your phone when you're on
the go, your iPad when you want
to kick back on the
couch, or maybe your Mac
when you're trying to
get some work done.
But we also want the transitions
between these moments
to be absolutely as natural
and seamless as possible.
Now, our Continuity features
start with something simple
and that's AirDrop,
because now AirDrop works
between iOS and the Mac.
[ Applause ]
It's really convenient.
But now we have something
that we really take it
to the next level and
that's called Handoff.
So, it turns out now that when
you're working on your Mac,
your devices around you
in proximity are aware
of each other and aware
of what you're up to.
And so, if you want to pick up
where you left off on your Mac
and your iPad, your iPad
is prompting you right
in the lower left of the screen.
Just swipe up and you
can pick up working
on what you're working on
your Mac right on your iPad.
And this--
[ Applause ]
This works in the other
direction as well.
So, let's say, you're
composing an email on your phone
and you walk up to your Mac.
Well, your Mac will
notice what you're doing
and prompt you right
on the dock.
You click it and you
can pick up finishing
that message right on your Mac.
[ Applause ]
Now, we've been able to take
this same proximity awareness
and make the process of
creating a hotspot easier
than ever before.
So now, if you're using your Mac
and you're away from a network
but your phone is nearby, when
you go up to your Wi-Fi menu,
your Mac, actually without any
configuration ever have been
done on your phone, sees
your phone and prompts you
so you click it and it
automatically sets up a hotspot.
You never type a
password and you're
on the network that easily.
[ Applause ]
And this works even
if your phone is
across the room sitting
in a handbag.
You just never have to touch it.
Now, the next that we really
wanted to handle is SMS.
Now, we all love iMessage.
We can continue our
conversations seamlessly
from device to device but
then we have these green
bubble friends.
And, you know, they have
inferior devices and they insist
on sending us messages,
and we don't want
to hold it against them.
But the problem is that
those messages don't show
up on our other devices
until now, because now--
[ Applause ]
-- your phone is able to access
or relay to automatically
and transparently send your
messages between devices.
Now, believe it or not,
we're able to do the same
thing with phone calls.
So now, when you
receive a phone call,
your Mac gives you caller ID
and you can even accept the call
and use your Mac
as a speaker phone.
[ Applause ]
And believe it or not, this
works even if your phone is
across the house in a charger.
You never have to miss a call.
Well, now that your
Mac is all phone savvy,
it's also a great way
to dial the phone.
So, if you're in Contacts and
you want to dial a number,
you can do it right there.
And even on a webpage, you
see a number you want to call,
you can call it right
from your Mac.
So I want to give you--
[ Applause ]
So if you're up for it, I'd
love to give you a demo now.
All right.
So, let's check out Continuity.
And we're going to
start with Handoff.
I'm going to pick
up my iPhone here.
And I was composing an email
about our karaoke night.
Does anyone want to--
you know, I'm by my Mac,
so let's use my Mac here.
And you notice my
Mac actually is aware
that I was using my phone.
So with a click, I
bring up that message
to right where I left of.
Does anyone want to
go-- and you know,
to give these people
some inspiration
about what they might be able
to experience at karaoke night,
you just summon a picture from
last year's karaoke event.
[ Laughter ]
Now, that ought to
get them going.
So, I'll send that
one on its way.
Now, of course, this works
in the other direction.
Oh, it looks like Andrea
is up for some karaoke.
And he sent me a URL just to a
good place to go for karaoke.
So, I can pull that up here.
Now, if I want to show
this page to a friend,
maybe pick up my iPad, you
notice as I look at my iPad.
Let's put that up on the screen.
There at the bottom is Safari.
I just flick up and it takes
me right to where I left off.
It's really amazing.
[ Applause ]
Next up, phone calling.
Hold it one sec.
Well, this is from my mom.
Now, she is surely
wants to grill me
about newest Fourth Tier
LLVM Compiler in Safari
but this is not the right time.
I know you'd all love to
hear from mom but I'm going
to scrape-- I'm sorry.
[ Laughter ]
I'm sorry.
She's a wonderful,
wonderful woman.
But that's-- this is my space.
[ Laughter ]
So, but, you know, I would
like to show you how we
can make phone calls.
And so, I can dial
from web pages.
So, for instance, if I wanted
to go dial a phone number
like this one right
here, I could just select
and hit it just like this.
And you notice I get an option
to call right here
inside of Safari.
But, you know, I wanted
to make a phone call
to a new Apple employee
that's joined in.
So, it's something we
do from time to time.
So, let me just bring up this.
Here we go.
A little welcome call?
Let's give him a WWDC welcome.
So, let's have my Mac
dial via my iPhone.
I talk to people like him
all the time of course.
This is very normal for me.
[ Phone Ringing ]
Hello?
Wow. Hey, it's
Craig Federighi here.
Hey, how are you doing?
This is Dre.
Hey, Doctor, you're on
speaker phone with via my Mac
with over 6,000 amazing
developers here at WWDC.
We all want to welcome
you to Apple.
Hey, thanks Craig.
I love a big audience.
I want to thank everybody there
for creating such
an amazing apps.
Yeah, they have
created some amazing apps.
By the way, I'm
glad you called.
I hear Tim gets in pretty early.
What time should I
show up for work?
[ Laughter ]
If you want to beat Tim into
the office, it'd be about 4:30.
But, I think, you
know, orientation--
new employee orientation
starts at 9:00.
So and you don't want to
miss the free t-shirts
so I'd shoot for 9:00.
Sounds good.
I can't wait to get to work
with the team at Apple.
Well, Dre, it's been
great chatting with you.
I'll see you around campus.
Thanks, Craig.
Talk soon.
All right, bye.
[ Applause ]
And, that's continuity, so
Yosemite, a beautiful new design
with notification center
with the new Today view
and customizable widgets,
spotlight with fast search
and access to all kinds of
great sources of information
on the internet, a
new iCloud Drive,
mail with great new features.
Safari, faster and
more elegant than ever.
And of course, continuity.
It's a wonderful new
release, Yosemite.
And it's available to you
developers here today.
[ Applause ]
Now, everyone else will get
it in the fall and believe it
or not, it will be free.
[ Applause ]
Now, we're doing something
a little unusual this summer
as well which is we're
having a public beta program.
So, if you're a non-developer
and you want
to help us improve Yosemite,
you can sign up on the web
and you can receive access
to Yosemite betas
throughout the summer.
That is OS X Yosemite.
I think you're going to love it.
I'm going to hand
it back to Tim.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
Thank, Craig.
It's a really terrific release.
I'm just glad I'm
in the beta program.
[ Laughter ]
Next up is iOS.
[ Applause ]
We've now sold well over 800
million iOS devices and each
of the categories of devices has
set its own significant sales
record in the past year.
iPod Touch has passed
100 million units.
iPad has passed 200
million units.
And iPhone has passed
half a billion units.
This is incredible.
But what's even more impressive
is how many new customers
to Apple that iOS
devices has brought to us.
Over 130 million customers
who bought an iOS device
in the past 12 months was
buying their first Apple device.
[ Applause ]
Now, many of these customers
were switchers from Android.
They had bought an
Android phone by mistake.
[ Laughter ]
And then had sought a better
experience and a better life.
[ Laughter ]
And decided to check
out iPhone and iOS.
Nearly, in fact, nearly half
of our customers in China
in the past six months
switched from Android to iPhone.
This is incredible and of course
that better experience
is our devices in iOS.
And iOS 7 took that
experience to even higher level.
The customer sat with iOS
7 is really off the charts.
Change wave recently
measured it at 97 percent.
These are customer sat
ratings that no one gets.
It's really enormous.
Now, one of the reasons why
customers say they love iOS is
that we make available
our software updates
for the OS available to as
many customers as possible.
And, if you look at what
has happened with iOS 7,
our latest release,
almost 9 out of 10 people
in our install base are running
our latest operating system.
[ Applause ]
Now, this is in stark
contrast to Android.
[ Laughter ]
If you look at their latest
release, less than one out of 10
of their customers are
on their latest software.
And, if you look at a
broader group, over a third
of their customers
are running a version
of Android from four years ago.
That's like ancient history.
[ Laughter ]
Now, that means that these
customers are not getting great
new features.
They're not able to
run your latest apps.
And, they don't get
security updates
that they may need to stay safe.
And, this is particularly
important for Android
which dominates the
mobile malware market.
[ Laughter ]
No wonder experts are
saying things like this.
Android fragmentation
is turning devices
into a toxic hell stew
of vulnerabilities.
Now, fortunately, iOS hasn't
had this kind of issues
because we do everything we can
to make our updates available
to as many people as possible.
So, we could not be
happier with iOS 7
and the momentum of iOS devices.
But, we are not standing still.
Today, we're announcing iOS 8.
[ Applause ]
And, iOS 8 is a giant release
and it's really two
stories not one.
It has great end user features.
But, it also has
incredible developer features
so you can extend your
experience and build apps
that you couldn't do before.
We'd like to get started with
describing it with talking
about the end user features.
And, to do that, I'd
like to bring Craig back
up to the stage.
Craig?
[ Applause ]
I missed you guys.
So, what? Let's talk
about iOS 8.
Now, iOS 8 of course builds
on the design of iOS 7
with enhancements for
both iPhone and iPad.
And, let's start with the phone.
Now, in iOS 8, we've
refined notification center.
But, what I really love are our
new interactive notifications.
So now, if you get a message
like this, just pull down
and you can reply from
right where you are.
[ Applause ]
You don't have to leave
the app you're in.
And this works for all
kinds of notifications.
If you get a calendar event
for instance, just pull down
and respond and it works
on the lock screen.
So, you can just swipe
across in the lock screen.
You get those action
buttons tapped
and you've dealt
with it right there.
Now, in iOS 7, we gave you
quick double-tap access to get
at your most recent apps.
Well now, you can also use
that same double tap to get
at the people you communicate
with most frequently.
It's really handy.
And, in iOS 7, we introduce
this great Tab View in Safari.
Well, we're bringing a great
Tab View to iPad as well
with this bird's eye
view of all of your tabs.
And, Safari also picks up
the Side Bar that we love
in Yosemite with access to your
bookmarks, your reading list
and your shared links.
Now, we've made managing your
mail easier than ever before.
So now, if you're reading a
message, you want to remember
to get back to it so you're
going to mark it on red.
We can do that with
just a single gesture.
And, if you want
to flag a message,
you can just pull across,
there's a flag option.
But, if you pull
all the way across,
you can delete with
just a gesture.
But the piece I love the
best is what we've done
with composing messages.
Have you ever found
yourself composing an email
and then you really wish like
you get at something else
in your inbox maybe
for that reply?
Well now, you can.
Just swipe that message
down and you have access
to the rest of your mail.
[ Applause ]
So, I'd like to give
you a demo of some
of these great iOS
8 enhancements now.
So, here we are on
our iOS 8 lock screen.
And, if I receive
a notification,
it looks like I happen to
get one just right then,
I can swipe across and you see
I have action so I can accept
or decline this meeting
right here.
And, of course, I'm
going to use the device,
if I'm in here maybe playing
some music here on iTunes radio,
I might get a notification.
And, if I do get notification, I
can just swipe down on it, too.
So, here's one, just swipe down.
Now, I get access
to my keyboard.
I can type right there.
Now, this works great for
third party apps as well.
So, for instance, looks like
I got tagged on Facebook,
I can like it right here with
an actionable notification.
And, sometimes, you
receive notifications
that you just really don't
want deal with right now
and you can just flick
those away like that.
That's really handy.
Now, we've made getting at
people easier than ever before.
So, if I just double-tap
my Home button,
so I have all the people I most
recently communicated with.
I swipe to the side and I have
access to all my favorites.
If I tap on one, I have controls
here to give them a phone call,
iMessage them or even
FaceTime right here
with just a double-tap
on the Home button.
It's really handy.
Now, I want to show you some
of the enhancements
we made to mail.
Let's go take a look an
iPad actually this time.
So, here we are on iPad.
I'm going to launch mail.
Now, I have a number
of unread messages here
so let's work our
way through them.
Here's a message from Open
Table with a dinner appointment.
And, you notice that the
reservation is actually called
out right here on the top.
Mail has actually given me an
intelligent suggestion here
to add it to my calendar.
I can tap Add and just
like this, it lets--
it prompts me to fill out and
add an event to my calendar.
That's really handy.
Now, sometimes, you
get a message like this
where you're going to have
to do some thinking about it.
Maybe get back to it later.
Well now, with just a single
swipe, I can mark it as unread.
It's really cool.
You can also flag really easily.
So, this is a message
I want to flag.
Just flick it across and flag.
Now, here's a nice message.
I don't know who this fellow is
but he says great collaboration.
You and Johnny have really
come together really well.
Let's take a look at that one.
Oh, dear God.
[ Laughter ]
Well, this would be a good time
to demonstrate our
quick delete feature.
So, I can drag all the way
across and delete at a glance.
I'm certain that
message won't haunt me
on the internet for
years to come.
So, let's talk about composing.
I got a message here from a
friend who's visiting in town,
who's looking for
a good restaurant.
So, I'll start replying
to this message.
And, I'll say, let's see--
check out and then, you know,
actually I got a
good recommendation
from another friend
here in my inbox,
so I'd like to get to that now.
Well, I can just swipe
this draft down like this.
Go right into another
place, another message
in my inbox, tap
out a selection.
That looks like exactly
what I want to send him
so I'll just copy that.
And now, with a tap
at the bottom,
I restore my draft
just like that.
I can paste and send
it on its way.
I think we're all going to
love doing mail this way.
That's a quick look, few
enhancements to iOS 8.
[ Applause ]
So, let's talk about Spotlight.
And of course, Spotlight
is a super convenient way
to search in your device.
You just pull down one
on your home screen
and you can execute
these searches,
find things like launching
apps or find an email message.
But now, with those same things
we showed you in Yosemite,
with Spotlight Suggestions,
you can get it so much more.
You can search for apps and find
matches of apps that you don't
yet have on the App Store.
You can search for
points of interest
and get Wikipedia
entries and directions.
You can search for news,
search for restaurants, songs,
not just in your own
library but also on iTunes.
And, when you search for a
movie, you can get results both
for theaters nearby as well as
content available for streaming.
And, when you search
inside of Safari in addition
to your great Google
Search suggestions,
you can also get a
suggestion at a glance
for the answer you're
looking for right
from Spotlight Suggestions.
So, that is the new Spotlight.
Next, the keyboard and the
technology we call QuickType.
Oh.
[ Laughter ]
So, prior to iPhone, this
was the state-of-the-art
in smartphone typing.
But, iPhone changed all of that
with the introduction of Touch.
And, we've been able to do
so much more like access
to special characters or
alternate character sets,
special keyboard layouts, even
handwriting and dictation.
But, underlying it all have
been the language models
under autocorrect.
Well now, in iOS 8,
QuickType supports predictive
typing suggestions.
So, as you type,
you get suggestions
for the next words you
might want to type,
and you can tap things out
faster than ever before
and it's incredibly smart.
So, it's context sensitive.
For instance in messages,
if someone asks you,
do you want to go for
dinner or a movie?
It's going to suggest
dinner or a movie.
[ Applause ]
And, it's personalized.
It learns how you type
to different people
in different apps.
So, maybe you're communicating
with a co-worker and it's going
to say, well, the meeting was
canceled, rescheduled, moved.
These are kind of formal terms.
But now, if you're
communicating with someone else,
we have a different
communication style,
you might get the meeting was
epic, awesome or a snoozer
because it learns how you type.
And, when it does, it does
so in a way that's always
protecting your privacy.
All that learning is done
local to the device and none
of your keystrokes
leave the device.
Now, QuickType has
great language models
for all of these languages.
[ Applause ]
So, I think we're all going to
be typing a whole lot faster.
Next of course, continuity.
You get all the great
continuity features.
So now, on your iPads,
you can pick
up where you left
off on your iPhone.
You can set up an
instant hotspot
with no configuration
on your iPad.
You can receive your
messages on your iPad
and when you receive a call
from someone going like this,
you can pick it up
right on your iPad.
It's really great and
that's continuity.
Next up, Messages.
So, Messages is the most
frequently used app on iOS.
And, in iOS 8, it's
better than ever.
So, when it comes
to group messaging,
we have some great enhancements.
You can now name your threads.
You can add or remove people
from a conversation underway.
[ Applause ]
And, if you've ever been on
one of those noisy threads
that just keeps buzzing
in your pocket, well,
you can do not disturb on a per
thread level and you can choose
when to leave the tread.
This is pretty important.
[ Applause ]
Now, you also can
share your location
with people in a conversation.
And, if they've shared
their location with you,
you can see it from write
with inside messages.
And you also have really
great at a glance view of all
of the pictures and attachments
that are shared on any thread.
But one feature that I really
love is our new Tap to Talk.
You just hold your finger
down on the microphone button
and then you can just
swipe up with your finger
when you're done talking
and send what you said.
And it's really great for
video messaging as well.
So to give you a quick demo
of the all new messages,
I'd like to bring up Greg
Joswiak to the stage.
Jos?
[ Applause & Cheering ]
&gt; Thank you Craig.
It's fun to be up here
to be the first one
to show you what a rich
and powerful platform
for communication
messages has become.
So let's get right into it.
So I got a message here
waiting from my friend
and co-worker, Kim Vorrath.
So I could just slide
that of course as usual.
It goes right into my messages.
And what I see here
is I have a thread
between me, Kim, and Craig.
But what I have that's new
in the upper right hand
corner is this Details button.
So if I tap it, it gives
me all kinds of information
about participants
in the message.
For one, Craig and Kim decided
to share their location with me.
So Craig of course
is up here with us
in San Francisco while Kim is
working hard back in Cupertino.
Thanks Kim for that.
One of the things I
can do is add contacts.
I can add people to this
conversation as we go,
but I can also choose
to share my location.
So if I just tap and Share
My Location, I can choose
to share my location for an
hour for the rest of the day
or I can keep sharing it until
I stop somewhere in the future.
But what's really convenient
is this Do Not Disturb button.
How many times you've
been in one
of those super chatty
group conversations
that your phone is
just continuing
to buzz over and over?
Well now, I can just
choose to Do Not Disturb
that particular thread and
not get my phone buzzing.
So, I'm going to find
that useful with Kim
and Craig, I know that for sure.
Or I can even Leave
this Conversation
with just a single tap.
What's also convenient
is the fact
that I have all the
attachments, all the photos
from this conversation
all in one place.
So they still appear in line
in the thread but now instead
of trying to find that picture
by scrolling, scrolling,
scrolling, they all come in
one place here in the thread,
so very, very convenient.
So let's go back to
that conversation,
Kim had asked me how it's going.
Well, I have lots of
ways to reply to her.
I could tap out which just
a few taps and, you know,
use my predictive
keyboard, a message.
But it's even cooler that I can
now do an audio or video message
to her with just a swipe.
So I'll send back an
audio message to her.
Hey Kim, I'm just hanging
out here with about 6,000
of our closest friends.
Having a good time while
Craig takes a much deserved
break backstage.
Slide up, sends the
message just like that.
Super easy.
And I can do the same
thing with a video message
or even with a selfie.
So I'm going to dare
a selfie here.
It's all down the camera button.
[ Laughter & Applause ]
Not my best look.
Let's see what Kim
has to say about that.
So, I can-- see, I got an
audio message from Kim,
all I have to do is tap the play
button and hear the message.
&gt; Impressive Jos.
You've totally mastered
the duck face selfie.
Well, I'm glad she likes it.
So it's super duper easy
to do this sort of things.
You notice that it said it
would expire in a couple
of minutes 'cause you don't
want to have this clean this up.
Audio and video messages
can take up space
so it self-destruct
unless you choose
to keep-- whoa, what's this?
So Craig should be backstage
but he apparently has sent me a
message and it looks important.
So if you don't mind I'm
going to play it back.
And I can play it back in line
even with a video message here.
Jos, we got a serious
situation developing back here.
I can't control this.
These are not going to work.
Bryan, you got
to do something.
I got it.
Jos, I'm going to need
you to buy some more time.
[ Laughter & Applause ]
&gt; Needless to say, hair
like that doesn't come easy.
So while he's dealing with
his crisis backstage--
oh look, I've actually got
an audio message from him.
Now, what's really cool
is I can actually listen
to audio messages and reply to
them from the lock screen simply
by raising the iPhone to my ear.
Hey Jos, we got the
crisis contained back here.
I'm good to go, so wrap it
up whenever you're ready.
And that's easy to
listen to a message.
I can reply to it the same way.
Craig, it's good to hear
that you survived the
great hair crisis of 2014.
I'll get things wrapped up here
and we'll get the
show back to you.
Lower it and the
message is sent.
Super easy.
So--
[ Applause ]
So that's the all new Messages
app, super easy, super powerful.
Send a message through
just a swipe or even just
by raising it to your ear.
So thank you everybody.
[ Applause ]
OK. So next up, iCloud Drive.
So, of course, iCloud
documents work great
across a single app
on your iOS devices.
But now, with iCloud Drive,
you also have a great way
to work across applications.
So say you're in an app here
like Sketchbook, you can bring
up your iCloud Drive panel
and open documents directly
from other applications
like a compatible document
inside of GoodReader.
And when you open it up in that
document, in that application
and edit it, those edits
are saved right back
to their original locations.
So you don't end up with all
of these different
versions and copy problems.
Now, of course, you also have
access to all of those documents
on your Mac and on
Windows as well.
So that's iCloud Drive.
Next up, something you weren't
expecting from me, Enterprise.
Now it turns out that iOS--
yeah, they got one Enterprise
guy over there, I know.
So iOS is a huge hit
in the Enterprise.
In fact, 98 percent of
the Fortune 500 uses iOS.
And we're going to
get the last two.
And it's in part
because of these great
iOS-tailored applications.
But it's also because of the
amazing array of technologies,
both technologies that
applied to all of us
in protecting our
privacy and security
but also Enterprise
manageability features
that we've added to
iOS over the years.
Now, one of them
that we just released
in the last few months I think
is emblematic of our philosophy
of the Enterprise, and that's
the Device Enrollment Program.
Now traditionally, if you
go to work at a company
and they want you to give you
a device, they actually have
to take the device they give
you, rip it out of its box,
connect it to some PC,
image it with software
to configure, it's a big pain.
But now with the Device
Enrollment Program,
you can actually get
your iPad or iPhone
in its original shrink wrap box.
And when you open it up, it'll
automatically configure itself
for your Enterprise,
setting up all of your mail
and getting your mail
messages, automatically setting
up your calendar, and even
downloading all your Enterprise
apps, it's that simple.
Well now, in iOS 8, we
continue our focus on security,
productivity and management.
iOS 8 has expanded
data protection.
So you get passcode protection
of all the major data types
including third-party apps.
We have a Per-message S/MIME
and we have a great productivity
feature I think we're all going
to like called VIP threads.
So now, there's a thread
you're on or message you send,
and you want to get notified
on the lock screen whenever
there's a reply on that thread,
you can get that
with just a tap.
Now we also have Automatic Reply
for Exchange, for Out of Office,
Free/Busy information
in calendar.
And we support third-party
Enterprise document providers
in addition to iCloud,
integrated right
in to iCloud capable
applications.
Now we also improved
our management--
yes, the Enterprise
guy back there.
[ Applause ]
So, we also extend
our management
to include managed
books and PDFs,
and this is of course especially
valuable for education.
So those are just a few
features for Enterprise.
Now, something that we all
care a lot about, Health.
Whoa.
[ Applause ]
So, developers have created a
vast array of healthcare devices
and accompanying applications,
everything from monitoring
your activity level,
to your heart rate,
to your weight,
and chronic medical conditions
like high blood pressure
and diabetes, but up to now
the information gathered
by those applications
lives in silos.
You can't get a single
comprehensive picture
of your health situation.
But now you can with HealthKit.
HealthKit provides
a single place
that applications can contribute
to a composite profile
of your activity and health.
And HealthKit comes
with a corresponding
application, Health.
And with Health, you can
monitor all of your metrics
that you're most
interested in your activity.
But not just that, you can
use third-party applications.
Now we carefully
protect your privacy
so you have total control over
which applications have access
to which part of your
healthcare information.
But you can for instance provide
different activity, weight,
heart rate information
to the Nike app.
And Nike is working to
integrate HealthKit,
so they use that information
to help you in your pursuit
of your personalized
fitness goals.
Now, we're also working
with the Mayo Clinic,
innovators in healthcare.
And with their integration
with HealthKit, they're going
to be able that when a patient
takes let's say a blood pressure
reading, HealthKit
automatically notifies their app
and their app is automatically
able to check whether
that reading is within
that patient's personalized
healthcare parameters
and thresholds.
And if not, it can contact
the hospital proactively,
notify a doctor and that
doctor can reach back
to that patient providing
more timely care.
Now--
[ Applause ]
Now we think this is going to be
really important for healthcare
and the CEO of the
Mayo Clinic agrees.
He says that, "We believe
Apple's HealthKit will
revolutionize the
health industry--
how the health industry
interacts with people.
We're proud to be
at the forefront
of this innovative technology
with the Mayo Clinic app."
We agree. Now we're also
working with leaders
in healthcare applications
like Epic systems.
Now they provide the technology
that enables hospitals serving
over 100 million Americans.
And so now with their
integration with HealthKit,
patients-- these leading
institutions will be able
to get closer in
sharing their information
with their doctors
and that is Health.
[ Applause ]
Next up, Family Sharing.
It's the easy way to
share what's important.
Now when I was a kid,
the refrigerator was the
center of family sharing.
Our refrigerator looked just
like this except the
kid who had gray hair.
But we've now in iOS made it
that easy to set up your family
on their iOS devices and once
you've set up your family
as a family unit,
you automatically get
to share photos with the shared
photo stream, to share calendars
with your family, to
share reminder list
and automatically
configure things
like with permission,
Find My Friends.
And find your kid's devices,
which is something I do
about every other day.
It's really handy.
Now, of course, we're also used
to in the home sharing
physical media.
But increasingly, our media
is in the form of songs
from iTunes, movies,
books, and apps.
Well now, with Family Sharing,
you can get it not just your
purchases but the purchase
of all the members
of your family.
[ Applause ]
You just click right
through and download.
And this is for up
to six family members
who all share the
same credit card.
And it works great for
kids as well and not just
because they can make
purchases on your credit card,
but in fact because when
they do make a purchase,
they get prompted ask
you for permission.
And you automatically get
messaged on your device.
[ Applause ]
And that's Family Sharing.
Next, Photos.
We all take a lot of photos
increasingly with our iPhones
and we share them with
whatever device we have handy.
Well now, we're bringing
together photos with iCloud
so that every photo you
take are available to you
on all of your devices.
[ Applause ]
We're not only preserving the
common organization edits you do
to all of your photos for your
consistent iCloud photo library
but your device actually
has access to more photos
in the cloud than it can
physically store locally
so you can get them
all wherever you are.
Now of course, if you
have these many photos,
you want great search and
so we now on iOS 8 Photos,
we give you great search
suggestions for instance
of locations, photos taken
near where you are right now,
photos taken a year ago today,
photos taken in your home,
but we also give you search.
And so that search lets you
match on things like location,
time, and also on albums
that you've set up.
Now, we also help you
perfect your photos
with great new Smart
Editing controls.
So we have special smart
controls for light and color
and also for things like
auto-straightening and cropping.
I'd like to give you a demo
of our new Photos app now.
[ Applause ]
All right.
Let's take a look at photos.
So here I am in my large
cloud photo collection,
and I have great search here,
so I have all my suggestion
but I can also start typing
and you notice I get matches
on location and time period.
But also an album, so here
I have beach day with Mandy.
And I can tap right in there,
look through these nice
photos, let's take a look.
Those are some good ones.
Now that's a photo that
I think has potential
but it's really quite dark
and kind of washed out.
Unfortunately, we have these
great smart editing controls
that I can use to fix it up, so
I'm going to bring up our levels
and you also have levels
for light and color
down there at the bottom.
I'm going tap on light,
and I get this great
smart light meter.
Now I can just drag this across
like this and it lightens
up the photo really nicely,
so I dial that in
just the way I want.
But what's happening under
the hood is really amazing.
You notice that to achieve
the lightning effect,
it brought brightness
and contrast up, exposure
and highlights down
and shadows up based
on detailed image analysis of
what would achieve that effect.
Now I could go in and
I could manually try
to tweak those parameters like
have that level of control
but I don't need to because
it does such a great job
and I also have that control
for color, so I can just drive
up the color for instance, bring
out the sky and the skin tones
and I look at the difference
of what we've been able
to achieve before, after,
it's really awesome.
[ Applause ]
Now what's really
great is that my edit
of course immediately went
up to my cloud photo library.
And so they're available
to all my devices,
so let's take a look at my iPad.
So here's my iPad.
Now I'm going to go on to my
favorites album, and we notice
that right now in favorites,
I don't have that picture
because I didn't favorite it.
But now that I've
made those nice edits,
the picture is looking great,
I think I'll make it one
of my favorites, I'll just tap
on my iPhone on a little heart
and you notice that it appears
automatically here on my iPad,
so I can go into that
photo right here.
Now we have those same editing
controls tailored for iPad,
so I'm going to go in to
do a crop and do a kind
of extreme close up crop
here like this, hit done
and of course these changes
are going to go up live
to my iPad photo library and
it go right across to my phone.
[ Applause ]
So of course you may be
wondering what about the Mac?
Well good news, we are
working on a new grounds
up photo solution for the Mac
built with iCloud in mind,
and that's going to be
shipping early next year but I'd
like to give you
a sneak peek now.
All right.
So let's take a look
at photos on the Mac.
As you see, I get beautiful
buttery scrolling here.
I have my moments right here,
I can pinch out if I want
from moments to collections
and all the way out to years.
I can scrub through my photos
like this even in year view.
If I find a photo I like,
just let go and zoom right in.
You watch as I magnify
this photo, the interplay
with the title bar,
it's really gorgeous.
I'm going to go ahead and browse
through these a little bit.
Now here's a photo
that looks really
like it's got some potential
but it could use
some brightening up,
can have the same
kinds of adjustments.
You notice here at this
light and color meters, well,
I can just close this control,
so we can watch what happens
in real time as I make
the lighting adjustment.
And notice how some of these
are going up and some are going
down to create this
effect, it's really great.
I can do the same with color,
let's just boost the color,
bring out the sky, bring out the
skin tones, and it's that easy,
the new photos app, to really
create beautiful images.
And that's a quick preview
of photos coming to Yosemite
in the future and to
the new photo solution
with iCloud photo
library coming with iOS 8.
[ Applause ]
So now on iOS 8, you
get all your photos
in your organization crush
your iOS devices and soon
with your Mac and via
the web, Windows as well.
Now this is all your
photos and also your videos.
And these are in
their original format
and their full resolution.
Now this uses your
iCloud storage,
so your first 5 gigs are free.
And we have some great new
affordable plans coming,
where you get 20 gigs for just
99 cents a month and 200 gigs
for 3.99, so we can all afford
to get all our photos
safely up in the cloud.
That is photos.
[ Applause ]
So, a great set of major
features coming to iOS.
But of course, there's
always a whole lot more
than I have time
to talk about here.
I do want to hit on just two
more quickly, and one is Siri.
Now, we have-- if you take
your phone and you plug it
in for instance in the car,
you can say, "Hey Siri,"
and start talking to
Siri without having
to even touch your phone.
And we have song
recognition with Shazam.
So now, if you just start up
Siri and there's a song playing
around you, it will
tell you what it is
and you can even purchase it
right there from within Siri.
Siri also now supports
streaming voice recognition.
So as you talk, you can
see what it's recognizing.
It's more responsive than
ever, and we have support
for 22 new dictation languages.
Finally, in China we now
have greatly improved maps
with vector based maps and
turn by turn directions.
We also have support for
lunar calendar which is great
for holidays and birthdays.
Improved Chinese predictive
input and improved weather data.
So that is a look-- thank you.
[ Applause ]
So that's a look at the
consumer part of iOS 8.
To tell you the other
half of the story,
I'm going to hand
it back to Tim.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
Thanks, Craig.
Amazing new features, and if we
ended the keynote now it would
be a giant release.
But there is a lot more.
The second part of the
story is what iOS 8 provides
for developers.
And extending your capability to
make even more incredible apps
and apps you could
not create before.
Now, all of these apps are
delivered via the App Store.
The App Store now has over 1.2
million of your apps on it.
This is a phenomenal number.
And the marketplace around these
apps is unbelievably vibrant,
300,000,000 people visit
the App Store every week.
And these people aren't just
browsing, they are downloading.
They've now downloaded
over 75 billion apps.
These are mind blowing numbers.
Now, what we want to do is
make the App Store even better.
And so, we're rolling out
a number of new features
on the store, starting with
we're adding an Explore tab
to help users find the app
they're looking for more.
So you can browse through
categories and subcategories.
We're adding top
trending searches
to make search even better.
It's great to see WWDC
at the top by the way.
We're making-- finding
your search even better
by making it faster by adding
a continuous scrolling list.
We're adding related
searches to make it easier
to find exactly the
app you're looking for.
And with the new
Editor's Choice logo,
users can find the best apps.
Also for the first time,
we're giving the developers the
capability to form app bundles,
so users can buy multiple apps--
[ Applause ]
I do read your emails.
So users can buy multiple apps
at a discounted price
with just one tap.
Also, we're introducing
app previews,
so developers can
make short videos--
[ Applause ]
-- so developers can make short
videos of some great features.
And the users can make
certain it's an app
that they would want.
We're also introducing for the
first time today a new service,
a new beta test service
called TestFlight.
[ Applause ]
Developers can invite users
to beta test their app
and get the results right in
TestFlight, and it's all free.
Now, there are many more
features at the App Store
and you hear about
them through the week
and in the afternoon sessions
but we are really investing
a ton in the App Store.
It is a huge release.
Everything will be
available in the fall.
Now, that brings us to the SDK.
And for those of you
that are not developers,
the SDK is a Software
Development Kit
that enables developers to
make all of the amazing apps.
This release is the
biggest release
since the launch
of the App Store.
And it will give developers
the capabilities and tools
to make things that
you haven't dreamed of
and to push to a
whole new level.
And to tell you all
about the SDK,
I want to invite my colleague,
Superman, back to the stage.
[ Applause ]
This is clearly some kind
of endurance training
thing Tim is doing to me.
So, with this year's SDK, the
team has done just an unreal job
with over 4,000 new
developer APIs.
Now, I want to start
with something
that I think is perhaps
most profound
and that's Extensibility.
So with Extensibility,
applications
from the App Store will be
able to extend the system
and offer services
to other apps.
[ Applause ]
Now of course, one
of the reasons we're also
comfortable installing
so many apps from the App
Store are iOS' security model.
Apps are isolated
inside of sandboxes
where they can access their
own data but can't get
at your personal information
or mess with other apps
without your permission.
Well, the handle
Extensibility in an iOS way,
we wanted to build on the
same sandboxing model.
So now extensions live inside
an application's own sandbox
with access to its own data,
but other applications can reach
out by way of iOS'
security mechanisms,
talk to that extension.
That extension can even
project UI right back
in to the originating app.
Now this enables
some great things.
For instance, in addition
to the systems built-in
sharing options,
an app like Pinterest can
offer share sheet to Safari.
And if you look at
actions, for instance,
an app like Bing could offer
translation right inside
of Safari accessing the web
pages web content right there.
Now we're also supporting photo
filters inside the photos,
and enabling third parties
to define their own
document providers that work
within the iCloud
drive-enabled application.
Finally, we're enabling third
party apps to define widgets
that can now go in
Notification Center.
[ Applause ]
I think it feels
like time for a demo.
So let's start with
photo filters.
So, we're back here in photos
and I've got a nice
photo here of a flower.
And I'm going to go ahead and
edit and you notice an addition
to the options here at
the bottom of the screen,
we have at the top left
this extensions button.
I'm going to click
that, tap that rather.
And you notice I have
several extensions available,
one from VSCO Cam and
one from Waterlogue.
I'm going to select Waterlogue.
And now the Waterlogue extension
is able to run right here
in the context of photos to
manipulate my photo bringing
up their own UI, deliver this
beautiful water color effect
to my photo, and when I'm
done, it's right back inside
of my photo album,
it's that easy.
[ Applause ]
Then next let's take
a look at widgets.
So I'm going to just pull
down Notification Center.
I have my existing widgets
here in my Today view.
Did you notice an addition
to my widget is down here
at the bottom it says
"One New Widget Available"
because I've downloaded
an app recently
that contains a Notification
Center widget.
So I'm going to tap Edit.
And you notice its SportsCenter.
So I can tap the plus
next to SportsCenter,
position it where I want, I'm
on my widgets in my Today view.
Tap Done, and now
I have information
on my favorite sports
teams right here inside
of Notification Center.
Now this works great
on iPad as well.
Let's take a look at iPad.
So iPad, I'm going to bring
down Notification Center.
And you notice I have this
interactive widget from eBay.
So, I'm bidding on a guitar and
apparently I'm being outbid.
So I can now write inside of
notification, take advantage
of the interactivity widgets.
I can tap and bid
and just like this,
I can submit a leading bid all
inside of Notification Center.
Now to wrap it up, I want to
show you extensions in Safari.
I'm going to bring up Safari.
Use our great new tab view.
It's a page I've been looking
at here with some information
on a beautiful guitar and I'd
like to learn more about it but,
unfortunately, you notice
the text here is in Japanese
and I do not read Japanese.
Fortunately, I have a Bing
translation extension,
so I can just bring
up my action sheet.
And you notice down here in
the second row, Bing translate,
I'm going to tap on
that and Bing is able
to translate this web
page right in line.
Look at that.
[ Applause ]
Now for our extension's
grand finale,
let's put that on
my Pinterest board.
You see Pinterest has
an extension right here.
I'm going to tap on that and
this is actually able to bring
up a UI defined by Pinterest
where I can select my board,
maybe select my guitar's board.
Now the Pinterest
extension is accessed
to the underlying
web page, so I can--
let me slide through
the different photos
on the page till I find
the one I want to share.
That's it.
Tap and I pinned it.
And that's a quick look
at extensions in iOS 8.
[ Applause ]
Now there's one important kind
of extension that I did fail
to mention and that's
the ability
to install system-wide
third party keyboards.
[ Applause ]
So now if you have special
keyboard you want to use,
you can install those in iOS.
And by default, those
of course run inside
of the most restrictive
sandbox with no network access
because we want to make sure
to protect your privacy.
But if that keyboard requires
or you want to grant it ability,
it can ask for access
to the network
to provide extended
functionality.
We put those controls
in your hands.
That's extensions on iOS 8.
[ Applause ]
Next up, Touch ID.
From the moment we
introduced Touch ID,
developers were excited
about the potential
and there's no question why,
Touch ID has been
extremely popular
and people authenticating
in their devices.
If you look at passcode usage
on iOS before Touch
ID was less than half.
On iPhone 5s 83 percent,
people love using Touch ID.
And now, third party
apps can take advantage
of Touch ID as well.
[ Applause ]
So Touch ID protects logins
and user data and it works
by unlocking Keychain items.
So it identifies successful
fingerprint matches
but it always keeps the
fingerprint data itself
completely protected inside
of the Secure Enclave
in the A7 processor.
The fingerprint information
is never exposed
to third party apps or the rest
of the system for that matter.
It's very secure.
That's Touch ID.
Then next, Cameras.
We're providing Camera APIs
from manual control of exposure,
white balance and focus.
And we've enhanced the PhotoKit
API with faster performance,
the ability not just to
read but also to write
to the photo library and this
is now your cloud photo library
and perform non-destructive
edits.
It's really great.
Now, we talked about
the great HealthKit API,
but now we'd also have HomeKit.
[ Applause ]
Now, there are a lot of great
home automation devices coming
on the market these days and
they have companion apps,
things like lights and
door locks, webcams,
garage doors, and thermostats.
But, you know, each of them
have their own application
and they end up defining
their own network protocol,
their own security mechanisms.
Well, we thought we could bring
some rationality to the space.
We started working
with the leaders
in home automation devices.
And we've come up with HomeKit
with a common network protocol
that has secure pairing
to ensure
that only your iPhone
can open your garage door
or unlock your door.
And in addition to being able
to control individual devices
in your home, with HomeKit you
can group devices and changes
in the scenes and then with
Siri integration you can say
something like, "Get ready
for bed," and be assured
that your garage door is
closed, your door is locked,
the thermostat is lower,
and your lights are
dimmed, that's HomeKit.
[ Applause ]
Next, CloudKit.
So today, if you're a developer
and you're writing
an application
and it needs a web component,
well, you end up really having
to write two apps in one.
In addition to the writing in
the client side using Xcode
and our frameworks, you have
to write the server
side of the app.
You have to write server side
app logic, you have to deal
with authentication, asset
storage, database storage,
search, even push
notifications and then you got
to pay somebody to host it all.
Well, now, with CloudKit,
CloudKit takes
over the cloud part
and provide you
with a client side
programming model
that lets you access iCloud
authentication storage,
search and more.
And when it comes to paying,
CloudKit is effectively
free, with limits.
So, CloudKit scales the
data allocated to your app
and bandwidth based on the
number of users using your app.
And this goes all the way up
to granting you free a petabyte
of assets, 10 terabytes
of database
and all the bandwidth you
can constructively use.
That is CloudKit.
[ Applause ]
Next, I want to move on to
something huge in the area
of 3D graphics, and
it's called Metal, so--
[ Laughter ]
As you know, OpenGL is
the standards based way
for high performance 3D graphics
on iOS, giving you access
to the power of the
A7 processor.
But increasingly, if you look at
what goes on in the performance
of the game, in addition to what
the game wants to accomplish,
OpenGL ends up being a
thick layer of overhead
between the game
and the hardware.
Well, now, we have Metal.
And Metal dramatically reduces
that overhead giving
the game near bare
to the metal access
to the power of A7.
The results are stunning up
to 10x faster draw call rates.
Now, in addition to these
dramatically reduced overheads,
you get access not
just to graphics
but to the compute
power of the GPU,
and Metal supports
pre-compiled shaders
and efficient multithreading
so you can always get the
most out of the processor.
Now, we've been working
with the leading providers
of gaming engines
on mobile platforms
and what they've been able
to accomplish with Metal
in just a few weeks
is truly stunning.
Let's start with EA and the
work they've done taking their
console level title Plants vs.
Zombies and bringing it to iOS.
They're able to put over 1.3
million triangles on the screen
at a time and do depth
of motion, effects,
depth of field effects that they
could never imagine achieving.
In fact, they're using their
Frostbyte console engine
that they thought could never
come to mobile and now it can.
And let's look at Crytek.
Crytek was able to bring their
console-level geom cache to iOS
and they were able to get
up to 4000 draw calls
per frame going here.
This is up to 10x, the kind
of performance they
were seeing previously.
Now, to show you live what
can be done with Metal,
I'd like to bring up the
founder of Epic Games
to the stage, Tim Sweeney.
Tim, come on up.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
We've had the opportunity
to work with Metal
and to illustrate some
of the possibilities,
we created a Zen Garden.
Now this environment was built
in Unreal Engine 4
on a high-end Mac.
And now thanks to Metal, we're
running it on iPad in Realtime
with full fidelity
and performance.
Metal's efficiency enable us
an order of magnitude increase
in detail making it possible
for developers like us
to create a new generation
of vivid
and interactive 3D experiences.
Now Josh Adams is the
programmer who wrote much
of the code that's running.
Josh, can you explain
what we're seeing here?
Yeah, sure.
First of all thanks to Metal
support for precompiled shaders,
we can have a huge
variety of materials
without a load time impact.
And our first stop we'll
check out this cherry tree
where I can drag on the
screen to paint the petals
on to the tree and they
start falling to the ground.
There are about 5,000 petals
here being physically simulated
and I can interact with them
by touching on the screen
to blow wind through the area.
All right, next up we
have a Koi pond filled
with hundreds of fish.
Metal has freed up enough
CPU time and we can have each
of them running their own
artificial intelligence
which you can see here as
I drag around the water.
And there's a few more fish
here than a real Koi pond
but since Metal lets us
do it, we figured why not.
And of course every Zen garden
needs some sand to rake.
So I go over here I can
rake any pattern I want
into the sand here.
Now artist love that they
can make an effect like this
without needing a
programmer like me to make
that one-off effect for
a drop core reduction
or other optimizations.
And for our final
moment of Zen walk
over to this water fountain.
Now I can tap on it, pour out
some water which then turns
to a couple hundred butterflies
but of course not
going to stop there.
So I can touch the screen
to call more of them to me
and then guide them
around the area.
So there are about 3,500
individually animated
and rendered butterfly
meshes here.
Now I had to keep telling the
artist to turn the numbers up
and up because they do not think
it was going to be possible.
Pretty cool huh?
[ Applause ]
Thanks.
There are thousands of objects
being rendered here and it seem
that we couldn't have
dreamed of building prior
to Metal delivering
a tenfold increase
in rendering efficiency.
To have this level of
graphics capability on iPhone
and iPad now is a
stunning breakthrough.
We're proud to have been a part
of it and of course we'd love
to share this with you.
So as soon as iOS 8 is
available we will be making
that Zen garden available
in the app store for free.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
Its amazing and that was--
it's easy to forget on an iPad.
Its incredible graphics
they were able to achieve
and I think we are all
feeling very Zen now.
So that's very good.
So that's Metal.
Now I want to move
from high-end 3D gaming
to casual gaming in Sprite Kit.
We introduced Sprite
Kit last year at WWDC.
And it's been a big hit
with people building casual
games on the app store.
And now this year we've
really enhanced Sprite Kit
with some things that make
your casual games just
that much more fun.
We have support for light
sources, field forces,
per-pixel physics that
actually allow your objects
to automatically interact
with proper physics based
on their drawn shapes and
even inverse kinematics.
And now also this year
for the first time
on iOS we're bringing SceneKit.
[ Applause ]
Now SceneKit is a
3D scene renderer
and now it's been enhanced
as designed for casual games
with an integrated physics
engine, particle systems
and support for scripted
actions.
So these are two great solutions
for casual games on iOS.
Next, Xcode--
[ Applause ]
Now Xcode is the tool set we use
to build all applications
for the Mac and iOS.
And Xcode is in fact one
of the most popular
pro-apps on our platform.
The last version was
downloaded 14 million times.
It's unbelievable.
Now of course central to
Xcode is the language we use
to develop our apps,
Objective-C.
Now Objective-C has served
us so well for 20 years.
We absolutely love it.
But we had to ask ourselves
the question what would it be
like if we had Objective-C
without the baggage of C?
[ Laughter ]
Well we did more
than think about it.
We have a new programming
language.
[ Applause ]
The language is called Swift
and it totally rules [laughter].
Swift is fast.
It is modern.
It is designed for safety.
And it enables the level of
interactivity and development
that you've never
seen on the platform.
When it comes to
speed, Swift is great.
Compare Python a popular
scripting language
with Objective-C, when it
comes to something like,
let's say complex object sort.
Objective-C is a lot faster.
But Swift is faster still.
And take something like
RC4 encryption extremely
computationally intensive.
Python gets utterly crushed
in this particular benchmark.
And Objective-- but
look at Swift.
Now Swift is also modern
with features like Closures,
Generics, Type inference,
Multiple return types,
and Namespaces.
[ Applause ]
You know how many
people at home are going,
what the heck are these
guys talking about?
[ Laughter ]
With Swift you're able to
reduce a common pattern
that you might see in your
Objective-C code like this.
And reduce it to
something as simple as this.
And Swift defines
away large classes
of common programming errors
they just aren't possible.
Now, Swift is completely native
to Cocoa and Cocoa Touch.
It's built with the
same LLVM compiler
as Objective-C using the same
Optimizer and Autovectorizer.
And it has the same ARC
memory management model.
And the same runtime which means
that your Swift code can fit
right alongside your Objective-C
and your C code in
the same application.
[ Applause ]
Now Swift also enables a level
dynamism and interactivity
in development that
we've never seen before
for the feature we
call playgrounds.
To demonstrate Swift and
playgrounds in action,
I'd like to bring to
the stage Chris Lattner.
Come on up Chris.
[ Applause ]
Thank you Craig.
I am thrilled to be here
and to be the first person
to give you a taste of Swift.
Let me show you how fun
and interactive it is
to write Swift code.
This is the Swift playground,
as I start typing I get
an immediately response.
It is actually running
my code as I type it
and displaying the result
in the sidebar to the right.
Of course, Swift
user type inference
and has powerful string
processing capabilities
which make it as easy to
use as a scripting language
without sacrificing
any performance.
Swift was designed from
the ground up for Cocoa
and Cocoa Touch, so of course
I have their full power
at my fingertips.
Now, I can build
anything with Swift
from a social media
application all the way
up to a high-performance,
3D game using Metal.
But today to keep it simple,
I think I'll write a
simple casual 2D game.
Let's start by using NSImage.
Let's start by using
NSImage to load a resource.
As you can see here, I've--
the playground sees
I've loaded an image,
I can ever see it right
here from within Xcode.
Now, Swift is loaded with
high-end features like Generics
that allow me to get a lot
done with very little code.
Here you can see I'm
using an array of strings
and using the functional map
algorithm to apply closure
to every element which allows
me to load an entire list
of images all with the
simple line of code.
Now, all these resources of part
of this game that I'm working on
and one piece I still need to
finish up is the flight path
for the blimp that we have.
Now this is a simple loop
that computes the position
for the blimp overtime
as my game plays.
And in addition to seeing
individual values Swift
playgrounds even allow me to
visualize the entire history
of a value overtime as
my application runs.
And so now I can immediately see
that this equation will
cause my blimp to slowly sink
as the scene plays out.
But I think I can do better
and that's not exactly
what I'm looking for.
So I can change the code and
I get an immediate response.
Simply by changing the equation
the blimp will now rise and fall
as the scene plays out
which is a lot more
of what I'm looking for.
So, now that we have this the
way we want, we can take this
and copy it and let's go to
the game that I'm working on.
It's right here.
Now, this is a playground
just like before.
But here, I have a game in the
code written using Sprite Kit.
Now, you can see our blimp
going left and right,
straight across the scene.
And, I can try out
the flight path
that we just developed
simply by pasting it in
and getting the immediate
feedback I'm looking for.
Now, the blimp is rising and
falling just like I wanted.
Because Swift enables
such powerful interactive
and dynamic programming
experiences,
it makes it really easy
to try out new things.
And, just by adding
a few lines of code,
I can enable Sprite Kit's per
pixel collisions, field forces
and lighting effects gaining a
much more interesting result.
Now, Swift Playgrounds even
give you full power over time.
And, with this timeline at
the bottom of the screen,
I can go forwards and backwards
through the execution
of my game.
So, I can really see
those effects in action.
You can see the balloons
interacting with each other
and with the blimp
just like that.
Playgrounds give me
unprecedented power
to see my app in detail and
give me full control when I want
to refine and polish
my application.
But, of course, Swift
works great with Xcode
and runs great on iOS.
So, let's now jump and see what
the finished product looks like.
Here we go.
And, this is the game
that we just built.
It looks pretty great.
Now, as Craig told you earlier,
we've also brought
Scene Kit to iOS.
With Scene Kit, it's super easy
to build a 3D version
of our game.
And, that's just a quick
taste and quick look at Swift.
I think you guys are going
to absolutely love it.
[ Applause ]
Thank you very much.
So, that's Swift.
It gives you access to all
of Cocoa and Cocoa Touch.
So, you can build everything
from a simple example,
like you saw there with Chris,
to the most powerful
applications you can imagine.
And Swift is going to be ready
for primetime out of the gates.
It comes with complete
Xcode support with indexing,
code completion and debugging.
And, there's a Swift language
guide available to you now
in iBooks along with complete
reference documentation.
And, when iOS and OS X
are available, day one,
you can submit apps written
in Swift to the App Store.
That is Swift.
[ Applause ]
So, as you've been able to see,
iOS 8 is a huge developer
release
and a great end user
release with features
like the new QuickType keyboard,
Tap to Talk in Messages, Health,
family sharing and
great new photos
with iCloud photo library.
But, it's also an
unprecedented developer release
with technology like
extensions, Metal and Swift.
That's iOS 8.
It's going to be available to
those of you here in Beta today.
[ Applause ]
And, you guessed it, available
to everyone else in the fall
and it will run on
all of these devices.
That is iOS 8.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
Great job.
It's an incredible
set of features
and an incredible release.
It's been a fun morning.
You can probably
see that from us.
I hope you've enjoyed
it as well.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
This morning, you've seen
Yosemite, the future of OS X
with an incredible new
design, amazing new features
and engineered to work
seamlessly with iOS.
You've seen iOS 8, the
biggest release of iOS
since the introduction
of the App Store.
It's huge for developers and
massive for everyone else.
And perhaps, more importantly,
you've seen how our
operating systems, devices
and services all work
together in harmony.
Together, they provide
an integrated
and continuous experience
across all of our products.
And, you've seen how developers
can extend their experience
further than they've
ever done before
and how they can create powerful
apps even faster and more easily
than they've ever been able to.
Apple engineers platforms,
devices and services together,
we do this so we can
create a seamless experience
for our users that is
unparalleled in the industry.
This is something
only Apple can do.
You've seen a few people
on stage this morning
but there are thousands of
people that made today possible.
And I'd like to take a
moment before we depart
and recognize them.
Would everyone from Apple stand
up that had something to do
with bringing today--
making today possible?
Stand up, don't be bashful.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
And, there's thousands more back
in Cupertino who were watching
and I want to thank them, too,
and from all over the world.
It's a privilege of a lifetime
for me to work with all
of these incredible people.
I hope everyone has
a huge conference.
Enjoy the week.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]