Betsy Langowski: In 2017,
the iPhone X was released.
Linking against the iOS 11 SDK
let your app take advantage
of the beautiful new display.
This year, we are introducing
the iPhone XS,
the iPhone XS Max,
and the iPhone XR.
While iPhone XS has been
completely redesigned
from the ground up,
the screen size is the same
as an iPhone X,
so this video will focus on
the iPhone XS Max and iPhone XR
with their all-new resolutions.
If your app primarily uses
UIKit frameworks
and you've already adapted
your app for iPhone X,
you should be in great shape.
All you'll need to do
is link against iOS 12
to take full advantage
of these great new phones.
If you need a refresher on how
to update your app for iPhone X,
and now iPhone XS Max
and iPhone XR,
check out the video,
"Building Apps for iPhone X."
This video walks you
through making sure
the TrueDepth camera
doesn't occlude your UI,
ensuring your UI elements
are positioned
away from the Home indicator,
and other common adjustments
that you may need to make.
While most of the heavy lifting
is done for you by UIKit,
you may still need
to optimize your app,
and this video provides guidance
that is great for iPhone XS Max
and iPhone XR,
as well as iPhone X.
Let's talk about
a couple of things
that we've made better
for you this year
to make updating your apps
for iPhone XS Max
and iPhone XR a breeze.
If you watched
"Building Apps for iPhone X,"
you remember the importance
of testing in landscape mode.
One of the places this is
critical is in collection views.
I've built this really simple
sample app,
which is just
a collection view controller,
embedded in
a navigation controller,
which is embedded in
a tab bar controller.
There are offsets
to space out the cells,
but otherwise this is just
using the defaults.
At first glance, in portrait,
it looks really good.
But in landscape,
this app has a problem:
the cells on the left side are
behind the TrueDepth camera.
In order to address this,
the collection view's
section inset reference
needs to be set
to the safe area,
instead of
the default content inset.
This can be done in code,
and when the iPhone X
was first released,
that was the only way to do it.
But since this app
was built with storyboards,
in more recent Xcode,
we can make this change
directly in Interface Builder.
With the collection view
selected in the storyboard,
we can select
the Size Inspector
and change the Inset From value
to safe area.
Now when I build
and run my app,
my collection view avoids the
TrueDepth camera in landscape,
no code changes needed.
Auto layout is the Cocoa
and Cocoa Touch layout system.
If your app uses auto layout,
you'll find that
most of the work of optimizing
for new screen sizes,
like those on the iPhone XS Max
and iPhone XR,
is done for you.
If you aren't taking advantage
of the great benefits
you get from auto layout,
now is definitely
the time to update,
because this year
we dramatically improved
its performance.
Here are some examples
of iOS 11's auto layout
performance in gray
compared with iOS 12's
auto layout performance in blue.
Look how much less time
moving trees take in iOS 12
compared with iOS 11.
Using auto layout in your app
just got a lot faster.
If you'd like
a behind-the-scenes look
at how we did it, check out
the WWDC 2018 video,
"High Performance Auto Layout."
One change for iPhone XS Max
and iPhone XR specifically
is in the behavior of
UISplitViewController
in landscape.
It's a lot like how it works in
Mail in portrait mode on iPad.
Take a look at this very simple
test app I made
running in the iPhone XS Max
simulator.
My master view with four cells
comes in with
the press of a button
and is dismissed similarly.
My app got this behavior
automatically
on the new hardware
because I set
a displayModeButtonItem.
This behavior will also be set
if you use presentsWithGesture.
Let's take a peek at
what this looks like in code.
In my App Delegate,
I've gotten
the UISplitViewController's
displayModeButtonItem
and set it
as the left bar button item
in the navigation bar
for my customer to tap.
So now I'm opted-in
to the behavior
on the iPhone XS Max
and iPhone XR.
I'm also setting
presentsWithGesture to true.
This makes it possible
for my customer
to access the master view
with a swipe.
This is optional,
and it can be set to false
if needed for your app.
One thing to note.
If you've relied on setting
preferredDisplayMode
to automatic,
this is now
the automatic behavior.
If you've done
some customization
and you'd like to opt out
of this behavior,
simply avoid using the
displayModeButtonItem entirely
and set presentsWithGesture
to false.
You can also set
preferredDisplayMode
to allVisible.
OK.
Let's move on to talk about
some common pitfalls.
Some apps may have
a background image set
to specific dimensions,
or certain assets pinned
to a spot on the screen.
This is most common in games,
but your app may use
a technique like this
for a variety of reasons.
If your app has set
a scaled image,
when you run it on an
iPhone XS Max or iPhone XR,
you may notice your content
is scaled incorrectly.
Unlike apps that use
standard UIKit frameworks,
while these phones
are still new,
you may need to do
a little bit of special-casing
and tell your app --
or the framework
your app is using --
about the new screen.
The display dimensions
for both
the iPhone XR
and iPhone XS Max
are 414 points wide
by 896 points tall.
As you're building your assets,
keep in mind that
the iPhone XR is a 2x device,
and the iPhone XS Max
is a 3x device.
So in pixels,
the resolution of iPhone XR
is 828 by 1,792 pixels.
The resolution
of the iPhone XS Max
is 1,242 by 2,688 pixels.
Caution!
You should only hard-code
screen dimensions
if your framework
absolutely requires it.
While this can make
your game or similar app
work right out of the gate,
you should avoid
using these methods
unless you absolutely need to.
Please let UIKit
do the work for you
and use auto layout instead.
While it may be tempting
to force your app
to behave in specific ways
on various hardware models,
you should avoid
making special cases
per piece of hardware.
This will take time away from
developing new features,
and it's largely redundant work.
Additionally,
when your code is running
on a model of phone
it doesn't recognize,
unexpected problems can occur.
This can hurt your customers
if you aren't able
to update your app right away.
If you made a special case for
your iOS app to run on iPhone X,
now you have to redo
all your hard work
for iPhone XS Max
and iPhone XR.
Even if you need to set
dimensions within your app
to accommodate
graphical needs,
do not search for a device model
and gate behavior
behind that string check.
You should never
write code that reads like,
"Is this an iPhone X?
Do A.
Else? Do B."
This is a great opportunity
to make sure
you have adopted
safe-area insets
universally throughout your app
and save your future self
a lot of time and effort.
Now is also a great time
to be really diligent about
how you're branching your code
when you're looking
for feature availability.
Just like the other iPhones
you already support,
such as iPhone SE
and all iPads,
iPhone XR doesn't support
3D Touch and dual cameras,
so it's important that you don't
rely on those behaviors.
Let's use 3D Touch
as an example.
The Home app is a fantastic
example of an application
that uses 3D Touch
on supported devices
but provides
the full feature set
on devices that do not
support 3D Touch,
or for users who may have
turned it off.
Checking whether a device uses
3D Touch is simple.
Let's take a look
at some sample code.
First, check at launch
whether or not
the device supports the feature,
as shown highlighted here.
However, remember a user
can turn off 3D Touch
while your app is running.
Therefore, you should also
do this check
as part of your implementation
of the traitCollectionDidChange
delegate method.
In either case, branch your code
to use an alternative
such as
UILongPressGestureRecognizer
for devices that don't support
3D Touch,
so that the full feature set
is represented for all devices.
When in doubt, make sure
your code can handle nil
and is robust enough
to gracefully fail
when getting back
something unexpected.
For most apps,
there won't be much work
for you this year
to support iPhone XS,
iPhone XS Max,
and iPhone XR,
especially if you already
are optimized for iPhone X.
If you need any support,
there's lots available
from the iPhone X videos
and this year's
WWDC 2018 sessions.
Check out
the related content,
and you can find more
on developer.apple.com.