Apple Watch Series 4
includes significant
enhancements
for designers and developers.
Series 4 watches have new
displays with larger dimensions,
along with new APIs
and improvements in performance,
enhancing your ability
to deliver rich information
and actions to the people
who use your app.
You'll want to take these
new dimensions into account
as your create
or update your app.
Series 4 watches are larger
than watches in previous series.
They come in two sizes, measured
on the exterior of the case:
40mm and 44mm.
Previous series of Apple Watch
are 38mm and 42mm.
And the display dimensions
of these watches
measure 272 by 340 pixels
on 38mm watches,
and 312 by 390 pixels
on 42mm watches.
The displays of Series 4 watches
have grown significantly,
measuring 324 by 394 pixels
for 40mm,
and 368 by 448 pixels for 44mm.
Not only is display larger,
but the border around it
is thinner,
bringing more attention
to interactive elements,
and making the information
feel richer and more immersive.
You'll want to account
for all display dimensions.
Your app should deliver
the same information
and actions to the user,
regardless of screen size.
As you consider your layouts,
notice that the display
of the 40mm Series 4 watch
is actually very similar
in dimension
to the display of the 42mm
watches of previous series.
The new 40mm watch
has a display size
that is 12 pixels wider
and 4 pixels taller.
Looking across the case sizes,
40 and 42mm watches
sit in the middle of a spectrum.
If you target your screens
layouts here,
you should then ensure
your layouts scale down
to 38mm dimensions,
and up for 44mm dimensions.
The Design Resources
on developer.apple.com
contain assets and templates
to get you started
in designing for all 4 sizes.
Be aware that some watchOS
interface elements
scale with the watch size.
The templates contain
extensive collections
of these elements,
organized by watch size,
to ensure that your mock-ups are
as pixel-precise as possible.
So now let's talk about
how these new displays
impact the layout
of your screens.
The most notable difference
of the new display is its shape.
Like iPhone X,
Apple Watch Series 4
has rounded corners,
creating a symmetrical look
within the curved corners
of the case.
WatchKit will assist you
in the presentation
of text and controls,
so that your UI appears
in an optimal location
in the viewport.
WatchKit elements will adapt
to the new displays.
At the top,
your app's status bar
will account for
the rounded corners.
As in previous versions
of watchOS,
the clock will appear
on every screen,
and your app can use
the title area
to provide a helpful heading
or title
describing the purpose
of the screen.
Both of these elements
will be indented,
and this indentation should
create left and right margins
that extend vertically through
the display of content
in your app.
These are
System Minimum Layout Margins.
Graphic elements
and button backgrounds
should extend
beyond these margins
and run nearly edge to edge,
up to the one pixel margin
that runs by default
on either side.
Text should align
to the left margin,
extending from the left edge
of the text in the status bar.
To account for the corners
in scroll views,
there are clear areas
at the top and bottom
of the content area.
These are known as
scroll clear areas,
and they ensure that text
and buttons
are nudged fully into view
when the user completes
a scrolling action.
For example, a button at
the bottom of a scroll view
will settle in the safe area
above the clear area.
If you're using a full-screen
SpriteKit or SceneKit scene,
you'll want to use
the margins and insets
to nudge your content
into view.
The best watch experiences
are simple and glanceable,
so you may have views
within your app
that are intentionally
single-screen
and should not scroll.
For example,
if you want to make sure
that a button rests
in the clear area,
rather than getting nudged up
by the system,
you can do so by setting
an attribute in Xcode.
In the attribute inspector
for the view,
you can select
Fixed to screen edges,
and this will ensure that
the content within that view
will not scroll.
Now let's talk about
updating your app
for Apple Watch Series 4.
Your app will run
on Series 4 watches
even before you recompile it
for watchOS 5.
It will be displayed at 38mm
dimensions on 40mm watches,
and at 42mm dimensions
on 44mm watches.
It will be centered
in Series 4 displays.
And from a user point of view,
your app will appear
and behave predictably.
Recompiling your app
for watchOS 5
will allow your app to occupy
the full width and height
of the new display.
As long as you've implemented
your WatchKit elements
relative to their containers
rather than at fixed widths,
your app will expand to fill
the additional screen space
on Series 4 watches,
and this will feel much more
immersive and engaging
to your users.
If your app contains
a full-screen SpriteKit
or SceneKit scene,
you'll want to make sure
that text and controls
in your scene
are rendered correctly
on Series 4 watches.
You should access the
System Minimum Layout Margins
to ensure that your content
is inset properly
from the left and right edges
of the screen,
and the Content Safe Area Inset
information
to ensure that text and actions
settle appropriately
in the content area of the watch
when the user scrolls.
Series 4 introduces new haptics
that correspond with the
rotation of the Digital Crown,
creating a more tactile
experience across Apple Watch.
By default,
haptic detents, or taps,
are produced when the
Digital Crown is rotated.
So common user interactions,
like scrolling
or selecting an item
in a picker,
will deliver tactile
feedback to the user.
You should evaluate your
app's experience
with this new haptic feedback
on Series 4 watches.
Users will become accustomed to
a consistent tactile experience,
so if your app coordinates
events in the UI
with Digital Crown rotation,
you'll want to make sure
that those UI events
line up with these
new haptic effects.
Next, let's discuss the new text
styles introduced in watchOS 5,
and the implementation
of Dynamic Type
on Series 4 watches.
In watchOS 5,
the Dynamic Type Library
was expanded to include
four new larger sizes.
Large Title,
and Titles 1, 2, and 3
provide more ways to ensure
that content and actions
are glanceable
on the watch screen.
As you're implementing
and testing these styles,
remember that there
are different
default content categories
that correspond
to the watch case size.
Small is the default
category for 38mm,
Large for 40mm and 42mm,
and XLarge for 44mm.
While watches may start
with different default settings,
each offers the same spectrum
to accommodate a wide range
of user settings.
Adhering to these styles
will ensure that your app
is delivered predictably
to all users.
Finally, let's discuss
enhancements
related to the visual assets
in your watch project.
You can now streamline
the production of graphics
by using PDFs, allowing for
high-resolution scaling
across device sizes.
If you prepare your graphics
with a scale factor of 2
and save them as PDFs,
you can create a single file
for usage across all
four watch sizes.
When you bring this PDF asset
into Xcode,
place it in the Asset Catalog
of your Watch project,
drop the asset in
the Universal 2x box.
And then, in the
attribute inspector,
adjust the Auto Scaling
property to Automatic.
This scales your graphics down
by 9 percent for 38mm displays,
and up 10 percent
for 44mm displays.
One last note: To account
for the UI of the 44mm watch,
there are two new
app icon sizes.
These new icons will be used
for the short look notification
and the Home screen icon.
Guides and dimensions
for these icons
can be found in the templates
in the Design Resources,
which have been newly updated
for Apple Watch Series 4.
There's also a thorough
introduction
to watchOS 5 features
in the video,
"What's New in watchOS"
from WWDC.
This video,
the Design Resources,
and the Human Interface
Guidelines can be found
at developer.apple.com.