Hi, my name is Lauren Strehlow.
I'm a design evangelist,
and we're going
to be talking about
designing
for subscription success.
Subscriptions are the fastest
growing business model
on the App Store.
But why is it almost every time
you're ready to sign up
for some awesome new service,
or subscribe to some new,
exciting content,
this is the feeling
that you get?
That’s because
it's all too common
for subscriptions to feel
complicated, confusing,
and justtake too long
to sign up.
So for a great user experience,
make your subscription
effortless, transparent,
and engaging.
In other words,
make it easy to subscribe.
Let's focus on each
of these principles
to improve the user experience
and design
for subscription success.
What does it mean for your
subscription to be effortless?
First, it means people
should know
that you have
a subscription.
They shouldn't have to look
for how to sign up.
So be visible, get out there,
and don’t be shy!
Let people know that you have
a subscription
and ask them to sign up.
One approach would be to persist
a subscribe button
in you app’s interface.
So here,
in the New York Times app,
they persist -- tastefully --
a subscribe button
that is visible across
all of their articles,
and this is done really well.
It's not annoying or pushy
because it families together
with their interface.
Don't present your subscription
like an a pop-up ad
or notification,
because ads and notifications
are intended to be dismissed,
and you don't want people
to dismiss your subscription.
Another way to be visible would
be to present your subscription
when a person has shown interest
in a feature or piece of content
that you offer
through your subscription.
This is the datingapp, HER,
and as a category,
dating apps have been
in the subscription business
for a long time
and they do it really well.
So let's just say you are
swiping through a few profiles
and accidentally pass on someone
who is cute,
so at that moment
you attempt to rewind.
Well, the app HER tastefully
presents an option to subscribe,
because the rewind feature
is a part of their subscription.
It's an appropriate time
to present this offer
because you've shown interest.
And HER does a great job
presenting the values
of their subscription offer
right here with this beautiful,
light animation.
So make it easy
for people to sign up,
make sure they know you have
a subscription.
Be visible, so you canchoose
to present your subscription
when a person has
expressed interest
or tastefully persist
an option to subscribe.
But no matter which option
you choose,
all subscription apps
should include a way
to sign up from Settings
or Account from within the app,
because that's an intuitive
place where people would go
to look to sign up.
Also, to make your subscription
effortless,
you need to remove friction.
Friction is asking
for too much effort
by asking for
too much information
and requiring too many steps
to sign up.
But how do you know
when you've asked for too much?
Well, this data should help.
This graph represents a snapshot
of one month of data
from the top three entertainment
video streaming apps in the U.S.
While their names
have been removed,
the important data here is
the clicks to conversion ratio.
A subscription flow
with three clicks
led to a 61 percent
conversion rate,
and a subscription flow
with four clicks
led to a 48 percent
conversion rate.
However, nine clicks...
the conversation rate drops
significantly to seven percent.
Now, while this is
just a sample,
it's clear that you should
only ask
for what is absolutely necessary
because quite literally,
less is more.
Less clicks,
less friction,
will equal more conversion
and more subscribers.
Focus people
on singing up first.
Personalization,
favoriting,
and requesting additional
personal details
can all wait until after someone
has signed up.
By being visible
and removing friction,
your app’s subscription
will be effortless
and easier for people
to subscribe.
Next, let's talk about
your subscription
being transparent
because transparency
is the best policy,
and you need
to provide clear terms,
so people understand
what they are signing up for.
Strive to be glanceable;
in one view
and in just a few seconds,
people should be able
to clearly understand
what your subscription offer is
and how to sign up.
When making
your subscription offer,
always include a concise
value proposition,
a strong call to action,
a place to login
for existing subscribers,
the ability to restore
a purchase
if someone has a new device,
and a place to sign up
that includes
clear terms and pricing,
and always offer multiple tiers,
because somebody may want
to sign up for a day,
a week, a month, or two years,
so try offering three or four
different subscription tiers
to figure out what works best
for your audience.
And be sure to follow
App Review guidelines
to ensure that your
subscription offer
is within policy.
People have to have the ability
to easily see
terms and conditions
when they're asked to subscribe.
The MLB At Bat app does
a great job
and offers all of this
in one easy-to-understand,
glanceableview.
And all of this is important
because most of us
are signing up on our phones.
So please,
keep it simple.
By providing clear terms,
people will be able to make
an informed decision
to subscribe.
All right,
I saved the best for last.
Your app needs to be engaging
from the start
before people subscribe.
And the best way to engage them
is through experiencing your app
and all of its
wonderful contents.
Being able to experience
and try before you buy
is a part of how we all make
purchase decisions today.
From trying on clothes
to attending an open house
or even test driving that car
before you buy or lease it.
People are able to experience
before they have to make
a purchase decision,
and the same principle
applies to your app.
There are three ways to engage
people through experience
and that will make it easier
for them to subscribe.
First is a free trial,
where people can try out
the entire app for free,
for a limited time.
Free trials work best
for established brands,
when people already have an idea
of what is included
with the subscription.
So if you have
an established brand,
a free trial is a great way
to let people engage
with your app
and experience it
before they subscribe.
You can also make the majority
of your app available for free
and offer a premium feature
as a subscription.
For example,
in the app Sleep Cycle,
you can use most of the features
for free,
but the Trends feature --
shown here --
is only available to people
who have subscribed.
Sleep Cycle makes it really easy
for people to sign up
right from here,
and this is a great technique
to offer people
a peak of the content
behind this blur,
as it gives people an idea
of the kind of data
they would see as a subscriber.
Third, sampling content
is a great way
to engage people
through experience.
Sampling helps people understand
what type of content
they would have access to
as a subscriber,
and this works well
for a majority of apps.
In the New York Times app,
you're able to read 10 articles
free per month
as a non-subscriber.
This is a great sampling
experience
because the New York Times
lets people have control
over what they sample,
and it allows people
to find the content
that they're interested in.
In turn, that helps them
better understand
the value
of the overall subscription.
The objective here is to let
people experience
and become engaged
with your app's content,
and that content
and that experience
will make it much easier
for them to subscribe.
So no matter which option
you choose,
make sure it works
for your audience.
Think about their current
user experience
and the type of content
that they currently have
available in your app
and how adding a subscription
could impact
that current experience.
So design your subscription
to be effortless
by being visible and reducing
friction to sign up,
be transparent with your terms
and pricing,
and engage people
before they subscribe
through a rich experience
of your app.
Then, it'll be easy to sign up.