Hi, I am
Lawrence from the NFC team.
Welcome to this Core NFC update.
We have got a new feature
for Core NFC this year
that will not only enhance
the NFC experience,
but also greatly simplify
the process of handling NFC tags
within your applications.
If you are new to Core NFC,
I recommend that you watch
the "Introduction to Core NFC"
video released last year.
With the new background tag
reading feature,
the iPhone is able
to automatically read NFC tags
and deliver them
to the appropriate apps.
The mechanism
is able to perform
the necessary app launch
or bringing the application
to the foreground state.
We are excited to see
how this can make the user
experience even better
and make it easier for apps
to handle NFC tags.
In this video, I will discuss
the NFC tag data requirements,
the expected user experience,
when background tag reading
is supported,
and some example code snippets
to get you started.
Background tag reading
will work with
any NDEF formatted tag
whose NDEF message
includes a URL record.
Only the first discovered
URL record in the NDEF message
will be processed.
The URL record must contain
a valid Apple Universal Link URL
in order for the message
to be routed to an application.
iOS will route the message
to the application
registered with
the Apple Universal Link.
While the screen is on,
background tag reading
will scan for nearby NFC tags.
Once a compatible tag
is successfully read,
a pop-up
from the Notification Center
will appear
on the iPhone screen.
Tapping on the notification
will trigger the delivery
of a NSUserActivity object
to the associated application
using the Apple Universal Link
mechanisms.
By default,
Safari will handle
all unregistered
application links
and it will
only process the URL payload.
There are also
other URL schemes
that trigger
a default iOS behavior,
which I will discuss later on.
Any unprocessed notification
will be saved
in the Notification Center
for future reference.
Here is what happens
when the user taps an NFC tag.
A notification will be shown,
and tapping on the notification
will launch
the registered application.
Once the application
is running,
tapping on the NFC tag again
will trigger a new notification.
[ALERT TONE]
When a tag is read
in the locked state,
the user will be prompted
to first unlock the phone
before the tag data
can be processed.
[ALERT TONE]
Background tag reading
is supported on iPhone XS,
iPhone XS Max,
and iPhone XR.
The phone must first be unlocked
at least once after boot up
for background tag reading
to be operational.
After first unlock,
the device will scan
for NFC tags in the background
whenever the display is on
regardless of the lock state,
except for
the following conditions:
a Core NFC reader session
is in progress,
Wallet or Apple Pay are in use,
cameras are in use,
or the device
is in Airplane Mode.
Now let us walk through the
required implementation steps
in your application
to receive the content
of the NFC tag.
This is broken down
into three main steps.
You will need to register
the associated domains
for your application as per
the Universal Link requirements.
Then you will need to adopt the
UIApplicationDelegate protocol,
application(_:continue:
restorationHandler:) function.
Finally, you will need
to extract the NDEF message
from the ndefMessagePayload
property
of the NSUserActivity object.
To register your domain
in your app,
open your project in Xcode
and enter the server host domain
in the Associated Domains
section.
Here is a code snippet
illustrating how to receive
a NSUserActivity object
in your UIKit application.
First, import
the Core NFC framework.
Implement the
UIApplicationDelegate
protocol method,
application (_:continue:
restorationHandler:).
Validate the activity type is
NSUserActivityTypeBrowsingWeb
in the handler.
Read the NFCNDEFMessage
from the ndefMessagePayload
property.
This contains
the entire NDEF message
read from the NFC tag.
The message contains an array
of NFC NDEF payload records.
Each NDEF record
contains the typeNameFormat,
the Type, the Identifier,
and the data payload.
One of the NFC NDEF payload
will contain the URL record
with the Universal Link
that triggered the launch
of your application.
Please refer
to the NFC Forum specifications
regarding the various
record type definitions.
If the received
NSUserActivity object
did not originate from
the background tag reading,
then the resulting
NFCNDEFMessage
will contain exactly one
NFC NDEF payload object
with its typeNameFormat property
set to NFCTypeNameFormatEmpty.
If the URL record does not
contain a Universal Link,
iOS can still handle
many of the same URI schemes
as the QR code scanner
such as HomeKit, SMS,
GPS, and others.
Here is an example
of some of the various
supported schemes.
You can find more information
about Core NFC
on developer.apple.com.