Betsy Langowski: Linking
against the 12.1 SDK
will allow your app
to take advantage
of the full displays
on the new iPad Pros.
Not only does
the 11-inch iPad Pro
feature a brand-new screen size
and a new aspect ratio,
both devices now have
rounded corners
and no Home button.
You may need to do
a little bit of work
to make sure your iPad apps
look great on these devices,
but there are
a lot of resources available.
And if you've been following
best practices,
that work
should be very minimal.
If you've adapted an iPhone app
for iPhone X or later,
you'll find this process
very familiar on iPad.
Adapting safe area insets
throughout your app,
as well as making sure to not
special case per device model,
is the best way to future proof
your application.
For more technical information
about how to do that,
as well as information
about edge cases
and the times when
you can't use these techniques,
see the video
"Building apps for iPhone X"
and the video
"Building apps for iPhone XS,
iPhone XS Max, and iPhone XR."
Here are two examples
of the most common mistakes made
when running apps
on the new iPad Pros.
For much more specific
design information,
check out the related video
"Designing for iPad Pro
and Apple Pencil."
Here's a very simple iPad app
that looks OK
when built for an iPad
with a Home button.
But when I run it
on a new 11-inch iPad Pro,
you can see that the tab bar
interferes with
the Home indicator.
A common reason this happens,
and the reason
it's happening here,
is because while this looks like
a standard tab bar,
it's actually a custom tab bar.
Safe area insets
given by Interface Builder
have been ignored
and this custom content
has instead been aligned
with the edge of the view.
Another reason this may happen
is if you're not using
storyboards
and are instead using API
to identify the screen bounds.
The absolute best way
to fix this
is to simply use storyboards
and safe area insets,
as well as native UI elements.
Your app will look great
across devices
and you'll be future proofed.
Take a look at another app.
It's a full-screen game
with custom UI elements.
It looks great on an iPad
with a Home button,
but on the new 11-inch iPad Pro,
there are a few problems.
The content at the top
and bottom is cut off
and the custom buttons
feel too close
to the new rounded corners.
This can happen
for a number of reasons.
In this case,
that app is assuming
a four-by-three aspect ratio,
which is no longer true
for all iPads.
if you have a Metal app
or are using
API level adjustment,
you'll need to go back
to your designer
and make sure your designs
are conforming to safe areas
and being mindful
of the new rounded corners.
In games in particular,
it's also important to ensure
you didn't have any controls
or gestures related to game play
near the Home indicator as well.
If you don't link against
the 12.1 SDK,
your app will be running
compatibility mode.
While running
at the full screen size
is a much more
immersive experience,
linking against the 12.1 SDK
is important for another reason.
On iPad,
apps can run side by side,
like Maps and Clock, seen here.
Even if your app
has been linked against 12.1,
if people are running it
side by side
with an app
that hasn't been updated,
both apps run in a new kind
of compatibility mode.
Here's a simple test app.
It's been rebuilt
with a 12.1 SDK,
so now it takes advantage
of the full display
on the new 11-inch iPad Pro.
Here it is running
side by side with Maps,
another app
that's linked against 12.1,
and they both look great.
Still taking advantage
of the entire screen.
But when it's run side by side
with the WWDC app,
which hasn't yet been linked
against 12.1,
the test app is now forced back
into a new kind of combability
mode of common insets.
By updating your app quickly,
not only do you get
the more immersive experience,
you ensure that the other apps
that may be running
side by side with your app
maintain their
immersive experience.
This common inset
combability mode
doesn't reflect a real life
configuration of hardware
and so your apps haven't
necessarily been tested in it.
This is another great reason
why using safe area insets
and auto layout is a good idea.
It's important to design
your apps and write your code
in such a way that they can run
on whatever trait
or combination of traits
they detect,
regardless of hardware.
By taking some time
to ensure your iPad apps
can handle this
common inset combability mode,
you'll also be ensuring
a smooth transition next year
when you can bring
UIKit apps to the Mac.
This year we've introduced
a brand-new Apple Pencil.
All of the feature set from the
original Apple Pencil remains,
but we've introduced
a new gesture
unique to the second-generation
Apple Pencil: the double tap.
Double tap enables
three new actions,
all configurable
in the Settings app.
People can switch between
the current tool they're using
and the eraser.
They can switch between
the tool they're using
and the last tool they used,
or they can show
the color palette.
People can also turn off
double tap entirely.
If your app supports
the Apple Pencil,
but doesn't have
a drawing or tooling element,
you can implement
custom actions.
However, these should be used
very judiciously.
This is what your implementation
might look like.
You can find more robust sample
code in the related resources.
In your app view,
you detect the double tap event
by creating
UIPencilInteraction object
and assigning a delegate to it.
You can also add customization,
if appropriate for your app.
Remember, your app will
continue to be used and loved
by your customers on iPads
that pair with
the original Apple Pencil.
So it's important
not to gate functionality
behind the double tap gesture.
Your customized interactions
should never be the default.
Your app should always reflect
the system settings
and then give people an option
to change to a custom action.
Reflecting the system gestures
is as simple as calling
UIPencilInteraction.
preferredTapAction
and handling
the four built-in cases
as reflected
in the Settings app.
iPad Pro now has
a high-speed USB-C port.
This enables dynamic range
and frame matching,
which is familiar from Apple TV.
iPad Pro supports
HDR 4K up to 60 Hz
and external displays
of up to 5K.
There's no special adaption
necessary.
Everything that
already worked for you
in your second screen support
will continue to work.
USB-C is a high-speed USB port,
which enables many of the same
pro-level technologies
that you have brought
to your Mac,
including USB audio,
USB Ethernet, and USB MIDI.
And it also allows
for simultaneous output.
This facilitates, for example,
connecting a DSLR camera
and a 5K display
to your iPad Pro
at the same time.
For more information
on how to build
fantastic second screen support
into your app,
check out the WWDC 2018 video
"Adding Delight
to Your iOS App."
iPad Pro brings Face ID
to the iPad.
Unlike the iPhone X,
there is no
TrueDepth camera housing.
The camera sits
in-line with the bezel.
Face ID works in portrait,
as well as in landscape.
If your app uses
Touch ID for authentication,
you'll automatically get
the new Face ID behavior
and your existing code
will be compatible.
Just like when you adapted
your app for iPhone X,
you'll need to do
a couple of things
for proper robust
Face ID support.
You'll need to add a localized
NSFaceIDUsageDescription string
to your plist so your app
properly asks for consent
to use Face ID.
Make sure you update
your strings to reflect Face ID.
You can do this manually,
or even better,
you can use the local
authentication property,
Biometry type,
introduced in iOS 11,
to handle this check for you.
Consider the order
of your authentication flow.
Since Face ID
is an automatic action,
avoid authenticating immediately
upon launch.
Let your customer choose
when they'd like to begin
the authentication flow
so they're ready.
For much more information,
including sample code,
see the related video
"Face ID and your Apps."
The new 11-inch
and 12.9-inch iPad Pros
are the most powerful iPads yet.
Their packed with new
technologies that will empower
exciting Core ML
and machine learning apps,
enable Metal-based games
to deliver their most
beautiful experience yet,
and drive ARKit 2 and
the next generation of AR apps.
But one of the best features
of iPad Pro
is how simple it will be for you
to bring your existing
applications to these iPads.
By following existing guidelines
and staying familiar
with best practices,
it's easy to get your app up
and running for your customers.