Mike Stern: The new iPad Pro
features an all-screen design
so people can focus
on what matters most:
immersing themselves
in your app or game.
And the second generation
Apple Pencil
includes
a new double-tap feature
that makes it even more capable
and convenient.
Let's talk about
how to update your app's design
to take advantage
of these new features.
The 11-inch iPad Pro display
is 1,194 by 834 points
at 2x resolution.
The 12.9-inch iPad Pro's display
is 1,366 by 1,024 points
at 2x resolution.
In pixels, that's 2,388 by 1,668
and 2,732 by 2,048.
The 12.9-inch display
is the same width and height
as the previous generation.
The 11-inch iPad Pro display
has the same height
as a 10.5-inch iPad Pro,
while being 82 points,
or 164 pixels, wider.
The new iPad Pros
feature a thin bezel
and rounded corners.
As with current generation
iPhone displays,
avoid placing
critical information or controls
into the extreme corners
of your interface.
For many apps, the status bar
and UIKit navigation bar,
toolbar, and tab bar
will automatically
inset elements correctly.
And, as with iPhone,
a Home indicator
lets people know
they can swipe up
to return to the Home screen
and switch apps.
To make sure your app or game
looks great on iPad Pro,
you'll want to follow
three best practices
when laying out your interface.
First, use safe area
layout guides
to prevent interface elements
from getting clipped
by the display's
rounded corners,
or covered
by the Home indicator.
Safe areas are determined
by insets from each edge
of the screen.
With nothing on screen,
all insets are zero,
except for the bottom.
The bottom safe area inset
keeps elements
from getting covered
by the Home indicator.
The inset is 20 points
in portrait orientation
and in landscape.
While it may be tempting
to put UI elements
on either side
of the Home indicator,
it's not recommended.
The Home indicator
is centered in the display.
In a split view, its position
relative to your app will change
and may cover
interface elements.
When a status bar is displayed,
the top inset value
is 24 points.
That's slightly taller than
the 20-point top inset on iPhone
and previous generation iPads.
A quick but important side note.
Apps running in Slide Over
will have zero height
top and bottom
safe area insets.
The safe area is further inset
to accommodate
a navigation bar
and tab bar or toolbar.
In both orientations,
the left and right
safe area insets are zero.
That's different from iPhone,
where left and right insets
keep elements
from getting covered
by the device's sensor housing.
Next, use layout margins
to inset content
from the left and right
screen edges.
Layout margins provide
breathing space between content
and the display's
left and right edges.
They're great
for aligning content
to elements
in the navigation bar,
toolbar, and status bar,
and they keep content
from scrolling into
the display's rounded corners.
The width of layout margins
varies based on size class.
They are 20 points for regular
and 16 points for compact.
Finally, be ready
to accommodate
multiple aspect ratios.
All previous iPads
had a 4:3 aspect ratio.
The new 11-inch iPad Pro
has a wider aspect ratio.
If your app
is designed and built
for a 4:3 aspect ratio only,
you'll need to allow
for more flexibility
in your design and code.
For example, a game that's only
designed for a 4:3 aspect ratio
may wind up having black bars
along the smaller screen edges
if it's scaled
to fit the display.
If the game were scaled
to fill the display,
parts of the UI
could wind up off screen.
So take care to thoughtfully
position and scale
individual interface elements
so that your app and game
looks great,
regardless of the display's
aspect ratio.
Alongside our latest
generation iPad Pro,
we're introducing a new,
more powerful Apple Pencil.
The new Pencil has
all the same capabilities
as the previous generation.
This includes the ability
to use pressure, or force,
to control things like
brush opacity and size,
and the ability to sense
altitude and azimuth,
two properties that,
when combined with each other,
deliver a fantastic
tilt experience
for expressive
and realistic shading.
The new Apple Pencil
adds a double-tap gesture.
In the Settings app,
people can choose
one of four behaviors
for double-tap.
These system-wide behaviors
offer people a consistent
and predictable experience.
People can switch between
the currently selected
tool and eraser,
switch between the
current tool and last used tool,
show a color palette,
or if they prefer,
turn the double-tap gesture off.
Because every
app is unique,
you'll need to give some thought
to what double-tap does
in your app.
To help you make the right call,
please consider
the following best practices,
starting with the most basic.
If a person has turned
double-tap off
at the system level,
your app should do nothing
in response to double-tap.
If someone using your app
has turned double-tap off,
they'll expect every app
to respect that choice.
More generally, your app
should follow the system setting
whenever possible.
Apple Pencil
is a mark-making tool
and the system settings
reflect that.
If your app
has multiple drawing tools,
an eraser, and color palette,
people will expect your app
to mirror whatever choice
they've made in Settings.
Being inconsistent will make
your app less intuitive,
especially when multitasking
with another app
that supports Apple Pencil.
If you decide to offer
another behavior for double-tap
beyond the choices shown here,
make that custom behavior
opt-in,
meaning it should be optional
and not enabled by default.
Display the option
to enable your custom behavior
within your app's settings.
This will require people
to make an explicit
and deliberate choice
to override
the system-level behavior.
It will make it more clear
why double-tapping Apple Pencil
leads to a different behavior
in your app.
And if they decide to turn off
your app's custom behavior,
they'll be more likely
to remember how.
Now, there are apps that work
great with Apple Pencil
but do not have multiple tools
or a color palette.
If that describes your app,
it won't be possible
to follow the system settings.
However, you can still
provide a double-tap behavior
that's consistent with
the spirit of these settings.
Meaning, double-tap should
modify the behavior
of Apple Pencil.
So, for example, a photo app
may include effects
with masks the user can
paint onto their images.
Double-tapping Apple Pencil
could toggle between
two painting modes:
Adding to or subtracting
from the effect mask.
What double-tapping
should not do
is perform an action
that directly modifies content.
An action performed
with double-tap
could be done accidentally
and cause significant
workflow issues.
Now, whatever double-tapping
does in your app,
always be sure to provide clear
and immediate visual feedback
about what double-tapping did.
It's important
that people realize
they've changed
the behavior of their pencil
before they resume
drawing or writing.
And, finally, be prepared
to deliver a great experience
to existing Pencil users.
More specifically,
double-tapping
shouldn't provide
special functionality
that isn't easily achievable
through your app's interface.
For more iPad Pro and
Apple Pencil design guidance,
please visit the
Apple Human Interface Guidelines
at developer.apple.com/design.
And while you're there,
download the latest version of
the iOS Apple Design Resources.
We've updated the iPad templates
for Sketch and Photoshop.
Thank you!