In this presentation
we will focus on tile shading,
the new programmable stage
in Apple's A11 GPU
that provides
compute capabilities
inline within render passes.
Tile shading enables
a whole new level of performance
and efficiency in Metal 2.
Rendering and compute operations
can now share data
through the higher bandwidth
and lower power tile memory.
Tile shading is deeply
integrated with imageblocks.
You'll be able to analyze
imageblock contents,
summarize that content,
store imageblocks mid-scene,
or even change
imageblock layouts.
Tile shading is also
tightly integrated
with threadgroup memory
and can be used to cache
tile constant data
for the later tile
or fragment stages.
Let's start by motivating
the need for tile shading.
Performing compute
between render passes
has become more common
in recent years.
For example, tiled deferred
and forward rendering algorithms
intersect lights
against screen-aligned tiles
in order to reduce shading cost.
The idea behind these algorithms
is that not all lights
affect all pixels,
but culling per pixel
may be too expensive,
so we amortize the cost
over tile regions.
Previously in Metal
for A Series GPUs,
performing compute mid-render
required storing
render target data
that was cached in tile memory
back out to device memory,
so that a compute pass
could then consume it.
Compute would then
have to also store its results
back to device memory
before rendering would resume.
This repeated data movement
between local
and external memories
is bandwidth intensive.
With Metal 2 and the A11 GPU,
such algorithms
can now operate exclusively
within the exposed tile memory
using tile shading,
which takes the place
of the compute pass.
Render target contents are now
cached in tile memory once.
Tile shading then operates
directly on the imageblock
and can even its results
to threadgroup memory,
which is also backed
by tile memory
for later use by rendering.
Now that we've seen
how tile shaders
allow you to operate
within tile memory more often,
let's take a closer look at
how tile shading
interacts with draws.
Launching threads
within a compute pass
is called a dispatch,
and Metal adopts the same name
for tile shading operations
within a render pass.
Tile dispatches may be
freely interleaved with draws
and are executed
in API submission order.
Metal guarantees
that the results of draws
issued before the dispatch
are visible when that dispatch
is executed.
Likewise, Metal guarantees that
the results of each dispatch
are visible when the next draw
or dispatch is executed.
This synchronization guarantee
allows race-free access
to tile memory.
No such guarantee is made
between draws though.
Another important concept
in tile shading
is how threads are organized
into threadgroups and grids.
With traditional
compute dispatches,
threadgroups are organized
into tightly packed grids.
Within a render pass, however,
the tile grid is constant
across the entire pass,
but the threadgroup size
can differ for each dispatch.
If we zoom in on a tile,
we see that this allows you
to map each thread
to a unique pixel
or map each thread
to multiple pixels.
The mapping of threads
to resources
has no special meaning
to Metal though.
You can launch threads that have
no mapping to pixels whatsoever,
as would be the case
for the light culling example
we previously discussed.
In that example,
your threadgroup size
might match the number of lights
that need intersection testing.
Tile shading threadgroups are
launched for each tile
regardless of any geometry
present.
For example, a triangle
affecting a subset of tiles,
need only be processed
by those tiles.
A subsequent tile dispatch,
however,
will be processed
by every tile of the screen.
Doing so is important
because that dispatch
may be initializing tile memory
for later geometry
that can land in those tiles.
Viewport and scissor states
do not restrict tile shading
either.
In general,
tile shading is unaffected
by traditional render states.
OK, so now let's turn
to the API changes
that support tile shading.
A render pass can be configured
with one of three tile sizes,
which will determine
your imageblock dimensions.
You most often want to choose
the largest tile size
that fits your imageblock --
which is 32 KB on A11 GPUs --
to minimize any overhead
of the GPU's
primitive processing stage.
Some algorithms may, however,
benefit from choosing
a smaller tile size
when fragment or tile processing
is particularly complex,
to increase the amount
of tile parallelism
in the shader cores.
As we've already seen,
threadgroup memory
is also sourced from tile memory
so it's size may also constrain
your choice of tile size.
Creating a tile shading pipeline
is similar to creating
a traditional pipeline.
You attach functions
to a pipeline descriptor
to create a pipeline state.
For tile shading,
Metal introduces
a new pipeline descriptor type.
It's similar to the existing
render pipeline descriptor,
but removes
render state properties
such as blending.
It's also similar
to the existing
compute pipeline descriptor
because only one
function can be bound.
That function, however,
can either be
a compute kernel
or a fragment function.
Compute kernels provide access
to all the tile shading
and imageblock features
we've discussed so far.
Fragment-based tile shading
is more limited
but plays a specific
and important role
that I'll talk about later on.
First, I'd like to touch
on imageblock capabilities
in tile pipelines.
Since tile shading executes
compute dispatches
inline with rendering,
it has access to both implicit
and explicit imageblocks,
just like fragment functions.
Unlike fragment functions,
however,
kernel-based tile shaders can
access the entire imageblock.
Let's take a look at the syntax.
We disambiguate between
the implicit and explicit forms
of the templated imageblock type
using a second
template argument.
We must disambiguate
because each
has different access semantics.
The implicit form
has value semantics,
meaning that we copy pixels
into and out of the imageblock.
The explicit form
has the reference semantics
discussed in
the previous presentation.
We've already seen how
imageblocks within a render pass
persist for
the lifetime of the tile
and how we leverage this
to communicate across
draws and dispatches.
In our opening example
I also mentioned
that the same is true
for threadgroup memory.
Persistent threadgroup memory
is unique to tile shading
and is well-suited for storing
data that's constant
across the tile,
such as culled light lists.
Let's take a look
at how we leverage this
in the shading language.
In this example,
our kernel-based tile function
is provided the full light list
for culling against
its tile bounds.
It's also given minimum
and maximum depth
of the tile
from an earlier tile dispatch.
It then places the culled result
in threadgroup memory
so that later fragment shaders
have access to it.
Both tile dispatch
and fragment draws
must agree on
the threadgroup bind point.
Let's finally consider the role
fragment-based
tile pipelines play.
Tile shading encourages you
to leverage tile memory
by merging what would previously
have been multiple passes.
Tile memory is
a precious resource,
so we need explicit imageblocks
to pack more data
into that space.
But a static tile memory layout
for an entire pass
is still unlikely to fit,
so we need to flexibly
transition tile memory layouts
as we move through the different
phases of our computation.
Fragment-based tile pipelines
enable this transitioning.
The barrier semantics
I described earlier
ensure that all
tile memory access
is complete
before the transition begins.
And since fragment shaders
copy data
to and from imageblocks,
we can ensure that each pixel
is transitioned atomically.
Let's look at an example.
In this example,
we finished with our
deferred rendering phase
and would like to reconfigure
the imageblock to implement
an approximate order-independent
transparency technique called
Multi-Layer Alpha Blending.
We do so using
a fragment-based tile function
that takes
the old layout as input
and returns the new layout.
And as is often the case,
you often need
to initialize the new layout
using data
from the old layout.
Here we bring over
the final lit value
from the deferred
rendering phase.
To better understand
tile shading,
please be sure
to check out our sample code.
It demonstrates how
to efficiently forward shade
with many lights
in a single pass.
Tile shading is used
to cull lights
that do not affect the tile.
Finally, the GPU Debugger
in Xcode
makes inspecting
threadgroup memory easy
by formatting the data based on
how you use it in your shader.
After taking a capture
with Xcode's GPU Debugger,
you can see
each threadgroup memory
as buffers in the tile section
of the bound resources view.
From there,
you can use the buffer viewer
to inspect the data
formatted in same way
that your shader uses it.
In this presentation,
we saw how tile shading
enables developers
to analyze and manipulate
whole tile contents,
communicate across draws,
and repurpose tile memory
through different phases
of computation.
Taken together,
tile shaders enable developers
to merge multiple render
and compute passes
in order to better leverage
the higher bandwidth
and lower power tile memory
of the A11 GPU.
For more information
about Metal 2
and links to the sample code
please visit
the Developer website
at
developer.apple.com/metal.