Updating your watchOS 4 app
for Apple Watch Series 3
makes it easier than ever
to stay connected,
and allows you to leverage
the new barometric altimeter.
Apple Watch began
with a dependence upon
its connection to iPhone
for all networking.
However, since watchOS 2,
Apple Watch has had the ability
to communicate over Wi-Fi
if your iPhone is off
or out of range,
and you are in range
of a Wi-Fi hotspot
your iPhone has
previously connected to.
Apple Watch Series 3
with cellular
now allows your app
to communicate directly
over a cellular connection
if your iPhone is out of range
and Wi-Fi is not available
where you are.
Not only can your app
update its data from anywhere,
but push notifications
received by your iPhone
will be automatically forwarded
to your Apple Watch
when it is on
a cellular connection.
To make sure that your app works
over any and all
connection possibilities,
it’s now even more important
to use URLSession
for networking requests
in your watch app.
URLSession is the class
used for creating and managing
networking connections
in watchOS.
Using URLSession
from your watch app code,
allows you to initiate
network requests
directly from Apple Watch.
When your iPhone
is in range of Apple Watch,
these requests will be proxied
behind the scenes through iPhone
to leverage its connection.
Otherwise, requests will occur
directly through Wi-Fi hotspots
or cell connection.
When using URLSession
while Apple Watch is only
on a cellular connection,
be aware that sessions
may be handled slightly
differently by the system.
Let’s look at the different
types of sessions
and what you can expect.
For default
and ephemeral sessions,
these type of sessions
will work as they normally do
when the application
state is active.
You can check the current
application state using
the applicationState property on
the shared WKExtension object.
However, these type of sessions
are not allowed
if the application state
is inactive or background.
There is one caveat to this,
as they are allowed if your app
is currently using
the background navigation mode.
Next, let’s look at
background sessions.
With background sessions,
smaller transfers are preferred,
and any transfer could
be deferred until a point
where the system has
a better opportunity
to make network requests.
This is determined
at a system level
and takes into account many
facets such as power level,
connection strength,
and tasks other apps
are needing to accomplish.
With background sessions,
once the request has been made
and a response has returned,
if your app is in
the frontmostapp state,
your app
will be woken immediately
and handed the response.
Outside of
the frontmost app state,
the system will wake
your app with the response
when it determines
it is a good time to do so,
or when the application state
becomes active again.
Now let’s go over a few
best practices to make sure
you get the most out of your
networking code on watchOS.
The first is to use the new
waitsForConnectivity property
on your
URLSessionConfiguration object.
Setting this to true
on a non-background session
will allow the system
to wait until connectivity
is sufficient
to make the request,
instead of immediately failing.
There is a delegate method
to know when
the connection is waiting,
so you can handle
the situation.
We encourage using this property
for all requests that are not
dependent on being immediate,
since they will fire immediately
as long as connectivity
is available.
If not, the system
will wait on making the request
until connectivity resumes.
This allows you to focus
on what makes your app great
instead of focusing
on reachability code.
Using
the applicationWillResignActive
method on
the WKExtensionDelegate object
allows you
to optimize what happens
when the application state
changes from active to inactive
or background when you have
a networking request in process.
In other words, when someone
puts their wrist down
while using your app.
By using this method,
you can decide to cancel
your existing request,
or create it again
as a background session.
Finally, it’s always best to use
the shared singleton URLSession
object for multiple tasks,
instead of creating
a session for each task.
Creating and invalidating
many sessions
creates unnecessary overhead
for the system,
and it’s best
to use the shared session,
or as few as needed.
Let’s move on to the
Watch Connectivity framework.
As Apple Watch becomes
more independent
with its connectivity,
it’s important to identify where
using Watch Connectivity
can help make a great
watch app experience.
The initial launch of an app
on Apple Watch
may require a token for
authentication with a service.
Using Watch Connectivity
is a great way
to pass this information
that may already be established
in the iPhone app.
If your app is a coaching app
for workouts,
or something similar,
you may want to initially
transfer some larger audio files
to Apple Watch once someone
begins using your app.
Watch Connectivity can handle
these type of transfers,
and can help your app
installation remain small
and supplement the app
with resources later.
The updateApplicationContext
method on WCSession
allows you to have the iPhone
send over a dictionary of data
that the watch app has access to
the next time it activates.
This is a good way to keep fresh
data flowing to the watch app
in case of situations where
the iPhone app gets newer data
and the watch app hasn’t had
an opportunity to update yet.
When the watch app launches,
you can display this newer data
while you initiate
a network request
for more up-to-date data.
It’s very important
that you build in the ability
to fallback
to a network request.
With Apple Watch
being more independent,
there is less guarantee
that your watch app
will have up-to-date data
from the iPhone.
Now let’s turn our attention
to the new barometric altimeter
in Apple Watch Series 3,
which enables you to now add
elevation gain or descent
to workout summaries
when someone is away
from their iPhone.
This also helps provide
more accurate
active energy burned
calculations to HealthKit,
and in turn, your app.
Using Core Motion,
your app can now
be informed about
relative altitude changes
from where your app begins
receiving updates.
Relative altitude changes
means that if you begin updates
while standing at
an elevation of 800 meters,
and move 50 meters
higher in elevation,
the relative altitude value
will be 50 meters.
If you move 80 meters lower
than where you began,
the relative altitude value
will then be negative 80 meters.
Core Motion includes
the CMAltimeter class,
which you will use
to receive updates.
CMAltimeter can determine
and tell you if the device
has the capabilities to give
relative altitude updates.
You should always
check this first
before asking Core Motion
more about relative altitude.
In watchOS 4, CMAltimeter
can now provide you with
the authorization status
for Motion and Fitness activity.
Depending on what your app
is allowed to access,
you may need to handle cases
where authorization
is denied or restricted.
Finally, CMAltimeter provides
the ability to start and stop
relative altitude updates.
These updates are delivered on
a two-and-a-half second cadence
on watchOS 4,
due to signal filtering
that we apply
to the raw sensor data.
When you receive an update,
you will have a handler
that passes you
a CMAltitudeData object.
The CMAltitudeData object
gives you
the relative altitude change
data for that update.
This includes
the following pieces of data:
first is the timestamp.
This object is a time interval
and is given as
the number of seconds
since the reference date.
To convert this value
to a Date object,
you can easily use the
timeIntervalSinceReferenceDate
initializer method
on the Date class.
The next property
is relative altitude.
This represents
the change in altitude
since the last reported event.
Remember that this
will be a relative value,
so if the device moves
lower or higher in elevation,
this value will represent
the change in elevation
and not the specific altitude.
This value is given in meters.
The last property is pressure.
Since the altimeter onboard
is a barometric altimeter,
Core Motion can provide you
with the recorded pressure
alongside the relative
altitude change.
This value is given
in kilopascals.
Let’s walk through
an example of how to start
relative altitude updates
using CMAltimeter,
as well as how to properly
check for device capabilities
and authorization status.
Previous to this
beginAltitudeUpdates method,
I’ve imported the Core Motion
framework into my class
and created an instance
variable called altimeter,
of type CMAltimeter.
That’s the object we will use
to start and stop
relative altitude updates
later on.
In our function, the first thing
we should do is check
to see if relative altitude
is available on the device.
If it’s not, we may want
to alter the UI
to let the person know that
this data will not be available
as they use the app.
Next, we need to check
if authorization status
is denied or restricted.
Here, we’re making sure
authorization status
isn’t denied, nor restricted.
If the authorization status
is authorized we can continue,
and if the authorization status
is not determined,
the system
will prompt for access,
if the person has not
been previously prompted.
Once the app is authorized to
use Motion and Fitness activity,
we may ask Core Motion to start
relative altitude updates.
This call on a previously
created CMAltimeter object
has us pass in
which operation queue
we’d like to receive updates on,
as well as provides a handler
to run each time new data
is handed to us by Core Motion.
In this case,
we’ve set the operation queue
to the main queue since we will
be updating UI in the handler.
Moving to the handler, it passes
us a CMAltitudeData object,
containing the values
we are interested in,
or possibly an error
if something went wrong
in the update.
After ensuring we have
no error to handle,
we simply grab
the relativeAltitude value
from the CMAltitudeData object,
store its float value,
and use that to update the UI.
We could just as easily
use the timestamp
or pressure properties,
as mentioned earlier.
Once we no longer need
to receive updates,
we tell Core Motion to stop
relative altitude updates,
using our previously used
CMAltimeter object.
And that’s it!
For more information about
developing for Apple Watch
and using URLSession
and Core Motion,
please view the resources
links at the following page.
Thank you.