>> Hello everyone.
Thank you for coming.
My name is Jacques
Gasselin and I'm the manager
of Game Technologies
Team here at Apple.
Today, I'm talking
about Game Controllers.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
So, as you heard
yesterday, in the state
of the union just I'll
mention we have a lot
of games in our platform.
It's immensely successful.
We have games that capture
your imagination, we have games
that you play on the go
or at home in the couch
and games interact
with the user.
They give you an experience
and that's what this is
all about, interaction.
Game controllers will allow you
to give the users
another experience,
another way to interact
with your game content
and that I think
is very important.
But you won't just have game
controllers we still have the
existing mechanics on the phone.
So, touch is fantastic
and a flexible way
for giving the users ways to
provide actions through tapping,
tilting when motion, swiping
or touching direct
locations from the screen.
Game controllers on the
other hand are fantastic
for directional inputs.
And with our precious sensitive
buttons they give you an option
to provide gameplay mechanics
such as picking a ball
or throwing a ball maybe
executing a special maneuver
in a flight simulator
or whatever else you
guys come up with.
So, when we bring this two
together you have an amazing
opportunity to thrill your users
and give them an even
better experience
and perhaps bringing
games to the next level.
So, we have two parts.
There's a hardware
specification by the MFi program
which makes sure that
hardware is consistent
so you're users know
what they're going to get
and they know that what
they've purchased is going
to work with your content.
There's also a software
framework
which is what you will be
interacting with in order
to read inputs from this
controllers and this ensures
that with the hardware
specification
and the software
specification you know
that the controller you have
testing with is going to work
with the controller that
you use or is using.
And this is obviously
for iOS and OS X.
So, to talk about the
actual controllers
and MFi specification I'd like
to invite Edwin Foo up on stage.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Jacques.
Good afternoon everybody.
I'm Edwin from our accessories
engineering team and I'm really,
really excited to
be up here talking--
to talk to you of today
about the hardware component
of this feature that
worse in conjunction
with the software component
that Jacques' team
has worked so hard on.
And it's-- in our
opinion I think we--
it's a really good thing that we
have brought this two together
just like we do for our own
products this [inaudible]
of hardware and software.
And so, for the next few
minutes I'm going to share
with you game developers in the
audience what you'll be able
to expect from MFi
game controllers.
So, to start off with,
when we sat down I thought
about the hardware
specification controllers.
We had two goals in line.
First, we wanted to make sure
that your users will be able
to go out there and buy any MFi
game controller with this badge
on it what the-- behind
me on this screen here.
And buy with confidence
knowing that it will work
with all your games and
quite frankly all games
on the App Store that work with
the game controller framework.
They was-- we don't want there
to be any ambiguity about this.
And in turn, what this does
is it enables you the game
developers to focus on making
great games and not have
to worry about dealing
with all the differences
between the controllers
and how do I code to deal
with idiosyncrasies of
controller A from company A
and controller B from company B.
We want this to be a
benefit to you too.
And for those of you in the
audience we have a closet full
of controllers that you
bought throughout the years
to test with your games.
Well, you don't need
that anymore.
You only need to buy
one MFi controller,
get your game working
with it and go publish.
So, what will you
be able to expect
from MFi and game controllers?
Well, it all starts with
consistent control layouts.
We've defined three
which I'll be going
into in the next
couple of slides.
But these layouts
are all the same.
You will not-- they
have to worry
about whether controls
are missing a button
that you need for
a game to work.
The controllers will
be transport agnostic.
So, they may use both wired
and wireless creativity options
but they will still report
changes in control of state
and button state to your game
at a consistent and fast rates.
All the buttons on MFi game
controllers will be pressure
sensitive, every single one.
And because we have
this ability in the--
through via the MFi
program to set a standard
for both mechanical, electrical
and firmware requirements
all the buttons will have a
consistent mechanical feel and
this maybe important to some
of you in the audience as well.
That-- but that's not all,
we also know that thumbsticks
and D-pads have they're
definitely been a topic
that were-- has required a lot
of time in the past when working
on games mainly because not
all of them are created equal.
Some of them drift, some of them
have dead zones, varying sizes,
some of them won't-- can't even
let you actually use the entire
area when you roll
your finger around.
You won't need to worry that
with MFi game controllers.
You can depend on and
trust that the controllers
that you see here on these
controllers will work
consistently in a
game regardless
of whatever code
password you may take.
And-- but of course, we will
still see a lot of variation
in terms of industrial design
and color choices and that sort
of thing and that's perfectly
fine we want to see that,
we want-- I'm sure your users
will appreciate having those
options as well, but the
core behavior and the way
that this controllers work is
something that you can trust
and depend on to be consistent.
So, let's talk about the
first controller type.
What you see here is a
form-fitting standard gamepad.
So, let me explain the
terminology a little bit.
By forfeiting what I mean is
that the gamepad physically
in cases the device.
So, forfeiting is a
fancy word for case.
The key takeaway here though
for our US game developer is
that it means that the user
can still touch the screen.
And there was API and the
game controller framework
for your game to check
and know for certain
that yes the user can't
still touch the screen.
Therefore, you can take
advantage of that if you
like to create this hybrid
experience of Multi-Touch
and tackle buttons
on controllers
that Jacques just spoke about.
The standard gamepad has a one
directional pad in the left,
it will always be on the
left 1 ABXY face button group
that will always be on the right
and will always have
these color designs with.
And one row shoulder
buttons L and R.
You also see a little
pause button there
which will be present in
all three controller types
but that will be spoken about
in detail a little bit later
in this session.
From the form-fitting
standard gamepad we go
to the form-fitting
extended gamepad.
And that adds two Thumbsticks
on either side and an extra set
of triggers right below the
left and right shoulder buttons.
And you can see there that the
labeling changes as well from L
and R to L1, L2 and R1, R2.
You can depend on that, all of
them will be labeled this way.
So, as you point out that just
because the extended
gamepad exist does not mean
that you have to take
advantage of all the controls.
This is something that you as
a game designer get to pick.
And we fully expect that
there will be some games
that when hooked up to an
extended gamepad don't use the
extra controls, that's
perfectly OK.
Last but not least is the
standalone extended gamepad.
And standalone means that it
is not attached to the device.
That's it, it doesn't
have to be complicated.
The important thing here is
that all standalone
gamepads are extended.
They will have the thumbsticks
and they will all
have the triggers.
So, remember that.
And also keep in mind
that standalone gamepads will
have the player ID indicators
as you can see there are a
little four dots in the middle.
And again, later
in the session one
of the colleagues will be
explaining how to take advantage
of those for your game.
So, let's recap.
There are three controller types
for MFi game controllers
starting with the standard,
form-fitting gamepad, the
extended form-fitting gamepad
and the extended
standalone gamepad.
All right.
So, some of you in the audience
may actually be interested
in making MFi game controllers.
And if so, this is
the slide for you.
As Jacques explained earlier and
as you heard during the state
of the union address MFi
game controllers will need
manufacturers to
join the MFi program.
It's very simple.
Go to the URL you see here
on the slide, sign up here
with your company information.
And, you know, and
then you'll be hearing
from our presenter fairly soon.
Access to the MFi program
grants technical information
such as the specification
that we have put together
concerning MFi game controllers.
Hardware components such as the
lightning connector that some
of you may choose to use
in your game controller.
Test tools, technical
support and last
but not least certification
procedures that you
as a controller manufacturer
will use when it comes time
to get ready to bring
your product to market.
Once your product passes
certification then you will get
to-- go to market and use
those logos compatibility icons
that all of the mutual
customers know how to recognize.
So, now I'm pretty sure or
I guess you can take a guess
that the varying questions
everyone in mind at this point
in time is when will see
MFi game controllers?
Well, I can help you
answer that right now.
We have already been
working with key partners.
You can see two of them on
the slide Logitech and Moga
and they-- let me assure you
that they are working very
diligently to bring controllers
to market later this fall.
In fact, in the [inaudible]
downstairs
as what's previously
mentioned you will find
that there are some prototype
Logitech controllers already
out there for you--
for you game developers
to start working with.
So, you can't say that we're
slowing you down on this.
You know, get started
they're right there.
And quite frankly we can't
wait to see what all of you
in the audience come up with.
We're' really excited and hope
that you'll be willing to walk
down this road with us.
And so at this point,
I want to hand things
over to my colleague JJ so
he can talk to you about how
to connect the controllers.
Thanks everyone.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Edwin.
So, let's talk about the
software and how you're going
to be interacting with the
game controller framework.
What I'm going to be talking
to you about is an overview
of a commonly used class in
the game controller framework.
And then we're talking about how
to handle controllers connecting
and disconnecting
from your devices.
Now, this is a reality
players are going to connect
and disconnect controllers
in your game and you're going
to want to handle
those appropriately.
I'm also going to talk about
how to read controller inputs.
So, once your game knows which
controller or controllers it has
to access how do you actually
read what the thumbsitck
position is?
How do you read what
player is pushing
as far as face buttons goes?
I'm also going to talk about
other important controls
on the controls like
the pause button
and the player indicator LEDs
and what your responsibilities
as game developers are with
regards to these controls.
And lastly, we're going to wrap
up by talking about
best practices.
How to take all this
technical information and think
about all this new
capabilities afforded to you
so that you can integrate
game controllers in a away
that makes your games
really special.
[ Pause ]
So, the central class
you're going
to be using a lot is
called GCController.
You're going to be using this
to connect to controllers
and instances of this class
represent a connected controller
to your device.
Now, this is the same class
for all three supported
controller types.
GCController has a
lot of capabilities.
It allows you to
find controllers.
So, we have methods
so that you can query
which controllers are currently
connected to my device.
Sometimes you might
want to be notified
as controllers are
connected and disconnected
and we have ways for
you to know that.
And there's also ways for you
to discover wireless controllers
that haven't been used
with this device before.
GCController also
provides you ways
to read the inputs
off of the device.
So, again, how you know where
the D-pad is being pressed,
thumbsticks, triggers and so on.
And lastly, it gives
you information
about the controller whether
or not it's a form-fitting
controller.
The vendor who manufactured
this controller perhaps to show
in a player facing UI like
in a team picker dialogue.
And also gives you the player
index which is surfaced
in the physical controller
via the player indicator LEDs.
So, let's talk about
connecting and disconnecting.
We have a class method called
controllers on GCController
and this gives you an array
of the currently
connected controllers.
The array instances or the
array elements are instances
of type GCController.
And if there are no currently
connected controllers then this
array will return empty.
Now, the beauty of this is that
controllers as they're connected
and disconnected this
method automatically update
that information for you.
So, you can be guaranteed
that whenever you call this
method you have a current idea
of which controllers
are connected.
Let's look at a code example.
A lot of games will choose
to have a central method that's
called throughout their game
and it resolves new
controllers that come in.
And in this example
we're calling
that method set up controllers.
The first thing we
do at the top of set
up controllers is we call
the controllers class method.
And we take all the currently
connected controllers
and we cache them into our
controller array property.
Then based on whether or not
we have controllers we can
take action.
Keep this method in
mind set up controllers.
I'm going to be referring to it
throughout the rest of the talk.
Sometimes you don't want to be--
sometimes you don't want
to necessarily ask what
controllers are currently
connected right now rather
you want to be notified
when a controller
connects and disconnects.
And we provide capabilities for
you to get notified of that.
Using NSNotificationCenter
you can add observers
when called GCController
did connect notification.
This is for obviously detecting
when controllers connect.
Similarly, to be notified
when a controller disconnects
we have GCController did
disconnect notification.
You'll notice in this example,
the selector we've chosen is
our set up controller's method
that you saw on the
previous screen.
So, as controllers are connected
and disconnected we're going
to be funneling back
into that method.
Now, some controllers are going
to be wireless and these types
of controllers need
to be discovered
and paired before the
first time they're used
with a particular device.
These generally only
needs to happen once.
Once the user has paired
a wireless controller
with the device then after
that the controller will
automatically be recognized
and we don't need to go
through this discovery
paring process again.
So, as game developers you
can afford a convenience
to your players and allow them
to do this rate within
your game.
This is great for players
who have just unboxed their
brand new controller and go
to your game first
and don't have to--
or rather they can
jump into the game
without having to
leave your game.
So, you can just initiate
this discovery process
with the method that we call
start wireless controller
discovery with completion
handler.
When you call this
wireless discovery kicks off
asynchronously and it doesn't
block you're able to go
about your business and your
app can remain responsive.
And whenever the discovery
process finishes your supplied
completion handler is called.
And it's called in one
of three situations.
One, either all the controllers
have been discovered.
Two, the discovery process
has timed-out or three,
you've explicitly told it to
stop early, and if you decide
to do that you can do so via
the stop wireless controller
discovery method.
Now, you're going
to want to use this
in conjunction with
notifications.
So, as you kickoff the wireless
discovery process the discovery
is happening asynchronously
in the background
and while that's happening and
controllers are being discovered
and paired notifications fire.
And so, if you set up the
notifications that I showed you
on the previous slide that
will be happened automatically.
So, you can see we're
building this in layers.
Let's look at a code example.
In this example, we've
arbitrarily chosen
that the user-- we're going
to allow the user the ability
to start the wireless
discovery themselves.
So, maybe the user hits a button
in your interface say the
first thing we do is start
up a spinner so that
the user knows
that they're input
action has been accepted
and we kickoff the start
wireless controller discovery
with completion handler method.
Now, again, this
happens asynchronously,
and whenever it returns
we can take action
and the first thing we're doing
in this case is we're
stopping our spinner.
Since we're affording
the users the ability
to start this process themselves
we should also provide them a
way to cancel it.
And you do that again
by calling stop wireless
controller discovery.
You'll note that this method
doesn't take a completion
handler because when this is
called the completion handler
in the start method
above is called for you.
And it's safe to call stop
wireless controller discovery
even if your start wireless
controller discovery handler has
already called.
Now, I have a few
caveats to mention
to you regarding
connecting and disconnecting.
Controllers take time to be
recognized on app start up.
Now, the framework does this
for you asynchronously
and automatically.
But one of the side effects is
that the controllers
class method is going
to be empty inside of
application did finish launching
for options with options.
But this is OK, if you setup
your notifications there
for controllers connecting
and disconnecting inside
of application did
finish launching
with options you're
guaranteed not
to miss any connections
and disconnections.
Now, we recognize there
are some games out there
who might have large engines
or a lot of art assets to load.
And their not ready
to start listening
for controller notifications
inside
of application did finish
launching with options.
And that's OK.
You can call-- you can setup
your notifications whenever make
sense for your game.
Just make sure right before that
you call the controllers array
so you capture any controllers
which may have already
been connected.
All right, so now we have
controllers that are connected
and we're ready to read the
input off of those controllers.
Now, you recall we have
three supported physical
controller types.
And the way these are mapped
in the software are via
what we call profiles.
So, the standard gamepad has
a standard gamepad profile.
And the two extended gamepads
share a single profile
that we call he extended
gamepad profile.
Now, the standard gamepad
profile that's why the standard
gamepad has four face buttons,
two shoulder buttons
and a D-pad.
And the way these are mapped
in the software are via
properties on the gamepad.
So, you have button A,
button B, button X, button Y.
Left shoulder, right
shoulder and D-pad.
Now, the standard gamepad
profile is a property called
gamepad on controllers.
You can see that listed
up in the subheading.
Moving on to the extended
gamepads you will recall these
add two thumbsticks
and two triggers on top
of the standard gamepad.
And here highlighted in yellow
you can see the extra properties
on the extended gamepad profile.
Now, the standard gamepad
is going to be supported
by all controllers regardless
of whether it's a
standard controller
or an extended controller.
So, you as software developers
are guaranteed that as long
as your controller supports,
as long as your code supports
the standard gamepad all the
controllers that are used
with games will work.
With extended gamepads not every
controller will support the
extended gamepad profile namely
the standard gamepad obliviously
doesn't have thumbsticks.
It doesn't have triggers.
So, check this property,
check the extended gamepad
property on controllers.
If it's new hat means
that extended gamepads
are not supported.
I'd like to bring your attention
to the fact that thumbsticks
and D-pads while being two
totally physically separate
devices share a control
type direction pad.
Similarly, the triggers
and the face buttons
and the shoulder buttons all
share a button input type.
So, let's dive into these
various element types.
Buttons are represented
in our framework
by a class called
GCControllerButtonInput.
And they are treated
in the classic digital sense
whether they're pressed or not
with a bullion in the
framework called Pressed.
If this is true the button is
pressed, if not its not pressed.
But since our buttons are also
pressure sensitive you have the
option of reading a value
property which returns a float.
This tells you how much force
that button is being pressed
with at the current moment.
And this is a float
normalized between zero and one.
All right, let's talk about
GCControllerDirectionPad.
Again, this is shared across
multiple physical inputs
such as the D-pad
and the thumbstick.
And we give you options as
game developers to use these
in a way that suits your game.
So, you can read them as four
buttons up, down, left and right
or you can read them as two
axis, the xAxis and the yAxis.
If we look at the axis type
GCControllerAxisInput you will
note that it has
a value property.
And this tracks the
movement along that axis.
It's normalized from negative
one on one end to positive one
on the other end
with zero in between.
Now, the hardware
spec guarantees
that any non-zero value is the
player intentionally moving the
D-pad or the thumbstick away
from the neutral
resting position.
So, for those of you in
the audience who are used
to programming your
own dead zones
for controllers don't
do that here.
The hardware spec guarantees
a consistent dead zone
and if you add your
own dead zone
on top you're compromising the
crispiness of the controls.
All right.
Now, let's talk about how do
we actually read the values off
of these controller inputs.
The first and probably most
common way that you're going
to be doing this is via Polling.
Polling allows you to find
out what the current value
of that controller
input is right now.
Using conjunction with polling
every game loop you can track
the movement of various
controller inputs
across various frames
of your game,
things like thumbstick position.
Now, sometimes you don't want
to know what the current
value is right now.
You want to be notified
when the value changes.
And to be notified of this you
can use value change call backs.
So, you can use this in
scenarios where you want
to be notified when the player
starts polling the right trigger
for instance.
Setup a value change call back
and you'll be notified
when that happens.
Lastly you can take snapshots
and snapshots are ways
of capturing the entire
controller state in one object.
You can use this for
a lot of useful things
like recording button input.
You can compare current
controller state this frame
to a previous frame.
You can record input to send
across the wire to--
to record to a file.
Now, let's look at
some examples.
For polling like I said
you're typically going
to be doing this each
game loop iteration
and it's really just a simple
as reading the properties
off of the profiles.
So, in this first example
we have the standard gamepad
profile on the controller
and from there we're showing
you two different ways
to read the states
of the Y button.
Next, we show an example
from the extended gamepad
profile three different ways
on how to read the Y
axis thumbstick value.
You can treat it as a Y axis
or you can read it
as the up button.
Now, here's a polling example
in context of game code.
We've got our update method.
This is what's called
one each game loop.
And within there we grab the
profile off the controller,
the extended gamepad
in this case.
And all the while the right
trigger is being pressed we're
going to firing lasers.
While the left trigger is
being pressed we're going
to launch missiles.
And lastly, we're going to apply
thrust to our spaceship based
on the current value of the
thumbsticks Y axis value.
Now, value change
handlers are accomplished
by passing in a block.
So, you choose which
controller element you want
to be notified when it changes.
And you also pass a block
of code that runs whenever
that value does happen
to change.
The framework is constantly
updating the profiles
on the main thread
at sixty hertz.
And we'll notify any value
change handlers you have setup.
Now, handlers can be
registered on specific elements
such as individual buttons.
They can be registered on
collections of elements
such as the D-pad or thumbsticks
or they can be registered
on the entire controller
profile itself.
So, you can be notified
when anything
on the controller changes.
Here's an example.
So, again we grab the
profile off of the controller.
And this is an alternate way
of firing our lasers whenever
the right trigger is pressed.
So, we get a value--
value change handler which calls
us whenever the right trigger's
position changes.
When it does we check if
the button is pressed and if
so we fire our lasers.
Let's look at another example.
You can share a single handler
among several-- several inputs.
So, in this case we're
implementing a touch any button
to continue.
We grab the profile.
We setup our handler which we're
calling myFaceButtonsHandler.
And then we assign
that handler to each
of the four face buttons.
When any of them are
pressed the code runs
and we dismiss the
UI in this case.
Lastly, an example on how to
setup value change handlers
on collections of elements.
In this case whenever the
right thumbstick is moved we
get notified.
This is good for situation
where you might want
to say move the right
thumbstick to look around
and be notified when
that happens.
Now, value change handlers are
called in a hierarchical order
from individual elements
through the collections and on,
up into the controller itself.
So, example of a
D-pad being pressed.
First the framework checks
if there are any
value change handlers
on the four face buttons--
or sorry, the four buttons
that represent the D-pad.
If so those are called.
Then it goes through the
two axis on the D-pad.
If you have setup
value change handlers
for those they are
called as well.
Then it calls the value change
handler on the D-pad itself
if you've assigned
one and lastly
on to the controller profile.
All right.
Let's talk about snapshots now.
Snapshots allow us to collect
the entire current controller's
state in one object.
And we allow you to
move the data from to
and from NSData Objects
very easily via methods
that I'll show you in a moment.
And once you have an
NSData Representation
of the snapshot you can do
whatever you want with it.
You can start to file.
You can start to URL.
You can unpack it after that.
Snapshots are also
mutable so in addition
to recording a controller input
you can retrieve controller
input and assign it
back into a snapshot.
Now, you're going to want to
use snapshots in conjunction
with polling or value
change handlers.
So, in your main game loop
as your polling you could be
collecting snapshots each frame
or inside your value change
handlers you could be collecting
snapshots as well.
This is great for recording
controller input, for sending it
over a network, for various
debugging activities.
Let's look at us a controller--
or sorry, a snapshot example.
So, in this example we're
going to take a snapshot
and write it to a file.
To do that we call the
save snapshot method
on the gamepad profile.
This gives us our snapshot
object GCGamepadSnapshot.
Then we use a method on
GCGamepadSnapshot called--
or a property called
snapshotData
and that gives us the NSData
representation of the snapshot
and then using NSData we
can go ahead and write
that snapshot to a file.
Let's look at an example
going to the other way.
So, in this case we provide
a file and we use NSData
to retrieve that file.
And then we go ahead and
initialize a snapshot object
with that using our
initWithSnapshotData method.
And now I think its
time for a demo.
So, I'd to call Jacques back up
on stage and Tomash from Crytek.
[ Applause ]
>> Hello everyone.
This is a demo of
integrating controllers based
on all upcoming games
called the Collectibles
which will be released
later this year.
The framework integration
was easy.
There was no need to adjust
to dead zones or drifting.
It just works.
So, today I would like
to talk about design.
We have a great touch base
navigation and cover bionics.
And it was a fun challenge to
extend them to controllers.
Let's take the navigation first.
With touch controls the player
can either move the characters
individually by throwing a bat
or as a squad by double tapping.
For controllers we
take the solution
to extend squad movement with
D-pad based direct control.
To find the cover with touch
controlled the player have
to draw a path for controllers
we created a slightly
different dynamic.
The players can choose
from four directions
and the system automatically
send the characters
to the best possible
cover in that area.
In complicated situations the
player can still use the touch
control and move individual
characters to cover.
And I think we should call
in the-- the gun ship.
>> Oh, sorry.
>> Yup. This is a great example
where the user can
simultaneously use the
controller and the
touch control.
Use the D-pad to move
the gun ship target
and in the same time
use the touch screen
to navigate the characters.
In this demo the controller
joins the touch control
and they fit together naturally.
I hope you like that.
I have to know-- know that
this was only a technical
demonstration with some
nice graphics and only
with two game mechanics from all
upcoming game, the Collectibles.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> I want to take
you through the--
the nitty-gritty details of
what was actually happening
under the hood here.
So, here we have a very
simplistic view of a gamepad.
So, you see the D-pad on
the left, the face buttons
on the right with
the correct colors
and the two shoulder buttons.
So, as I press the D-pad you
notice I can detect the four
cardinal and the four
inter cardinal directions.
I can also just take
the pressure right now.
So, you I' pushing the
left as hard as I can.
I can also push it less hard.
So, you there's a float
value between zero and one
for the direction I'm pushing.
This actually allows
you to get 360 degrees
of analog input on the D-pad.
The same applies to face buttons
so as I press A you
notice first it's pressed
and I can press it harder
enlarging the circle there is,
B the same, X and Y
and of course the shoulder
buttons too, right and left.
And that's how easy that is.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> All right, let's talk about
a few additional controls,
the pause button and the
player indicator LED's.
Now, the hardware
spec guarantees
that every controller
has a pause button.
And if your game supports game
controllers you must support
or you must handle the
pause button being pressed.
And you're going to want
to treat this as a toggle.
Go from pause to unpause
and unpause back to paused.
Consider your UI
state, some situations
in your game it maybe
appropriate to do nothing.
Let's look at an example.
So, were back inside of our
setup controllers method
and its really as
simple as this,
whenever you have a controller
that your game is going to use,
use the controller
paused handler,
set that up in this case
whenever the controllers pause
button is pressed.
This block is run and we toggle
the pause state of the game.
Also controllers are going
to have player indicator
LED's on them.
And it's your job
to assign these.
These communicates
to your player
that your game has recognized
the controller and is using it.
And in the case of multi
controller games we will give
the player an indication as to
which player they
are in your game.
These LED's are persistent and
so as a controller disconnects
and reconnects its going to
maintain the same player index.
Now, the player index property
on a controller is what you use
to set the player
indicator LED's.
We have a constant called
GCControllerPlayerIndexUnset.
And in this example
were checking
if the indexes indeed
unset and if
so assigning it to player one.
You'll notice we have a
zero based index game.
In a multiple controller
game you might check if any
of the currently connected
controllers are unset and if
so display a UI to the player
so that they can choose
which players go on
which teams for instance.
All right.
Now, that you have all the
technical information let's take
a step back and talk about best
practices following these you're
going to be able to integrate
game controllers in a way
that really makes
sense and works
with the player's intentions.
So, first of all just
to reiterate games cannot
require a controller.
Game controllers are
optional for players.
You're going to want
to focus your efforts
on the native controls
of the system.
So, that means touch
and motion on iOS
and keyboard and mouse on OS X.
And this is so that you
can reach a hundred percent
of the players who
play your game.
For the players who buy a
gamepad controller you can offer
them the enhanced experience
that you're going to create.
Also, follow standard
gameplay conventions.
So, the face buttons A and B you
can use those and we recommend
that you use them as the
A button being your action
or confirmation button and the B
button being your cancel button.
Now, when talking
about connecting
and disconnecting think of this
from the player's perspective.
There's player intent
behind each
of these notifications
that you get.
When you have a connected
event the player has plugged
in their controller into the
game, or into your device
and they want to play
with the controller.
And so, in that case off
load some of the native input
on to the controller
wherever appropriate.
Also eliminate the
player indicator LED's
so that the player knows
that the game has
recognized the controllers
and is ready to use them.
And lastly, a lot of games have
on screen overlays
like a pause button.
This is entirely appropriate
for a touch base game.
But with a controller connected
the controller already has a
pause button so you can
offload that on screen element
to the controller freeing
up additional real
estate on your screen.
Similarly when disconnecting the
player is saying I don't want
to use this controller
any longer at the moment
or maybe there is elements
or maybe there's reasons
out of their control why this
controller happen to disconnect.
In either case, pause
the gameplay
if you're engaged in gameplay.
Also, return to regular controls
'cause the game has no guarantee
that the player is
going to return back
with controller based controls.
And lastly, think
through your input
so as Jacques mentioned touch
controls allow you amazing
abilities to directly manipulate
your onscreen objects.
And controllers are
great for other tasks
like precise inputs filling the
tactile feedback of the buttons
in the controllers
against your fingers.
Repeatability of actions.
And there's real magic we think
in marrying these two together.
And as game designers
you have to think
about what game mechanics make
most sense with touch and motion
and which ones makes
most sense to use
as physical controller inputs.
For more information please
contact Allan Shaffer or any
of the resources on the screen.
There's some upcoming
sessions you're going
to want to be aware of.
Sprite Kit is an
amazing new framework
for creating sprite based games.
We have two sessions tomorrow
and there's also an
OpenGL session on Thursday.
Thank you for your attention.
[ Applause ]