[ Applause ]
>> Welcome.
My name is Jim.
I'm an engineer on the
OpenCL team at Apple.
Our purpose with today's
session is threefold.
First, I'm going to talk to
the newbies in the audience,
those of you who have an
application, are wondering
about OpenCL, if
it's appropriate
for your application.
My goal is to give
you a checklist.
So if you answer the
questions on the checklist,
you'll have a good idea
of OpenCL is appropriate
for your application
and also how to use it.
Then my colleague, Abe,
is going to talk to you
about some best practices
and some performance tips
for using OpenCL in Mavericks.
And then last we have
Dave McGavran from Adobe,
and he's going to show you
how Adobe has used OpenCL
to accelerate portions of
the video processing pipeline
in Adobe Premiere, and he
has a really cool demo,
so stick around for that.
So let's first talk about
where OpenCL is going to work.
When we launched CL in Snow
Leopard, you could use OpenCL
on the CPU on any Mac, but
if you wanted to use OpenCL
on the GPU, you were limited to
those machines we were shipping
that had certain discrete
GPUs, an AMD or NVIDIA GPU.
So what about Mavericks?
Well, now we're happy to say
that you can also use the
integrated GPUs from Intel,
starting with HD 4000.
So what that means for you guys
is that OpenCL is now supported
on the CPU and the GPU on all
shipping Macs, so that's great.
So let's get to this
checklist I was talking about.
Your first question you ask is
"am I waiting for something?"
So what do I mean by that?
I mean you start up
your application,
you click the Go button
to do something cool,
and there's a progress
bar, and you wait
and you wait and you wait.
Or maybe you have some cool
video processing program
and you want to render effects
on the frames in realtime
but once you kick on the
effects everything slows down,
it's choppy.
That's what I'm talking about.
So, like any good
developer, what do you do?
You fire up Instruments
and take a look
at your application running, you
look at it with Time Profiler.
And that's going to let you
zero in and find the part
of the program and
causing you to slow down.
That's the piece I want you
to hold in your mind as we go
through this checklist.
But maybe the answer
to this question is no,
but maybe the reason
is you've avoided doing
something intensive.
So maybe there's this
really cool new algorithm
that you really wanted to put
into your application
but you were afraid.
You were afraid that
if you did that,
it's going to slow it down,
your users will hate you,
so you don't have to be afraid,
maybe OpenCL is the doorway
to this new algorithm
that you want to use.
So let's say you can
answer yes to either
of these two questions.
So then you want to ask yourself
about that piece of code,
about that code pathway, "do
I have a parallel workload?"
Now, a lot of you people
probably know what I mean
when I say a parallel workload,
but let's just make sure
everyone is on the same page
like we always do with
a really terrible haiku.
Pieces of data, all changing in
the same way, few dependencies.
So you can count my syllables
and I'll go through these lines
and tell you what they mean.
Pieces of data is
pretty obvious.
Anytime you're going to do
computation you have data
that you need to process.
All changing in the same way
is a little bit more subtle.
That means that for each
piece of data, you're going
to apply the same
instructions, the same program
to each piece of data.
And few dependencies is
the worst one of all.
What that means is
that the results
of one computation
is not needed for any
of the other computations, or
while I'm doing my computation,
I don't need to know
what my neighbor did.
They're all independent.
So that's what we mean when
we say "a parallel workload."
So let's make this
concrete, image processing.
Canonical example.
You want to sepia tone this big
cat, so you're going to pluck
out a pixel, you're going
to throw it through the math
that changes it to sepia,
and then you're going
to plop it back into
the right spot.
Okay, that's a classical
example of a parallel workload,
and in fact core image
in Mavericks is running
on top of CL on the GPU.
But we don't want you
to think that CL is only
for graphics type stuff.
So, when we showed CL first
in 2009 we showed you this
really cool physics simulation.
Now, we showed you the
results using pretty graphics,
but the guts of what was
happening, the computation
that was moving the bodies
around in space according
to the physics calculations,
that's just arbitrary
computation, and we want you
to remember that when
thinking about CL.
CL is good for arbitrary
computation like this.
And in fact, an example
of a parallel workload
that you might not even consider
is grepping a large file.
Think about what you
do when you grep.
You open up this file, you
look at the file line by line
and you apply the same
regular expression
to each line of the file.
That's an example of a problem
that you might be able
to apply CL to solve.
So let's say you
look at your problem
and it's not exactly parallel.
So the question then becomes
"Can you earn a parallel
workload?",
and this is usually
the trickiest piece.
What I mean by "earn" is,
can you take your non-parallel
problem and twist it somehow
or change it so that
it becomes parallel?
So let's look at an example
of a problem like that.
Consider computing a
histogram of an image.
So for the image you have
some RGBA image, 8-bit color,
and you have a histogram
for each color channel,
one bucket per possible
color value.
And what you do is you look
at the pixels in the image --
so let's just look
at one of them --
so we look at this guy and we
see he has a red value of 79,
green of 148, and blue of 186.
Fine. So we go to each
histogram, we find the bin
that we're supposed to increment
and we knock it up by 1.
So for example here we
would increment the 79 bin
for red, increment it by 1.
So, at the end of the day
you have this nice histogram
which gives you a
distribution of the color
as it's used in the image.
And you'll have a good idea
of how colors are being used,
and more importantly your
algorithm will have an idea
of how color is being used.
Image histogram is
an intermediate step
in a lot of cool algorithms.
So this feels like one of these
parallel problems I just talked
about, so what's the problem?
Why is this not parallel
to begin with?
Well, let's look at just
2 pixels in parallel,
so let's look at these two.
Now, these two happen to have
the same blue channel value.
So what's going to happen?
They're both going to go to
that blue bin they map to,
let's say the value
in there is 35 --
they're both going to read out
35, increment it by 1 to 36,
and try to write it back.
So that's a problem.
You have a classic collision.
You're going to have the
incorrect value in that slot.
So what do we do when we
hit a problem like this?
Well, normally you synchronize
around that code, you would make
that an atomic operation.
You've taken some problem
that seems very parallel
but there's this
serial bit of it
that just really ruins your day.
So now we have to get clever.
So what we can do instead
is we break the image
into groups of pixels.
So let's take a look
at one group.
Let's look at that one.
So what we're going to do in
this group is the same thing
that we were going to
do to the whole image.
We're still going to
compute a histogram
for that group of pixels.
But instead of a
global histogram,
we're going to update
only a partial histogram.
So this group's going to
have its own histogram
for each color channel,
and it's only going
to update that histogram.
And all the groups, each group
has its own partial histogram.
So the thing is, these
collisions that I talked
about for the whole
image, they still exist
for the partial histograms,
but only within this group.
And OpenCL has a lot
of language facilities
that expose underlying
hardware that let you deal
with these collisions
within a group very quickly.
So we also get a win, because
all these groups can operate
in parallel, so we've taken this
and we've made this parallel.
Okay, so we're done, right.
Well, not yet, because
now we kind
of have what we don't
really want.
We have this big pile
of partial histograms.
What we wanted was
one total histogram.
So now we have a second step,
a new step to the algorithm.
This time our data
is not the image.
Forget about the image; it's
this partial histogram set.
And now each independent
thread of execution --
which in OpenCL is called a
work item -- they have a job.
This guy's job is
to sum up bin 79.
So what will he do?
He walks down through all
the partial histograms,
summing up bin 79, and
he writes the result
in that total histogram.
Now, he's the only one
writing to that slot,
so there's no more collisions
in the total histogram.
So what we've done here is
we've taken this problem,
this image histogram problem,
we've twisted it just a little
bit and made it purely parallel.
And the cool thing is,
we do this for all the
partial histograms,
all threads operating
all together,
all these work items
in parallel.
So if you can answer
yes to either
of these first two
questions and yes to either
of the second two questions,
then you have a problem
that is probably
appropriate for OpenCL.
That's good.
So now the question is "do I
run it on the CPU or the GPU?"
You've probably heard that you
can run it in either place.
This breaks down
to three questions.
Where is my data now,
where is my data destined,
and by that I mean
destined to be used,
and how hard am I working
on each piece of data?
So let's look at some data.
Now, this happens to be image
data, but again, remember,
arbitrary computations,
just some data on the host,
and by host I just mean your
CPU, in its memory space,
memory that you get
through malloc, for example.
Okay, so when you do
computation on this data,
you process it somehow.
The computation is
exemplified by this green arrow.
If you were to measure
the total time you spent,
it's going to be the total time
you spent doing the compute.
This is a normal situation;
now let's bring OpenCL
into the picture.
When you're doing compute
with an OpenCL device,
OpenCL has to be able to see
that memory you want to work on.
So normally you have to sort of
"transfer" it over to OpenCL,
and we'll define that
transfer in a second.
Then you can do your
compute in OpenCL,
and then if your host
wants to use that memory,
it has to be able
to see that memory.
So then you have to give
that memory back to the host.
So now when we're talking
about the total time,
it's not just your compute
time, hopefully faster,
it's also this transfer time.
So let's talk about that, this
transfer time, what is that?
It depends on your device.
If you're on a discrete GPU,
that's a function of the amount
of data you want to send and
your bus speed, the PCIe bus.
That makes sense, got to
get it over to the VRAM,
get it over to the device.
But if you're working on the
CPU as your OpenCL device,
this transfer time is
nothing, because the host
and the OpenCL device share
the same memory space.
And if you're on
the integrated GPU,
sometimes this is also nothing.
Now, that's a maybe
because this is only true
if you're using OpenCL buffers.
If you're using images, a
copy still has to be made,
because the integrated GPU will
set up that image data in a way
that takes advantage of
texture caches, stuff like that.
So now you have an idea of
what that transfer cost is.
Now, what about the compute --
now this might go without
saying, but if you're working
on a problem like I described,
one of these data
parallel problems,
the OpenCL device is
going to beat the code
that you're writing on the host.
So let's just get that out there
right now, so for these kind
of problems, OpenCL
is going to win.
So let's look at a problem like
this, where you're doing a lot
of computation relative
to the amount
of data transfer you're doing.
Lot of compute versus
data transfer.
In this case this is an ideal
scenario for the discrete GPU.
This is where you want
to use the discrete GPU,
because this transfer
cost that you incur
by using the discrete GPU
is dwarfed by the amount
of win you get for the compute.
Now, what about a
situation like this.
Here you're doing
a lot of transfer
and not so much compute.
You're spending too much
time doing transfer.
In this case you might want
to consider it using the
OpenCL CPU device or staying
on the integrated GPU, and then
that transfer cost may go away.
Now, remember, I talked about
the question of where is my data
at now and where is
it destined to be.
Well, let's imagine that you're
using an OpenCL device, the GPU,
that it happens to also
be the display device.
You might be sharing data with
say, OpenGL, like Chris talked
about in the previous session
or IOSurface, like this.
This data is the same and
it's already on the GPU.
Likewise, you might be doing
some computation then using the
result of that to be displayed
to the user, for example; again,
shared through GL or shared
through IOSurface,
or you may have both.
In this case, it's
kind of obvious:
stay on the GPU and
do your compute.
Your data's already there,
it's going to be used
there, just stay there.
Even in a situation like this,
where your data is starting
on the host and then is going
to be displayed to the user
on the GPU after processing,
it makes sense even
if the transfer cost might
be a little bit high,
to go to the CL device --
that's the same as the display
device -- do your compute there,
because that leaves your host
free to do other computation.
So let's just talk a bit,
for those of you who weren't
in the previous session,
about the kind of data
that might be on the device.
We said we can share
with GL or IOSurface,
so let's talk about GL.
Now, GL has a lot of
different that it can have.
As an example, it can have
vertex buffer objects,
it can have textures,
and you use those
and you render some
cool picture.
Now, that picture might
be a texture attachment
or a render buffer
attachment to an FBO.
Great. And along the way
you can hit that in OpenGL
with some cool shaders to
produce some nice effects.
So where does CL fit
into this picture?
Well, typically you would
share something like the VBO
as a CL mem object,
as a CL buffer.
And likewise, you
would share textures
or render buffer
attachments with OpenCL
as an image memory object.
And where it fits into the
pipeline is right here.
You're going to use a CL to
modify or generate vertex data
in that VBO, and then you might
want to do some post processing
in CL after you're done
with your other GL pipeline,
and you might want to do
that because you can maybe
express things more cleanly
in the OpenCL programming
language than you could in say,
a GLSL shader, or you might
want to launch your CL kernel
over a smaller domain than
what GLSL will let you do.
Now I do want to say
one thing to the people
who are already using
CLGL sharing.
So previously in 2011 we
told you that the sort
of paradigm you should follow
when using shared objects in CL
from GL is flush, acquire,
compute, release --
you're going to finish with your
GL commands and call glFlush,
and then you're going to
clEnqueueAcquireGLPObjects,
do your compute, wail on it
with CL, whatever you want,
and then call
clEnqueueReleaseGLObjects.
And within that function call
we internally will call clFlush
for you to make sure
your CL commands made it
down to the GPU before
GL would go do more work
with those objects.
That has changed.
In Mavericks we want you
to follow something else.
You notice that "acquire" has
disappeared from the list.
Flush, compute, flush,
or maybe "Flush
when you're done,"
something like that.
So first you're going to
call glFlushRenderAPPLE,
and then you're going
to do your compute,
to call clFlush.
Now, you call that.
Before, we did that for you.
And notice this is
glFlushRenderAPPLE, so why that?
Well, for single-buffered
contexts,
this allows you to avoid a blit.
If you have a double-buffered
context, this doesn't matter.
It's the same as glFlush.
There's no penalty to
using it so just use it.
And then I mentioned IOSurface
is another way you might be
sharing with CL.
So if Mac OS X technologies
are Tolkienian creatures,
IOSurface would be Gandalf.
It's a container for 2D image
data, and it's really magical
in that you can set up an
IOSurface in one process
and then just using the
IOSurface handle you can use it
in another process,
through the IOSurface API,
and that process might be 64-bit
where the other process
is 32-bit.
And more, that process might
be sharing the IOSurface
with OpenGL, which is hammering
on this data on the GPU.
And we make sure, under the
covers, that this data is always
in the right place
at the right time
and you have the consistent,
correct view of the data.
So it's really cool,
especially for those
of you working on video.
You can get your video frames
as IOSurfaces fairly easily
and then share those with CL
or GL and do some cool things
to them, so please do that.
Now, we talked about IOSurface
sharing in detail in 2011.
I talked about that in the
talk, "What's New in OpenCL,"
so if you want to learn more
details, go listen to that talk.
It's on the developer website.
And also, Ken Dyke had an
excellent talk in 2010 called
"Taking Advantage of
Multiple GPUs" where he talks
about IOSurface in some detail.
So that brings us back
to this checklist.
So those of you who walked
in here and had no idea
if CL was appropriate for you,
you should have a better idea,
but if not, come talk
to us in the lab.
It's right after the
session; we'll be there.
I do want to say something
about the OpenCL programming
model, though, before I go.
So if you look at
the OpenCL spec,
you'll see that it's 400 pages.
And even the OpenCL Programming
Guide, which is a good book,
a gentler introduction, it's
not exactly a lightweight tome.
But I'm going to give you an
easy way to think about OpenCL.
It breaks down into two pieces.
It's a C-like programming
language and a runtime API,
so let's talk about
the language first.
We say "C-like" because it's
basically C with some new types,
and has some nice
built-in functions
to make your life easier.
And you describe your work
from the perspective
of one piece of data.
Remember, we talked
about in the haiku,
"all changing in the same way."
That's what you do in
your OpenCL kernel,
which what you write with the
OpenCL programming language.
You do this all the time,
every day when you write code.
You write a loop, and
in your loop you say
"For My data, do this thing."
Well, "this thing,"
that's your OpenCL kernel.
Let's look at an example.
Here's a bunch of C code.
Let's go through it bit by bit.
So first, what are we doing?
We're converting a big
image from RGB to HSV.
So first we're going
to loop over the data.
That's what we have to
do, a pixel at a time.
Once we're inside the
loop what pixel do I do?
Oh, I'll use the
loop indices to find
out what pixel I
should modify, great.
I grab that pixel, I
shift out the color values
because it's stored in one
integer, and then I convert
that to floating
point because my RGB
to HSV conversion function,
which I'm going to show you
in a second, expects float.
Fine. I call that function
and I write back the
result to my output image.
Seems easy.
And let's take a look at
this RGB to HSV function.
You don't have to know what's
going on here, I just want you
to notice it's a
simple function,
takes in some parameters,
RGB, and writes out HSV,
according to the algorithm
for the algorithm
for converting this.
So let's turn this
into an OpenCL kernel.
Now, remember, an OpenCL kernel
is launched over some domain.
In this case we've
launched our kernel
over a 2-dimensional domain
that corresponds exactly
to the number of pixels
in the X and Y dimension.
So this kernel will run for
each pixel of the image.
And you can see here
that every instance
of the kernel that's running
is going to have access
to that input and output image.
So how do we find out
what pixel to work on?
Well, here we call some
OpenCL built-in functions,
getglobalid(0) and
getglobalid(1).
That gives us the global ID in
the first and second dimensions.
This happens to correspond
to X and Y.
So then we use another
OpenCL built-in, readimagef.
And that will tap the input
image at that coordinate
and give us back 4
channel float data.
Now, notice, this
doesn't know anything
about the underlying
image format.
That's one nice thing about
using an OpenCL kernel.
You can swap out image
formats and OpenCL,
the kernel will still do
the right thing for you.
And then you're going to
call the conversion function
like before, and you're going
to use another built-in,
writeimagef, to write
the output.
So let's dive into
the kernel version
of this conversion function.
So here it is.
Now you probably don't
have a photographic memory,
but it looks a lot like
the previous version.
I do want to call out one thing.
You can see here that we
only have one parameter.
We're taking the input pixel
and then returning a
float4 output pixel.
But otherwise, this looks a
lot like the previous function,
so let's just bounce back
and forth between them here.
So here's the CL version
and that's the C version.
So CL, C.
So you can go back
afterwards and see
that they're almost identical,
so it really is just the guts
of the loop that
we've extracted out.
That's not always that easy, but
usually this is where you start
when you're writing
your CL kernel.
So let's talk for a second
about the runtime API.
Now, if you look at the OpenCL
API there's a lot of functions
in there, but really they break
down into three categories,
I'd say, discovery,
setup, and execution.
Discovery.
That lets you ask, "hey,
OpenCL, what devices are there
on my Mac for doing compute?"
Straightforward.
And then more interestingly,
"hey, given this device,
what's the best way
to break up my work?"
And that's because your
integrated GPU and your CPU
and your discrete GPU, they
all have different parallel
capabilities, so you would
use the answers from this part
of the API to decide how to
break up your work the best.
Setup. "Hey OpenCL,
I have this kernel,
compile it and let me use it."
Or "hey, OpenCL, set
aside this memory.
I'm going to do some
compute and I want
to write the result there."
That's setup, pretty
straightforward.
And then finally, execution.
Once you have this all set
up, you want to say, "okay,
fill up that memory with
this data that I have here
on the host, or run this
kernel and run that one.
Do my work," basically.
So, hopefully I've
given you an idea of how
to start thinking about OpenCL.
And like I said, if you have
more questions, come down
and see us in the lab.
And with that I'd like
to hand it off to Abe,
who's going to talk to you
about some practical tasks.
[ Applause ]
>> Abe: Good afternoon.
My name's Abe Stevens, and I'm
an engineer on the OpenCL team,
and today I'm going to talk
about some practical tasks
that you can do with OpenCL,
and I'm going to focus
on a couple features that we've
added for OpenCL and 10.9.
I'm going to tell you how
to take advantage of some
of the program loading
and compiler features
that we've added to
decrease the startup time
of your applications, and then
I'm going to take a step back
and talk about how to save
power on laptop configurations
by using the discrete GPU and
setting your application up so
that it can transition
to the integrated CPU,
since we now support
Intel HD graphics on all
of our shipping configurations.
And then I'm going to talk
about a couple features
that are related in some ways
to what Jim just told you about.
Jim was talking about how
to look at the transfer time
that your application requires
to transfer data from the host
to the GPU, and I'm going
to show you a couple ways
of reducing that transfer
time and reducing the amount
of copying your application
has to do.
So let me start off
by talking about how
to address the start-up time,
or the time it takes for you
to load OpenCL programs when
you start your application.
In OpenCL there are really
three different functions
that contribute to a slow
startup: building a CL program,
compiling that program
and linking that program,
which are three different
steps that a program has to go
through before you end up
with an executable binary
that you can execute on a GPU.
Now, in OpenCL you can generate
these programs using three
different types of input.
You can start with a
piece of CL source code,
and that can be either a string
that you produced at runtime
or maybe a string that
you loaded from a .cl file
that you shipped with
your application.
It can be an LLVM bitcode file,
and that can be a bitcode file
that you generated in Xcode
using a .cl file at build time
and that was shipped
with your app.
And then the third type
of input that I'll talk
about the most today is an
executable binary specifically
for the device that's in the
system that's running the app.
And this is something
that you can create
at runtime the first time your
app launches and then use it
on subsequent launches to really
decrease that startup time.
So let me show you how much
faster using executable binaries
can really be.
Let's say we have a
really simple application.
This is a 30-line CL
kernel which is going
to load a couple pixels
or read pixel values.
It's actually used as
a macro here to load,
pixels and a stencil, and then
it's going to take these values,
compute them and use them to
process a simple video effect.
Now, if you take this
application or this kernel
and you sort of set
up the system
in the worst possible
kind of case,
where the compiler
service hasn't started,
the program hasn't ever run
before, it might take the system
about 200 milliseconds
to compile that CL kernel
and give you an executable
program binary.
Now, if you had started with the
same system in that cold state
with a bitcode file that
you generated in Xcode,
you could do it in about
half the amount of time,
so about 80 milliseconds.
Now, if you had a warm system
or maybe you'd launched
the application recently
and the compiler service
was started and some
of the data was cached it
actually gets a lot faster.
That source, compiling from
source, can go down to about 1
to 2 milliseconds, same
thing for the bitcode file
and here is the kicker.
Here's the really neat thing.
If you'd had an executable
binary already,
and so you could skip
all that compiler work,
you could actually get started
and start executing the program
in under 1 millisecond.
So let me show you how to set
up your application to do that.
Well the first step is
to actually start off
with either a .cl source
file or a bitcode file,
and you would want to
take this and load it
into your application,
and in this case I'm going
to show you how to
use a bitcode file.
Bitcode files are a great
way of avoiding having
to ship source code
in your application.
You can ship the bitcode
file in this case for 32 GPUs
and load it at runtime.
Here I'm going to load
this using some Cocoa code
and then pass it to
CLCreate program with binary
and then build the program,
then I end up with this
executable device binary.
I can take that binary
and save it to a cache,
and I'll show you how to figure
out where to put that cache
in a second, but in order
to extract the binary I
just call CLGetProgramInfo
and pack it into a Coca
data object and then store
that out to the file system.
So I call GetProgramInfo and
get the size of the binary
and then the actual binary
data itself, and then send it
out to the file system.
Now, let's say the user has
stopped using the application
and they started up again
later on, and I want to figure
out if I have a cache
file that I can load.
So if I look in my
caches directory,
I can compute just using
some simple Cocoa code here,
a location that a cache file
would be located and then try
to pull it into memory, and
if that's successful, I can go
and pass the executable binary
into CLCreateProgram with binary
and then CLBUild program.
So that's what I'm
going to do here.
You'll notice there's actually
some error checking code
in here, and this is important.
It's possible that
the runtime will --
even if you did have that
binary, even if we were able
to load it successfully from
the file system, it's possible
that the runtime might refuse
to load an executable binary
and it could do that for a
couple of different reasons.
It might be that your user took
their home directory and moved
on to a different machine
or they moved that binary
onto a different computer, maybe
they installed a software update
and the software update
installed new graphics driver
versions and the graphics driver
versions ended up not supporting
that particular executable
binary version.
And if that happens, your app
has to have a fallback path
that it can go back
to to regenerate the
executable device binary.
And so of course, that
fallback path could be as simple
as going back to whatever
mechanism we used two slides ago
to produce the binary in the
first place if you go back
to source code or
to a bitcode file.
So after you pull that binary
from disk and you pass it to CL,
CreateProgramwith Binary and
CL build program, check to see
if this invalid binary error
came back, and if it did,
make sure your app is a fallback
path and of course you won't
at the sub millisecond build
time but you'll be able
to take advantage of the faster
device executable binary load
times on subsequent
launches of your app.
So I took the code that we
just saw, and I applied it
to a couple different
programs, the 30-line program
that I showed you the
very first part of,
and then a 1,000-line program
that was actually from an app
that we were working on,
and then I had a much larger
test case, 4,000 line program.
And you can see that the
time to load source code
in each case kind of went
up quite a bit for each
of these different programs.
I went from 200 milliseconds
to 3,000 milliseconds
in the worst case.
But the best case here to load
that executable binary was
always under 1 millisecond.
And so really, depending on --
regardless of how big your
program ends up being,
taking advantage of that
executable binary can save you a
lot of time at startup.
Now I'd like to talk
about another topic,
which is that in 10.9, OpenCL
is supported on integrated GPUs,
the Intel HD Graphics,
and of course,
it's also supported
on discrete GPUs.
And so if you're working
on a configuration
like this Macbook Pro Retina,
you'll see that the
discrete GPU, the Nvidia 650
and the integrated
GPU both support CL,
and if you can take
advantage of both of those,
one thing you can do is
save power for your users.
And so OpenGL apps
have actually been able
to do this for quite some time.
Now, an OpenGL app running on
this GPU has a choice to make;
it can either run only
on the discrete device
or it can support what's called
automatic graphic switching,
and when it supports automatic
graphing switching it's been
written in a certain way
and it follows conventions
that allow it to transition
from the discrete GPU
to the integrated GPU if the
system tells it to do so,
and if it does that,
all the applications
in the system are able
to make that transition,
that can save power for the user
when there aren't any
applications running
that require that discrete GPU.
So let me show you how
to do this with OpenCL.
Now if you have an
OpenGL application,
you probably have
an NSOpenGLView.
If you're working
on an application
that doesn't use Cocoa, you can
actually do the same kind --
perform the same operations
in a slightly different way,
but in your NSOpenGLView
you probably have some code
that checks to see what the
current virtual screen is.
And here, my NSOpenGL
View is keeping track
of the last virtual it used
to render the previous frame,
and it's going to compare
that to the virtual screen
that the GL context is
asking you to render
into for the next frame,
and it'll check to see
if these two things
are different.
And if the two virtual
screens are mismatched,
it's going to execute a couple
of8 GL commands to check and see
if the new device, that
new virtual screen,
the device associated with that
is capable of running everything
that it needs to execute.
And it might adapt its usage,
it might use smaller textures
or avoid using certain
extensions
or otherwise adapt its usage.
Now, we want to do the same
kind of thing in OpenCL
when we detect that
this render has changed.
And so since OpenCL
doesn't use virtual screens;
it uses CL Device IDS, we need
to call the function that --
actually, Chris showed you this
function in the previous talk --
CGLGetDevices for
CurrentVirtual Screen Apple.
What that'll do is it'll map
whatever our current Virtual
Screen is from a virtual screen
to, ID'd back to a CL device ID,
and then we can start creating
that CL Device ID and learn more
about the new device that
we're supposed to use.
So CL does actually a
lot of the conversion
between two devices
automatically because a bit part
of the OpenCL API is the ability
to work with multiple devices
and to say run operations
on two different CPUs,
or the CPU and GPU.
So a lot of the CL objects
are context level objects,
and they'll handle sort of
switching from one device
to another automatically.
Memory objects, images
and buffers will do that.
CL kernel objects will handle
moving between the two devices
and of course programs, if
they're built for both devices,
will handle the transition
as well.
Also if you have
an event dependency
or you create an event
on one command cue,
that event will sort of work
and will track a dependency
if you associate it -- or you
tell a command that's cued
on a different command
cue to wait for the event.
There are a couple of things
that you need to
check in OpenCL.
And those are that you have
to make sure your context
that you're using
contains both devices
and so you can create
command cues for both devices.
And of course, you have to make
sure that if you create programs
for the two devices,
that you create them
for either the right executable
binaries, or if there are PPUs
in this case, that
you create them
with this GPU 32 bitcode file.
And so there are other things
that you might have
to check as well.
These are less common.
It's possible that if your
program is using Double
Precision and you have
some highly tuned numerics
in your program,
when you compile this
for the integrated
device, it'll be --
instead of running
with double it'll run
with single prevision floating
point, and you have to make sure
that that's enough precision
for your application.
Another thing to check is
that a lot of the capabilities
of the devices are a
little bit different,
and so the kernel work group
size of the integrated GPU
and the discrete GPU
will be different,
so when you initialize OpenCL,
you compile your programs,
you should check to see what
your kernel work group size is
of the discrete GPU, of course,
and record that and figure
out how large of
kernels to launch,
and then do the same thing
for the integrated GPU.
That way when you detect this
switch, it'll be really easy
for you to switch
to in cuing kernels
that use the appropriate likely
smaller work group sizes.
So now I'd like to go over a
couple of performance features
that we've added in 10.9,
and these features have to do
with reducing the cost of memory
transfers or reducing the time
that our application
will spend waiting
for transfers to complete.
And the first thing
I'd like to talk
about is buffers and images.
In OpenCL, buffers are
really just like pointers
to memory in your kernel.
You can read and write them,
manipulate them as
global pointers.
You probably saw those in the
example Jim showed earlier.
Buffers support atomic
operations and on most GPUs,
the global memory that you use
to access buffers is
usually not cached,
and so sometimes it
can be higher latency
to access tasks as
buffer objects.
Image objects are kind
of like GL textures.
They're either read
only or write only,
so you have to decide when
you're writing a kernel
if you're going to either
only read or only write
for a particular object.
And they support
harbor filtering.
So what if you had an instance
where you wanted
to support both?
Say for example, you
had this set of kernels
where you have a histogram
operation and then you would
like to output data in
a floating point array
but then later on, perform a
read image operation where you'd
like some hardware
texture filtering.
Well, in 10.9 we
supported the image 2D
for buffering extension,
and this allows us
to basically take a buffer
object that we've created here
and wrap it with
an image object.
So here the image
object has been sized
so that it contains enough
pixels to fill the buffer,
and I'm essentially wrapping the
allocated buffer with an image,
and then in my kernel
I'll be able to --
or in two different
kernels, I'll be able
to access the same underlying
piece of memory once as a buffer
and then also as an image.
So when you're using
image 2D from buffer,
you have to be careful of a
couple of different things.
One thing is that if you've
created the buffer using
UseHostPointer, which
is a popular technique,
you have to make sure that
the UseHostPointer address
that you pass in matches the
device's base address alignment.
You also have to make sure
that if you specify a row pitch
that the row pitch
matches or is a multiple
of the pitch alignment for
that particular device.
Now, in computeApps,
data movement is --
there are a lot of different
patterns for data movement
and Jim talked about
a few of these
in the previous section
of the talk.
One common pattern is a pattern
where you write some data
to the device, you process
on it, you execute a couple
of kernels, and then
you read back that data.
And so that would look something
like this, and this is common
in say video kind of operation
where for each frame you're
writing it to ComputeDevice,
processing it for a little
while, and then reading it back
and maybe encoding it.
In this kind of a
system, let's say it takes
about 2 milliseconds to
move those pieces of data
to the device and 6 milliseconds
to do the processing.
Well, that would be about 10
milliseconds per iteration.
And so if I was going
to do 100 iterations,
I'd end up spending
1,000 milliseconds
and I'd only really actually
be doing compute work
for 60% of that time.
Well, it turns out in many
discrete GPUs there's some DMA
hardware that can allow us to
overlap the read and write work
with the compute work.
And so if we take a look
at a piece of compute work,
say integration N here,
we can try to think
about what the system
might schedule using
in a DMA engine for iteration N.
So for example, the system
could schedule the readback
of the previous frame.
So we know that the
system is done,
the GPU is done processing
work for NMIs 1
and so it can do the
readback for that frame.
It could also actually,
since there's no dependency
between each frame, it
could also do the --
it could also write for
it and write iteration
and +1s data out to the GPU.
And so if we repeat
this pattern,
we can see that we can
keep the DMAengine busy
and also keep the
computeEngine busy
for most of these iterations.
And so if I look across
all of my 100 iterations,
I might be able to do this
in about 40% less time --
a little more than 40% the time
by fully subscribing
both the DMA
and the compute sides
of the device.
To set this up in OpenCL,
I'd want to write some code
that looks something like this.
Here I'm using nonblocking
read and write commands,
and of course my
EnqueueKerneland my
EnqueueNDRange command is always
nonblocking, so I'm going to set
up the first kernel and
then have a pipeline loop
that iterates over
the body of the work,
and then at the end I clean that
up by enqueueing the last kernel
and then reading
back the last result.
And this code will work for
M input and output buffers.
In a sort of practical system
I'd probably have a relatively
much smaller pool of buffers
that I'd work on, much smaller
than say 100 buffers, and I
might have to track dependencies
and make sure that it's
safe to reuse a buffer
after it's been sent
to the device.
So before I close, I'd like to
talk about some programming tips
for using OpenCL and
these apply to 10.9
and to the other implementations
of OpenCL that we've shipped.
One tip that we have is
that when you're able to,
you should prefer passing page
line pointers to the system.
So if you create or an image
as a used host pointer,
try to pass in something that
page lined, you can also pass
in pageline pointers when you
have to read or write data
into the system and
the driver will try
to take an optimized
path when you do that.
One way of getting
pageline pointers is
to call POSIX Memoline
instead of Malik
when you're allocating
a host buffer.
Another tip that we have
is to avoid using CLFInish.
It's great for debugging
and for isolating a problem
in your code, but it'll create
sort of large bottlenecks
or bubbles in your
pipeline, and is not something
that you should use in
production code in most cases.
If you do need help debugging,
you can use CLLog error,
which is an environment
variable that you can set
and it will turn on
verbose log messages
in case there's an API
problem, or if you're trying
to debug a problem with
a kernel on the GPU,
consider using printf.
So Open CL Mavericks, today
we talked about a mechanism
for loading your program faster
using executable binaries,
and the important part there
was to have a fallback mechanism
so that if there is a binary
and compatibility your app
can fall back and load either
from the code files
or from source.
Then we talked about how to
make sure your app follows the
conventions that are necessary
to support automatic
graphic switching
so that you can reduce
battery life if you're able
to move everything over
to the integrated GPU.
And lastly, we talked
about a couple mechanisms
that are available to
decrease the overhead of having
to copy data from the
host to the device.
And so now I'd like to hand
the talk over to David McGavran
from Adobe, who's going to tell
us about how he's used OpenCL
and Adobe Premiere Pro, and
I think he has a demo for us.
[ Applause ]
>> David McGavran:
Good afternoon.
My name's David McGavran, I'm
the senior engineering manager
on Adobe Premiere Pro.
So about a year and a
half ago, we announced
that we ported the
entire GP rendering engine
in Premiere Pro to OpenCL.
That was a big announcement
for us.
It was a really exciting
time for us and we were doing
that specifically to
target the Macbook Pro
that shipped at that time.
So we're very excited about
that, and we came here
to WWDC last year and we
talked to this session
about the improvements we
made in Premiere using OpenCL
and it was really exciting.
This year I want to talk about
what we've done since then.
We obviously didn't
stop working,
and OpenCL is a great way
to really excite our users
and really make them
enjoy working in Premiere.
So I want to talk about the
differences in Premiere Pro CS6
to what we're doing in Adobe
Premiere Pro CC that's shipping
in four days.
So last year in Premiere Pro
CS6, we were very careful
about what we targeted.
It was a massive effort to port
the entire GPU engine to OpenCL,
and so we were very careful.
We targeted just 2 GPUs.
We targeted the GPUs that
were in the Macbook Pro line
at the time, so the
650M and the 670M.
Well, we've been getting
much better at OpenCL,
and we've done a
lot more testing,
so the first thing we're
going to do is we're going
to really increase the places
where you can use
Premiere Pro on OpenCL.
So you can see here,
we support just
about every card that's
shipping in Macintoshes today.
The other thing that
we've done is now
that we know how well we can
take advantage of OpenCL,
sometimes cards come out
after we ship a version.
So traditionally we've
white-listed a card,
and then that's the
card that would work.
If you got a new card,
it took us a little while
to catch up with you.
So now that we're really
confident in OpenCL,
we're also allowing it so that
you can turn on a new card
as a user, and as long as it has
a gig of RAM on the video card,
and passes some basic video
card tests, you'll be confident
that it's going to
run well on your GPU,
so that's pretty exciting.
So we've really taken advantage
of all the different
computers that are out there.
Furthermore, we've really
worked hard on continuing
to improve the program elements.
We've showed you some pretty
amazing demos with CS6
about what you can
do with OpenCL,
but we still want to
always go further.
We really want to take
advantage of every bit
of power on the machine.
So we did three things.
Last year we were saying that
one of the pitfalls we ran
into with OpenCL was trying
to get pin memory to work.
We struggled with it, we didn't
quite get it done in time,
we've gotten that done now,
so OpenCL with pin memory is
working really well for us,
and it really shows some real
world performance improvements.
We've also been working
with some of the stuff
that you saw earlier in these
slides to take advantage
of the image to buffer
translation.
That was a pretty
heavy problem for us.
We have a lot of kernels that
run really well on images,
and a lot of kernels that
run really well on buffers,
having to copy between those
was a pretty expensive piece
of problem for us.
So we take advantage
of this new thing,
and that's quite exciting.
You also saw something
in the keynote
about the new Mac Pro
shipping with dual GPUs.
So in Adobe Premiere Pro CC,
when you're rendering a sequence
down to a file, we fully take
advantage of multiple GPUs
in your system, so that
obviously gives you a really big
performance improvement
when you're running
on a system like that.
So we're really excited about
the Mac Pro announcement
and what it's going to do
for Premiere Pro customers.
So last year -- I
brought up this slide
to show all the different things
that Premiere does on OpenCL.
So if you're doing
basic video processing,
you need to do DM releasing,
you need to do compositing,
you need to use blend modes, you
need to upload all this stuff
onto your graphics card
and you can do effects,
you can do transitions,
you can do color,
effects, and all that stuff.
So we always want
to continue to see
if the other stuff
we can do on the GPU.
So this year with Premiere Pro
CC we've added a few effects.
Now, this doesn't really
look like a big list.
We have some new blurs, we have
wipe and slide, some basic stuff
that you would expect for us
to do on the OpenCL kernels.
But on the bottom right there
you'll see the Lumetri deep
color engine.
I want to talk about
that for a little bit.
The Lumetri deep color engine
came from an acquisition we made
about a year and a half ago.
It's a technology from
a company called Aridos.
They have a super high-end color
grading application called Speed
grade, and that was a very,
very powerful application
that they used to do things
like grade the entire Blue
ray release of James Bond --
all the entire series.
We took that entire GPU
engine that they had,
brought it into Premiere Pro
under the Mercury
Playback engine,
and ported it all to OpenCL.
So this in itself,
this omen effect,
is built up of 60
kernels, all doing really,
really complicated
stuff, on the GPU.
And this allows the editors
using Premiere Pro now
to actually apply creative
looks to their movies
that I'll show you in
a demo in a minute,
and that just changes the
way they completely use the
Premiere Pro.
You cannot do that
without the GPU.
It was a painful experience to
sit there and use that engine
without the GP running
behind you.
So that's how we can
really take advantage
of OpenCL to delight our users.
So using these performance
improvements,
what are we seeing?
So if we just talk about the pin
memory, and the image to buffer
and just do a simple encode
without them and with them,
we're seeing about a 30%
performance improvement.
That's pretty good, considering
we got a massive performance
improvement just switching
to OpenCL, so that we can go
with another 30%, that's
pretty good for our users.
If we take everything into
account that we're talking
about -- the new blurs,
the new transitions,
and the multiple GPUs, we're
seeing somewhere upward
of 200% performance
improvements on an encode.
This is very exciting.
You take Premiere Sequence,
you render the same sequence
with all these optimizations
and it's 200% faster.
This is what OpenCL can
really do for your users.
So last year, after we were
done with our initial port
and all the engineers took
their breath and calmed
down for a little bit, we said
there were still some things we
would like to do with OpenCL
that we didn't have in CS6.
This is a slide we put up.
So with Premiere Pro CC --
again, you can get it in 4 days,
we're very excited about that --
we've increased the set of
effects that work in OpenCL.
We now support third
party effects.
Now, this is something brand new
that I didn't talk about yet.
Traditionally in Premiere
Pro CS6 if you went out
and bought an effect plug-in
that works in Premiere,
they didn't really get the
opportunity to use the OpenCL.
They could use OpenCL
but they'd have
to take it off the GPU device,
put it back up on the device
in their OpenCL context, do
the compute, pull it back down
and give it back to
us and we put it back
up -- that's not good.
So we've now expanded our SDKs
so that third party developers
can actually write their kernel
-- their plug-ins and effects
using OpenCL and stay on the GPU
and be as fast as any
of our native effects.
So that's really exciting.
We didn't get to GPU
encoding and decoding,
still something we're
investigating.
We're waiting for that to
make sense for our users,
but we did go to do multiple
GPU support, and that's very,
verity exciting, especially
with the keynote announcements.
So another thing that
we're still interested
in doing is taking our scopes
and putting them on a GPU
and we haven't done that yet.
We also have some really other
great ideas that we're not ready
to talk about today, because
OpenCL has really allowed us
to do some great stuff.
So now I want to
show you a demo.
So here we have Adobe Premiere
Pro CC, and I'm just going
to start playing back here.
This is a real project
done in Premiere Pro.
This is the documentary
about Danny Kaye from Waiting
for Lightning, and everything
you're seeing here is processed
on the GPU using OpenCL.
You read the files off disk
on the CPU, you put them
up onto the GPU and
everything that's going
on here is on the GPU.
I know 4Ks all the rage; some
of this footage is
5K from the Red Epic.
There's no proxies, this
is all full res stuff.
We're mixing Canon 5 Vmark 2
footage, we're mixing DNHXD,
pro res, red, red epic, 54K,
all on this timeline here.
All the effects you're seeing
are being done on OpenCL.
So this is really how you can
change the way you use your
applications using OpenCL.
So that's pretty exciting.
So I want to show you
one other section here.
And so what I'm going
to do here is I'm going
to start playing back this
section of the timeline
and just put it on loop.
So here we can now go in and go
into my timeline here and look
for a color corrector in here
and just add that to this clip.
And now you can go over here
and you can very easily start
change the creative look
of that effect in Realtime
while they're playing back.
Now, that's pretty
exciting, right.
That changes the way you
can really edit video.
While it's playing back you
can start adding effects to it.
But I did show you
that last year
but this is actually
something different.
This isn't a single
clip in the timeline.
This is a clip composite
with a bunch of other clips,
but that clip itself is a
nested sequence with a bunch
of other video files in it.
That's an extremely complex
set of composites that I'm able
to add a color correction to
and actually edit in real time.
So that's pretty exciting.
And this is in a Macbook
Pro retina using 5K footage
in real time editing
without any proxies.
So that's pretty exciting right,
and that's all possible
because of OpenCL.
So I talked a little bit about
the Lumetri deep color engine,
so here's another movie clip.
This is from a movie
called "Whalen's Song."
And here you can see it looks
like, it's good, it's pretty,
but this is sort of how
it comes off the camera.
And that looks nice,
but let's try
to make this look a
little bit more cinematic.
It's what you'd expect
to see in teh theater.
So the first thing I'm going
to do is I'm going to just put
down a mat so you get that sort
of cinematic wide screen look,
and I'm going to go into my
what we call a looks browser.
So looks are very
complex descriptions
of what you can do
with video grading.
So it's not just a
color correction;
it can add vignettes, masks,
feathering, very complex stuff
to creatively change the
way your video looks.
So this is our look
browser and these are
like I said everything in there.
I'm just going to apply
that to an adjustment layer.
And all of a sudden,
you know have a sort
of a more cinematic
look to your video.
This is very complex way,
and this is what you can do
when you're shooting with
some of these new cameras
that are shooting
in logC and you want
to give your director
much more of a look
of what your film's
going to look
like when it goes
to the big screen.
You can do this now
in the process
of editing video in real time.
This is all happening
on the GPU using OpenCL.
So we're really excited
about the way OpenCL's
allowing our users to do things
that they could never actually
do before in a video editor.
So that's Adobe Premiere Pro CC
and all the great improvements
we made with OpenCL.
So thank you very much, and I'm
going to give it back to Abe.
[ Applause ]
>> Abe: Okay.
Well, thanks for coming
this session and listening
to what we had to tell you here
about using OpenCL
and Mavericks.
If you have more questions
about using OpenCL and 10.9
or about anything that you
saw here in this session,
you should talk to Alan
Schaefer who's our Graphics
and Games Technology evangelist.
Also, there are a couple
of related sessions
that you might want
to take a look at.
Now, the first session here
actually happened earlier today
in this room.
It was the OpenGL session.
There's also a session on Core
Image, which is the technology
in Mavericks that uses OpenCL
and thanks very much
for your attention.
[ Applause ]