>> Ladies and gentlemen,
please welcome your hosts
for the 2013 ADA
Awards, Senior Partner,
Partnership Management Shaan
Pruden, and Senior Director,
Technology Evangelism
John Geleynse.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon
>> Welcome.
We have a great -- great
event for you right now,
and we just -- we're just so
thrilled that you are here.
You came back after
the state of the union.
This is a non-technical session
so you can just relax and enjoy
as we celebrate some
really cool apps.
>> These are exciting times
of growth and innovation.
>> You know, today we are
here to celebrate excellence
in design and innovation
on iOS and OS X.
>> Each year finding the
best apps becomes more
and more challenging.
>> There are more developers,
more apps, more technologies,
more ideas, more
innovation every day.
>> Before we began, we
want to acknowledge you,
the developers who've
worked so hard to make all
of the amazing iOS and OS
X apps that people love
and that have changed
our culture.
>> They've changed the way that
we work, the way that we play,
and the way that we connect.
And we just -- we just want
to take a moment to thank you
for your hard work and anybody
else who's watching this event
once it gets on video.
[ Applause ]
>> Tonight's winners were
selected by dozens of judges
from across Apple using a
variety of selection criteria.
>> You know, this is my
thirteenth year doing the Design
Awards and we have changed
the way that we judge things,
but we still look for many of
the same qualities in apps.
We look for apps
that are attractive
and have strong visual design.
We look for apps that
have intuitive interaction
or really great gameplay.
We look for apps that have
great attention to detail.
And we look for apps with
high production value.
We also look for apps
that are high performance,
that are super responsive,
and give immediate feedback.
We look for apps that have
deep system integration
and that take advantage of all
relevant Apple technologies.
And finally, we look for
apps that are unique,
apps that bring an innovation
or new approach to something,
or they bring innovative
gameplay in a way
that we've never seen before.
And these are the
kinds of things --
well-designed, state-of-the-art,
and innovative --
these are the attributes
that bring people back again
and again and again
to great apps.
>> Each winner today will
receive an amazing set
of prizes: The 13-inch
MacBook Air, an Apple TV,
a 27-inch iMac, 15-inch MacBook
Pro with Retina display --
>> And winners will also
receive a 64-gig iPad Mini,
a fourth-generation iPad
Wi-Fi with Retina display,
a 64-gig unlocked iPhone
5, and a 64-gig iPod Touch.
So basically
[ Applause ]
we're giving winners
pretty much one
of everything that Apple makes.
>> Oh, and don't forget,
the winners also receive one
of these coveted Cubes.
>> And you know, there's so many
new people here at the AD --
at WWDC this year, and at the
ceremony I bet you didn't knows
that these cubes light
up when you touch them.
They are touch sensitive and
the Apple logo glows just
like the back of your
MacBook Pro screen.
So that is very cool.
>> So let's get on
with our winners.
Just quickly, some logistics.
If you are chosen as a
winner this afternoon,
please quickly come up through
the house and join us on stage
through one of these sets
of stairs at the front,
and then when we're finished,
you're going to exit
stage right.
>> We've got a lot of winners
so we need you to move fast
to the stage so we're not
sitting here all evening.
>> We're going to
begin with students.
So let's start with Finish by
Ryan Orbuch and Michael Hansen.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
>> Here you go.
>> Thank you.
>> Congratulations.
>> Why don't you come over here.
>> Finish is a streamlined
task management app
for procrastinators built
by two high school
students from Colorado.
It gets in your face when
you need it and stays
out of your way when you
don't to help you focus
on completing important tasks.
Let's take a look.
>> So some screenshots here.
So I don't know where the
other student is but --
so I guess you did
all the work, yeah.
>> Michael, he's at home.
>> All right.
Michael's at home.
Well, he's going to
benefit from this anyway.
You know, this is an
app that manages short,
medium, long-term tasks.
These guys put it together
probably 'cause they're not
that good with that and they
are procrastinators themselves.
But we thought this
was such a great app
by a couple of students.
It uses numerous
iOS technologies,
integrates with Facebook
and Twitter
so that you can share tasks
with other students that are
in your class or in your year.
It looks great on
Retina display,
and is totally optimized
for iPhone 5.
So congratulations.
Great work.
>> Thank you.
>> That's Finish.
That's it right over there.
Okay.
[ Applause ]
>> Just walk down those stairs.
[ Music ]
>> And that's Finish.
Our other student winner is
mosaic.io by Ishaan Gulrajani,
Alex List, and Zain Shah.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
Congratulations.
This app is built
by students from MIT
and the University
of Pittsburgh.
It magically connects
two or more iOS devices
into a beautiful mosaic.
View photos and files with
the swipe of a finger.
It's like having your very
own personal hypertable.
Let's take a look.
>> All right.
So here's a video that we asked
these guys to put together,
and they had no idea that
they were doing this for us.
But these are self-taught
iOS developers.
They put a prototype for this
app together in a weekend,
and it creates a mosaic
across multiple screens;
so you select an image, and
then it uses core animation,
device motion, and gestures
to determine the devices'
relative location to each other
and which determine which
part of the image it draws.
So watch this.
They're going to add an iPad;
now they're going to swipe
across the three devices, and
it will reposition that image
across those three devices.
So very, very cool app.
Great job.
Two students.
>> Congratulations.
>> Again.
>> You can go out that way.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> That was mosaic.io, and those
were our two student winners.
Let's move on to our next
winner which is Coda 2 by Panic.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
>> Congratulations.
Right over -- that's all right.
Congratulations.
Hi. Nice to see you again.
>> Of course not.
>> Coda is an incredibly
innovated all-in-one editor
for your web code.
This new version has
added features and updates
to almost every aspect
of the product including some
really compelling integration
with their iPad app Diet Coda.
>> You know, who doesn't
know the Panic guys, right?
And I think that they're
going to love adding this
to their display of ADAs.
But, you know, Coda 1, five
years ago or six years ago
in 2007, won and ADA, and we
at the time thought it was just
such an incredible app.
And we felt that these
guys deserved a new ADA
because Coda 2, it's been
six years in the oven,
and it is just -- it
is so much stronger
and it's a majoring
update to the app
that they had previously.
And you know what?
More than anything else, we felt
that this app was
a shining example
of what a great Mac app is
supposed to look like and behave
like and be built like.
And it's a highly flexible
IDE for web development
with very customizable UI;
it has an extensive use of --
extensive support for plug-ins
so they can add on a lot
of extra functionality; and they
support endless web development
technologies and languages --
ActionScript, ASP, CFML, CSS,
HTML, Java, JavaScript,
and the list goes on.
This app is deeply integrated
with OS X, and the guys
at Panic know how to do this.
Many of you probably
consult with them
for assistance --
technical assistance.
The app is built on AppKit,
as are most OS X apps,
but they do everything
the right way.
They're built on core animation,
iCloud, Notification Center;
they use QuickLook;
they're integrated
with AirPlay and more.
And probably the coolest
and most innovative feature
is AirPlay, which is tied
to Diet Coda on the iPad
>> AirPreview.
>> AirPreview, sorry.
It allows you to
dynamically preview the work
that you're doing, the
code that you're making,
you can preview that
on the iPad.
And so Coda and Diet
Coda together,
they complement one another,
and they provide an
award-winning OS X
and iOS web development
solution.
And so congratulations.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
That's Coda.
Our next winner is
Ridiculous Fishing --
A Tale of Redemption
by Vlambeer.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
>> Congratulations.
>> This is a handcrafted game
about fishing with weapons,
chainsaws, and toasters.
Follow Billy on his
search for redemption
from an uncertain past in
this never-ending infinite
arcade world.
>> Yeah. What you're
seeing back here is --
this is an app that deliver --
a game that delivers hours
of unique entertainment.
It's expertly crafted in the
lo-fi retro video game style.
I mean, all of the graphics are
intentionally done this way.
It has engaging physics-based
gameplay mixed with humor
and a really fun
soundtrack that reverses
as you go back up
to the surface.
It embraces Game Center, makes
extensive use of Multi-touch,
device motion, core
audio, and OpenGL ES.
It's built for iOS and
optimized for iPhone 5.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> That's Ridiculous Fishing.
And our next winner
is WWF Together
by the World Wildlife Fund.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
>> Congratulations.
Want the trophy?
Congratulations.
This app explores the
lives of endangered species
such as tigers, elephants,
and polar bears.
Built from the ground
up with iPad in mind,
it features exquisite
visual design
and inventive interactions.
>> This is an incredible app.
It was probably one of the
coolest apps we've seen on iPad.
It's got outstanding attention
to detail, beautiful aesthetic,
wonderful sound design
and musical score.
There's some really engaging
writing, some rich typography,
gorgeous photography, and then
the interaction method for --
whereby you move through these
different endangered species,
and then you drill down
into more information
about them is fantastic.
It's just got this great
attention to detail.
And we loved their use of
Multi-touch, clever gestures,
Core Location support,
OpenGL ES, and so much more.
This is a fantastic app,
and it's tailored for
and exclusive on iPad.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> That was WWF Together.
And our next winner is Evernote
5 by Evernote Corporation.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
Coming from both sides.
Congratulations.
[ Music ]
>> It will turn off eventually.
>> There you go.
Evernote helps you remember
everything and anything
that happens in your life.
Beyond notes, that lets you
save interesting webpages,
create to-dos, attach
images, PDFs, and more.
And it lets you sync
between your Mac,
iPhone, iPad, and the web.
>> The folks at Evernote
took this app on the Mac,
it's across multiple
IOS devices as well,
but they took the
Mac app recently
and they completely
rewrote this client.
And they gave it a redesigned
Retina display optimized modern
single-window UI.
>> We'll do photos later.
>> They also took advantage of
more technologies on Mac OS X
than a lot of apps I've seen.
They integrate with iCloud,
Notification Center, Reminders,
they've got QuickLook
support, Secure Keychain,
Disk encryption, Core Location.
They support Full-screen for
browsing through your notes.
They're fully accessible.
And they leverage
In App purchase.
Great list, and there's
even more to say.
And they provide a variety
of ways to locate your notes
and to dig up the things
that you've stored
away in the archive.
They're localized
into 25 languages --
this is on the Mac -- and with
Mac iPad and iPhone versions
of the app, and even
a Safari extension.
These guys -- this teams
and your extended team,
have shown -- I think
they've set the bar
for showing how you can
differentiate an app
on these platforms and
do with the right way.
And so they built some great
products for iOS and for Mac
and we wanted to
award them for that.
>> Thank you.
>> Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> That's Evernote.
Our next winner is
Badland by Frogmind.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
Congratulations.
Badland is an atmospheric
action adventure platformer
that takes side scrollers
to the next level.
It features innovative
physics-based gameplay
and extremely beautiful
graphics and sound.
>> Yeah. If you've not played
this game, you have got
to pick this up and
check it out.
It has intuitive one-touch
controls where you're tapping
on screen to raise the little
critter up or let him go down,
immersive sound design -- this
awesome with earphones on.
There's some really balanced
physics-based gameplay.
And players discover
imaginative traps
and overcome endless
obstacles as they go
through these different
scenes and environments.
There's excellent
production value
and brilliant execution
in this app.
Heavy use of OpenGL
ES, obviously.
It's designed for
Retina display,
and it's specifically
designed for iOS devices, iPad,
iPhone and, iPod Touch and
it's available only on iOS.
Congrats.
[ Applause ]
That's Badland.
And our next winner is Yahoo!
Weather by Yahoo.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
Congratulations.
See weather like never before.
This app combines stunning
photos with location,
time of day, and
current conditions.
The forecast is beautiful.
>> Yeah. This app is an app
that totally stands apart.
It's got simple, uncluttered,
and beautiful visual design;
stunning photography; has
great layouts and typography;
compelling animations
as you move
through the different
cities; and the attention
to detail we felt meant
that this app stood
out in a really saturated
category.
This is the way to get
attention: By doing something
that is fantastic like this.
It's available in 30 languages
and it's optimized for iOS.
Congratulations.
>> Thank you.
>> You guys can head
off that way.
>> Congrats.
Thank you.
[ Music ]
And that's Yahoo!
Weather. Our next winner
is Letterpress by atebits.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
Congratulations.
Beauty meets brains in
Letterpress, a fresh take
on word games that's a perfect
blend of fun and strategy.
Find words and steal
tiles to color the board.
>> I think the most interesting
thing about this app is,
I don't think you were good
with words in school, were you?
Yeah. Terrible with
words in school.
So that's what you got to do is
write apps that are, you know --
but this is a deceptively
and highly addictive game.
It draws you in again and
again because of that.
And it stands out for its
beautiful understated UI.
It's got simple gestures,
subtle animations,
and a really restrained
sound design.
We love this app.
And it illustrates masterful
asynchronous gameplay
with Game Center, and is
available on only on iOS.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> And that's Letterpress.
>> Wait, though.
But I just want to ask
you something though.
>> Yes.
>> What's up with
the hair this year?
>> I was inspired
by the color scheme
of the conference this year.
>> Oh, nice.
>> I blend in with the things
downstairs in registration.
>> Like a chameleon?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Great.
>> Okay. Our next winner:
Procreate by Sketch Paint Create
by Savage Interactive.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
Congratulations.
>> You guys --
>> Some good Aussies
I understand.
Yeah.
>> There you go.
>> Artists love this app.
It comes packed with 48
brushes with everything
from true-to-life pencils and
inks to unique digital tools.
It's a complete art
studio at your fingertips.
>> This app is exclusive to iPad
and iOS, and it is a powerhouse
of IOS technologies using
ARC, Grand Central Dispatch,
and OpenGL ES extensively.
And because of that, it's able
to deliver state-of-the-art
performance and responsiveness
with 64-bit precision.
It renders canvasses --
canvas sizes up to 4K x 4K at
a smooth 60-frame per second.
And anything that you draw
on this app can be shared
via Photoshop, given --
handed over to Photoshop or
shared via Twitter or Facebook,
given to mail, photos, and a
variety of others destinations.
And you can customize
virtually anything in this app:
You can customize your brushes.
You can customize your
different digital tools.
And if that's not enough, you
can go and purchase more brushes
or pencils or tools
through In App Purchase.
And the App does this
really innovative preview
of your brushes and
pencils in --
before you purchase
them in In App Purchase.
It also uses Core
Bluetooth smoothly to connect
with devices like styluses.
This app has advanced
layer management
and compositing, as well.
And, you know, we just -- we
couldn't put this app down.
The judges consistently
ranked it high.
And it earns an ADA for
technical, aesthetic,
and creative excellence.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> That's Procreate.
We're on to our last
winner I see --
>> Really?
>> -- over here.
Yes. It is Sky Gamblers: Storm
Raiders by Atypical Games.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
>> You're first,
you get the trophy.
Congratulations.
>> Congratulations.
Congrats. Hi.
>> Let's move that
way a little bit.
>> Participate in
dogfights, protect fleets,
or attack enemy basis in
this amazing World War II air
combat game.
It includes accurately
re-created locations,
realistic weather, and
interactive cockpits.
>> And if you've not played this
game, again, like the Badlands,
pick up a copy of this either
for the Mac or for iOS.
It's got impressive
graphics and sound design.
It's Retina enabled
and AirPlay enabled.
It looks awesome on
the Mac or on iOS.
And it's got amazing
OpenGL based --
based capabilities and
effects that are provided.
Specular masks, bump mapping,
atmospheric scattering,
volumetric clouds.
As he's shooting here,
you're getting bullet
cartridges flying off --
flying out of the guns.
Supports radial blur.
Shows off heat haze
and refractive raindrops
on rainy days.
It's amazing.
This app is iCloud
enabled so as you play it
across multiple devices,
it knows what levels you
are at -- that you're at.
And there's extensive
cross-platform Game Center
support, meaning that you can
play Mac versus Mac or Mac
versus iOS and do
that over Game Center.
It's localized into 10 languages
and this app is available
only on OS X and iOS.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> Congratulations, gentlemen.
Nice job.
[ Applause ]
And that was Sky Gamblers.
And so those are our
winners for today.
In addition to the great price
package we discussed earlier,
these winners will be
featured on the App Store,
on our Facebook page,
as well as on Twitter.
>> Nice.
>> But that's not all we
wanted to share with you today.
>> Because every year there
are dozens of students who come
to WWDC on a scholarship.
>> This year the
scholarship process required
that applicants submit an app.
They had four days or
less to work on it.
And the app was to tell
us about themselves.
>> And we were so impressed
with some of these apps
that we had received, you
know, that people had submitted
for their scholarship,
that we wanted to show some
of the best submissions.
>> So we created
a special version
of the Apple Design
Award trophy,
and we'd like to give
away a few of these now.
Please join -- oh, yeah.
And there's one other thing.
>> Well, they not
only get the trophy.
In addition, these budding
developers get each a 64-GB iPod
Mini -- iPad Mini.
[ Chuckle ]
>> So please join
me in welcoming
on stage three student
scholarship winners.
Louis Harboe, Bryan
Keller, and Puck Meerburg.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
You must be Puck.
Nice to meet you.
Congratulations.
>> How you doing?
>> Congrats you.
Are you Louis?
We're going to start with you.
These three did some pretty
impressive work and we'd
like to tell you about them now.
>> Stand here.
>> Let's start with
Louis Harboe,
in the middle here I believe.
Louis is 17 years old and
attends the University
of Chicago's Laboratory
High School.
>> Louis began developing
on iOS in the seventh grade,
and he's already collaborated
on several apps in the App Store
that have been featured in the
"Chicago Sun-Times"
and on "Cult of Mac."
His WWDC Scholarship App,
which you're seeing here
on screen scrolling through it,
is called "My Adventure book,"
and it presents a scrolling
list of photos and videos
that tell the story or
provide details about his apps,
his education, his experiences,
his friends, his family,
and etc. You tap on each
one of these, they expand
and provide more detail.
And Louis also interned
at Square recently here
in San Francisco, and this tab,
this little photo right
there, tells you that.
So pretty amazing stuff
for four days of work.
Congratulations, Louis.
[ Applause ]
>> Next, let's look at
Bryan Keller's work.
Brian's 19 years old, attends
Marist College in New York,
and is studying computer
science.
>> So Bryan is really extremely
passionate about programming
and he's got an app in the App
Store today called "Augmentative
and Alternative Communication."
And he believes that
technology should be intuitive
and approachable.
And the app that you're seeing
right here is just named
"Bryan Keller."
It's not available in the App
Store -- none of theirs is --
but it presents a word cloud
that could be tapped and zoomed
to reveal details about his
apps, his family, his life,
his school, his sports,
and his interests.
And we picked it because it
had hockey I think is one
of the words, right?
No. Kidding.
We picked up it because
we liked it.
>> So that's Bryan's app.
>> Good job.
[ Applause ]
>> Tremendous.
And finally, Puck Meerburg.
Puck is 13 years old.
He's from Delft in the
Netherlands, and he loves
to code, as you will see.
>> So pay close attention
here, okay.
Puck learned HTML, PHP, and
JavaScript when he was six,
all right; he's been recognized
as the Internet Hero of 2011
by the VNN, a Dutch television
network; he's presented
at TEDx Amsterdam when he was
11; and he's released ten apps
on the App Store already
that have been downloaded
200,000 times.
This guy.
[ Applause ]
I mean, the app that you're
seeing behind me is his WWDC
submission called WWDC, and
it uses UIKit, Core Animation,
Multi-Touch, Core Graphics to
present a comprehensive resume
of his life and interests.
And each section is different.
This one, you're tapping
on these clouds,
dragging them around.
They're just kind of floating
around telling you
what he dreams of doing
and where he plans to be.
Which is at Apple I
guess one day, yeah?
or something.
All right.
Anyway, we just wanted
to highlight these three
students for amazing work.
Four days of work
by each of them.
Tremendous.
Congratulations.
>> Congratulations.
We're going to have you
exit right that way.
Congratulations.
[ Music ]
>> Now, one thing
I will say, too,
is all ADA winners
are also going
to be wearing special lanyard,
so if you see these three
guys walking around,
please introduce yourself
to them, talk to them,
learn from them or something,
and just help them out.
And also there's the
other ADA winners as well.
Please acknowledge them
throughout the week and find
out how they did what they did.
>> So these are our
ADA 2013 winners.
>> These are 11 great apps that
demonstrate technical, design,
and creative excellence.
>> Eleven really great
apps they set the standards
that other apps should
reach for.
>> And 11 really great apps that
people are going to come back
to again and again and again.
And like we've said in a lot
of the sessions today already,
we can't wait to see
what you are going to do
on iOS VII and OS 10 Mavericks.
And so we look forward to
having your app featured here
on stage next year in the ADA
as we will be looking for apps
that exploit these
operating systems.
>> Thanks for joining us.
We'll see you next year.
[ Applause ]