[ Silence ]
>> Good morning and welcome.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
My name is Quinn Taylor, I'm an
Internal Applications Engineer
at Apple, and I'm excited
to be talking today
about Designing Code
for Performance.
It's great to see such a
big crowd here, obviously,
you're all interested
in performance
as well and that's fantastic.
So, to start off, I want
to give you a little bit
of introduction, the motivation
for this talk, why
it came to be.
It's no secret that the raging
success of the App Store has led
to a huge influx of new
developers to the platform.
As you've heard Tim
say on Tues--
on Monday, about two-thirds of
you are here at this conference
for the first time,
that's fantastic.
Many of you are in fact new to
programming in the recent past.
You come from a diverse
array of backgrounds
and experience levels,
and that's great.
You have a lot of different
kinds of wonderful apps
that you can contribute
for our customers
in the App Store that they love.
However, across all these
domains and different types
of applications, one
thing that's constant is
that everyone uses data
structures and it's common
to have performance issues.
No matter what your app does,
you're going to be using arrays
and dictionaries and so on, and
it's important to understand how
that can affect your
application.
When you have issues like this,
often they're puzzling unless
you have some knowledge
of what's going on under the
hood and what's happening
so you can evaluate
your app and improve.
So, the goal of this session is
really to teach you how to fish.
I'm not here to give
you a one-off tip
about how you can fix a specific
problem, but really to look
at the grand scheme of things,
understand when it comes
to data structures, how can
I make my app perform the
best possible.
So the things we're going
to cover today: first off,
when to focus on performance,
how to evaluate what we call
"computational complexity",
how to choose
and use data structures in
your application, and last,
how to design your
code for performance.
We'll give some concrete
examples.
So to start off, when
to focus on performance.
Now you may think: "This
is a trick question,
the answer is 'always', right?"
That's true to a certain extent,
and we'll talk about
that in detail.
To start off with a quote,
I have this on my wall,
this is from Steve Jobs,
"We don't get a chance to do
that many things, and every
one should be really excellent.
We've all chosen to do
this with our lives.
So it better be damn good.
It better be worth it."
I love this quote
because it motivates me
to make my applications the
best that I possibly can,
and try to eke performance
out of every angle.
However, you notice
that he says,
"Every one should be
really excellent,"
that's not necessarily perfect.
We as developers know that
our applications have flaws.
We do the best that we can
to make them as polished
as possible before
we hand them over,
but we have a limited
amount of time.
Steve also said, "You
have to pick carefully.
Innovation is saying
no to 1,000 things."
So how do we strike
the balance here
when it comes to performance?
You may have seen a
quote from Donald Knuth,
a famous computer
scientist, where he says,
"Premature optimization
is the root of all evil."
People tend to throw this
around at developer forums
and some people will use
this almost an excuse to say,
"You don't need to worry about
performance at all, right?
It's not going to
be a big deal."
Sometimes that's the case.
But unfortunately, we usually
only see this middle sentence
of the quote.
But he said a lot more,
he said, "We should forget
about small efficiencies
about 97 percent of the time.
Yet we should not pass
up our opportunities
in that critical 3 percent."
So there comes a
time when focusing
on performance is really
important for your application.
I like to summarize this by
saying, "Optimize performance
when it will make a
meaningful difference."
That's what we're going
to be talking about today,
is how I can choose to see--
is this going to make a
difference for my application?
So, to talk about that, there's
a principle called Amdahl's Law
which is really about
helping you pick your battles
in performance.
So this law was proposed
by Gene Amdahl,
a very famous computer
architect, and basically,
it has to do with predicting
the maximum improvement
that you can expect by speeding
up some portion of your code.
This depends obviously on
what percentage of time
that code is taking to
begin with, to see what kind
of speedup you can achieve.
And the payoff is much larger
for the dominant piece of code,
the thing that's
taking the most time;
these appear fairly obvious.
So the question is,
will the payoff
of improving the
performance of this piece
of the code be worth the
effort, the time that it's going
to take me to do that?
And this applies
directly to concurrency.
In fact, as this law was
originally stated, it had to do
with multi-core processing
and breaking your code
up into multiple pieces, and
that has great tie-ins as well
to Grand Central
Dispatch and using blocks.
So let me give you an
example of Amdahl's Law.
Say that you have a process
that has two segments, A and B,
and one takes 80 seconds
and one takes 20 seconds.
So we have a certain
amount of time.
Now, if you can spend a
bit of time and optimize
and cut the time spent by
process B-- segment B in half,
then you have a great win.
Now you're at 90 percent of
your previous performance.
However, if you can apply
the same effort to speed
up process A and cut
that time in half,
now you've gone to 60 percent.
This is a much bigger win,
and this is what we talk
about when we say
"identifying bottlenecks",
looking at the actual
problems in your code.
So that's where you really
want to focus on performance.
You know, it's great to have a
performance win in segment B,
but everyone has things that
they have to do, so you've got
to choose wisely
what you work on.
So back to Donald Knuth,
he talked about premature
optimization.
Now, premature optimization
generally leads
to unnecessary complexity
in your code.
You take something
that's simple and to try
to get more performance out of
it, you change and tweak things
and make it more
complex and clever.
Sometimes that's great.
But, "if it ain't
broke, don't fix it".
You don't have to fix something
that's not necessarily a problem
for your code.
You have a ton of features
that you need to implement
for your app, and polishing it
to make it great for your users.
So I'd like to focus
on something I call
"informed design" which leads
to elegant and efficient code.
Informed design is all
about considering your
performance early on,
even during the design phase.
You can do that before you
even write a line of code.
And it helps you to
intelligently avoid problems
that you can actually
face in the real world,
rather than premature
optimization
and fixing a problem
that may not be
such a big problem after all.
And this is useful because it
can help you avoid designing
slowness into your application,
only to fix it later.
So if you can think about
it up front, it's a big win.
OK. So now let's move
to talking about how
to design for performance.
If you have a performance
issue that you've identified
in your code, there's
three broad ways
that you can resolve that.
The first is, don't do it.
If there's unnecessary work,
then you can completely
cut it out.
The second is do it as rarely as
possible, and the third is do it
as efficiently as possible.
Now, these are generally in
increasing order of difficulty.
It's very easy to just remove
code that you no longer need,
but getting something to
be more efficient can be
really difficult.
In order to answer these
questions and choose
which approach works
for your scenario,
you really have to
have some context.
Is the work necessary?
If not, I may be
able to remove it.
Is redundant work being done?
Doing the same thing
over and over again,
I may be able to
reuse that work.
Or, is there a more
efficient way?
And that last question is
really the most tricky.
How do I know if I can do better
than what I'm doing right now?
So, to answer that question,
we'll go into the next portion
of the talk, where we talk
about computational
complexity and cost.
Now, these are some big words
so I'll explain out for you
in kind of broad terms.
So we're talking about the
cost of code, and by this,
I don't mean how much you
pay for an app in the store
or how much it cost you
to have people develop it.
Every piece of code takes
some amount of time to run
because there's work being
done, and it's obvious
that more work takes more time.
However, it's not
necessarily obvious
that sometimes you can
have really short code
that does a lot of work and
it can hide some complexity.
There's a cost associated
with a particular code,
perhaps an API call or so on,
or you're using a library.
Now, the effects of data
growth can vary quite a bit
when you're choosing
an algorithm,
and it can really impact your
performance, particularly
as your data size grows.
It may be disproportional,
in fact, to the number
of objects that you add.
And consequently, small
tests often won't turn
up this kind of problems.
We try to do as much testing as
we can before we send our app
out into the world, but you've
probably all experienced
that your customers will use
your app in new and exciting
and sometimes terrifying ways,
and throw a lot of data at it
in ways that you
didn't anticipate.
And sometimes these
performance issues will crop
up where you least want them to.
Fortunately, this kind of
complexity can often be analyzed
without even running the code,
much like the Xcode
static analyzer can do.
And the key to this is
understanding the complexity
of the code that you're running
and how much work is being done.
Now, Computer Science has
entire semester courses devoted
to this, that leaves sophomore
students really puzzled.
We don't the have time to
get into an entire semester,
but I'm going to give you
kind of a crash course
and help you have a framework
for understanding complexity
and analyzing your code.
So, in Computer Science, we talk
about something called
"Big O" notation.
So this is a way of ranking
algorithms by efficiency,
generally, by their
time efficiency,
or memory efficiency, or so on.
And the letter O stands for
the order, the order of growth
of this, and we'll talk
about this in detail.
And it really relates to how the
performance changes as the scale
of the work that you're doing--
when you increase the number
of objects you're
working with, for example.
So, with Big O notation,
what we're really seeking
to do is approximate the worst
case behavior for an algorithm,
the most work that you
might ever have to do.
Ideally with an algorithm, you
may be able to skip out early
and so on if you're doing
searches and that type of thing.
But Big O is concerned with "how
bad could this possibly be"?
So then that's my absolute
worst case of performance.
And in general, we
ignore coefficients
and lower order terms
and logarithmic bases
because what we really
care about is the order,
whether it's N or N squared,
as we'll go into
detail in just a moment.
Now, for any given task,
it's important to realize
that there are inherent limits.
There are some things
that just take time.
We'd like to do everything
instantly
but that's not always possible.
A perfect example of
this, Fred Brooks,
famous software engineer:
"Nine women can't make
a baby in one month."
As many women as
you assign to it,
you'd like to do
it concurrently,
it would be much more
convenient for them,
but it's simply not possible.
There's a hard limit
on this, right?
So we're going to talk
about Big O complexity,
and I want to identify
for you a few key
and common order functions.
So I have a table here, in
the first column, notation,
you'll see how you might see it
written and these are pronounced
"Big O of 1" or "order 1",
"order log N", "order
N", and so on.
You might also hear it referred
to by the name "constant time",
"logarithmic time", "linear
time", "quadratic time",
and so on, these
are interchangeable.
And then provided in the
third column some examples
of common algorithms
or tasks that fall
into these different categories.
I won't go into them in
detail here on this slide,
but this is great for
reference to come back and see
where does my task actually fit?
And we'll talk a little bit
more in detail about identifying
which of these your
task belongs to.
Now, a few of these
are most common.
You'll see this all over the
place and they're very common
for algorithms that
you'll be working with.
So I'll talk about
these in detail.
So the first-- before I get
into some specific details,
let me show you a comparison
of these order functions.
So it's easy to see
them in a table,
but maybe it doesn't hit
home why this is important.
First off, this is what order N
squared complexity looks like,
like a parabola, order N
log N, order N, order log N,
and order 1 or constant time.
Now, the first thing that
you can see is these diverge
really rapidly.
When you get to a
large number of items
across the bottom scale,
you have some of these
that it gets really complex
and shoots its way
up towards the top.
That means your performance is
going to be bad, you're doing
that much more work, right?
The other thing to
notice is that down
at the bottom left corner,
they're really close together.
So for small scale, it
may not be necessary
to find a really
optimal algorithm.
This would be a range
where you want to watch
out for premature optimization.
Am I really going to
have an issue here,
because they're all
pretty close together.
So those are some
things to be aware off.
So, I'm going to go through some
examples of a few sample pieces
of code that have some
of these complexities.
And remember, the key for this
is, is that we want to look
of the growth-- at the growth of
the amount of work as the size
of our input increases.
So first is a very simple one.
Let's say that we have
an array of integers
and I have a function where
I pass in an integer value
and an index, and I
simply want to know:
does this value appear
at that index?
Now you can see we're only doing
one operation, and you may know
that indexing into an
array is extremely fast.
So, in this case, it's order 1;
regardless of what
index I choose,
it's going to return
nearly instantly.
So if we have a sample array,
you can see I may
query one index and say
that that value is not there,
here I found it,
and there I've not.
So I don't have to
look at anything else
in the array, just one spot.
So that makes this order 1.
If we change this
up just slightly,
now we have an order
N algorithm.
So, now I'm interested in seeing
if a particular value
appears anywhere in an array,
not just at a given index.
In order to do that,
because I don't know
where it would appear, if it's
there at all, I have to look
through each index in the array.
So we have a for loop when
we start at the beginning
and we go towards the end,
and then we test to
see if it's there.
If at any point I
find it, I return yes.
But, the worst case is that it's
not there in the array at all,
and I have to check
thought every single index
in order to determine that.
So, you could see here, I
have to march one by one
down the array until
I find the object,
or determine that
it's not there.
So in worst case, order N.
For order N squared, let's
say we have a similar array,
I give it a value and I want
to say, does this value appear
at least twice anywhere
in the array?
In order to do that, I have
to compare every two possible
pairings of indexes in the array
to see if they're equal.
So what that means is that
I have to do two for loops.
I have an outer for loop
and an inner for loop,
and each of these is
an order N algorithm.
And inside this for loop once
I get to comparing two indexes,
you see, I compare each of these
two to see if they're equal
and if at any point I find them,
I can bail out and say yes.
And you can see that we're
doing a lot more work here;
j is moving back and forth like
a madman, and i is just trying
to keep up, and finally
here at the end,
we find those two
matching values.
Now in the worst case, there
may be no values at all--
these two values may not
be present in the array,
or the value may not be
present twice in the array,
but we have to go to the
very end to find that out.
Now, some of you
may look at this
and realize this is a
rather naive implementation.
I'm starting the j loop
at zero every time.
So, for example, when i gets
to the very end of the array
and j starts at the
beginning, I've already compared
that when i was at the
beginning and j was at the end.
So that's kind of silly
to have to do that.
So instead you could choose
to start the inner for loop
at i plus 1 for example,
and you eliminate half
of your comparisons.
That's great, that's
a great win.
So now we're to N
squared over 2,
but it's still N squared growth.
So the key to this is
although it's now much faster
for a given input
size, it's still going
to have the same
growth properties:
as you add one more object,
or one more item to the array,
you're going to add
N comparisons.
That's the important thing
from this, so order N squared.
OK. So, calculating complexity.
We've seen that you can
combine these order functions.
For the N squared example I just
showed, we have two for loops
and each of those is order N,
and we have nested complexities,
we multiply those together,
N times N, we get N squared.
When you have sequential
complexities,
we add those together and
then we take the largest term.
So for example, this function
would reduce to N squared.
We have one N squared
call, and two N,
and three that are constant
time, but all we care
about it the N squared,
nothing else,
because that's the
growth of this function.
OK. So we've seen
that with source code.
However, sometimes you may not
have access to the source code,
or not be aware of what work
it's doing, and in such cases,
you can often estimate.
You can consider what the
code would have to do,
what kind of work it's
trying to accomplish,
and another complementary
alternative is
to profile with Instruments.
This can be a great way to find
performance issues in your code.
There are many sessions
from previous years
about using Instruments,
and in fact,
Xcode 5 as you saw earlier this
week introduces new debug gauges
including memory and CPU
use that can help you
with identifying
these kind of issues.
Now, some APIs may
appear to be very similar
but it's important
not to confuse them
when you're estimating, just
look at the name and say, "Oh,
I know what that is"
because of the name.
For example, we have
a containsObject API
on both NSArray and NSSet.
But it would be folly to
assume that they're the same.
So let's look at NSArray first.
It's containsObject,
we want to see
if a given object appears
anywhere in the array.
What work does it do?
Well, in this case,
the documentation actually
tells us explicitly
that it sends the isEqual
message to each object
in the array until one
of them returns true,
or it reaches the
end of the array.
OK, so it goes through
each object.
That certainly sounds
like order N complexity,
and that's certainly
a valid assumption,
I think that that's
pretty reasonable.
Now, we may think, well, what
if I can enumerate
these concurrently
and compare the objects?
That would be sort of a win.
And it would, it would reduce
it by a constant factor
but it would still
be a linear operation
with the size of the array.
OK. So let's see NSSet.
NSSet also has a containsObject,
it has the same name.
I give it an object,
it does the same thing:
it tells me whether it's
in the collection or not.
It looks just like the one
that we just saw in NSArray.
Is it also order N?
You might assume
that it would be.
However, it's actually
order 1, it's constant time.
Regardless of the
size of the set,
containsObject is always
really fast, that's great.
There's a caveat, please don't
go start replacing NSArray
with NSSet everywhere in
your code because it's fast.
There's context to
understand about why this is
and if it will work for you.
So, the reason that it's faster
is it must be doing less work.
It's doing the same amount
of work, roughly speaking,
regardless of how
large my collection is.
So we'll talk about that.
The reason that this is is
something called hashing.
We'll talk about
hash-based organization.
So, NSSet uses a hash table for
storage, as does NSDictionary.
Every object has a
deterministic hash value.
You may have seen
the hash method.
This is defined on NSObject--
we'll talk about in detail--
and it returns an unsigned
integer value that you can use
to store this object
in a hash table.
And equal objects should
always have the same hash;
we'll talk about this in more
detail and give examples.
When in a hash table, objects
are grouped into "buckets",
parts of the array based on
the hash that they provide.
And the structure has a hash
function that takes a hash
and maps it to a given bucket.
It can decide that this range of
hashes goes in the first bucket,
and this one, and so on,
and it can divide those up.
And the goal of this
hash function is
to achieve uniform
distribution, so that you have
about the same number of objects
in all the buckets
in the hash table.
When you achieve this, lookup
in a hash table really only has
to consider the objects that
are in a particular bucket.
It knows if an object is
going to be there it will be
in this bucket, and it can check
isEqual on only a few objects,
or none at all if there's
none in the bucket.
This is an obvious win.
If you have an array that's a
thousand objects, you may have
to check up to a thousand items
in order to see if it's there.
But with a set, you may have
to check only a handful.
This is great.
So let me give you a concrete
example with an animation here.
Say we have a hash function and
we have a hash table we're going
to store some objects in.
Let's say that we want
to store the names
of all Apple CEOs
past and present.
So let's start off
with Tim Cook.
We run this through our hash
function, and it determines
that Tim Cook by the
hash belongs in bucket 2.
Great, so we set him there.
We add Steve Jobs and
that gets determined to go
in bucket 0, great, no problem.
Now we're going to
add Gil Amelio,
and our hash function
decides that it goes
in the same bucket
as Steve Jobs.
We have a collision
in our hash table,
rather unfortunate
and somewhat awkward.
[laughter] In order to see if
we should insert this object,
we have to compare, so we
check isEqual, and in fact,
we see that Steve
Jobs is not equal
to Gil Amelio, thank goodness.
And so what happens
is we move one aside
and we chain these together,
they both occupy the
same bucket, great.
Now we add Michael Spindler,
no collision here,
goes into bucket 5.
We add John Sculley, and
once again we get a hash
table collision.
So the hash function decides
it goes in the same place.
So once again, we compare each
of these objects to
see is this equal.
They are not equal, so we
move them aside and we stick
that in the same bucket.
So, this is all well and
good, except you'll notice
that now the majority of my
objects are all in one bucket
in the hash table, and half
of my hash table is completely
empty, I'm not using it.
This is obviously non-optimal.
If I have some sort of simple
query to see if someone is
in the list for example, and my
hash function happens to map it
to the same bucket, I now
have to check through each
of those objects to see if
they're equal to Bill Gates
to determine no, he's
not in the table.
All right, so this is
definitely not optimal.
Fortunately, something
like NSSet can choose
to optimize the hash
function on the fly.
If it realizes that your
performance is not as good
as you could expect, it
reserves the right to be able
to move objects around, to
change the hash function
and redistribute them evenly.
So here we're in a
much better situation
and our lookups are restored
to being really fast.
OK, great.
So how can you participate
in this?
Defining your identity for your
object is how you take part
of this hash-based identity.
So NSObject, as I mentioned,
defines an isEqual method
and a hash method, and
they're functionally equivalent
to comparing the pointers,
the object addresses
for these two objects,
and returning just
the address itself.
Now, Apple-provided subclasses
of NSObject will override
this as necessary.
For example, NSString has its
own hash, NSDate, NSNumber
and so on, there's a variety
that do this, and in fact,
arrays, and sets themselves also
have their own hash and isEqual.
Custom objects that you
create should choose
to override these methods
if pointer quality is not
sufficient for your needs.
For example, say that you
have two person objects
and you want them to
be considered equal
if the Social Security Number
is the same for both of them,
something to that effect.
And you can learn a
lot more about this--
this will be in the slides
for reference afterward--
about object comparison and
implementing these methods.
There are a few rules of
the road if you're going
to implement these
on your own object.
If isEqual returns
true for two objects,
then the hash must be the
same for both of these.
This is critical because
if you have two objects
that should be the same
but have different hashes,
they could get put in
different places in a hash table
and you won't be able to
find them when you're looking
for them, you'll get
incorrect results.
However, the same hash value
does not necessarily imply
that isEqual must be true.
You can have two objects
that have the same hash value
but isEqual will
be the tie breaker.
If you decide to
implement isEqual,
you really should also define
hash for this very reason:
so that you can guarantee
that they are the same.
Now, a good hash, as
you're implementing one,
should minimize collisions.
A poor hash will really cause
your performance to tank.
All right, for example,
in the worst case,
let's say that you're
like, "I don't know
about this hash thing,
I'm just going to return 1
for all of my objects."
They all have the same hash
which means they're all going
to go to the same
bucket in a hash table,
which means you've now turned
an NSSet into an NSArray
and killed your performance.
That's the opposite
of what we want.
So we want to be careful
about that and we'll talk
about that in just a moment.
One other key important thing is
that when you have hash lookup,
your hashes really should
be stable and predictable.
If your hash tends
to change while it's
in the collection,
it's really bad.
You're not going to
be able to find it.
So there are two options really.
The first is not to modify
and object in a collection.
If you have a mutable string and
you've put it in as the key--
or an object in a set, for
example, and you change
that string, the hash will
change and you're going
to have all sorts of hilarity
and hair-pulling that ensues.
The second option is to not
base your hash on mutable state.
This may be an option for you,
so that's something
to consider as well.
So let me show you a
sample implementation.
You all have the WWDC app
on your phones and iPads,
and there is a news object,
as you see in the news
update throughout the week,
we have these news
objects to represent that.
This is a simplified
representation.
Here we're just looking it
has a title and a time stamp.
So I want to focus on
these two implementations.
Now, for hash, you see that we
need to return some hash value
and we're just returning the
hash that NSString provides us
from this title property.
However, if we have
two news items
that may have the same title
and thus have the same hash,
we can break the tie
by calling isEqual
and compare both the
title and the time stamp,
and we also check to see
if it's the same object.
So, there are a lot more
examples of things like this
in the documentation
that I encourage you
to check out afterward.
OK. So next I want
to talk to you
about data structures
performance,
kind of applying
what we've learned.
We've got the math-y
part out of the way
about Big O complexity
and hashes and so on.
So I'm going to talk
to you a little
but about choosing
data structures
and the performance
characteristics about them.
So let's start with an analogy.
Say that you have books
that you need to organize.
There's a lot of different ways
that you could choose
to organize books.
Say you could sort them
by topic or author,
title, even size or color.
You can choose an arbitrary
characteristic and choose
to sort them that way.
Everyone does this with their
CD collections, and, well,
iTunes has solved
that problem now.
But everyone has their
own preferred way
to sort things and
organize them.
However, each of these options
makes some things really easy
and others difficult.
Say that you've chosen to
organize alphabetically
by author and then
later you want
to find all the New York
Times' best sellers,
or you want to find children's
books, those are scattered all
over in your collection and
it's not easy to look them
up when they're sorted
by author.
So this is something
to be aware of.
It's also important to plan
for scale when appropriate
as you're choosing
your data structures.
For example, it's a
completely different thing
to organize a small bookshelf
here where you can say,
"Go find the small green book"
and instantly you've all
found it because it's small,
versus organizing a
really large library.
Things that will work at small
scale may not necessarily
when you get to large
amounts of data.
You have to have a
more intelligent way
to organize things.
So, choosing a strategy,
every data structure
has some tradeoffs.
It has things that it's best
at and things that is not
as well suited for, and
you want to use the one
that best fits your needs.
When you choose a data structure
that's not the best fit,
it really hurts your
performance.
For example, using a
hammer to drive in a screw,
not the ideal tool
for the situation.
Even if you have the right tool,
you may not be using
it optimally.
If you have a hammer with
a nail and you just pressed
down really hardly-- as hard as
you can, it's not going to be
as effective as whacking
it really hard, right?
So, it's really important
to choose the right thing
for your needs and
use it correctly.
And we encourage
you to always prefer
to use the built-in
API whenever possible.
The collections that
are available
in the Foundation framework
are extensively tested.
They've been around for years.
We use them just as much
as you do, and we want them
to be really, really fast
just as much as you do.
These also-- using the built-in
frameworks also guarantees
that in the future when we have
improvements, such as you'll see
in OS X Mavericks and in iOS 7,
that you will also get
those improvements for free.
Your apps will suddenly
become faster, which is great.
So, getting down to actually
choosing a data structure,
there's a few things you
have to know for context.
The first is knowing
what you need.
Is it important that my
objects have an order?
Will I allow duplicates
in my collection?
Do I have to be able to add or
remove objects, have it mutable?
What operations are
most critical
for me to be really fast?
What am I going to be
doing with my structure?
And even where will my
data come from and go to?
For example, you may
choose differently
if your data will
come from user input,
or from a property list
file, or Core Data,
or JSON over the web or so on.
There's certain things that
may change your decision.
And the second thing is
to know what to expect
from your collection, which
we'll go into in detail.
There are certain things
that are broadly true
across all of our collections.
For example, getting
the count of items
in a collection is always really
fast, that's constant time.
We cache that for you because
that's a common operation.
Enumerating through
all the objects
in a collection is generally
linear time, because you have
to visit each of N objects.
Even if you have a set or
dictionary, lookup is fast
but going through
each of them is going
to take the same amount of time.
And other operations will
vary by the collection.
So, before I go over
individual data structures,
I want to share just a
note about mutability.
The best guideline with
mutability, we got a lot
of questions about this, is
to use it when you need it,
when it's semantically
correct, when you're adding
and removing objects
from a collection.
Immutable collections
do have benefits.
If you don't need mutability,
it can be to your benefit
to use an immutable
collection instead.
Foremost among these
benefits is thread safety.
If a collection is
immutable such as an NSArray,
you know that no other thread
can add or remove objects,
and you don't have to worry
about exceptions or crashes.
Also, there are memory and speed
optimizations that are possible
with immutable collections
because we know
that they're not going
to change in size.
We can allocate just the
exact right amount of memory
for the objects that
you've provided.
Now, another option is to make a
collection immutable afterwards.
Make a copy of it that you
can use for quick reference
and get those benefits,
but still be able to build
up your collection
with add and remove.
And lastly, if you do use
mutability, it's often great
if you can help us to help you.
You know how your
collection is being used.
We design it for a broad
range of different uses,
and you know specifically what
you're going to do with it.
And there's times that
you can provide hints
that help us get you
the best performance.
One example is initializing
a collection
with initWithCapacity.
Now, what this does is
gives us kind of a hint
about how many objects
you're likely to store
in a given collection.
So for example, if you say "I'm
only going to store three items
in this mutable array
and add and remove them",
you can provide that
capacity up front
and we can optimize accordingly.
Now, don't-- It's not wise to
try to outsmart the collections
and ask for a really
large capacity.
The collections are
really finely tuned
and optimized to
take care of that.
And even if you do provide
the capacity hint up front,
the collection can
dynamically grow and shrink
as objects are added
and removed.
So this just provides us an
up front way to kind of get
in the ballpark of
what you need.
OK. So I'm going to go
on a quick tour of some
of the data structures
in Foundation,
some of the most
valuable players;
give you a brief
overview and talk
about their performance
characteristics.
First, NSArray and MutableArray.
You're all familiar with this.
It's a workhorse of
the Cocoa library.
It's an ordered collection,
it allows indexed access,
and you can have duplicate
objects in an array.
Operations that are
really fast are anything
that includes indexing:
objectAtIndex,
firstObject and lastObject.
Adding and removing
at either end
of a mutable array is
actually really fast as well.
This may come as a surprise;
adding at the end would seem
really fast, but you may think
that if you add at the
beginning you'd have
to shift everything over.
However, that tends to be
a common use case for a lot
of our developers, so
we've optimized that
and we've given the guarantee
that inserting at the front,
the very front of a mutable
array is also really fast.
So that's a great thing
to be aware of as well,
to not be afraid to
insert at the front.
Slower operations include
anything that involves search
and looking through
any of these indexes
as we've already
mentioned before.
Also, adding and removing at
an arbitrary index somewhere
in the middle of the array,
not at either of the ends,
would tend to be a
little bit slower.
One specialty operation I'd like
to call out is binary search.
If you're not familiar
with this,
binary search is a quick way
to narrow down your search.
There are a couple
pre-conditions.
You have to have some
sorted range of data.
So if I know that my array is
already sorted in ascending
or descending order, I could use
binary search to quickly narrow
down and cut out half of
the objects each time.
And this is a great win
because this is an order log N
operation, as compared
to order N.
If you remember from the graph,
order N was a line that goes
up at a 45-degree angle
and order log N stays
really close to the bottom.
It's got great performance
as your objects sizes scale.
Next is NSSet and NSMutableSet.
This is an unordered collection,
it does not allow duplicates,
and it has hash-based lookup
as we discussed previously.
In sets, adding,
removing and searching
for objects are really fast,
precisely because of
the hash-based lookup.
Now, there are some
specialty operations
that are really convenient
on NSSet.
For example, set arithmetic.
If you think of a Venn diagram
where you've got two circles
that overlap, you can find
the intersection between them,
you can see if one is
completely contained
in the other, and so on.
And if you have mutable
sets, you can extend this
and intersect the set
and modify one set
to only contain the objects
that also appear in another set,
or minus set, or
union set and so on.
This can be really
convenient for merging
and separating different
collections of objects.
Good thing to be aware of.
Caveats with NSSet, when
you convert from an array
to an NSSet, you can do that
but you do lose your ordering
of the array, and you
lose any duplicates
that may appear in the array.
Those will be stripped
out with a set.
If you convert back to an array,
you may get a smaller array,
and you almost certainly get
one that's in a different order
that the one you passed in.
Related to this is that you
can't store a set directly
in a property list or
in JSON, as we'll talk
about in a little bit.
You can convert to an array and
back as you're reading them out,
but these are caveats
to be aware of.
A brief of note on NSCountedSet.
This is really a handy one that
many people are not aware of.
It's also unordered
just a like a set,
no duplicates and hash lookup.
It's a subclass of NSMutableSet,
so it has all the
same operations
and the same characteristics.
Its big trick though, is that it
tracks the net insertion count
of each object.
So, objects still only appear
once in a counted set, however,
if you insert the
same object again,
the count for that object
will increase to 2 and so on.
If you remove that
object, it decreases
and if it's removed it's at 0.
This can be really convenient
if you're trying to count
up occurrences of a particular
object, maybe words in text
or something like that.
It's kind of a histogram
binning type of thing,
so great thing to be aware of.
Next is NSDictionary
and NSMutableDictionary.
This you're also
very familiar with.
It's an unordered collection,
it has key value entries
to store those associated
together,
it has unique key values,
and it uses hash lookup
just a like a set.
So, adding, removing and
searching are also really fast
in a dictionary, anything where
you're looking for an object
by the key, adding or
removing and searching.
Specialty operations, one thing
that's convenient is it has some
handy API for reading
and writing directly
from a property list file.
And also one other thing
that was added in 10.8
and iOS 6 is really handy.
If you have a mutable
array and you know up front
which keys will ever appear in
this mutable dictionary, sorry,
mutable dictionary, you
can provide a key set,
an array of those keys up front.
And there's a class
method on NSDictionary.
You give it an array of keys,
it will give you a
sharedKeySet object.
If you provide that when
creating an NSMutableDictionary,
it can create a really
optimal hash algorithm
for organizing those
particular keys.
It knows up front what's
likely to be there.
And it can be a great
situation if you need mutability
but you want speed and you
know the keys you're going
to have up front.
Caveats of NSDictionary, you're
probably familiar with the fact
that any keys that you provide
to NSDictionary are
going to be copied in.
They have to conform to
the NSCopying protocol.
And you should never mutate an
object that is a dictionary key.
The hash will change
very likely,
and you probably won't
be able to find it
and you'll get incorrect
results.
This is a major thing
to be aware of.
NSOrderedSet
and NSMutableOrderedSet
are an ordered collection,
similar to arrays, they don't
allow duplicates like a set,
and they support both index
and hash-based lookup.
This class was introduced
in iOS 5 and OS X 10.7.
And it's effectively across
between a set and array.
It's not a subclass
of either one,
although you can get an array
or set representation that--
one convenient thing about
these are they're live-updating.
So as objects are added or
removed to the mutable set,
those array and set
representations will be updated
as well.
Now, a caveat of this
is that you're going
to have increased memory usage.
You can't get the best of
both worlds as a free lunch.
So because we're
maintaining ordering,
we have an array internally.
And because we're
guaranteeing uniqueness
and no duplicate objects,
we also have a set.
So roughly double memory usage.
And also when you-- If you
want to store an ordered set
in a property list, you'd
have to convert it to an array
and then back as
you bring it out.
NSIndexSet and NSMutableIndexSet
differ
because they don't store
objects, they store indexes,
integer values, so it's a
collection of unique indexes
and these are really handy
for referencing some subset
of objects in an NSArray.
And it's really handy especially
because you can avoid the
memory overhead of making a copy
or saying objectsAtIndexes,
you can give it an index set
and it gives you a
new autoreleased array
with those objects in it.
If you want to avoid that
overhead, you can just enumerate
through the objects
at particular indexes
without creating a new array,
and it's really handy for that.
Index set has really
efficient storage
and coalescing of indexes.
So if you have a mutable index
set and you add the indexes 1
and 3, it will store
those separately.
If you add 2 as well, it's
intelligent enough to coalesce
and say, "I'm going to
store the range 1 to 3."
And if you add more indexes
that are consecutive,
it will group those
all together,
so it's really efficient
with storage.
It also supports set arithmetic
such as intersection, subset,
and difference like we
saw with mutable sets.
One caveat of this is when
you're using index set
and you apply it to
an NSMutableArray,
if that array changes after
you've obtained the index set,
you can have all
sorts of bad results.
For example, you have a mutable
array, you've gotten a group
of indexes, and then you
remove all the objects
or some of them in the array.
If you try to get
objectsAtIndexes,
you can easily get
a range exception
because that index no
longer exists in array.
So this is something
to be aware of.
NSMapTable and NSHashTable
are very interesting.
They are very similar
to NSMutableDictionary
and NSMutableSet.
There's a couple
of key differences.
They offer a lot more
flexibility with some
of these additional options.
You can use pointer
identity rather than choosing
to use isEqual, as you would
in these other collections.
It can contain any kind of
pointer, not just an object;
it could be a void or any kind
of C pointer you
can store in here.
You can optionally say that
you want weak references,
so that if all the strong
references to an object stored
as a key or value in a
map table, for example,
if any of those go away then
that entry would automatically
be removed for you.
And this works under ARC as
well with zeroing references.
And you can optionally say that
you don't want to copy on insert
as you add an object to
a map table, for example,
it won't copy the key.
You can specify that.
Now, you can't convert a
map table or a hash table
that contains these
raw C pointers directly
to their counterpart,
mutable dictionary or so on,
because they don't translate
over well, and also a caution
to be aware of premature
optimization.
This is one of those
situations that where you think,
this is going to be just what I
need, but you'll sacrifice some
of your compatibility with APIs
that require an NSDictionary,
and for most cases it's
probably not necessary.
It's a great tool to be aware
of, but it's not something
that you're generally
going to use.
This was also introduced
in OS X 10.5
and the corresponding iOS
release, so you should be able
to use this broadly
throughout your applications.
And last is NSCache.
This is also similar
to NSMutableDictionary,
and it's a great
tool to have as well.
Primarily, there's
a few big benefits.
First and foremost is
that it's threadsafe,
unlike a mutable dictionary.
It doesn't copy your keys
unlike a mutable dictionary,
and it supports auto-removal
under memory pressure.
So when the OS needs
to reclaim memory,
it can automatically boot
out entries from this cache.
This is ideal for objects
that you can regenerate
or obtain again easily.
For more detail on this,
I highly recommend the talk
Building Efficient OS X Apps.
A lot of this also
applies to iOS as well.
It focuses a lot on memory
usage and disk IO and energy,
and it will go into much
more depth about NSCache
and purgeable data, and
what you can do to work well
and be a good citizen when
memory pressure comes to bear.
So, wrapping up these
data structures,
I have just two brief
asides as it relates
to data structures
and storing them.
So first, property lists.
You're all familiar with them
that you can store hierarchies
of data, in XML or
binary format.
Each of you at least has an
Info.plist in your application,
and may use them
in other places.
They support property
list objects.
It's a set of six objects in
Foundation: arrays, data, date,
dictionary, number, and string.
Any others that you can't, for
example, convert to a string,
you would have to use NSCoding
and archive it into an NSData
and store it in the
property list.
So you do have some
flexibility there.
It's good to be aware, though,
that mutability is
not preserved.
If I build up mutable
dictionaries and arrays
in a hierarchy that I like and
then store it to property list
and read it back out,
they're no longer mutable.
I'll get the immutable
variants of those.
That's important to know.
Property lists are generally
not efficient for lots
of binary data, like
encoding things into NSData
and sticking them in there,
or for really large files,
particularly if you're
using an XML format.
There may be better
alternatives to look into.
You'll see property lists
commonly with NSUserDefaults,
for storing user preferences
for your application,
it's a common way
to interact with it.
NSPropertyListSerialization is
also a really handy way to deal
with this for input and
output of property lists.
And I encourage you to
look at NSKeyedArchiver
and NSKeyedUnarchiver
if you have needs
to store other data
in a property list.
The second aside is on JSON.
This is JavaScript Object
Notation and originated
in JavaScript, but
it's supported
across a broad variety
of platforms.
It's a lightweight data
interchange format that's human
readable and it's really
handy, and it's commonly used
for things like web
services or sending things
between different platforms.
And it works with a
few Foundation classes.
Some of them are
similar to property list.
You'll see array,
dictionary, number and string,
but there's also NSNull.
If you're not familiar with
this, this is null placeholder.
Collections in Cocoa don't
allow you to store nil inside
of a collection, but JSON
does allow null objects,
and you'll see those transfer
across as NSNull place holders.
And there are also
some restrictions,
such as the top level object in
JSON needs to be a dictionary,
and you can only use strings
for the keys in your dictionary,
you can't use numbers
or other things.
And you should definitely be
aware of NSJSONSerialization.
This was introduced
a few releases ago,
and it's a really convenient
way to deal with JSON.
It supports reading and writing,
you can even pass an object
and see if it will
form valid JSON.
You can also specify
whether you want mutability
when you read objects
out of JSON,
which is different
from property lists.
And this class has been improved
and iterated a lot over time.
It's fast and it's built-in,
you don't have to link
in a static library,
for example, on iOS.
You can count on the
improvements to efficiency
and performance over time.
And you'll see even
more improvements
in iOS 7 and in Mavericks.
OK. So that wraps up about
data structure and performance.
That's a lot of information.
For our final section, I'm going
to kind of tie this all together
and talk about real
world applications.
How we can take all this about
"Big O" complexity and talking
about data structures
performance
and how fast they are, and
apply that to my actual code.
So I'm going to give you
example again from our code.
From the WWDC App, we
refresh the sessions.
You all saw this on Monday.
You're anxiously waiting
for those TBAs to disappear
and see what the
sessions were going to be.
And we have this
functionality to refresh those.
So the data is stored in
Core Data on the application,
on your device, and we
periodically fetch updates
from the server to check
if there's new information.
Now, we did notice some
performances issues
in earlier versions
of the applications.
At first we were
getting great speed,
but as the conference
became more fleshed out
and more sessions were added,
the speed got progressively
slower, and noticeably slower,
not just a little bit,
but a lot more over time.
And it became kind
of unbearable.
And when we profiled it,
we found that there
was non-linear growth.
We obviously had some sort
of complexity problem,
doing too much work.
So I'm going to walk you
through a simple example here.
So this is what we did at first.
We have an array of sessions
that we get from the server,
we've just fetched, and then we
iterate through each of those,
so we want to handle each
of these refreshed sessions
so we have a for loop,
that's order N complexity.
And then we do a Core Data fetch
to see what we have
locally on our device.
We look for a session with that
particular ID, and then we see,
if I had a session with
that then I'm going
to merge them together,
if this is a new session,
I'm going to insert
it into Core Data.
So we were seeing
non-linear performance.
And probably the suspicion
is this may be N squared.
Well, the for loop has to be
there, and the part at the end
about merging sessions
looks pretty simple.
So the work must be
somewhere in between,
right here in the
Core Data fetch.
Now let's think about
what work it has to do.
Well, we're forming a predicate
to search where we say,
"Find me a WWDCSession object
where the session ID is equal
to this session that
I just gave you".
So when I tell Core Data
to do that, we think,
what would it have to do?
Well, because it may not have
ordering on the other side,
probably what it's doing
is it's going through each
of the sessions and seeing
if that session ID matches,
which is an order N algorithm.
So there we have
our hidden work.
We have an order
N loop and order N
for finding the session,
this Core Data fetch.
That's where our N squared is.
So, let's just hoist
that right out,
let's take the Core Data out,
we'll optimize that
a little bit.
Let's say that we now
change it so that instead
of fetching one session
at a time, we get the list
of session IDs that we've
just gotten and we fetch all
of those at the same time.
Now we have them all in
one array and that's great.
We should see order
N performance now,
except we don't.
If you have keen eyes,
you'll notice there's still
some work left inside the loop.
Now, although we know
what session it is
and we've just moved
the session--
the problem, all the work
out of Core Data of finding
that session, we've
moved it into a line
where we're calling
indexOfObject.
Now we have an array
of all these sessions,
but we're still doing
a linear search.
We're stepping through each
of these until we find the one
with the right session.
So, we haven't really
eliminated the problem.
But there is a great
way around it.
Since we're using session IDs
that are unique across these,
we do a slight modification,
and after we've gotten all
those sessions up front,
we create a dictionary where
the objects are the sessions
themselves, and we key
them by the session ID,
'cause these are
going to be unique.
And now, inside the loop, you
can see that we just have look
at that dictionary
and find the one--
the session has that
particular session ID,
and look up in a dictionary is
order 1, it's no longer order N.
So we just solved our problem.
We've taken this algorithm from
order N squared to order N,
and now all of you can get your
session updates really quickly.
There's not 5,000 of
you waiting forever
for all those sessions
to reload.
So that's a real world example
from our own application.
So, I want to also
give a couple of tips
about eliminating extra work.
Really what you want to
do is minimize redundancy
and in particular
the expensive code.
So what we just saw in the
previous example was each time
to the for loop we
we're searching
through the same array just
for a different session ID.
If there's a way that we can
get that out of a loop and do
that work just once, do it less
frequently, that's a big win.
Also, take advantage of
faster lookup when possible,
like we did with
the NSDictionary.
Sets can also be useful for
this when that's appropriate.
Using mutable collections
and strings
when it makes sense can also
be a big performance win.
And I'll show you an example
of that in just a moment.
And also streamline how
you access your data.
Don't make it hard for yourself
to get to the data that you need
as quickly as possible.
You can organize your
data in such a way
that it's structured
intelligently
and your lookup will
be really fast.
And again, try not to
reinvent the wheel.
There's times where you
need to write your own code
but there are situations,
for example, joining an array
of components with strings.
You may have a group of strings
that you want to comma separate.
You could write your own code to
do that and append into a string
and so on, but there's
already API
where you can give it
an array of objects
and give it some string that
you want as the delimiter,
and it can join them
together for you.
So wherever possible use
those, you'll benefit
from the optimizations and
eliminate extra work, you know,
that we're doing as fast
as we can think to do it.
So, an example on
eliminating this extra work,
let's say that you have a method
that takes an array and I want
to scan through that and do
something with these objects,
and if the result is not nil,
I want to add it to a new array
and I'm going to
return that back
from this function--
from this method.
The big problem here is really
that each time we're creating a
new immutable copy of an array.
This is an obvious no-no
and we can avoid this.
Instead of doing that, you can
create a mutable array up front
and add the objects to
the array which is going
to be really fast, and then
at the end when we're done,
we can call copy which gives
us back an immutable NSArray
and we can return that.
So we take a full
advantage of the mutability
when it make sense for us, and
we still fulfill the contract
of our method by saying we'll
return an actual NSArray.
And you could do similar
things with appending
to an NSMutableString or
NSMutableData and so on.
The key takeaway from this
whole section, I like to say,
don't leave performance
on the table.
If there's performance there
just waiting for you to take it
and be faster, don't
leave it there.
Take advantage of it.
You know, if I could be using
an NSDictionary for this rather
than an NSArray, I might
as well do that, you know?
You have to weigh the
benefits, the pros and cons
of choosing either way.
But I really encourage
you to think deeply
about the performance that
you're going to expect to see
with your data structures.
There's a lot more information
that you can find on this.
Dave DeLong is our App
Frameworks Evangelist,
and he'll be a great point
man for any questions you have
on this, and also in the Cocoa
Labs, the Developer Forums,
and then I have three
documentation links
that are really useful for
more in-depth understanding
of collections, property
lists, and archives
and serialization and so on.
There's two related
sessions, I mentioned the one
on Building Efficient OS X
Apps, and Hidden Gems in Cocoa
and Cocoa Touch is immediately
following in this room.
This is a great overview
of a lot
of things you may not be
familiar with or even aware
of throughout the Cocoa
and Cocoa Touch frameworks,
also in Xcode and
different things like that.
So just to summarize, I
have a few key takeaways
that I want you to remember if
nothing else from this session.
The first is that complexity
kills large-scale performance.
If you have a lot of work and
your complexity grows over time,
when you get to large
amounts of data,
your performance will tank.
You need to be aware of that.
Second, know how much
work your code is doing.
Know what it's actually
trying to accomplish,
that's where a lot of the
hidden complexity lies.
Avoid redundancy and
strive for efficiency,
this is those last two points of
how you can resolve these kind
of performance issues.
If you're doing something
over and over again,
take it out of a
loop, do it just once.
If you're doing something
in an inefficient way,
try to find a better algorithm.
Focus on the biggest
performance wins first,
as we talked about Amdahl's Law.
Find the bottlenecks and
eliminate them first,
don't prematurely optimize.
Prefer to use the
built-in collections
and API wherever possible so you
can benefit from optimizations
and improvements over time.
Design according to
your particular needs.
Choose a data structure that
fits how you need to access it.
Something that will make it
really fast for the tasks
that you need to do, and
it's going to be convenient.
And last, think about
performance early.
There's a difference between
premature optimization
and being-- having common sense
about the performance
of your application.
When you use some
of this knowledge
about understanding how
complexity can affect your
performance, it enables you to
make great decisions up front
about how to store your data so
that you can access it quickly,
you'll be happy, and your
users will be delighted
with the performance
of your application.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]