[ Silence ]
[ Applause ]
>> My name is Chris.
I get to give you a quick
tour on some more details
on what's new in Xcode.
Xcode 5 is the product of
a real passion and drive
for building really great tools.
It builds on the foundation of
Xcode 4 which is really solid,
that has a few additional,
very pragmatic things
to solve common problems that
maybe you've been asking for,
as some really big leaps,
and also has a nice new look
and feel, so let's dive in
and see what's going on here.
So I hope you've already had
a chance to install Xcode 5
on your machines and
play with it a little bit
and hopefully you'll have
already seen the new look.
In a word, Xcode 5 is about
deference to your content.
It's all about bringing
your code front and center
so that you can focus
on your application,
and what you're doing instead
of thinking about Xcode.
Now, the new look is
clean and beautiful.
But perhaps, the biggest
change is to the new Toolbar.
New Toolbar is now
30 percent smaller,
which is a huge improvement
particularly if you're using one
of our new 11-inch MacBook Airs.
Now, when you take
Xcode full screen,
the Toolbar virtually disappears
giving you this amazing full
screen experience and
Xcode just looks gorgeous,
our beautiful Retina displays.
Now, there's many changes in
Xcode, one of the big ones is
that documentation
has been split
out to its own full
top level window
with complete tab support.
Documentation is super important
and now, you have direct access
to a Table of Contents,
your Bookmarks,
Xcode even makes it super easy
to share links right
from the ID.
Now, Xcode 5 intentionally
feels a lot like Xcode 4,
but there's one aspect
of the field
that we thought could
be much improved,
and that's in performance.
Now, Xcode 5 just feels great.
It's fast and responsive,
common operations
like plugging a device
now responds instantly.
Tabs, you can create them
when you want them
and they feel snappy.
And common operations like
doing an incremental build,
searching in your project
and building NIB files are
now up to twice as fast.
I think you're really
going to like it
if you have not played with it.
Now, there're many big
feature changes in Xcode,
one of the most obvious
is in Source Control.
Source Control in Xcode 4 has
always been super powerful.
But Xcode 5 takes
it even farther
by directly supporting
branch-based development
workflows that many of you
use to build your features.
And of course, the first
place you want to start
with Source Control is by
checking out your project.
If you haven't seen it, this is
the beautiful new Xcode Welcome
window which is just-- just
stunning in its simplicity.
Now you can start a new project,
get going with an
existing project or,
if you check one out, you dive
in to the newly enhanced
Checkout Workflow.
The new Checkout Workflow
makes it really easy to browse
around different repositories,
keeps track your favorites
and recent locations.
Its just generally is designed
to get going really quickly.
When you jump into the
editor, things are even better
because now you'll see that
you have a new top-level Source
Control Menu item.
Why does this matter?
Well now, Source Control is
available to you all the time,
right from the editor.
You have common-- you have
access to common operations
like doing a Commit, and these
operations now know exactly
which project, or
workspace you're working on.
So they're completely
contact sensitive.
It's not a matter of applying
Source Control operations
to an abstract list of
repositories that you have
to keep straight yourself.
And again, branch-based
development workflows Xcode now
makes it really easy to create
new branches, switch branches,
and even merge right
from the editor.
It's just that easy.
Now, it doesn't stop there.
Xcode even brings per line
blame information right
into the editor.
This makes this really easy to
find out who changed the line
of code, which for me is
actually really important
because when I finally get
to the root of some bug,
the first thing I need to
do is find out who did it
and go point the finger at him.
So now in addition to
being super powerful,
Source Control Xcode 5 is
also super configurable,
and we think this is really
important because it means
that Source Control can
work the way you want it to.
Now, Source Control can be
told exactly what you want--
want you want it to do
for you automatically.
If you're using an external
version controlled tool,
you can turnoff Xcode
source control entirely.
And if you prefer the
left and the right sides
of disk to be swapped?
Hey, now you can do that too.
It's just that easy.
Now, while Source Control
being super powerful
and configurable is great.
There's one thing that I
really don't like configuring,
and that's provisioning
profiles.
[ Applause ]
With Xcode 5 and a new
automatic configuration feature,
this is a thing in the past.
So, what is automatic
configuration?
In a word, it's super simple.
Now, you just tell
Xcode your Apple ID,
and it automatically
knows your connection
to the developer program to
the App Stores, and that means
that Xcode can get your-- set
up your provisioning profiles,
create entitlements,
and it knows your team
identities right away,
just from that one little
piece of information.
OK. So what does
that do for you?
Well now, Xcode knows
who you are,
including the many different
who's that you may be.
It allows you to enter that
directly into the project editor
which makes it super
easy to switch
between your different
identities,
maybe your contractor
and you work
on different projects,
or different clients.
Maybe you have work projects
and, you know, you love coding
so much you have your
own home projects, right?
Now it's really easy to control
this all directly with an Xcode.
It's just super easy.
[ Applause ]
Now, much bigger win of
Automatic Configuration comes
when you pull in a second
feature called Capabilities.
A Capability is a high
level concept in Xcode
that pulls together
everything you need
to add an Apple service
to your application.
Things like iCloud or Game
Center, they require the client
and server to be in sync.
Now previously, setting
up iCloud
for example would require they
do multiple steps with an Xcode,
and then multiple steps
on the portal even before
you start writing code.
With capabilities, and
automatic configuration,
it's now-it can be easier.
It's just a matter of turning
it on and your feature set
up for you automatically.
Xcode handles all the grunt work
of sending provisioning
profiles, create entitlements,
even goes and links
in a framework,
and updates your Info.plist
all for you automatically.
So now, you don't have to
keep track of how to do this
and you just don't have
to worry about it anymore.
So now that we've set
up our application,
we've checked it out,
we're ready to go,
let's talk about how to
design it and let's talk
about specifically
the interface.
Now you all saw iOS 7's
great new design and look
and you may be wondering how do
you get your applications to fit
in and feel like part
of the ecosystem?
Well, Xcode 5 makes it super
easy and has several power tools
that will make your
applications look great.
Now, the first feature
is Auto Layout.
Auto Layout is not
a new technology,
but it's super important.
It allows your applications
to respond to dynamic changes
and layout constraints.
Well, what does this mean?
Well, examples of these
are the resolution increase
on the iPhone 5, or if--
I'm sure you're all localizing
your applications, right?
If your strings are changing
size because you switch
to German mode and
everything is crazy long there,
you want your application
to look beautifully no matter
what language people are using
it in, right?
Well, Auto Layout is perfectly
designed to solve this problem
and given the constraint
changes--
or the control metric
changes in iOS 7,
it's more important than ever.
And this is why Xcode
5 has gone back
to redesign how Auto
Layout works to put you
in complete control of your
Auto Layout constraints.
[ Applause ]
So the best thing about this
is it couldn't be simpler.
Now, you can add and even delete
constraints whenever you want.
If you add a constraint,
Xcode won't change it on you.
And Xcode provides-
[ Applause ]
And Xcode provides a
lot of great features
for solving common problems,
telling you if there's something
that needs to be fixed
and adding constraints
for you automatically because
all the previous on-demand
behavior is now at your
fingertips when you want it.
It's really great.
So to wrap-up our quick overview
of layout and interface design,
I want to talk quickly
about the Asset Catalog.
The Asset Catalog is a new
feature of Xcode 5 that shows
up as a single entry
in your project.
This entry now collects all
of your image-based resources
such as your Launch Images
icons, list images that you use
in your project together
into one place.
Well, in addition to
cleaning up all the clutter
from your project, Xcode knows
about the multiple different
resolutions you need.
It knows about what
devices you're targeting
and what resolution
icons and all that stuff
that you previously had to
just know, naming conventions,
everything and it
handles it for you.
If you're missing something,
it's now immediately obvious.
Also because-- also Xcode
knows about new iOS 7 APIs
and so it can even
optimize the loading
of your image-based resources
using these new APIs.
And it does it for you
automatically so you don't have
to worry about it, it's great.
And building on the
Asset Catalog,
you saw the great new Image
Slicing feature of Xcode.
These makes it easier than ever
to make your images resizable
and it just feels natural.
Now, to show you how to bring
your application to iOS 7,
I'd like to invite up Jon
Hess to show you how to do it.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Chris.
My colleagues and I have been
working on iOS Application
for tracking your runs and
exercising application.
It lets you seen here by
routes, earn achievements
and challenge your friends.
I want to show you just how easy
it is to update this application
for iOS 7 using the new
features of Xcode 5.
First, we need to get started
with a new copy of
our application.
From right here on the Welcome
screen, I can choose to check
out an existing project.
In the streamline
reposit checkout workflow,
I can see all my repositories,
my recent repositories,
or I can focus in
right on my favorites.
I'm going to grab a copy of JogR
and check it out to the desktop.
Now, we have several independent
yet related tasks that I want
to show you today for
updating our application.
This is a great opportunity
for us to use a Branch.
Creating a Branch
in Xcode 5 is easy.
From right here in the Source
Control Menu at the top
of the Main Menu, I'm
going to choose New Branch.
I'm going to give it
a Name, and I'm done.
Creating a Branch in
Xcode 5 is just one step.
Now, earlier when I
checked out my project,
you may have noticed there are
several repositories available
for me to access.
I have configured each of those
in the accounts preferences
in Xcode.
Another type of account that I
can configure is my Apple ID.
And if my Apple ID
configured, I can choose a team
to associate with
my application.
By associating a team with
my application, Xcode help--
able to help me in
all sorts of ways.
For example, I can find the
right signing identities
and credentials to use
when building application.
It also helps me here
in the Capabilities tab
where I can see a list
of all the Apple services
that I can adopt
in my application.
I'm specifically interested
in the new background
modes feature of iOS 7.
I want to be able to
update our applications
so that it continues to get
location data as the user runs.
Turning on the feature is easy.
I'm just going to
flip the switch,
take a look at available
options,
and often do location updates.
Xcode takes care of
all of the details.
We have to update Info.plist
keys, link new frameworks,
change entitlements,
provisioning profiles,
it's all taken care of
for me, and I don't have
to remember each of
those small details.
That's great because I
have trouble remembering
those details.
Another area where I have
trouble remembering the details
is with image names.
I can never remember if an
image is supposed to be named,
@2x tilde iPhone,
or tilde iPhone@2x.
Xcode solves all that for
me, there's a new feature
in Xcode 5, Asset Catalogs.
With an Asset Catalog,
I can name the resources
any way that I want.
I can get started with
an Asset Catalog just
like any other document
by creating a new instance
from the templates.
I want to show you how to
move my existing content
into a new catalog.
From right here on the project
editor, I can see my app icon.
And I can choose to
use an Asset Catalog.
Xcode is going to
migrate my app icon
into an Asset Catalog for me.
I'm going to choose to bring
my Launch Image along too
and migrate them both.
Here in the groups and files
tree, I can see my new content,
the app icon, and
my Launch Images.
There're some new empty slots
here available for content
that I haven't filled in yet.
Specifically, there's
the 60 by 60 app icon
for iOS 7 for iPhones.
I have an icon for that
right here in my dock.
I can just drag it in and drop
it into place and I'm done.
I also have all these other
images in my project that I'd
like to important as well.
From here in the Add
Menu, I can choose
to import content
from myproject.
Xcode is going to analyze
all the files in my project
and suggest the ones
that are members
of the same target
as my Asset Catalog.
I'm going to go ahead and
choose to Import these
and because I'd followed
the naming conventions
of existing releases of iOS,
Xcode is able to aggregate
and group all those
images automatically.
Now, in the groups in the
groups and files tree ,
I can focus on the source
code that I edit everyday.
Another area that I
want to take a look
at today is my Storyboard.
I want to make sure that
all of my scenes look great
with the new appearance
of iOS 7.
By quickly surveying, the
content of each of the scenes,
I see they all look great.
But over here at the end,
I can see that this Segmented
Control has quite a bit
of padding around it.
Let's focus on that.
The Segmented Control in iOS 7
is significantly more compact
than its predecessor.
This is an opportunity for me.
I can focus on my
content instead
of the Chrome used
to manipulate it.
I'll move the Segmented Control
here to the bottom of the scene.
And I want to resize
the image to be larger.
Some straight, but
honestly, I'm a bit of worried
about how this is going to
look on older versions of iOS.
I could build and run in the
simulator, navigate my way
to the scene, come back here,
make some changes, rinse, wash,
repeat, but we have
streamlined this in Xcode 5.
Using the assistant, I can
choose to see a preview
of my application to see how
it will look in all sorts
of different context,
specifically I can look
and see how it will appear
with iOS 6 using these controls
in the bottom right corner.
Sure enough, this Segmented
Control doesn't fit.
It's too tall and it's clipped
in that small space down there.
With the current layout
system that I'm using, Springs
and Struts, I can't specify
what I want to specify.
I want to be able to say
that the Segmented Control
should have a fixed distance
of padding between the image
above it and the control itself
and between the control
and the containing view
to this underneath.
Auto Layout is a perfect
solution for this.
With Auto Layout, not only
can I specify those exact sort
of constraints that I mentioned
there with the spacing above
and below the control.
But I can also specify
things like alignments,
I can have a control
always be centered,
I can even say the two controls
should be sized equally,
is bigger-- the bigger
one of the two of them,
until there's not space for both
of them, and then I can say,
which one should shrink first.
Let me show you just how
easy it is to get started
with all these precision
controls for Auto Layout.
In the file spector
for my Storyboard,
I can enable Auto Layout.
And you can see everything in my
interfaces is exactly the way is
when I-- is-- before
I checked on the box.
Now, I get to start
adding constraints to take
over complete control over
the dynamic resizing behavior
of all the elements
in my interface.
There's many new ways
to add constraints.
Constraints are what
control this behavior.
One of my favorite new ways to
add constraints in Xcode 5 is
by directly control dragging
between two elements.
I'm going to hold the
control key and click and drag
from the Segmented Control.
And by choosing the containing
view, I can fix the bottom space
from the Segmented
Control to its container.
By repeating the gesture
to the image view above it,
I can pin the same
vertical spacing
between the Segmented
Control and the Image.
Zooming in on my
Segmented Control,
I can see the two new
constraints that I've added.
But right now, they're orange.
Interface Builder is telling me
that my constraint
network isn't complete.
I have fully specified the
controls vertical position
and size, but I haven't
said anything
about its horizontal layout.
I need more constraints.
I could control drag
between the Segmented Control
and the other edges and repeat
for the image views and labels
that I have making up the
rest of the interface.
But in addition to having these
precision editing controls
for constraints, Interface
Builder also has features
to make broad sweeping changes
all of your constraints.
I'm going to click
here in the background
and select all my views at once.
And in the Menu, I'm going to
choose Add Missing Constraints.
Interface Builder analyzes the
layout of all the views that are
in my canvas and looks at all
the interesting constraints
that I've already established
and finds the constraints
that it thinks would be
best to complete my layout.
Zooming in on my
Segmented Control,
I can see the constraints
are now blue indicating
that I've completed the layout.
Specifically, I can see
two new constraints,
a centering constraint here
and a padding constraint
on the left fixing the distance
from the Segmented Control
to the edge of the container.
Now, these two controls-- these
two constraints together imply
that I'll also have an equal
distance on the right hand side.
But this isn't the way that I
like to think about this layout.
I like to think of the Segmented
Control as being pinned
by equal distances on both the
left and the right and that--
leaving that to imply that
the control is centered.
No problem, with auto layout,
you're in complete control
of the constraints in Xcode 5.
This automatically generated
its centering constraint,
I can just select
it and delete it.
I can replace it with a
constraint from the right edge
of the Segmented
Control of the container.
Now the layout is exactly the
same but more importantly,
it's in the terms
that I like to think
about it and understand it.
Doing the assistant editor, I
can see that switching to iOS 6,
my application looks
great with no compromises.
Now, is the more important
time than ever for you
to adapt Auto Layout in your
applications and with Xcode 5,
it couldn't be easier.
Back to you Chris.
[Applause]
>> All right.
Thanks John.
Now that you've seen how
to design the interface
for your app, let's
talk about the compiler
and language features
used to implement it.
Where Xcode 4 supported
two different compilers,
Xcode 5 leaves the last
remnants of GCC behind,
focusing on a single
great compiler technology,
the Apple LLVM compiler.
[applause] The Apple LLVM
compiler is a great compiler
and this is why we use it to
build iOS 7, OS X Mavericks,
and Xcode 5 with this compiler.
Now, you may be wondering
why is it 5?
What's new?
Well, this year, we've gone back
to challenge basic assumptions
of C that have been baked
in since the early 1970s
to solve fundamental
problems with header files?
Oh wait, wait, header files,
what's the problem here?
Let's think about what
happens when you go
to compile a source
file of your project.
Say it's 100 lines a code,
it's no big deal, right?
This should compile fast.
Well, the compiler starts
parsing it and sees an include
or an import, and it has
start handling that, right?
Well, say you pull in a UIKit.
UIKit then imports a few other
things and the compiler has
to go parse that and it
has to recursively chase
down all the things that your
file includes and now copies
and pastes all the codes from
all those header files together
into what's called
the translation unit
which is everything that
that file references.
Now, this thing is
something really big.
Instead of 100 lines of
code, it's tens of thousands.
Instead of 10K, it's
10 megs, right?
This takes a lot
of time to parse.
And it's particularly redundant
when you think about the fact
that that the compiler does this
for every single file
in your application.
Now, this is not a new
problem by any means
and we do have a few
pretty terrible hacks
like Precompiled Headers
that helps solve some
of these problems.
But Precompiled Headers, you can
only have one Precompiled Header
per source file.
You also have to manage
your Precompiled Header.
And I don't know about you,
but why am I handling a
compiler doing something
that it should be doing for me?
This doesn't make sense.
Here we are in the 2013, right?
Well, with Xcode 5, there's
a new feature called Modules
which defines this away.
A module is an optimized
symbol database
for system header files.
What does this do?
Well now, things work a
little bit differently
but they feel very similar.
The compiler starts by
building a set of modules
for the system header files so
it pulls all the texts from all
of these headers together into
an automatized symbol database
that makes it super easy and
fast for the compiler to query.
And now when you're going to
compile a single source file,
maybe it sees a reference
to UIView,
it can just do a simple
database query to find
out everything it needs
to know about UIView.
It doesn't have to go
parse tens of megabytes
of code just to find a way.
And this database gets shared
across all the files
in your project.
Suddenly getting a little
bit more interesting?
And remember that it's
not just the compiler
that parses your code.
Xcode uses LLVM for all of
its source code features
like indexing and code
completion, syntax highlighting,
and even Xcode gets
to use these modules.
Well, what does this do?
Well, the best thing
about modules is
that they are completely
transparent.
They're on by default from your
projects and you can get them
in your applications just by
enabling a simple build setter.
If you do this, now suddenly,
the need to handle PCH
is dramatically reduced,
but the compiler also knows
about the frameworks
you're using,
which means that now the
compiler can automatically link
those frameworks into
your application.
You don't have to drag
frameworks in your project name
or get terrible link errors
about symbols you have no idea--
[ Applause ]
But the big story with
modules is simply performance
and how fast the
compiler and our tools go.
And I mean, there's
lots of examples
but to give you one
really concrete example,
when the Mail app in iOS 7
decided to switch the modules,
they saw their total build
time decreased by 40 percent,
which is a huge reduction
in build time.
And better than that, their
indexing time was reduced
by almost two and a half times.
This is a major improvement in
productivity working with Xcode.
Now, modules work
with Objective-C and C
and system header files, but we
know that many of you are C++--
passionate about C++ and
maybe are game developer
and you'll be really thrilled
to know that in Xcode 5,
we're continuing to lead the
industry in C++11 support.
And at this point, Xcode now
supports all the major C++11
language and library
features, including things
like inheriting constructors
which are a great way
to define away a huge amount
of boiler plate in
your C++ classes.
Now, in addition to just being
able to parse your source code
and be able to handle your
program, you also want to--
you also want the compiler
to give you a really
optimized code as well.
And if you upgrade and build
your application with Xcode 5,
you will very likely find
that it runs a lot faster
because the compiler is
better in innumerable ways.
But there's one feature I
really want to highlight
and that's the new
LLVM Auto-Vectorizer.
The Auto-Vectorizer analyzes
your code to find places
where you could be doing two,
four, eight, even sixteen
or thirty-two operations
at a time
by using the vector features
of all the modern processors
that we're targeting.
The Auto-Vectorizer is
simply about performance
and if you're doing dense
number crunching code,
you can see massive
speedups in your application.
Here's an example of
an eight times speed
up on a Neural networking
program,
matrix operations three times
faster, scientific code,
compression, it's 50
and 60 percent faster,
all by enabling a
single build setting.
The Auto-Vectorizer supports
both AMD and Intel chips.
It even includes support for
the new AVX2 instruction set
and the Haswell processors
announced just yesterday.
That's pretty great and
you should try that.
Now, if you use the compiler
from the command line,
you'll be perhaps
excited to know
that Mavericks has made this
even better than before.
Now, Mavericks includes stubs
for command line tools built
right into the operating system
which means that if
you install Xcode,
you'll find that you already
have command line tools
and as you upgrade Xcode
from the Mac App Store,
your command line tools
are all automatically kept
up to date for you.
It couldn't be easier.
[applause] Now, compilers are
fun and they build our code
and that's important stuff.
But the compiler technology
does other things for us.
It also works in Xcode to
help IDE features make us
more productive.
And this year, in addition
to just parsing your code,
the LLVM compiler goes
just a little bit further
and parses your comments
as well.
Why? I don't know.
Well, the great thing
about this is,
is now Xcode can extract
doc comments from your APIs.
[ Applause ]
And service them right
in code completion
and in the QuickHelp APIs.
So they look just
like system help.
Now, if you're working
on somebody else's APIs,
this gives you a lot
of reason for that--
for you to really
encourage them to please,
please document your APIs.
Now, the compiler is
used in a lot of ways.
One of the really exciting ones
to me is the Static Analyzer.
The Static Analyzer in Xcode
uses deep compiler analysis
to find bugs in your program.
It's much better if the analyzer
finds it than you, trust me.
It's-- This year, the
analyzer has a number
of really great new checks,
but also goes much
deeper into your code.
It can now analyze across
method boundaries for both C++
and Objective-C methods.
And in C++, it even understands
constructors and destructors,
which means that now,
the analyzer knows
about smart pointers and a lot
of other really common
situations that occur in C++.
And as many of you have started
using the analyzer more often,
you've made it very clear
that you would really
like the ability to quickly
iterate on a single file
in your project and be able
to analyze that one project
without reanaly--
or that one file
without reanalyzing
your entire project.
Well, with Xcode 5,
it couldn't be easier.
It has new top-level commands
to both analyze a single file
and build a single file, make
it super easy to get that done.
Finally, to wrap up our
discussion of the compiler,
I want to give you a
quick update on ARC.
Now, maybe you know, we
released ARC for Objective-C
about two years ago and we've
seen some pretty massive
adoption in your applications.
It's been pretty-- you guys
have been doing a great job
with that.
I'm really excited to
say that with Xcode 5,
now Xcode has completed the
transition from GC to ARC.
It's a shocking thing.
[applause] And this is
one of the major reasons
that Xcode 5 is so
stable and fast.
Now, if you're one
of the few people
that still use Garbage
Collection on the Mac,
I want to really strongly
encourage you to move on to ARC.
Garbage Collection is
deprecated technology
and will be going
away really soon now.
And I think that when
you switch to ARC,
you'll find that your
applications are faster
and because ARC has a
deterministic programming model,
you'll find that it's much
easier to understand your code
and what it's doing and also to
debug it when things go wrong.
So, speaking of debugging,
let's jump right now
into the Xcode debugger and
talk about what's new there.
Similar to the compiler story,
Xcode previously supported
two different debuggers.
And LLDB is a really powerful
set of debugger technology.
It supports not only
the modern Objective-C
and C++ language
features, it even looks deep
into the Objective-C runtime
and has really powerful data
formatters built right in.
This is one of the many reasons
that LLDB, I'm very happy
to say is leaving
GDB in the dust.
GDB is gone.
So, building on top of the
underlying power of LLDB,
the Xcode debugger has a
lot of great new features.
And the one that I want to
start talking about is datatips.
Datatips are a great
way to see the value
of your variables right in
your code as you're stepping
through it and that's where
you're already looking anyways.
In datatips in Xcode 5
are simpler, cleaner,
more compact and more useful.
Datatips show summary
information from LLDB.
But now, it's also really easy
just by clicking the Info button
to see-- to print out a
variables description.
You don't even have
to go to the console
and hit-- type PO [applause].
And of course, textural is great
but graphical is even better.
And for graphical resources,
you can now see them
right in the debugger.
[applause] It's great for
Bezier Path and images
and a number of different
things.
And you know, for those of you
who have occasionally
felt the need
to give Xcode a friendly
poke in the eye,
now you can do it
right in the debugger.
Moving on from datatips,
let's talk about breakpoints.
Breakpoints in Xcode
are as powerful as ever.
And you may not know
it, but you can set
up really powerful
conditional break points
and even attach actions
right to your breakpoints.
This can let you debug some
of the nastiest logic problems
in your application
really simply.
And breakpoints can be
enabled either individually
in the gutter or all at once
with the breakpoint
activation button.
And Xcode 5 moves us right
down into the debug bar
to be right next to
the stepping controls
where you're already
doing your debugging.
Now, while we're here,
you'll see a new control
on debug bar as well.
And for App Kit apps, there's
some great new features.
Let's pull one out.
So here's our simple
App Kit app.
Well, right from the Xcode
debugger, you can now turn
on several different
options for example
to see the frames
for your views.
This is a great way to
debug layout problems
in your App Kit apps
and these show up live
as your application is running.
You can also have App Kit
flash, the area being redrawn
in your application which
is another great way
to debug performance problems.
Again, live is your App
Kit-- as your app is running.
Now, performance is
really important to Xcode.
And this is why in Xcode 5,
we're pulling lightweight
performance information right
into debugger with a new
feature called Debug Gauges.
Well, why are we doing this?
We have instruments, right?
Well, performance is
a really funny thing.
It's really, really easy
to ignore performance
until your app is
visibly slow or worse yet,
your customers start
complaining about it, right?
And the funny thing
about that is
that modern processors
are super fast,
which means it's
really easy for you
to be accidentally
consuming way too much power
without even knowing it
because your app appears normal.
Now, we all have kind
of a really good idea
of what our applications is
supposed to be doing, right?
And so, debug gauges are all
about showing you what's
actually happening.
So if there is a difference
between theory and reality,
you can see it right
in the debugger.
Now the debug gauges
show up right on top
of the debug navigator.
This gives you information
at a glance
about what's happening
in your application.
And if you click on
one of these gauges,
you get a great details view
that shows you more
information about that area.
Now, debug gauges
are not intended
to have all the detailed
performance information the
instrument does because they
need to be super lightweight.
They're designed to have
less than 1 percent overhead
for your application as it runs
which is why we can
enable them all the time
when your app is being debugged.
And if you want to get
more detailed information,
one click gets you right
into instruments and--
which gives you the full power
to debug any performance problem
that you have and your
application keeps running
exactly where it is
with instruments attached
and continuing on.
Now, in addition to CPU
and memory information,
we also have a number of
other really powerful gauges,
for example one for energy.
This lets you see the state--
current state of your
application, how it responds
to App Map and other
important energy events.
Now, instead of talking
about this,
to fully appreciate
debug gauges,
you just have to see them live.
And to show them to you now,
I'd like to invite up Ken Orr.
Ken.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
So I've been working on a new
feature in our Jogr app here
and I'd love to show
that to you now.
So we'll start by running.
And the first thing
you'll notice
in Xcode is the new
beautifully minimal--
minimalistic debug gauges right
here in the debug navigator.
So as Chris mentioned, if
I click on the CPU gauge,
we'll see the CPU report and
then up in the upper left,
we have an instant
readout of our CPU usage.
And then to the right, we'll
see how we're doing in terms
of the system, and below that,
we'll see our CPU
usage over time.
So let me go ahead and
show you that feature.
So I'm going to click on these
routes button which is going
to show us our jogging
routes on the map.
And we have one route which is
running along the Embarcardero
here in San Francisco, so
I'm going to click on that
and we'll see the details
about that jogging route.
And the feature that I've
been working on is this graph
at the top, this
nice bright graph
which shows you your
jogging speed
over the course of your jog.
Now, you know what, when I--
when I clicked on that route,
I actually saw a little bit of
a spike in the CPU right here.
And I-- that's not something
I was expecting to see.
So let's just do that again.
And actually it's
worse than that.
When I click on that
route, it slides in,
but it's really kind of laggy.
I might not notice that if I
hadn't actually seen this spike
on the graph.
So this is something I
want to definitely fix.
Now, we could jump right
into instruments here
but since I just wrote this
code, I have a fairly good idea
where the problem might be.
So let's go back to our code and
my guess is that the problem is
where we're creating
the UI Bezier Path
that represents that graph.
So what I want to do is I want
to activate our breakpoints.
I'll do that and then let's
trigger that breakpoint.
OK, so here we are
and create graph path.
All right, now I'm looking at
this first line of code here.
And what I'm noticing is
that I'm actually asking
for all the samples
in that jogging route.
So I could be asking for tens of
thousands of data points here,
when in reality, I only need
to ask for one data point
for every horizontal pixel.
So, I'm asking for
way, way too much data.
And that's something that's
very easy to fix by just instead
of doing maximum samples, we can
just say self.pounds.size.width.
So that will give us
just one data point
for every horizontal pixel
giving us exactly the right
amount of data.
All right.
Let's build and rerun that.
And then we want to go to
the map and we want to look
at the reports so that we
can see how we're doing.
OK. So let's click on a route.
OK, that looks much better.
So immediately, I noticed
that the view slid right in,
nice and buttery smooth,
just like I want it.
And then furthermore, I
noticed here in the CPU graph
that it was just a
tiny, tiny little blip.
So, that's the user
experience I'm going for here.
So I'm happy with that.
Yeah, let's just do
that a couple of times,
it's looking really good.
But actually, as I'm
watching the gauges,
which is something I always try
to do, I notice that the memory
of my app keeps climbing every
time I bring that view in.
Now, I certainly don't expect
that bringing in the same view
and pushing it out would cause
my memory to increase like that.
That's not something
I would expect.
I expect it to go up
and then come back down.
So we could see that, yeah, sure
enough every time I'm clicking
on this path, we get another
spike in memory usage.
So, certainly something
we want to address.
This will be a great way to
get us a nice one star review.
So we don't want that.
Let's go back over
here to our code.
And again, I have a guess
where this might be.
So I'm-- I have this
caching logic which takes
that UI Bezier Path, draws it
into an image, and I'm guessing
that we want to look
in this [inaudible].
So I'm going to enable
that breakpoint
and then I'm going
to trigger it.
OK. So here, we are in cache
graph image [inaudible].
All right.
Now when I debug an issue
like this, the first thing I
like to do is I like
to go through
and inspect all the variables.
So I want to make
sure that the values
of these variables
match my expectation.
So is anything obviously out
of bounds, and the way I do
that is I use datatips.
So I can just mouse over image
scale and you'll notice now
in Xcode 5, that the datatips
are so nice and concise,
so small, just showing
me the value.
That's exactly the piece
of data that I want to see
and that's all that we see.
And of course, I can
datatip over rect and I get
that nice textual
summary from LLDB.
And then I can also look at--
so I want to look at self
and I want to see its instance
variables and I can do that to,
you can just twist
it right open.
And you know, one of the
instance variables that I would
like to look at is this image.
Of course, there's
no summary for that.
I don't know what that would
show, but the way I want
to see the image as you
would guess is I want
to see it visually.
And with Quick Look
in the datatips
and in the variables
view, you can now do this.
And of course, there're
many more types
that offer Quick Look.
So things like, we've
got an attributed string.
You want to see the string and
you want to see the attributes
or say a Bezier Path
like you've seen.
Or even things like colors.
These things want to be
visual and now they are.
[ Applause ]
So I'll be honest, I've
been using this feature
for a little while now and
every time that I use it,
I am still amazed every time I
get one of these Quick Looks.
So, I think you're
really going to love that.
All right, so back over
here, looking at our code,
looked to the variables, not
seeing anything obviously wrong,
looking at the code,
nothing is jumping out.
It's just one of those times.
The problem is not apparent.
So actually, Xcode 5 has another
tool at our disposal here,
and that is the ability
to analyze a single file.
So I'm going to take advantage
of that now and I'm going
to run the Static
Analyzer on just this file
and we'll see what
that turns up.
Sure enough, it looks indeed
like we do have an issue here.
So let's click on this so
we can see the details.
OK. So, it looks
like the problem is
that I'm creating
a CG image here.
Now CG images I'm
responsible for releasing those
and in fact, I'm
not releasing it.
So, that would be our memory
leak, it's an easy fix
so let's just do CG image
release, route image
and then let's build
and run that again.
Make sure that we
actually fix the problem.
So we'll click on the route,
we'll let the graphs settle
down a bit and then let's click
on the actual jogging route.
And then let's go back
and forth a few times
and see how the memory responds.
OK. So this is looking much
more like what I would expect.
So I see the memory go up, I
see it come back down, up down.
So, I feel pretty confident
that we fixed that issue.
So fantastic.
All right.
Now, there's one more thing
that I would like to do today,
and that's-- before I check on
this feature, so before I check
on my nice new graph, I actually
want to reduce the footprint
of our app to be smaller
than when I started.
I'd like to set the bar
high for my team so I want
to lead by example here.
And of course, the best way to
do this, we'd analyze my hit
which I can do right from
instruments and I can get
into instruments by
simply pressing Profile,
instruments launches with
the allocations template
and now we're set and ready to
go and dig in and find memory
that we can get rid off.
Really smooth workflow
from Xcode instruments.
So, in just a short
couple of minutes here,
we've seen that we have
found, we have fixed,
and we have verified
both the responsiveness
and the memory leak all using
the new debug gauges in Xcode 5.
And of course, as we saw it with
quick look which is available
in the datatips and also the
variables view, you're going
to have insight into
your variables
like you have never had before.
So we think you're
going to find debugging
in Xcode 5 faster
and easier than ever.
Thank you.
Chris?
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Ken.
Let's move on from
debugging and talk
about the great enhancements
to testing.
Testing is super important
and Xcode 5 takes it
really far forward.
The idea here is to fully
embrace test driven development
and do it in a way that
you've never seen before.
The first feature involved in
this is the new test navigator.
Navigators in Xcode are--
exist to define and
support the common workflows
that you want in
your applications.
The new Test Navigator shows
up just like you'd expect.
As you dive in, you can see
that the navigator shows
you the current state
of your test the last time
you run-- you've run them.
Navigator pulls together
all the actions you want
to apply to test.
It makes it really easy to
add test, even test targets.
But what you really want to do
is be able to run your test.
And in addition to being able
to run them all with command U,
you can now run a single
test right from the navigator
or even define an ad hoc
group of tests and run it,
all without modifying
any schemes.
That's really simple.
[applause] This is a great
way to intervally develop
and test your code as, you know,
all the way from writing
the test first with the APIs
to implementing the APIs and
making sure it all happens.
Now, testing is super important
in Xcode 5 and as part of this,
we're pulling the OC unit
testing framework right
into the Xcode family with
the new test framework XCTest.
Now XCTest is very similar
to OC unit in many ways.
But it's the start of a
continued investment in testing
and will take us much
farther than Xcode 5.
[applause] Among the
many improvements
in testing you can now run
test from the command line
and test just work
the way you think--
you know, just work
the way they should.
Now, with all these improvements
in Static Analyzer and testing,
you may find yourself
running the analyzer
and your test all the time.
And wouldn't it be great if you
didn't have to do this manually.
Well now, with the new feature
called Bots, this can happen
for you automatically.
A Bot is a humble
friendly servant that runs
on an Xcode server
or an OS X server
to handle your continuous
integration tasks running
something known as an
integration, an Xcode lexicon.
An integration is a series
of reproducible steps
that can contain things like
doing a build, running tests,
running the analyzer,
even signing
and archiving your application.
Bots take the mundane work
of running tests off your local
machine and put it on a server
or it can be happening
automatic for you--
automatically for you
continuously and shared
within your whole team.
So now in addition to just
running tests, Bots keeps track
of history and Xcode
provides a beautiful interface
for exploring the
history of a Bot.
Now you can see exactly what
happen in any integration.
If there are any problems, Xcode
makes it really easy to dive in
and find out what went wrong.
Now, this is really
important because, you know,
some failures are easy, you
know, it can again checks
in a bozo commit and
totally breaks everything,
fine, that's easy.
But the more complicated
cases are when you have a test
that fails only on
a single device,
maybe a specific screen
resolution where a process of--
you know, specific processor.
These are the kinds of things
that's really powerful to have,
the tools in Xcode to analyze
and understand what is going on.
And we think you're
going to love it.
Now, Bots can be configured
in many different ways,
but we have two recommended
configurations you should think
about using.
The first is a continuous Bot.
This little guy, checks out your
code from SVN or git, builds it,
runs test in the analyzer and
then as new changes come in,
it does it all over again.
This is a great way to
find regressions as soon
after they're introduced
as possible
which makes it much
easier to fix problems.
Now, the second recommended
configuration is a little
bit different.
This is a periodic
or nightly build.
The idea here is to
emulate your production step
as closely as possible.
So this means that in addition
to building or running tests,
it also signs and
archives your application.
Why do you want to do this?
Well, this is really great
for a number of reasons.
First of all, you
now have a history
of your application over time.
Built the way you do
your production steps
so you can see your
application as it is involved.
This also means that as
you wake up every morning,
you now have a reference build.
You can live on and
that your QA people
or whoever can use
as the days build.
It's really a great way
to pull together your team
and all be focused on one thing.
Now Bots are super configurable.
Xcode schemes are
perfectly matched for Bots.
But Bots also build on
the power of OS X server.
And a server brings a
lot to the table as well.
A server is the perfect
place to archive your logs
and your build products giving
your team access to them all
in one central location.
But it's also really fantastic
place to plug in a whole bunch
of devices because you get
many different Bots for lots
of different projects
all testing
on the same fleet of devices.
And with Bots, it's
really, really easy.
Now to show you how these
all works, I'd like to invite
up Mike Ferris to show
it to you in action.
Mike?
[ Applause ]
>> Let me get right
started here.
I've been working
on a Mac version--
oop, a Mac version of our
social jogging application.
And I've added iCloud support
so that I can plan my runs
and taunt my friends
with challenges while
I'm sitting on my chair.
And I've been writing some
tests for the challenge feature
with the XCTest framework.
I'm using the test
navigator to focus on my test.
I can see that a bunch of my
tests are passing, but a number
of them haven't been run yet.
I've actually implemented
a brand new test suite
for the challenge feature
here and while I was in there,
I implemented a few other
test cases for some things
where I noticed we had
holes in our test coverage.
And since I've added a bunch of
new tests, I'll run them all now
to bring my status up to date.
And I can see that I
have some failures.
A number of the new challenge
tests failed, but also one
of these other tests
that I added--
and I wasn't really
expecting that.
So I'd like to look
at that first.
This task actually looks
pretty straightforward
and I don't see why
it shouldn't work.
So, this actually must be
a bug in my application
and that's great because this
is exactly the kind of thing
that UITests are meant to catch.
In this case, it looks like a
lot of this is mostly working
but it's one of my inboxes
isn't getting cleared
out appropriately.
I'm going to command click
on the call that's
being tested here
to jump right to
the source code.
And I can see that yeah,
sure enough, I'm just kind
of forgetting to update one
of the dictionaries I
used to index the jogs.
So, I'll fix that now.
And to verify that I've
actually fixed the problem,
I can just click on the status
icon in the test navigator
for that one test to run
it again and make sure
that the problem has been fixed.
All right.
So that's one less bug
in my app and I'm glad
that I found those
holes in the coverage.
Now I know what's going on with
the rest of these test failures.
I'm actually using
test-driven development
to implement this feature
so I wrote the test first
and now I need to actually go
and implement the functionality.
So to do that, I'm going to
switch to the project navigator
to focus back in on
my application code.
And go to the challenge
manager class which is
where this feature is
going to be implemented.
You can see that I have some
methods stubbed out here
that need to be filled in.
And while I'm working on
this, I want to make sure
that I'm keeping my
test close at hand.
I'll use a new category in
the related files pop-up
that gives me access
to test cases
that exercise the code
that I'm working on.
And I'll hold down
option while I choose this
so that I can get it in
the assistant editor.
Now, as I move around and
work on the different parts
of my model code, Xcode is
always showing me relevant test
cases in the assistant editor
so I can keep an eye on them.
Now I happen to have
the implementation
for these methods
in a code snippet.
So I'll add those now.
And because the tests
are sitting right next
to my main code in the assistant
editor, as I'm implementing each
of these methods, I
can very easily verify
that I've done it correctly by
just running the test as I go.
All right.
And it looks like I've
completed the implementation
of this feature.
Now, in Xcode 5, we want to
make it really easy for you guys
to write great applications
and the new testing
functionality is a big part
of that.
But tests are really only useful
if they're run frequently.
And wouldn't it be great if
your test could be running all
the time.
Well, that's what
Bots can do for you.
And they'll also
perform static analysis
and build archives
of your application.
Bots do this integration work
either whenever changes are made
to your project or on some
sets schedule of your choosing.
The iOS version of our jogging
application already has a Bot.
And when I'm in Xcode, I can
see any Bots for the projects
that I'm working on right
in the logs navigator.
This Bot had a test failure
the last time that it ran
and if I click on it, I can
see a more detailed report.
This tells me at a glance
how my Bot is doing.
There are issue counts
for the last integration,
graphs that show how
my Bot has been doing
over the past few integrations,
and a current list of build
and test issues that
the Bot has found.
I can double-click on one
of these issues to go right
for the code and this actually
shows one of the big benefits
of having this built
right in to Xcode.
I can easily close the
loop, get right to the place
where the problem is and fix it.
And let's go back to
the report for now.
One of the main reasons
of course
to have a Bot is to run tests.
And I can use the test tab
to get a lot more detail
about how the Bot is
doing with my test.
There's a trend graph here
that shows me how my
test have been doing
over the entire history
of this Bot.
And below, I see information
about each individual test case
that the Bot is running
and how it's been doing
over the past few integrations.
Here I can easily see
which tests are actually
failing right now
and when they started to fail.
So like with the issue display,
if I want, I can go to the code
for a test case that's failing
just by double-clicking.
But another way to
approach fixing a test is
to actually find
out who broke it,
track them down and
make them pay.
[laughter] So, let's
do that and I'm going
to deputize all of
you right now.
So, you're going to help me.
I can identify that
this is the integration
where this Bots started to fail.
And if I double-click
on the integration,
I'll go into the
integration report
which gives me a lot more
detail about the test.
And here I can see that this
Bot is actually running my test
on four different devices.
And not only that, but I can
clearly see that a couple
of these test failures
are only happening
on one particular
type of device.
Now, you can't always
be running your test
on every different hardware
configuration and OS version
that your app may support.
But the Bots can.
Now let's remember our mission
though, we're here to track
down the culprit here.
The integration report
also has a Commits tab
where we can see all of the new
Commits for this integration.
And I can see that in this
one, there was only one
and I can even jump right in
and see what source file changes
were made before I go track
down Jon to make him
fix this problem.
Jon we'll talk later.
Now I have a-- we've
been looking at the Bot
for the iOS version of Jogr and
I'm thinking that I really ought
to have one for the
Mac version as well.
So to create a new
Bot, it's just as easy
as choosing Create Bot
from the Product Menu.
This Bot is going to build
the Mac version of my project
and I'll give it a name.
I'd like this Bot to run every
time there are new changes made
to my-- committed
to the repository.
And by default, Xcode
is going to send--
the server rather is going
to send email to the people
who have committed new changes
whenever the Bots start to fail.
Xcode goes off and creates
the Bot and it takes me
to the new Bots report as
the first integration starts.
Now, Bots-- your Bots
are working continuously
to make sure that your
apps are going to be great.
And when they find problems,
you'll see them right in Xcode.
Another great way to keep track
of how your Bots are doing
for you and your whole team
is to use the Scoreboard.
We have one of these up on the
wall in our development area
on a big TV all the time so
that we always know how our Bots
are doing.
This way, we're always aware
of how the Bots are doing
and when something goes
wrong, we can all pitch
in to start fixing the problem.
With workspace centered
source control,
the improved testing support,
continuous integration,
and the team score board, Xcode
5 makes it easier than ever
for you and your entire team
to work together to
create great apps.
Back to you, Chris.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Mike.
Xcode 5 is available--
is available right now.
We think that it will help
you build better apps faster
and easier than ever before.
Now, Xcode 5 in the OS X and
OS X server are both available
for download from the
Apple Developer Website.
Xcode includes the SDKs for
both iOS 7 and OS X Mavericks
and it runs on either a Mountain
Lion or a Mavericks machine.
OS X works with either Xcode
but it itself must be
run on Mavericks to work.
Now, a great way to get started
here at the conference is
to run both of these
on the same machine
and it's really easy to do that.
If you have any questions,
we'd be really thrilled to talk
to you this week in
the lab here at WWDC.
Thank you all.
[ Silence ]