[ Silence ]
>> Good afternoon.
My name is Madhu Vudali, and I'm
here to introduce iAd Workbench,
a new advertising product
for iOS developers.
We know that many of you at
the conference are either new
to advertising or
never even thought
of advertising your apps.
So we'll briefly cover why you
should advertise your iOS apps
and why you should consider
iAd for your advertising.
We'll go over iAd Workbench and
my colleagues, Vineet Gossain
and Mike Amirault, will do
a couple of demos for you.
So let's jump in.
Say you have this beautiful
app that you had developed,
your awesome app, and
it's in the App Store
and users might find it.
If they know your app, they
might actually search for it
or if your app is
featured in any
of the App Store's features
like, New & Noteworthy
or Editors' Choice, they
might chance upon it.
Perhaps your app is in
many of the app collections
that the App Store has.
But consider the
fact that there are
over 900,000 apps
in the App Store.
And as Tim Cook pointed out
yesterday, hundred thousand
of those got added
just in the last year.
So there's a limited opportunity
for your apps to be found
in the App Store, but you
want to grow your user base.
You obviously built good times
building your app and it's
in the App Store you want
users for your App Store.
What do you do?
What should you do?
You should advertise.
With discovery in the App
Store, users find your app.
Pretty straightforward but
you're competing with lots
of apps in the App Store.
But in advertising,
you find your users.
You find the users that are
likely to download your app.
With advertising,
you're in control.
Obviously discovery and
advertising go hand and hand.
But again, with advertising,
you are in control
in finding the users
for your app.
Finding the users for
whom you built the app.
There are many options for
advertising, obviously.
But we're-- you're
an iOS developer
and your best option is iAd.
We can find users who are likely
to download apps like yours
because we know who
those users are.
We run the App Store.
We get the data from the
App Store and iTunes.
So we can find users for you.
Over the last three years, iAd
has been working with hundreds
of developers promoting
thousands of apps
and driving hundreds of millions
of visits to the App Store.
That's the scale and power of
iAd that we're offering you.
We are offering this new
platform for all iOS developers.
We're calling it iAd Workbench.
A do-it-yourself
campaign creation
and management application
with all the key features
you need for your apps.
So let me touch on
a couple of them.
Auction Marketplace.
With Auction Marketplace
you have CPC and CPA.
So that's cost-per-click
of your ad
or cost-per-acquisition
of a user.
So you can bid your CPC and
we will not charge you more
than that, or if you know
roughly what you would pay
for acquiring a user,
you can input that
and we will optimize
to achieve that goal.
And with audience
targeting, we have two options
for you, Auto and Manual.
So we've been operating
for the last three years
and we bring you the
power of those learnings
with auto targeting where we
find, or iAd Workbench finds
that right users for your apps.
But we also provide many
rich targeting options
and you can use them,
you can find them
through the manual
targeting that we have.
Third thing I want
touch on is ad banners.
You need creatives for your ads.
If you're working with
the creative agency
or you have in-house expertise
to develop Ad Creative,
you can upload them.
Or you can use many of the Apple
designed beautiful templates
for your ads.
So, all the key features
for your app promotions
are all here.
We launched this app yesterday,
this iAdWorkbench.apple.com
and already thousands
of iOS developers have
already started using.
Before we go into the
details of iAd Workbench,
I want Vineet Gossain to give
you a quick demo of the app.
Vineet?
>> Great. Thanks Madhu.
Now, as Madhu mentioned, I know
a lot of you guys are brand new
to advertising, so I want
to show you guys how quickly
and easily you can create
a new ad campaign using the
iAd Workbench.
It only takes a few minutes.
For those of you who are more
experienced in advertising,
I'll be back later to
give the demo of some
of the more powerful features
that are offered
by iAd Workbench.
Let's start with a quick
demo of creating a campaign.
So this is your Dashboard
when you first log
in to iAd Workbench.
We'll click on Create Campaign.
And the very first thing you
need to do is you need to choose
which app you want to promote.
All of your Apps are here.
Let's choose Klara
our productivity app.
You give it a campaign name,
Klara Summer Promotion,
and hit Next.
Oops, already exists.
OK, Campaign Summer Promotion 2.
That one does also exist.
OK, sorry.
Couple of test runs [laughter].
OK, so the next thing you
need to do is you need
to find your audience.
As Madhu mentioned,
we have two options,
the Auto option, or
the Manual option.
If you choose Manual, you get
several different targeting
categories such as device,
gender, age, if you know exactly
which user you want to target.
But for most of you,
your best bet is Auto.
For Auto, iAd will
automatically figure
out who are the best
users to show your ad
to at the right time
to maximize downloads.
For this campaign, we'll
choose Auto as well.
The next option is
your Flight Dates.
Basically, when your want
your campaign to run,
you can time your campaign to
run with the specific promotion
or specific holiday, or you
can just have it start today.
For this demo, let's
just have it start today.
The final piece is entering
your campaign budget.
For the budget, that's basically
how much you want to spend
on this campaign over
the life of the campaign.
For this demo, we
use 2,500 dollars.
But you can go as low as 50.
You can choose the
Daily Spend Goal,
if you want to limit how much
you're spending on a daily basis
but that field is optional.
We'll stick with
the pre-calculation
which evenly spends the budget
across the duration
of the campaign.
And then the final option is how
you want to pay for your ads.
You have two options
as Madhu mentioned,
CPA or cost-per-acquisition,
basically how much
you're willing to pay
for each additional
download of your app.
Your other option, CPC,
or cost-per-click is basically
you're giving us the maximum
you're willing to pay for
each click on one of your ads.
Let's stick with CPA and
we'll put in 2 dollars
and 50 cents as a CPA goal.
You can hit this
Calculate button
and what we'll do is we'll do
an estimate and give an estimate
of how many expected
impressions or number
of times your ad will
appear in front of users.
The expected number of taps, how
many taps you can expect people
to actually have clicked
on your ad and roughly
about how many downloads
you can expect
to result from this campaign.
You can go in and tweak
these numbers if you--
you can go in and tweak the
budget numbers or the CPA goal
if you feel you want
to get more downloads.
But let's just stick
for this for now.
We hit Next, and then the
next piece is you have
to choose the artwork that you
wish to show to the end users
as part of your campaign.
We have two options.
You can upload your own where
all you need to do is you need
to provide the various artwork
for the devices that you wish
to target, or you have
the option of using one
of our Apple design templates.
Now, each of our templates,
we have five different templates
each with multiple color schemes
and each of them is animated.
For this campaign,
let's use a JetSet.
For each template, you provide
three things, the title, Klara;
the message, "Getting
things done,
faster" and a call to action.
We'll do download now.
You can replay the animation,
so you can see what it will look
like to the end users and you
enter in everything just once
and we'll automatically
create the templates for each
of the devices that
you wish to target.
So, in this case we created
both iPhone and iPad banners.
If we're happy with that
we give it a banner name,
Klara JetSet, and hit Next.
And now, the final piece
is the Banner Summary.
On the Banner Summary,
you can choose
to create additional banners if
you so desire in case you want
to compare how one banner
does against another.
But for this demo, we'll stick
with just a single banner.
Now, the final step is
the Campaign Summary.
Within the Campaign Summary,
this is your final review,
make sure everything is OK.
Confirm your budget, 2,500
dollars, our CPA goal
of 2 dollars and 50
cents, our Klara banner,
we hit Submit and you're done.
Since it's-- there you go.
So, your campaign is
created and quick and easy,
and you're ready to go.
Back to you Madhu.
[ Applause ]
>> That was awesome.
Thank you Vineet.
I was certainly timing him
and it was about five minutes
and that's the fastest
he's done.
So that's a new record Vineet.
So, let's go into an
overview of iAd Workbench.
So, we want to cover
three topics: one,
how you can get started; two,
how you can create campaigns;
and three, how you can manage
the performance of the campaigns
that you have created.
Getting started.
Getting started is very easy.
You log in, you sign up
and setup your payment.
Log-in with your
developer credentials.
Sign up to the terms and
conditions of iAd Workbench
with a new service from Apple
and you just have a different
terms and conditions,
and you setup your payment.
We accept major credit cards
or you can also apply
for a line of credit.
You're done with your sign up.
Next, you create Campaigns.
Vineet went through a fairly
quick campaign creation process.
Let's go a little deeper
in each of these steps.
Selecting an app.
So every campaign is
anchored around an app
because that's what's
your promoting.
So, when you sign
up as a developer,
all your apps are already here.
So, you pick the app
you want to promote,
and you give your campaign
a name and you hit Next.
So, your campaign is
essentially the first step
of your campaign
creation is done.
Next step is selecting
an audience.
In the demo that we saw, we have
two options, Auto and Manual.
With Auto, you get the
optimized audience selection
from iAd Workbench.
What do we mean by that?
It means that iAd Workbench
finds the right user
at the right time, on the
right device in the right app
to maximize the downloads
for you.
Recall that I mentioned
that we've been operating
for over three years,
you're really benefiting
from those learnings when
you choose this option.
The other option is the
manual targeting option.
In this case iAd Workbench
provides you the targeting
options and you picked
what's best for you.
You still get the benefit
of the optimization except
that you've given us
the starting point
for the optimization.
Let's drill into what
are the various manual
targeting options.
On the left hand side are the
various basic targeting options.
So gender, age, various
age buckets, geotargeting,
State and DMA for now,
and day of week targeting.
These are basic options
for advertising.
On the right hand
side, you can--
you start with device targeting,
you can target all the iOS
devices that Apple makes.
So iPhone, iPod and
iPad and iPod touch.
Next I want to drill I little
bit into user preferences.
This is one of the most powerful
features that we provide you.
So with user preferences,
you target users based
on what they download in
iTunes and the App Store.
So at the top here, hope you
can read that, you have apps,
movies, music, books and so on.
So what does this showing
you is what-- if you tar--
choose this option, you're
targeting users based
on what they download
in the App Store.
Actual downloads, not just
likes, actual downloads.
Think about that.
If you're a game
developer and you want
to reach users who've
already downloaded games
and shown preference for
games, you can do that here.
Or let's say your game
appeals to action movie fans,
you can combine that
with a movie preference
for action movies.
That's the power you're getting.
We're using the data from
iTunes as well as the App Store
to find the right
user for your apps.
For our example app Klara,
which is a productivity app,
we're just choosing
business, finance,
productivity and utilities.
The next preference,
next targeting option
is app channels.
Here you're asking the question,
where do you want
your ad to run?
What you see here is the
taxonomy in the App Store.
You're determining, what's
the context for your ad.
You can browse the App Store
and see what this context mean.
So when you when you
choose these options,
you're determining, or you're
deciding what's the most
relevant context for your ads?
For Klara, which is
a productivity app
and fairly broad
based, we've chosen most
of the app channels
that we have here.
Your app may not me relevant
in all of these channels,
so that's a decision
that you need to make.
The more channels you pick,
the greater the reach
for your campaign.
The last option we
offer you is App Rating.
Some of you might have apps that
are not necessarily appropriate
in contexts that are 17+.
So, you can with the fair--
with the simple filter
you can exclude apps
that are 17+ from
your campaigns.
So these are the targeting
options that we have
under manual targeting,
and the burden is on you
to pick what's best for you.
You always, obviously, have the
optimization that comes with it.
But you can also
pick the Auto Option
where iAd Workbench does
the heavy lifting for you
to find the right
users for your app.
So two steps down, the third
step is to set a budget.
You're answering three
questions, how long do you want
to run your campaign,
how much do you want
to spend and at what price?
How long? So you're essentially
determining what the start date
and end date of a campaign.
You need to set the
duration of your campaign.
By default a campaign
starts today.
But you can pick any date
range that is relevant to you.
Maybe you're launching an update
for your product or your app.
You can pick a date for that.
Or perhaps you want to
coincide with back to school
or Black Friday, whatever.
You can choose these
options from here.
The next question you're
answering is how much?
You're setting a budget
and a daily spend goal.
A budget is what
you're willing to spend
for the entire campaign.
And the daily spend
goal is a way for you
to control the pacing of your
campaign during the entire
campaign-- for the duration
of the campaign, sorry.
And now we're answering
the question what price?
Two options that we mentioned
before, cost-per-click
where you're inputting the
maximum that you're willing
to pay for a click, so
when there's somebody taps
on your ad, that's the
maximum you're willing to pay.
We will not charge you more
than that, that's your bid.
Or you can indicate a
cost-per-acquisition goal,
a CPA goal.
Here you have a rough idea as to
what you are be willing to pay
to acquire a user, or for
download from the App Store.
You input that and iAd Workbench
optimizes to that goal.
So you have CPA and CPC
that you can choose.
Now you've answered
all three questions
and we've provide you
three answers there.
We provide you the impressions,
the taps, and the downloads,
as an estimate for
all your settings.
So the targeting that
you've chosen, the duration
that you've chosen, the
budget that you've chosen,
and your bid all determine
these three numbers.
We also have a nifty
gauge next to the numbers.
The numbers, the gauge
essentially indicates the
numbers or your settings
in the context
of what's available overall.
In this case, the needle is all
the way to the left telling me
that if I had more budget,
meaning if I had more
than 10,000 dollars to spend,
I could substantially increase
the number of users for my app.
But you-- for now, this
is what you get, OK?
So, three steps down, last step
or the fourth step
is adding banners.
As Vineet pointed out,
you can upload banners.
So if you're-- if you
work with creative agency
or you have in-house
expertise to create banners,
you can upload them
for all the devices
that you're targeting,
and you're all set.
But many of you might not have
access to creative agencies
and may not want to spend
even for all of that.
You get the benefit of
Apple designed beautiful
templates here.
The templates have
been designed to ensure
that your app is
highlighted in the banners.
So we have five templates,
each with five colors.
So you pick a template,
you give it a title,
you give it a message, and
you give it a call to action.
So all-- basically three
things that you need to do
for your banner and we
take care of the rest.
As Vineet pointed out you
can see a quick preview
of the various sizes
that you're getting
from the one banner
that you selected.
These are the various sizes
and the various devices
that you're targeting.
If you want to see
how the ads look,
appear on the actual devices,
you can send an email directly
from the application,
and using iAd Tester,
you can see how your ad
appears on the devices.
Pretty powerful.
Last step is submitting
the campaign.
You get on a single page all
the options that you've chosen.
You obviously see the app,
the name of the campaign
that you created, the
various targeting option
that you've chosen, as
well as the banners.
When you hit Submit,
your campaign goes
into the creative
approval process at Apple.
So that's campaign creation.
Now when you create campaigns,
obviously you're interested
in understanding how
they're performing
in the App Store,
in our marketplace.
You want to understand how
many downloads you're getting.
You're spending good money
to acquire those downloads,
and you perhaps have chosen
various targeting options
or various banners for your
app, for your campaigns,
and you really want
to understand the
performance of them.
So we provide you a
Dashboard and drill downs.
Dashboard gives you, on the
left hand side, a quick view
of what's going on in your
application for all your apps.
So you can see all the
apps and the campaigns
that you've created
for those apps.
You have, at a quick glance,
understand how those
various campaigns are doing.
You can initiate a new
campaign as Vineet did from--
directly from the Dashboard.
On the right hand side,
you have drill downs.
Again, you get granular
reporting
for all the options
that you've chosen.
You have the various targeting
options that you've chosen.
You have also the
various banners
that you've created
for your campaign.
You can do understand how these
two perhaps targeting options
are performing.
Or you could also
trend them overtime.
Lots of rich data
comparison tools as well
as insightful visuals for
you on the drill downs.
Rather than me talk about it,
let's have Vineet come back
and give us a demo of
managing performance.
Vineet?
>> Great. Thanks Madhu.
So yeah, now we've
created our campaign.
But now the question
is, how do you ensure
that your campaign is
doing as well as it could?
How do you ensure you're
maximizing your downloads?
Let's go to the Dashboard.
On the Dashboard, you see
the list of the campaigns
that are currently running.
So we have three campaigns
And within each of
the campaigns,
you see four key metrics.
The total amount you spent
so far on this campaign
and you can see how
that compares
to the budget that you set.
The average CPA, again, that
was cost-per-acquisition,
how much you're paying
on average
for each additional download?
You can compare that to the
goal that you set as well.
Average CPC, the actual cost,
you're paying per-click
on your ad.
And if you would set a CPC
bid, you would see it here
so you could do a
comparison as well.
And finally, probably the
metric you guys care most
about the total number of
downloads that have resulted
from your ad campaign.
So from the Dashboard,
you can quickly drill in.
Let's take a look at
this campaign and see
and get a refresher of what
exactly this campaign is
all about.
So for this campaign,
we have multiple lines.
So we haven't talked
about lines yet.
Basically a line is a
set of targeting options.
Madhu went over that various
targeting options, gender, age,
user preference et cetera.
What you can do is you can
group those options together
into a single line.
You could call it, "Men 18 -
24" or some other combination.
And for each line, you can
set an independent budget,
independent daily spend goal,
and an independent CPA goal
so you can track how one line
is doing against another to see,
what is your target market?
And you can quickly flip
through multiple lines
to see all the different
settings that you have.
So we have "Men 35
- 49", "Men 50+".
So right now, we're
breaking it down based
on gender and age range.
In addition, you can
see all of the banners
that you have associated
with your campaign.
We have multiple banners
and using multiple
different templates to see
which one performs the best.
And you can see there's a number
up at the top, eight lines.
Basically for each of the
banners you can choose
which lines you want
to associate them with.
You may have certain banners
that may appeal a certain
demographics and certain banners
that may appeal to
different demographics,
this way you have the
ability to pick and choose
which banners will
show up to which lines.
OK. So now we've gotten familiar
with how this campaign is going.
Let's go back to the
Dashboard and take a look
at how it's performing.
We click on Home button and
go back to the Dashboard.
We are looking at
this Klara campaign.
Let's drill into spend and
see how we're doing on spend.
So when you come to
the analytics page,
one of the first things you
should do is choose what time
range you wish to look at.
By default we start with
today but there's option
for yesterday, the last 7 days,
the last 30 days, et cetera.
Let's go with last 30 days.
Up at the top, you actually see
the numbers for your campaign,
the full lifetime
of your campaign.
So you always have
that at your fingertips
so you can compare not
only how you're doing based
on the time range
that you've chosen
but the overall life
of the campaign.
So now that we've chosen last
30 days, we can see in the graph
and you can see how
much is being spent
across those 30 days.
You can choose to graph
a different metric,
impressions, taps.
Let's stick with
the average CPA.
So you can see overall average
CPA is performing pretty well
and then you can overlay a
second metric on top of it
so you can vary to see
how the spend is doing
as compared to your average CPA.
In addition to the overlays,
you can actually click up here,
compare with the previous
period to see how your spend--
or your average CPA is doing
over the previous 30 days
or the-- versus the
current 30 days.
And finally, you can also click
on a tabular view and see all
of the detailed information
about each
of the metrics all at once.
And if you would like you
can download a CSV file
so you can import it into
numbers or into Excel and slice
and dice it as you wish.
OK, so now from here this
was all about the campaign
but we can also drill in
to see the individual lines
as I discussed.
When you click on Lines Tab, you
see all of the different lines
and how they're comparing
against each other.
You can choose a metric, we can
do it base on average CPA again
and see that "Men 18 - 24" has
higher CPA than "Men 25 - 34".
Right now we graph three lines.
You can choose which
lines you want.
You can unselect 25 - 34
and select "Women 25 -
34" and see how that's doing.
And then quickly the graph--
,oh, it looks like
that one has no spend.
OK, "Women 35 - 49", so you can
see how those three lines are
comparing to each other.
And then we have a similar
view on the banner side
so you can compare how banners
are doing against each other.
For this campaign, we actually
only have one banner that's
currently active so you
actually only see one banner.
You could-- If you don't
remember what Marigold Promo
actually relates to,
you can click on I icon
and get a refresher of
exactly what this banner is.
OK, let's go back to lines and
see what optimizations we can do
against lines to improve
our campaign's performance.
OK, let's look at the overall
lifetime of the campaign.
So at the bottom of the--
at the bottom of the screen,
you see a table which basically
has all the different--
all the different
metrics that we have.
We want to optimize
based on the average CPA.
We can sort by average CPA which
again is how much you're paying
on average for additional
download.
And we see that these two
lines, the average CPA,
a dollar sixty-eight and a
dollar eighty-four is much less
than the 3 dollars
that we inputted.
So those two lines seem to
be performing pretty well.
And as you can see,
the downloads
for those two lines seem to
be the best out of those two--
out of all the lines
that we have.
So not only are you getting more
downloads you're actually paying
less for each download, this
seems like a good combination.
So it would make sense for us
to actually add additional spend
to these two lines perhaps
taking it away from the spend
from some of the lines that
are not performing as well.
And so this is the
power that you have
when you're doing
manual targeting.
But the beauty of
Auto is that this--
these optimizations are
automatically done by iAd.
We automatically figure out
which demographics are the ones
that are performing best for
you giving you maximum downloads
and lowest CPA.
Back to you Madhu.
>> All right.
Thank you Vineet.
So we saw how you can
manage your performance.
Once you have setup
your campaigns,
you can go into the tool
and manage the performance
of those campaigns.
So iAd Workbench as I
mentioned is available now.
We launched it yesterday
and many
of you already started using it.
But what else could we do?
So coming in the Fall, we
have iAd Workbench for iOS.
So we have it on
the iPhone and iPad.
Many of you perhaps use
iTunes Connect Mobile
for managing your apps on
the go in the App Store.
Now the same app with the
additional iAd tab can be used
to manage your campaigns
on the go.
So what are the key
features here?
You have access to
actionable information.
So the same dashboard and
drill downs that we saw
on the web application are also
available on the iOS devices.
But they are customized
obviously for touch.
And you will see Mike
giving us a demo of that.
We also have alerts
and notifications
which is really important--
which are really important
in the mobile context.
We will tell you what's
going on with your account
or with your campaign on the
go so you can take action.
The action can be updating
dates, so if you want
to extend your campaign
or extend your budgets,
change your bid based on the
alerts that you might get
or based on the performance
you might want to pause
or unpause any of the
campaigns, lines or banners
that you have running.
So all of the functionality that
you see on the web for managing
and optimizing your campaigns is
also available for you on iOS.
So its coming this Fall but
Mike can do a demo for us now.
Mike?
>> Thank you.
So this is the iTunes
Connect Mobile application
and I'm sure a lot of
you are familiar with.
Let's fire it up.
And we'll sign in
with our Apple ID.
And the first thing you'll
notice that on the bottom,
there's now iAd tab that
wasn't there before.
And this is the campaign
Dashboard page.
It shows all the
campaigns that we have.
You can see some brief info
about them, their name,
their status, their
flight dates.
You can sort them by running,
not running, or completed.
Let's have a look at the
first campaign here BB iPad1.
We'll tap that.
These are the campaign
detail page.
At the top you will see-- again,
see some basic information
about this campaign, the name,
the flight dates, the status.
Down the bottom you'll see all
your campaign results to date.
So you will your spend in
relation to your budget,
your average CPC,
your average CPA
and your CPA goal and downloads.
And if you wanted to see how
these metrics accrued over time,
you can swipe the
table to the left
and you see a beautiful
graph of the data.
So this is for spend, average
CPC, average CPA and downloads.
By default, it's showing
the last 24 hour period.
You can also change the time
period for seven days, 30 days
or for the lifetime
of your campaign.
If you want to see the graph
in more detail you can rotate
your device to landscape
and see the graph
in full screen.
All the same graphs
that were available
in portrait are available
in landscape.
If you just want to jump to
a specific graph and not want
to have to swipe through to
find it, you can just tap
that metric in the table view.
So if we want to jump quickly to
spend, we can just tap on that
and look at the spend graph.
Let's switch back to portrait.
In the middle of the screen
you'll notice two buttons,
one for line items
and one for banners.
Use for the line items
associated worth this campaign
and for the banners.
Let's look at the line items.
This shows the three line items
that I have associated
with this campaign.
You'll see the name, the flight
dates, the status and the spent
in relation to the budget.
Let's tap into the first one.
This shows the line
detail screen, very similar
to the campaign detail screen.
We will see some basic
information at the top
about the status, the flight
dates and you will the results
to date down the bottom.
You will be able to see the
spend in relation to the budget,
the average CPC,
CPA and downloads.
And of course you can swipe
them to get the graphs.
In the middle section
there's a button for banners.
This will show us all the
banners we have associated
with this particular campaign.
So let's tap that
and have a look.
There're two banners
associated with this campaign
and its showing us the
spend on both of those.
Let's tap and look
at the first one.
This is the banner
detail very similar
to the campaign detail
and line detail.
We're going to have some basic
information about the banner
at the top, its status, and
down the bottom you'll have the
banner results to date.
And again, you can
swipe over and look
at the graphs for
the various data.
Now you notice in the top
right corner there there's a
Pause button.
You'll be able to pause
and restart your banner
directly from your device.
So let's pause this banner.
It'll ask us if we
want to continue.
Yes. And now the
banner is paused.
If we want to restart the
banner, we can just tap Restart
and continue and the
banner is now restarted.
Let's go back to the
campaign Dashboard page
by tapping the tab
at the bottom.
And you may have noticed at the
top it's telling us that one
of our campaigns
may need attention.
And the second campaign,
Prod Pack Promo has an
Alert icon next to it,
signifying that that is the
campaign that has a problem.
So let's tap that
and have a look.
You'll notice on
the lines button,
there's another alert
button, another alert icon.
So it's telling us that one of
our line items has a problem.
So, let's tap it
and check it out.
We have eight line items
associated with this campaign
and you'll notice that two
of them have the alert icon,
so two of the lines
have a problem.
Let's look at the second one.
And there we go.
At the top, it's telling us
exactly what the problem is.
It's saying a bid amount
may not be sufficient
to reach our campaign goal.
So that definitely seems
like something we should fix.
So on the top right corner
of the screen you'll
notice an Edit button.
Let's tap that and
edit this line item.
So this is the line item editor.
In here, you can change
the end date, the budget,
your max daily spend
and you CPA goal.
And you notice down the bottom,
you can also pause the line
or restart the line much
like you can with banners.
So, you can also see
down at the bottom
on the CPA goal line
there's the alert icon.
That letting us know that
that is a particular line
that we need to change.
So, let's tap on
that to edit it.
This will bring up
a standard keypad
but we've added two custom
buttons in there for you,
a plus 5 percent and
a minus 5 percent
so you can quickly change your
value by 5 percent increments.
So let's add 5 percent.
Nah, let's bump it
up another 5 percent.
When you're satisfied with
all the values and you want
to save it, just
touch the Done button
and the values are now saved.
So these are just some of the
features that will be available
in new iAd module within
iTunes Connect Mobile coming
in the Fall.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Mike.
So it's coming in the fall.
But iAd Workbench is already
available and thousands
of you are already using it.
So get started with
iAd Workbench.
It's cool, huh?
iadworkbench.apple.com,
we are in the labs.
We can help you get
started or you can start
with your developer accounts.
So some quick housekeeping,
there are related iAd sessions
about iAd Producer tomorrow
and on Thursday there's
iAd Integration to those
of you who are publishers.
And for more information you
have Mark Malone, the wonderful,
for any questions
you have on iAd.
And you can always go to
Apple Developer Forums.
Thank you and have a great WWDC.
[ Silence ]