>> Nathan de Vries:
Good afternoon everyone.
My name's Nathan de Vries
[phonetic] and today I'm going
to be talking to you about iAd
Integration into your Apps.
Now there are two major
opportunities the iAd presents
to developers.
The first is promoting
your applications
with the new iAd
Workbench feature
that was announced this week.
And the second thing is
a revenue opportunity
for your applications.
So using application to generate
revenue through advertising,
and that's what we're going
to be talking about today.
How to integrate iAds
into your applications
to generate revenue.
Now we're going to be doing
that by going through this flow.
We're going to start by talking
about the developer
benefits of iAd specifically.
Why it might be a
good choice for you
to generate revenue
in your applications.
Then we're going to look at some
core concepts that are critical
in understanding why your
application is generating
revenue in the way it is, how
you can improve on that revenue
by making adjustments
to your application,
and we're also going to go
into a little bit more detail
beyond those core concepts
and talk about specific
things that you can do
to optimize ad performance
in your applications.
Next we're going to briefly look
at how to join the iAd network.
It's very easy.
And lastly, which is the major
chunk of the presentation
which you're all here
for, is to look at some
of the developer API's
for integrating iAds
into your application.
So let's start with
the developer benefits.
First and foremost,
ignoring ads all together,
you put huge amount of effort
into your applications,
which they mix with applications
that have won the design awards,
blood, sweat and tears get
poured into your applications.
So you really want experiences
within your application
that match the amount of
effort that you put in.
So first and foremost, we really
want to delight your customers.
So that's why the advertisements
with iAd have very
high production values.
We put a lot of attention
to detail into the ads
so that your users get the same
beautiful enriched experiences
that they expect from your app.
As part of this rich experience,
iAd support media, playback,
and game-type experiences,
really adding
to the features of
your application.
Like your application that
has access to amazing API's
on the platform like Gyroscope
and Cameran and so on,
ads also have access
to these API's.
The ads are seamlessly
integrated with iOS' software
and as hardware, so there's
not this sandboxed limited
experience inside an ad.
It's just an app.
And this creates this kind
of immersive experience
for the user.
If they choose to
engage with an ad,
it feels like this amazing
experience for them.
And that's what we're
really trying to achieve.
And you can see here the
types of examples of ads
where you can really shake
the app and it interacts
with the ad, or you
can play music
or a game, watch move trailers.
These are all the
kinds of things
that advertisers are
providing in their ads.
And lastly, even though when the
user engages in an ad and their
in this [inaudible] experience,
their still in your app.
So as soon as I dismiss
the ad, they're right back
in your app where they left off.
Just seamlessly in and
straight out again.
So because the ad is inside
your app, we value the privacy
of the users of your
application.
This is why we request
permission before asking
for contact access in your
application, or photo access,
because we really
value the privacy
of the users of your
application.
Likewise, with advertising,
we also have
that same approach to privacy.
So we handle the privacy, so you
don't need to worry about it.
Users start using ads
within your application have
the same privacy thought
about that we do for your app.
The world's best
brands are using iAd.
So all around the world we have
agencies working with brands,
winning design awards
for advertising,
using the iAd platform.
So all creating is, these brands
are very familiar to your users,
so their much more likely to
engage in the advertising,
and that really drives
the immersive experience
for the users.
Every year we're
expanding so far.
We started in the U.S. We've
recently rolled out into Mexico.
There's 11 countries
now that we support.
So there's a great opportunity,
not just to advertise locally,
but also broadly,
and we'll speak
about that a little bit later.
It's also a menu
here to work out how
to monetize your application.
It's a great path to revenue.
When your application
displays an advertisement,
the advertising revenue that's
generated from the display,
and the interaction with those
ads, 70% of that revenue goes
to you as a developer.
So we think that's a really
great way for you to make money
with your applications.
And lastly, as developers, it's
incredibly easy to implement.
You'll be able to jump to
that later on when we go
into the developer
details, but we really feel
like we've made it as
easy as possible for you
to integrate ads into
your application.
There's no need to link
against additional SDK's,
so no need to maintain
and download other SDK's.
You can be up and running in
really small amount of code.
We also have some great sample
code which you'll notice
on the developer@apple.com
website, which I'll link
to a little bit later.
This provides the iAd
Suite sample code,
as well as developer
documentation.
If you were to really dive
in and see examples of how
to integrate ads into
your application.
And lastly, we think that's
always been pretty easy
to integrate ads, but we've
made it even easier this year
with iOS 7.
So we're looking
forward to your feedback
on some of the new stuff.
Next let's have a look
at some core concepts.
Integrating iAds
into your application
from a developer point of
view is incredibly easy.
You'll get up and
running very quickly.
But there are some core
concepts related to advertising
and iAds specifically that
are useful to have in the back
of your mind when you're
integrating the ads
because once you've
shipped your application,
it's in the app store, and
customers are using your app,
you're going to need
to track the progress
of revenue generated
by your app.
So some of these core concepts
are going to keep coming
up in your sales reports and
changes that you need to make
to your application
to improve some
of the ad performance,
so we'll start there.
First of all, what is
the iAd App Network?
Well we mentioned briefly
that there's the two things
that that the iAd network
really provides to developers;
the path to revenue, which
we're talking about today,
and also the promotional
aspect promoting your app.
So the iAd App Network is the
Apple business team working
with advertisers to produce
inventory and delivering them
to you, the developer
that's integrating iAds.
So what does this look like?
You've linked your application
against the iAd framework.
What this means is that
the iAd framework is going
to send requests to
the iAd App Network
on your behalf asking ads.
So we send ad requests to the
App Network, which replies,
as you'd expect, with ads.
So this combination of two
things: The requests being sent
to the network and the ads being
sent back form this concept
called the Fill Rate.
Those of you that are familiar
with advertising probably
have heard of this before,
but this is the measure of
performance of requests sent
by all of your applications,
versus the ads
that are delivered
by the network.
And we'll come back to
that when we're talking
about improving app performance.
Once you've been delivered an
ad, you still have to display it
on the screen, so just
getting an ad isn't enough,
you have to show it to the user.
That's the point of this.
So that's called an impression.
As soon as you display
an ad to a user,
it's called an impression,
and a certain percentage
of those impressions will
hopefully turn into Tap Throughs
when the user engages
with the ad.
And these two concepts combined
are called the Tap Through rate.
So the number of Tap Throughs,
versus the number of impressions
that you're shown in your app.
And you'll see these
as well in your reports
when you're measuring the
performance of your app.
So that's a few of
the core concepts.
We'll refer back to them
later on in the presentation.
Next let's look at some
tangible things that you can do
to improve the ad performance
of your application before you
even get started with the code.
So first and foremost, it
all starts with a great app.
You need to focus
on the customer.
Your app needs to have
utility and be useful,
so ignoring the advertising side
of things, your app just has
to be something that you
want lots of people to use.
They find it really useful.
They come back to it.
There's loyalty associated
with your app.
People just really have
to want to use our app.
I'm recommending going
to some of the sessions
on design during the conference,
or watching them on the videos,
because honing is
part of your app.
It is going to be a
key to the success
of advertising in your app.
Having a great app, or
something that's worth talking
about will generate
network effects.
So you'll start getting
reviews on the app store,
people will talk about your app,
and all of these things
result in more ad requests.
So as a side effect of focusing
on the customer and your app,
you're immediately going
to get more ad requests,
more ads served, which
is better for your app.
The next thing that you can
do is to place ads smartly.
Key here is not place
ads everywhere.
You have to really
consider user context,
as well as recognizing high
use areas in your application,
so when you're looking
at a holistic view
of your application,
really consider is
this view appropriate
to advertising how
many users are entering
into this part of my app.
You want to avoid
accidental taps.
So placing ads in spots
where users might accidently
tap the ad isn't a good thing
because it might
be an impression,
but if people are tapping on the
ad and immediately dismissing it
because it was a mistake?
That's not going to be very
good for your ad performance.
And really keep in
the back of your mind
when you're designing your
apps and integration of ads
into your apps, that user
context is incredibly important.
So you really need to weigh up
the benefit of an impression
versus what the user
was trying to do
when you were showing that ad.
So things like showing
advertisements
during registration.
Maybe you want to
show advertisements
after registration
because the success
of your app is predicated
on someone signing up,
enjoying the app, and
coming back to the app,
which will produce more
advertising revenue for you.
You should also consider
customer location.
I mentioned that we support
11 different countries
at the moment.
So you should take
this into account
when you're planning
your marketing strategy.
If you're only serving your
app to, say, the states,
then maybe you should consider
serving to other regions
because these regions will
also be sending ad requests,
but not getting anything back.
Or they might not even have
the app available in the store.
So really consider where
you're submitting your app,
to which stores, and take
into account these iAd
App Network countries.
One thing that you can do
with this is target your
marketing to those countries.
So if you've never thought
about advertising specifically
to a particular country, maybe
you should try doing that?
That will increase the number
of customers in that country,
and really drive up
those ad requests,
and assist with optimizing
the ad performance
of your application.
You could even consider
going a step further
and localizing your
applications.
The last country that we rolled
out the iAd App Network
to was Mexico.
It's right next door and
you could localize our app
in Spanish, and immediately
get access to a whole bunch
of customers that you would
never have had access to before.
Driving up ad requests,
impressions, Tap Throughs,
and improving your
app performance.
Another thing that you need
to consider is the
seasonality of advertising.
Consumer spending throughout
the year fluctuates,
so as does advertising spending.
Advertising spending kind of
tracks consumer spending, right?
So you should also
market accordingly.
If you know that there's going
to be a holiday period coming
up where spending is
going to be increased,
maybe you should focus
your marketing attention
to that time of the year.
Increase a little bit of
your marketing budget,
get some more customers into
your apps at that point in time,
and then you'll get more
requests at that time.
And, I guess the one
thing to take away
from this is it's a very,
it's a feedback loop.
As you drive more customers
to your app, you're going
to get more ad requests, which
are going to result in more ads,
which in turn turns into
impressions, and Tap Throughs,
and the iAd App Network
will use all of these things
to decide should I send
more ads to this app?
How many ads should
I send to this app?
So a really healthy
app is one that works
with this feedback loop that
really drives as many customers
as possible, creates
loyalty, and gets more ads.
So that's a little bit about
optimizing ad performance.
You might be wondering, well how
do I join the iAd App Network?
It's pretty easy.
If you've submitted an app
before, you would have gone
to the iTunes Connect website,
so the iAd preferences
configured in the same place.
All you need to do is
complete the iAd contract once.
And then on a per app basis,
you need to enable iAd
specifically for that app.
One thing to bear in
mind is that you need
to do this before
you submit your app.
So before you've finished
developing your app
and maybe you want to
create the descriptions
and the screenshots, and so
on, the App Store details
for your app, make sure you
enable iAd before you submit the
binary for our application.
So that's a little bit about
joining the iAd App Network.
Let's dig in to some of
the developer details
about integrating apps
into your application.
And to start with,
what we're going
to do is talk about banners.
The banner ad is a
slim device with view.
Sits at the bottom
of your content view.
And you can see one here.
It's typically a place at
the bottom of your content,
but remember back to the smart
placement bit of the talk
where you can adjust this
depending on music context
to avoid accidental
taps, but our guidance is
that it generally goes to
the bottom of the content.
As new ads become available,
the banner continuously loads,
so if your user passes out of
network access and comes back
into network access, these
banners will automatically bring
in new ads, and roll on and
off the screen automatically.
When you tap one
of these banners,
you get a full screen
immersive ad experience.
And lastly these
banner ads are supported
on both iPhone and iPad.
So you can use them
in both contexts.
To integrate these banners,
there's three easy steps.
First you need to link the iAd
framework, which is pretty easy.
We're going to get a
demonstration of that soon.
You need to import the iAd
header from the framework.
And lastly, you need to
choose the view controllers
in your application that are
appropriate for advertising.
So what I mentioned
before, that you had an app
with the banner view
across the bottom,
you should consider each
screen of your application
as being appropriate or
inappropriate to the banner ads.
And we've got this new API
and iOS 7 that allows you
to set a flag on any of your
View Controllers to say,
I would like banner
ads to be displayed
in this View Controller.
So we set the canDislayBannerAds
property to yes.
And what this does is
it takes the root view,
or the top level view
of your View Controller,
and it becomes the
originalContentView.
It becomes a mute property.
This allows us to wrap
your View Controller's view
in a Framework View which
allows us to animate the banner
on and off the screen.
So when you sent the
canDisplayBannerAds property
to yes, we wrap your
view in another view.
We start sending ad requests
to the network saying we would
like banner ads for
this particular device.
When the banner loads, so we
get an ad back from the network,
the banner moves on
screen, adjusting the size
of your original content view.
So the one thing you
need to keep in mind is
if you're referring to that
original view, you now need
to change all of your calls to
view on your View Controller
to originalContentView.
And you also need to make sure
that your originalContentView
respects Relay Out,
accommodating a new banner ad.
Once the banner is
on the screen,
the user has an opportunity
to tap on it.
So we get that full screen
ad experience on tap.
When the ad appears
on the screen,
you get the usual appearance
and disappearance callbacks
on your View Controller.
So what you should do
in the viewWillDisappear
callback is poise
and intensive media
activities, sounds, and so on,
that would interrupt
with the ad experience.
Because your goal is to have the
user enjoy the ad experience,
and not feel like the
app is using up CPU,
slowing things down, because
that disrupts the ad experience.
When the full screen
advertisement is dismissed,
then this is a good time to
resume any immediate activity
that you had running
in your app.
So now we've got
an ad on screen.
The user passes out of
network connectivity,
or there's no longer
ad Inventory available
to your app, the ad unloads.
So when the ad unloads,
the banner is moved off-screen
automatically by the framework,
and your original content view
is resized much in the same way
as it was resized when it
was bought on the screen.
So you've got these
View Controllers
and they're all configured,
or some of them are configured
with canDislayBannerAds.
There are certain circumstances
where you want a
temporarily disable banner ads
on a particular View Controller.
So we support that as well.
You simply need to set
the property back to No.
And when you're finished
with the app context,
where it's inappropriate for
a banner ad to be displayed,
or not ideal for a banner ad to
be displayed, then you can set
that property back to Yes.
Don't forget to re-enable.
Yes. We provide some great tools
for testing during development.
In the Developer Settings
pane on the device,
we have these two
great facilities
for adjusting the Fill Rate,
which we mentioned
in the core concepts.
This allows you to
configure your application
so that it never gets ads.
It always gets ads or
some variation in between.
This is as this was with
testing of your app.
You can also adjust
the Refresh Rate.
So this is how quickly ads cycle
in and out of your application.
One thing to bear in mind is
that this only affects
your apps.
So if you're carrying
a development device
and you total these Fill Rate
and Refresh Rate settings,
and then you run another
person's app from the store
that has iAds, it's not
going to affect the Fill Rate
and Refresh Rate of that app.
It's only apps that are
installed by you as a developer.
I'd like to bring
up David Wilson
to give us a demonstration
of how
to integrate banner ads
into our application.
>> David Wilson: So now that
we've talked about banner ads,
we're going to take a quick look
at a demo, just how easy it is
to take an existing application
and add this functionality
to it.
To do that, we're going to start
off with a simple application.
It's just two View Controllers.
It's a master detail.
The first one's going to show
a list of article headlines,
and when you tap on one of those
article headlines, you're going
to go into New View
Controller that shows
that article in a web view.
What we want to do in the
first part of this demo is
to add a banner view to the
bottom of the list of articles.
So I'm going to go ahead and
pop open the iOS Simulator here,
and this is the application
before we started doing anything
to it.
We've got top news here,
a list of quick articles.
We can click on one of these and
we've got ourselves an article.
So let's see what we need to do
to add iAd Support
to this application.
We're going to hide
this, go back,
to Xcode to bring
up our project.
And the first thing that
we need to do is link
against the iAd framework.
So we're going to make sure
we've got our project selected.
Select the appropriate
target here.
And go over the Build
Phases Tab.
Click the Plus Button.
We can find the iAd Framework.
And go ahead and add
that to our project.
The next thing that
we need to do is go
into our Master View Controller
here and Import the iAd Header.
That gives us access to the API,
specifically the
CanDislayBannerAds Property
on View Controller.
Once we've done that, all we
need to do is set that property
on the View Controller
when it wakes up.
We can go ahead and save.
We can re-run our demo here.
Now you'll see that
automatically.
An ad pops in from the bottom as
soon as the ad request is made,
and a new ad has loaded
into your application.
If we were to lose network
connectivity and this were
to cycle back out, you'd see it
just animate out smoothly just
as well as it animated in.
And with that, I'll bring Nathan
back up to continue the slides.
>> Nathan de Vries:
Thanks, David.
As you can see, it's pretty
easy to enable banner ads.
Just a simple property.
Very easy to do.
Pretty cool.
This is new in iOS 7.
So next we're going to talk
about a different type of ad.
We've seen a banner
ad which when tapped,
presents a full screen
advertisement.
The Interstitial is a
little bit different,
in that it doesn't have
that intermediary
view that you tap on.
It immediately launches into
a full-screen advertisement.
So what usually happens
is, as you're transitioning
from one part of your
application into another part,
you get this full-screen
advertisement up here.
So this is pretty cool.
This has been available since
iOS 4.3 on iPad, as of iOS 7,
this is all also
available on the iPhone,
so you can start using
this today on iPhone too.
Now when I talk about
automatic presentation
of a full-screen view,
when does that happen?
As of iOS 7, we now
have this new property
on View Controller
similar to the property
on the banner ads
called the Interstitial
Presentation Policy.
And what the iAd framework is
now able to do for you is watch
for View Controllers
to become visible,
and then present an
interstitial ad automatically
when that view becomes visible.
So if you've got
a view controller,
we can say there's two
View Controllers here;
one is off-screen, the current
View Controller on-screen,
and the next View
Controller off-screen.
We want to configure the
Interstitial Presentation Policy
of the next View
Controller to be automatic.
We want the iAd framework
to automatically manage
presentation of an interstitial
when it's appropriate based
on inventory and minimum time
between interstitial
presentations.
Now when we call
pushViewController to present
that View Controller,
an interstitial is
automatically presented on top.
When the user dismisses the
full-screen interstitial,
they're back to that
next View Controller.
They're back into the app.
There's also another option for
applications that are doing,
maybe single View
Controller style,
have the single View
Controller architecture.
Things like games, where
you need to have control
over the presentation
of the interstitial
because there's no View
Controller transitions.
So what you need to
do there is instead
of setting an automatic
Interstitial Presentation
Policy, you set a Manual
Presentation Policy.
And what this does, is it
still enables interstitials
to present automatically
and seamlessly, but you need
to request the presentation.
So if you're building a
game style application,
when you transition
from, say, the game back
into the menu would
be one example.
You can call Request
Interstitial Presentation,
and if an ad is available,
it will present.
One thing to bear in mind
with interstitial ads is
that when you're setting this
property on View Controllers
that might happen quite a while
after the user has
launched the application.
Setting the property on a View
Controller is really the only
way for the iAd framework
to know
that ad requests
should stop being sent
to the iAd App Network.
So what you can do
to improve on this is
to call Prepare Interstitial
Ads early
on in your application's
lifecycle
so that you don't miss
those early impressions.
And with that, I'm going
to bring David back
up to do a demo.
>> David Wilson: Okay.
So we're going to go back
to the application we
just took a look at,
and we added a banner view
to the bottom of the list
of articles, and now we want to
add interstitial presentation
when the user taps on one
of those articles to go
into the actual article view.
We can go back, remember, and
this is what our app looked
like when we last left it.
We've got ads at the
bottom, and you can see
that they're cycling there.
We can go back to Xcode.
Now as Nathan mentioned,
it's important to tell iAd
that you're going to want to
present interstitial as early
as possible in the
app's lifecycle.
That allows iAd to go ahead and
make ad requests on your behalf
so that an interstitial is ready
when the user takes the action
that would present it.
So the first thing we're going
to do is we're going to go
over to our app delegate.
We're going to import
the iAd Header here,
and then inside our app
delegates did finish launching
with Options Call.
We want to go ahead and
call UI View Controller,
Prepare Interstitial Ads.
This allows iAd to begin
making those ad requests
at the beginning of
your application.
That means the moment
the user takes action,
we're going to have
ads available for you.
Once we've done that,
we can go back
to our Master View
Controller here,
and we've already
imported the iAd Header,
which was the important bit.
And we go down to the bottom
of this to prepare for segue.
Here we've set up our
Detail View Controller.
We've set the Article URL on it.
And once we've done
that, we just also need
to set one more property,
which is the Interstitial
Presentation Policy.
And once we've done
that, we can save again.
We can go ahead and Run.
Okay. So we've got our
application back up.
Give it a second and the
banner should kick in here.
And then behind the scenes,
we're also making
interstitial requests
which we'll be loading
an ad for us.
Note that the default
fill rate for development
of the application is 80%.
You will want to change
that again as Nathan pointed
out if you want to test things
work all the time, versus never,
go ahead and click on one
of the articles here,
and not get an ad.
We got one down there.
There we go.
So the user's tapped on
the article headline.
They've gone in the
article view,
and the full-screen ad has
presented over the article view.
Once the user has finished
engaging with this ad,
they can go ahead and close that
ad, and they're back immediately
into your View Controller.
And with that, I'll bring Nathan
back up to continue the slides.
>> Nathan de Vries: So simply,
setting the Interstitial
Presentation Policy
on your View Controllers,
and you get this
automatic view controller
interstitial presentation.
It's pretty easy.
Pretty easy to get started.
So next we're going to look
at this ad type called the IAB
Medium Rectangle Advertisement.
So what is this?
It's a view that's very similar
to a banner view, except instead
of being positioned at the
bottom of your content,
it's positioned in-line
with your content.
The size of this
view is prescribed
by the Interactive
Advertising Viewer,
which is why it's called the
Medium Rectangle Advertisement.
You might have seen
this on websites.
It's 250 points by 300 points.
It also has a similar cycling
behavior as the banner view,
so as new ads become available,
the ad cycle in the view.
And, again, like
the banner content,
you also get full
screen ads on tap.
This was introduced
in iOS 6 [inaudible],
and it's available only on iPad.
So how do we create
one of these things?
As you noticed, it
was positioned in-line
in the content, so you have
this greater flexibility
and positioning of the
view within your content.
So to do that, we need to
create this banner view
of type medium rectangle.
So here you can see after we've
imported the headers like we did
for the banner view, we
created this new banner view
of type medium rectangle.
And this is going to create
nearly unloaded medium
rectangle view.
So we also need to configure
ourselves as the delegate
of this view because
as ads become available
and unavailable inside this
banner view, we need to be told
so we know when to
present the view onscreen
and take it off screen.
So we set ourselves
as the delegate,
and the protocol
that's used to talk
to that delegate is the 80
Banner View Delegate protocol.
So whichever object you've
assigned as the delegate needs
to conform to the 80 Banner
View Delegate protocol.
So we do that as well.
When the banner is
ready to load,
so we get this Delegate
Callback.
That callback is called the
Banner View Did Load Callback.
Called on the delegate.
And when this happens,
that's an opportunity for you
to present the ad on screen.
We now have an ad
fulfilled by an ad request.
We now need to turn
that into an impression.
So to do that, you can do your
custom layout however you would
like to present that view.
You could cross-fade it in,
readjust your other views,
and present that medium
rectangle ad in-line
with your content.
Similarly to banner ads, when
the medium rectangle is tapped,
you get the full-screen ad.
You also need to use
the view will disappear
and view will appear callbacks
to pause any activity and sounds
in your application to prevent
them clashing with any sounds
and media that are
being played in the ad.
When it comes time to unload
that medium rectangle,
the next callback you'll receive
on our Delegate is called the
bannerviewdidFailToReceiveAd
with Error Callback.
And this is an opportunity for
you to remove due to the reverse
of adding the view to the
view hierarchy, and you want
to move it off screen.
It's important to
keep in mind here
that you shouldn't just throw
away the medium rects ad view
because you can just
keep it around.
It'll continue to
cycle with new ads.
So as those new ads
become available,
you can simply add the same
medium rectangle ad view back
to your views hierarchy.
So much like banner
ads, we have some tools
for testing medium rectangles.
We still have the
adjustments to fill rate.
They also work with
these medium recs.
We have adjustments
to refresh rate.
Same as we discussed before.
But there's another additional
toggle that you can flip used
for medium rectangles because
you're positioning them often
in very specific ways
in line with content,
and what that switch does is
it helps you avoid any clipping
of that ad view.
So we really want to
avoid clipping the ad view
because that can prevent the
user from being able to see it
or the user being
able to tap it,
so by flipping the
highlight clipped banners,
you get these overlaid
red or green views on top
of your medium rects to show
whether it's being clipped
or not.
So make sure that you
run your application
with this flag enabled
in Settings
to make sure your medium
rects aren't being clipped.
So let's get a demo of that.
>> David Wilson: Okay.
So to enter it medium rectangles
into an application is a
little more complicated,
as Nathan mentioned.
So to do that, we're going to
start with a new application,
and this is sort of a
bit of a game simulation.
Most of the screen is going to
be taken up by the simulation.
There's some text at the bottom
that has some wasted white
space, and we're going to try
to take advantage of
some of that white space,
to include a medium rect
in the bottom left
corner of our screen.
Okay. So, anyway, you just
have to trust me that we have
as a simulation at the top, and
we have some text at the bottom,
and we've got a medium rectangle
that we're going to want to put
on the bottom left
corner of the screen.
So to do that, as we did
in our previous project,
the first thing we're
going to need to do is link
against the iAd framework.
So click on our project
here, go over to Build Phases
for the appropriate target.
Link binary with Libraries.
And we're going to link
in the iAd framework.
Remember this is an
iPad only feature,
so we can't actually demo
it with the iOS 7 STK today.
But you can build applications
to run against iOS 6.1,
and they will work with
the next seed for iOS 7.
Once we've linked
against the iAd framework,
the next thing we need to do
is go to our View Controller.
We're going to go ahead and
Import the iAd framework here
to give us access
to these API's.
And because we need
to have a delegate
for the medium rect banner view,
we're going to make
our View Controller
that 80 Banner View Delegate,
and then we're going to set
up a couple properties to hold
the new 80 Banner View Medium
Rect that we're going to create,
and to keep track of whether
or not the ad is
currently visible on screen.
We're going to need this so that
we can do the appropriate layout
as the banner view
loads and unloads.
So once we have those
properties inside Load View,
we can go ahead and
instantiate that.
Note that all we have to
do is alloc initWithAd:
ADAdTypeMediumRectangle,
and then remember
to set the delegate to
the View Controller.
Once we've done that, we need
to update our
viewDidLayoutSubviews method
so that we can include the
medium rect inside our layout.
So all we need to do here is
do some frame calculations
for the medium rect,
which puts it,
with the calculations
here we're doing is layout
out the medium rect in the
bottom left of the screen
if it's loaded, and
just off-screen
in the bottom left,
if it's not loaded.
That allows us to do smooth
animated transitions on
and off screen, as
the loaded property
of this banner view changes.
To do that, we're also going
to need to adjust the origin
of the frame that's next to it.
Once we've done that,
then we need
to actually start implementing
the delegate method callbacks
that will tell us when things
happen with this banner view.
So the first thing we're going
to do is go down to the bottom
and hide the rest of this.
Then we go to first start
out by implementing
bannerViewDidLoadAd.
This is our cue to move
the banner onscreen
if it's not already there.
This is iAd telling us that
there's a new ad that's in place
in the view and we should
display it to the user.
If it's already visible,
that's fine.
We don't need to
take any action.
If it's not, we're going
to set our property here
and then we're just going
to do a quick animation
to move this thing onscreen by
just calling setNeedsLayout,
layoutIfNeeded, and letting
the layout code that we did
up above handle this for us.
Now once the banner's been
onscreen for a little while,
we're going to have to move it
back off screen if it unloads,
say the user moves out
of network connectivity,
or we just run out of inventory.
So we're going to implement
in this case the
bannerViewDidFailToLoadAd
with error method.
This is almost identical
to moving it onscreen,
except we're going to
change our property to No,
and then we're going to
again do an animation based
on setNeedsLayout,
layoutIfNeeded.
So that'll move the
thing on and off screen,
but there's one more thing
we need to take care of,
and that's pausing our game
when the user actually
interacts with this ad.
We've got a simulation running.
It's taking up CPU.
Maybe the user is actually
interested in watching
that simulation, and we
don't want to let it just go
on behind the scenes while the
user's interacting with the ad.
So to do that, we're
going to go ahead
and implement view did
appear, view did disappear
on our view controller, and
all we need to do here is start
and stop timers that are
running our simulation.
If you had media, this would
also be your cure to pause
and then resume the media.
Once we've done that,
if our demo machine were
working we could run it again,
but that's pretty much
all you need to do
to get medium rects
integrated into your app.
And with that I'll
bring Nathan back out.
>> Nathan de Vries: So the next
ad type which we're excited
to talk about today, is
the pre-roll video ad.
We've had a lot of requests for
this, and it's new to iOS 7,
and what this lets you do
is integrate seamlessly
with the media player API's
to request playback all the
video before your video content.
So as I said, it's
brand new in iOS 7.
It's integrated with
the media player API's.
So the way you would
normally play back media
with the MP movie
player controller API,
you can now just
use a different API
to play a pre-roll
ad before that media.
When the pre-roll
starts playing,
this happens before the
media content starts playing,
your primary media
content starts playing,
and when the advertisement
finishes,
you get this seamless transition
to the main content video.
If the user engages with the
video while it's displayed
with this pre-roll video,
they get that standard
full-screen immersive ad
experience as well.
Just like all of the other
advertisements we support.
We also support Inline playback.
So if you've got an application
that doesn't assume
full-screen media playback,
then you can also use
pre-roll video in that scenario
by using the embedded style
for MP movie player controller,
and this is supported
on both iPhone and iPad.
So let's take a look
at how to create one
of these MP movie
player controllers.
In addition to the usual iAd
framework import that you need
to do for the other ad types,
the MP movie player
controller functionality is
in the media player framework.
So you'll need to
link media player
and also import the
media player headers.
We then need to create a new
MP movie player controller,
or an MP movie player
view controller,
depending on your application,
and set the content URL
of that movie player controller.
This is the usual video content
that you would have been
playing before you started
integrating iAd.
After we've done that, instead
of calling the play method
on the movie player controller,
iAd has this new category
method called playPrerollAdWith
CompletionHandler,
which allows you
to provide a completion
block that gets called
after the ad finishes, or if
there was no other ad available
at the time of requesting
a pre-roll ad.
Once you've called this API,
you can immediately add,
so inside that handler, once
the playback has finished,
or if there wasn't a
pre-roll available,
that's your opportunity
to call the play API
and play your original
video content.
Once you've called
this Play Pre-Roll Ad
with Completion Handler API,
you can then add the movie
player controllers view
to your view hierarchy,
or you can present the
movie player view controller
in your application.
If you've got an app that has
a scenario where you would
like to conditionally play
pre-roll for some users
and not others, or maybe you've
got some time based logic as to
when you want to show pre-roll
ads, you can do that too.
All you need to do is
call the play API instead
of calling the Play Pre-Roll
Ad with Completion Handler API.
And you can come up with your
own logic for when you do
and you don't, display
pre-roll ads,
and which situations are
optimal for your app.
Much like interstitial ads,
you also need to prepare early.
You need to tell
the ad framework
that it should start
sending requests as soon
as the application launches,
so that the first time
that a user taps on a video,
a pre-roll ad is more
likely to be available.
It's all about not missing
those early impressions.
So similarly to the
UI view controller,
preparing [inaudible]
ads called,
we now swap that with an MP
movie player controller prepare
pre-roll ads [inaudible].
And this will do the
same effective thing.
It's sending off
ad requests as soon
as your application
becomes available.
So there are a couple of gotchas
with the movie player
controller API.
Those of you that are already
using MP movie player controller
will need to keep in
mind that you may need
to adjust your application
to accommodate pre-roll ads.
The first thing that you
need to make sure of is
that if you're ever explicitly
playing your MP movie player
controller, you need to make
sure that that doesn't happen
until the completion
handler is pulled.
This is because it's the main
content starts playing while the
pre-roll is playing,
we'll immediately skip
to the main content.
So bear that in mind.
There's two slightly indirect
times that this can happen.
Many people will observe
these two notifications
on MP movie player controller,
when the video becomes available
for playback, and also
when the first frame
of the video is available
for display.
A lot of developers use
these and rightly so,
for playing back the media
content, but you need
to be aware that if you
call play in response
to these notifications, you
may skip the pre-roll adds,
so make sure that you don't
handle these notifications
until after the callback
handler is called, and likewise
if your customizing the UI
of the MP movie player
controller, which is supported.
You also need to hold off on
inserting any custom views
into the view controller's
view until after
that completion handler
is called
because you don't want your
views colliding with any
of the pre-roll content.
And let's bring David
up for a demo of that.
>>David: To start off with
to demonstrate pre-roll adds,
we're going to start with this
very simple collection view
application on the phone.
Just has one view controller
that's a collection of views,
and hold a set of thumbnails for
videos, and the user can tap one
of those thumbnails
to go into the video.
That's great.
We can go ahead and see
what that looks like.
We have a few short videos here.
We can tap one of them,
and the video plays.
What we want to do is instead
of just having the
video play immediately,
we want to put a pre-roll
in front of that video
so we can monetize
our application.
So let's take a look
at what that takes.
So we're going to
pull up Xcode again.
The first thing we need to do,
as we did in the previous
two demos, is to go ahead
and make sure we link
against the iAd framework.
We'll go ahead and
click on our project,
make sure the right target
is selected, build phases,
and link against
the iAd framework.
Once we've done that, just
as with the interstitials,
it's important to tell iAd early
in the application's lifecycle
that you want pre-roll ads.
This allows it to go ahead
and make requests early,
so that a pre-roll is available
when the user takes an
action that should show one.
So to do that, we're
going to again go
to our app delegate application
didFinishLaunchingWithOptions.
We're going to go ahead
and import the iAd header
and the media player header.
This gives us access to both the
MP movie player controller class
and the prepared pre-roll ads
category that iAd adds to that.
So inside
didFinishLaunchingWithOptions,
we're just going to call MP
movie player controller prepare
pre-roll adds, and that
kicks off the ad requests
so that we can have a pre-roll
ready when the user taps
on one of our thumbnails.
Speaking of that, we next need
to take care of actually doing
that when the user taps
on one of the thumbnails.
So to do that, we're going
to go to our view controller.
We're going to go back up to
the top first, and we're going
to import the iAd
header here as well.
We've already imported
the media player framework
since we're playing the videos.
And then we're going to go down
to the bottom and we're going
to go
to our collectionViewdidSelect
ItemAtIndexPath.
This is where we handled that
tap and begin playing the movie.
All we're doing at the moment is
instantiating an MP movie player
view controller and
setting the content URL,
and then presenting it.
The only change we need to
make here is to insert a call
to play pre-roll ad
with completion handler.
A note that we're calling MPV
controller movie player play
inside the completion handler.
So once the pre-roll has
finished or has failed to play,
we'll go ahead and
play our content.
Once we've done that, we can
go ahead and run this again.
We've launched application.
You see we've changed
almost nothing here.
We still got our
collection of videos.
And this time when the user
taps on one of these videos,
if an ad is available, a
pre-roll should play before it.
And here we go.
We've got these are tapped,
we've got the ad coming up,
the ad is playing, a few seconds
later, the user will be able
to either watch this ad to
completion or skip through.
And when that finishes,
the video immediately
begins playing.
And that's all it takes
to integrate pre-rolls
into your application.
With that, I'll bring
Nathan back up.
>> Nathan de Vries:
So as you can see,
if you've already got a
movie player application,
it's very easy to port it
across the playing pre-roll ads.
If you don't, then
it's very easy
to add these experiences
to your app.
So wrapping up a little bit,
we have these brand new
pre-roll ads available in iOS 7.
Some great new opportunities
for video apps
to produce more revenue
from their application
with pre-roll ads.
We have those medium rectangle
ads that are supported
on the iPad that can
be positioned in-line
with your content for a
more integrated experience.
We have new interstitial
support for iPhone,
which is new in iOS 7.
They're also supported on iPad.
And lastly we have these new
banner controller API's similar
to the interstitial
API's that allow you
to simply toggle a switch on
your view controllers to opt
in to advertising for
those content views.
And lastly, we spoke
a little bit
about optimizing your ad
performance, so when you go away
and you're thinking about
integrating these advertisements
into your application,
think back to these tips
for optimizing ad performance,
placing ads smartly,
looking at specific
regions and locales
for the way you might want
to optimize your marketing,
and lastly, make sure that
it all starts with the app.
Really focus on pleasing
your customers
and you'll generate far more
revenue from your applications.
Thank you.
For more information
about these slides
and iAd-related questions, you
should speak to our director
of technology evangelism,
John, or you should jump
onto the forums and
ask questions there.
We have a whole bunch of
us that answer questions.
To develop documentation
as I mentioned is part
of the developed benefits.
Is incredibly thorough.
So there's the iAd Sample Suite
that you want to check out,
and also the new
develop a documentation
for these new API's that
we're launching this release.
There's some related sessions if
you're interested in promotion
of your application, as
well as making revenue
from your application.
You should check out the videos
of the iAd workbench session.
And if you're interested
in content creation
for advertising, then there's
also two sessions related
to producing the ads themselves.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]