[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
>> Thank you.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
I'm really glad you like that.
Those words mean a great
deal to us, and you'll see
that reflected throughout
the show today.
Welcome to the Worldwide
Developers Conference.
You're going to have
incredible week.
This is our 24th WWDC.
It's the longest running
developer conference
that we're aware of.
It's truly worldwide.
We have attendees this
morning for over 60 countries
and two-thirds of the people
in the audience today are
here for the first time.
[ Applause ]
No hazing from the
upperclassman.
We've got a great week planned
for you with over 100 sessions
and over 120 hands-on labs so
you can bring in your code,
get some help tuning
it or get just
about any question answered.
We also have over 1,000
engineers here this week,
so grab them, make use of
them, they're here to help.
But don't ask them
about future roadmaps.
Now, the Developer Program
is incredibly vibrant.
We have over six million
registered developers with one
and a half million of those
added in the last year alone.
Demand for this show
has never been greater.
We sold out in just
over a minute.
[ Applause ]
I'm really sorry we couldn't
accommodate everyone.
This is the biggest
venue that we can get.
But we are posting
sessions online everyday
so that developers can
follow us remotely.
I'd like to get started
this morning
with the few updates
beginning with Apple retail.
Of course, our retail stores
are the best place to discover
and explore our products,
and over a million people
per day did that last year.
It's phenomenal.
Our stores are filled with
our colleagues who work
at our stores because
they're passionate
about how Apple technology
can enrich people's lives.
Our stores had become
integral parts
of the communities
that they serve.
Tens of thousands of school kids
pick their local Apple Store
as the destination for
their annual field trip.
And millions of customers
come to our stores
for personal training so that
they can learn to get the most
out of their Apple products.
We now have 407 stores
around the world.
We're operating in 14 countries.
And we've recently opened this
beautiful store in Berlin.
It is really awesome.
It's in a 100 year old building.
It was originally one of the
first theaters in Berlin.
We've painstakingly honored
the history of the building
by restoring the facade
and the original theater,
and added some classic
Apple touches along the way.
The theater is integral to
the building but separate
from the store, and we'll be
hosting many events throughout
the year for the communities
from music to films and more.
We had our signature
crowds at the opening.
And we were so excited about
this opening, we made a video
and I'd like to run it
for you this morning.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
That's Berlin.
It's a fantastic store
in a great location.
Only Apple could do this.
Now we also have some
pretty great digital stores.
And I know this is
incredibly important to those
of you in the audience.
The App Store celebrates
its 5th birthday next month.
Nothing like the App
Store existed before
and it has fundamentally
changed the world.
Customers love the
buying experience
and they love your
incredible apps.
And they've now downloaded
50 billion apps.
This is phenomenal.
That's a lot of zeros and
a truly staggering number
for less than five years.
Thanks to you, we now have
900,000 apps in the store
and the catalog is very active,
90 percent of those are
downloaded each month.
We have 375,000 apps that
have been designed for iPad
to take advantage of the
full beautiful canvas
that still compares
to just a few hundred
from those other guys.
And we have 575 million
accounts.
These are-- most of these
accounts have credit cards
and one-click buying
so it's simple
and elegant to buy your apps.
We had more accounts with
credit cards than any store
on the internet that
we're aware of.
Now, we are incredibly proud
this morning to announce
that we have now paid
developers 10 billion dollars.
[ Applause ]
And the momentum is incredible.
We paid out five billion of
that just in the last year.
Now to put that in context,
that's three times more
than all other platforms
combined.
[ Applause ]
One of the things we love
about the App Store is
that it levels the playing field
between large developers
and small developers.
Ron Conway said it very nicely.
"The App Store and the
iOS ecosystem give budding
developers with great ideas
the best chance for success."
This morning, I'd like
to introduce you to Anki.
Anki is using the iOS platform
to create an entirely new
category of experiences.
They are launching their company
for the first time
on stage today.
They are using iOS devices
and the iOS platform
to bring artificial intelligence
and robotics into
our daily lives.
I'd like to introduce Boris
Hoffman, CEO and co-founder
of Anki, to tell us
about his company
and their very first
new product.
Boris.
[ Applause ]
>> We stared Anki while
working on our PhDs in Robotics
at Carnegie Mellon University.
We worked on everything
from machine learning
to walking robots to
autonomous vehicles.
With the help of iOS devices,
we are bringing these robotics
and artificial intelligence
technologies out of the lab
and into people's lives.
And we're starting
by reinventing the
way people played.
Today, after over half a
decade of working on Anki,
we are so excited
to give you a peek
at our first product,
Anki Drive.
[ Pause ]
[Background Music] Assisting me
today is Brad Newman [inaudible]
engineer at Anki.
Now, we're going to
start by sharing some
of the technology
under the hood.
As we have these cars go
through a few formations,
realize that each of them is
completely driving themselves
and our app is coordinating
the entire experience
over Bluetooth Low Energy.
The cars can control their speed
and they steer on the track
by doing the same computations
your brain does when you drive.
They sense where they're
located and they react
to their surroundings
all in real time.
This red car, he's
our hero, Aidan.
We designed him and
all the other cars
to be incredibly smart.
Five hundred times per
second, they're running logic
to sense a track, their position
on it, adjusting their steering
and speed and communicating
back and forth
with our AI engine
on that iPhone.
I'll let Aidan join his friends
and tell him to hit the gas.
Watch this.
There we go.
All right.
So, as Aiden weaves
through the pack,
our app knows everything
that's happening in real time.
It's analyzing thousands
of potential actions
every single second.
And not just for Aiden
but for every single car.
We are using iOS devices
not just as remote controls
but as the brains behind an
immersive real world experience.
And that is what lets this
bring these cars to life.
Now let's do something
interesting here.
Brad. He's going to
tell these other cars
to try to block Aiden.
And just to be clear, none
of this is choreographed.
All we're doing is defining
a new objective for each car
and they'd figure out the rest.
Here, Aiden, he's using the
exact same logic he was using
before, sensing where he is
and reacting to the other cars
as he looks for an opening.
Expect now, these other guys are
on a mission to try
to block him.
Luckily--
[ Applause ]
Luckily, Aiden is equipped
to handle any situation.
>> Weapons enabled.
[ Laughter & Gunfire ]
>> This is a video--
[ Applause ]
This is a video game
in the real world.
We can customize
everything in software
from the characteristics
of the vehicles
to the weapons that
they can use.
We are taking all of the things
that we love about video games
and programming them
on to physical characters
you can actually touch.
With Anki Drive, we
use this technology
to take gaming to
a whole new level.
And the real fun starts
when you take control
of these cars yourselves.
With your iPhone or
iPod Touch, you can play
against your friends
or you can challenge--
take your chances
against the AI.
We are brining video
games to life
on the floor of your
living room.
Keep your eyes out for Anki
Drive coming to Apple Stores
and Apple Online this fall.
And we just pushed the
Anki Drive app today
so you can download it
and get a deeper look.
We are a robotics and
artificial intelligence company
and what you see here
is only the beginning.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks a lot.
>> Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> That's incredibly fun.
I think these guys are going
to be super successful.
I think it's a great example
of the power of the combination
of your incredible apps and the
iOS devices in the ecosystem.
I'd love to show you a lot more
today but we don't have time.
But I'd like to thank--
on behalf of Apple,
I'd like to thank all
of the developers here
for making such incredible apps.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
Next, I'd like to
talk about the Mac.
The Mac install base now is
incredibly strong at 72 million.
This is double what it
was just five years ago.
We announced the new iMac at
the end of last year and it went
on to become the number
one desktop in the US.
And the MacBook has
continued to define the future
of the notebook and is the
number one notebook in the US.
In fact, the Mac business
has outpaced the PC business
for several years now.
And if you look at
the last five years,
the average annual growth
rate isn't even close.
And if you look at the total
growth over that period of time,
the Mac is at a 100 percent
versus the PC a paltry,
18 percent.
[ Applause ]
Now for us, it's never
been about making the most.
We care much more that
the Mac is number one
in customer sat and quality.
And you don't just have
to take my word for it.
All of these guys agree.
Now, we have lots of innovation
for the Mac last year and one
of those was announced
here with Mountain Lion.
Mountain Lion of course is
our latest release of OS X.
We shipped 28 million copies
since we announced it making
it the best selling release
of all time.
And what's even more
impressive is that 35 percent
of our users are using the
latest version of using--
are using Mountain Lion.
Now, that compares to
Windows 8 which is kind
of struggling to get to five.
We're making the best
Macs we've ever made
but we're not standing still.
We've got lots of
innovation left.
And today, we want
to talk to you
about what we're
doing with OS X.
To do that, I'd like to invite
Craig Federighi up to the stage.
Craig.
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning.
You guys are too kind.
Good morning, let's
talk about OS X.
Our latest release,
Mountain Lion, is the ninth
of our big cat-named releases
in just over a decade.
As we turn our attention
now toward the 10th,
we've hit a real issue.
We do not want to be the
first software in history
to be delayed due to a
dwindling supply of cats.
Now, fortunately, we do have
a creative group at Apple
and we can think out of the box.
And so, we thought, may be
we could take this lion thing
in a different direction.
So, I'm proud to present
to you today OS X Sea Lion.
What do you think?
[ Applause ]
OK, may be not.
That could be a bit
of a dead-end, so.
In fact, we're really excited
about the future of the Mac
and we want a set of names
that are going to carry us
for at least the next 10 years.
And, you know, the answer really
was really obviously to us.
It's those places that
inspire us here in California,
in the place where OS X
is designed and built.
[ Applause ]
So for our first
California-themed release,
it went just outside our
backyard, just off the coast,
to a place with some
of the biggest waves
and most extreme surfing in all
of North America,
OS X Mavericks.
[ Applause ]
Now, Mavericks is a release
with deep technology focused
on extending battery life
and providing responsiveness.
It has great new apps and
enhancements for every Mac user,
and some features that
we think are going
to really appeal
to our power users.
And I want to talk
about just three
of them right now
starting with Finder Tabs.
[ Applause ]
Sounds like you guys you know
how this is going to work.
So, you of course can
work in the Finder
with multiple windows.
It's a very powerful tool.
But now you can draw all those
windows together in tabs.
And each tab can have its own
location, its own view mode.
It's a really powerful tool.
You can actually drag
contents and hover across tabs.
And of course, now that we
have Tabs in the Finder,
it's also a great app
to take full screen.
Next, Tagging.
>> Yes.
That guy. We're bringing
tagging to the Mac.
So now, when you
save a document,
in addition to providing
its location
and name, you can tag it.
And when you do, it will appear
right in the Finder sidebar.
And in fact, you can tag
things wherever they are,
whether they're in iCloud
or on a local file share,
and all those will be brought
together and appear in Finder.
And, tags are great for really
powerful search as well.
Next-- yeah.
Next, Multiple Displays.
Really, all right.
The Mac-- of course, we're not
giving you all the free multiple
display here.
This is software.
So, with multiple
displays in the Mac,
it's always been a powerful
way to spread out your work.
But now, in Mavericks,
you can get at your menus
across multiple displays.
You can summon your DOC
And when you take a window
full screen on one display,
it doesn't mess with your
desktop on the other display.
[ Applause ]
And I really love this.
When you pan your spaces,
you can do it independently
on each of your displays.
[ Applause ]
Finally, if you have an
AirPlay-connected HDTV,
it acts as a full power
separate display as well and I'd
like to show all of
these to you now.
[ Applause ]
All right, let's take our
first look here at Mavericks
and we're going to
start with the Finder.
So, here's Finder environment,
I got a lot going on,
a lot of windows, a lot
of different locations.
I'm going to go up
here to the Window Menu
and let's merge all my windows.
Just like that, they
hop into a set of tabs.
Now, of course, these tabs
at different locations,
different view settings for
each to those locations.
Creating a tab is
just as you'd expect.
Just click Plus.
I can select another location
like AirDrop, may be another
for this Work File Share.
I'm going right here.
And now that I have multiple
tabs, it's a really great way
to actually work
and copy documents.
If I want to copy this field
report, I can just hover
over the AirDrop tab, drop it
just like that, really nice.
And, of course, I can now
take Finder full screen.
Next, let's take
a look at tagging.
This is really cool.
So as I go to save a document,
you know as I can give it a name
like, let's say, Project Plan.
And in addition to its
location, in this case,
I'm going to save it in
iCloud, I can also give it a tag
from any of the tags
I've made up.
So I'm going to call
this document Important.
Looks pretty important to me.
And we'll go here into
the Finder and you see
in the Finder sidebar,
I have an Important tag
and I see all these documents.
They're from different
locations,
different applications, all
drawn together in sidebar.
We have other tags.
I've given things for things
that are draft and in review.
Now, of course with tags,
I can assign multiple
tags to the same document.
That's part of the
power of tags.
So I go here and I'm going to
say this one is also in review.
And you notice, as I sign
that tag, it now appears
in that location as well.
And if I want to assign a
totally new tag, I want to make
up a tag on the fly, you
can just type it right here.
This is a website
project I'm working on.
It's says Create
New Tag Website.
And just like that,
I've created a new tag
and you can see it right
here in the Finder.
I can give that tag
a color of course.
And now that I have that
tag, I can also assign tags
by just dragging things in
to the Tagger and the Finder.
So different assets from my
website, just drag them in
and they're tagged like that.
And tags are great
for searching.
So if I start typing,
let's say, Important,
it can find all documents
that are important.
Let's go to All My Files,
we'll find all documents,
they're both important
and that are in review.
Just like that, I found exactly
what I'm looking for with tags.
[ Applause ]
Next, let's take a look
at Multiple Displays.
I'm going to open up some
other kind of windows
that I'm often working with.
We'll open iPhoto here, may
be a keynote presentation.
And I actually have a
second display connected
to this MacBook Pro.
Let's show that up
there on display now.
Of course with multiple
displays,
I can just move windows across
displays like you'd expect.
But now, I can get up at my
Menu bar in the second display.
If I go down to the bottom,
I can summon the
DOC just like that.
If I want to open an app on the
second display, I can just open
that on the DOC here
and here is iTunes.
Take this app full
screen just like that.
And as I swipe spaces,
just right back there.
Just on that display, let's take
a keynote full screen as well.
I'm going to go back to
my first display here.
Let's even take iPhoto
full screen.
So now, I have different
full screen apps
on my different displays.
This is actually really
fantastic way to work.
Go in here into Favorite Travels
and I can now drag assets
across my full screen apps
like that, super cool.
And, Mission Control has
just been super charged
for multiple displays.
So, I'm going to go now
into Mission Control
and we see my different
full screen spaces
and desktops across
applications.
I can drag a window from
one display to another.
I can also go and drag
a full screen app right
across displays, bring
Preview open, and now I have
that full screen on
this display as well.
[ Applause ]
Finally, I actually have
an Apple TV around here.
Let's bring that into place.
So here's my Apple TV.
Now, this is pretty
over the top.
So I can actually go
here into AirPlay.
I'm going to connect
to this Apple TV.
So now, it's a full
power display as well.
You can see I have my
Menu bar and my DOC.
I can go over here
and get my DOC here.
And, I can go into
Mission Control, even,
and I can go get a window
across that other display.
We'll just drag Keynote
over here,
right on to my Apple
TV, and open it up.
There it is, full
displays in Mavericks.
[ Applause ]
Next, I'd like to talk
about some advanced
technologies in Mavericks.
You know, our power users are
increasingly doing their work
on the go.
They want great responsiveness
but they also want
great battery life.
And in Mavericks, we've
introduced a whole host
of technologies to
address that challenge.
Things like Compressed Memory
that make sure you have
memory available very quickly
when apps demand it.
Technologies like App Nap
that actually makes sure
we're directing power only
to those applications
where you're really
benefiting from it.
System-wide Core Animation
Accelerated Scrolling
and OpenGL 4 for super
responsive graphics.
And, a topic I want to go
into in a bit more detail
now, Timer Coalescing.
So you know, when you look at
battery life on your computer,
the real factor that software
has the most influence
over is CPU activity
and its draw on power.
And if you look at what
your system is doing
at any given time, what
you'll see as you look
under the hood is not a smooth
line, but actually hundreds
of interrupts occurring per
second where the system is going
from a power-efficient
sleep state up to a state
of high power use and back down.
And all of those transitions
actually consume a lot of power.
Well in Mavericks, we
intelligently align all
of that work, reducing those
numbers of transitions.
This, in combination with
technologies like App Nap
and other power optimizations,
reduce CPU utilization activity
for these kinds of
scenarios up to 72 percent.
It's pretty awesome.
[ Applause ]
Next, let's talk about
Compressed Memory.
Nothing affects the
performance of your Mac,
the responsiveness more of
a Mac, that's under load
than its ability to provide
free memory to an app.
Now, typically, when you
look at your app runtime,
all your memory is inactive.
In fact, a subset of your
memory is actively being used
and others is memory
we have to keep around
but isn't being used by the app.
Well, now if you open a
document, your system is going
to need to get free memory
and it does that in the past
by writing those inactive
bits of memory out to disk,
and that's a slow process.
Now, with Compressed Memory,
we're able to rapidly compress
the inactive memory making free
space available almost
instantaneously
to the application.
This can have great
effects on responsiveness
of systems under load.
You see, 1.4X kinds
of improvements,
even on fast SSD
systems for activities
like opening new documents
or reactivate an application,
and up to 1.5X improvement for
waking a system from standby,
these are just two of
many improvements to power
and performance in Mavericks.
Next, let's talk about Safari.
In the last decade of life,
Safari is focused not just
on providing the easiest to use
and most elegant
browsing experience,
but also the most innovative.
These are the kinds
of innovations
that Safari has brought,
private browsing,
blocking of third party
cookies for privacy,
making the web easier to read
with features like Reading List,
and the HTML5 audio and
video tag, all Safari-firsts.
And the engine in
Safari, WebKit,
is used by over 1.5
billion devices.
Well in Mountain Lion, we're
making Safari even better.
We have a great clean new
homepage with top sites.
From there, you can get at great
sidebar where you have access
to all of your bookmarks
and you can browse right
from your bookmarks.
And in that sidebar, we
also have Reading List
where now you can
continuously scroll
through your articles moving
from article to article
without ever having to click.
And a great new feature called
Shared Links where you see all
of the links shared by
people you're following
on Twitter and LinkedIn.
You can browse them right here.
Now in addition to these
end-user improvements,
there's also a lot going on
under the hood, big improvements
to JavaScript, a full
process-per-tab architecture,
and memory efficiency
improvements
with the shared memory resource
cache, and a whole bunch
of big power savings as well.
When you look at the effects
of these changes,
it's pretty profound.
If you take a synthetic
benchmark like SunSpider,
you see how Safari fairs
against the competition.
But, you know, researchers
have started to look
at more real world JavaScript
by sampling the JavaScript
that actually occurs on sites
like the Google homepage,
Facebook, Amazon.com.
And when you look at Safari's
performance on a benchmark
like that, JSBench, the
results are really incredible.
[ Applause ]
Safari is also awesome when
it comes now to memory usage,
using way less memory
than the other browsers
which means more memory for
you to browse with more tabs
and do more on your system.
And when it comes to energy
use, it's not even closed.
Safari uses way less
energy than Chrome.
And when you compare to
Firefox, it's just kind of sad.
So that's Safari.
I'd love to give
you a demo of some
of our advanced technologies
in Safari right now.
So, let's start with
responsiveness
and I'm going to
go now into mail.
And so here, we have a mailbox
with about 100,000 messages
in your inbox and I just want
to show you how you scroll now
with that accelerated scrolling.
Perfectly smooth,
incredibly fast,
almost 60 frames a
second whenever you do it,
it's just epic.
And when you look
here at scrolling
through a conversation,
this is a conversation
with 26 messages in it.
Again, just super glassy
smooth, super fast,
it's really, really nice.
Let's take a look
at that in Safari.
In Safari, we've
improved scrolling
for more popular websites and
actually optimized heavily
for retina displays so now, it's
just super fast, super smooth.
Now, let's take a look at power.
Yeah, there's a fan of
smooth scrolling right there
in the front.
I'm a fan of smooth
scrolling as well.
So let's take a look at power
use, so you have a power meter
up here that's showing
CPU activity in Safari
and you notice right
now, it's quite low
because we're not
doing anything.
But let's go into a website
that's going to use a lot
of power and you notice
the power meter shoot right
up because we're doing a lot of
animation here using all the CPU
and that's OK, that's
what the CPUs for,
it's doing something
cool for me right here.
But very often, you'll have
something like this happening
in an add off in the corner,
you've covered this window up
and yet, it's still
draining your battery life,
you don't even realized it.
Well now, with this technology
we call AppNap, we keep track
of what's going on and what
things you actually to see
to decide where to direct power.
So watch what happens when I
bring up this iTunes window
over the Safari window,
the power drops right down
and that's extending
your battery life.
But of course, that
thing is still running,
it's still available to me so if
I pull it aside, there it goes,
you can see everything
happening right now.
The power goes up, cover back
up, power goes right back down,
it's really going to
help your battery life.
Next, let's take a look at
the new Safari top sites.
Really clean, really nice.
We'll bring out the new sidebar.
You see I have all
my bookmarks here.
I have my bookmark
folders as well.
If I want to bring a side
over for my bookmarks
in the top sites, I can
just drag it out like this.
It's really nice.
I can open it up, animates in.
From the side bar, we also have
access to our shared links.
You see sites that I'm following
here on Twitter and LinkedIn
and click on a site-- a
link that's been shared.
It loads it up, I can
even retweet it right here
if I-- if I wish.
And we now have one-click
bookmarking
so I'll just click this plus
and it's going to hop right
in to my Reading
List right there.
Let's go take a look
at my Reading List.
See all the articles I've
added here to my Reading List?
I want you to watch how
scrolling works because now,
when I scroll and I'm
reading through one article,
I read this, this is great,
I'm really enjoying it.
Get to the bottom,
there's the next article.
I can just scroll right
through to the next article just
like that.
Awesome. We also have a
beautiful new look for Reader.
Here is Reader and I'm
going to bring up my--
I can actually close
up my sidebar here.
And now, as I scroll reading
and I just want to read
from one article to the
next, it's just like that.
Super clean and super nice and
that's Safari in Mavericks.
I think you're going to like it.
[ Applause ]
So, we have some
more improvements
that I think are going to really
help you with your browsing
and one of them is
iCloud Keychain, yeah.
You know, to really
be secure these days,
you want to have a different
complex password for every site
where you have a log in
but this inevitably brings
up the question,
"what's my password?"
and these solutions
are not recommended.
There is a better way.
With iCloud Keychain, we can
remember your website logins,
your credit card numbers,
even your Wi-Fi networks
and they're always encrypted,
synced across all of your system
so they are always
available to you.
Now, when you go to
sign up for a website,
you can of course enter your own
password and we'll remember it
but as well, Safari can auto
suggest a password for you.
You don't have to remember that
but it'll enter it in for you
and then sync it across
all of your systems
and login for you from then on.
[ Applause ]
iCloud Keychain is great
for your shopping as well.
When you come to a credit card
field, you can suggest any
of your remembered
credit cards, select one
and it'll just enter it in
for you just like that along
with your expiration date.
But you have to remember
your own security code,
that's what makes
it secure after all
and that's iCloud Keychain.
[ Applause ]
Next, some improvements
to Notifications.
So now, with Notifications on
the Mac, if you're a Californian
like me, you'll often get
this kind of notification,
"Hey want to go surf
these 30 foot waves?"
And you response, surely is
to mouse over the notification
and immediately right there,
reply, "Yeah sure I'm going
to surf that 30 foot wave."
You can reply right inside the
Notification and you can do this
for things like email
and quickly delete email
you might not want to deal
with without even
having to go to Mail.
If you get a FaceTime call,
you can response saying,
"Hey I'm going to call
you later," or remind
without having to
pick up the call.
It's really handy.
We also handle a new
kind of notification.
So if you have an app today
that sends push notifications
to iOS devices, well
now, you can sign
up to receive those push
notifications on your Mac
as well whether Safari
is running or not.
So, things like your
Fantasy Football alert,
maybe Breaking News, news
about that buy on eBay.
And now, in Mavericks when
your machine is sleeping,
when you wake it up, it
will tell you everything
that you missed while you're
away right on the lock screen.
And it will now update apps
for you right in the background
so you don't have
to do it yourself.
[ Applause ]
So that's Notifications.
Next up, Calendar,
let's take a look.
[ Applause ]
Absolutely no virtual cows
were harmed in the making
of this user interface.
We're going to be
adding that one
to our environmental
checklist, trust us.
So, in addition to that, you
have your Facebook events right
on your Calendar if you wish
and we have a great new
inspector that's even aware
of things like location,
travel time and weather.
And that's the Calendar.
[ Applause ]
Next, Maps.
The Maps team has been making
great improvements to the data
and Maps and Mac users
are going to benefit
because we have this
fantastic new Maps app.
Of course, with your street
maps, you have your 3D,
beautiful flyover
data, search for points
of interest, great info cards.
You can get turn by turn
directions and my favorite part,
when I have a route that
I've set up on my Mac
and now it's time to go, you
can just click right up here
and send it right to my iPhone
where it will appear
right on my lock screen.
[ Applause ]
And when I unlock my
phone, it takes me straight
in the navigation, super cool.
We're also providing
a developer SDK
so you can add mapping
functionality
to your apps as well.
So that's Maps.
Finally, we're bringing
iBooks to the Mac.
So now, you have access
to the full library
of 1.8 million books
in the iBook Store.
Your full library from your
iOS devices is available
on your Mac as well.
It's a great environment
for reading.
It's also a great
environment for taking notes
and it supports iBooks
Textbooks, they're beautiful
and they're interactive,
I love to give you a demo
on all of this right now.
[ Applause ]
So, let's start in Maps.
So here we are in
Paris, you can just zoom
in a place in Paris there.
You can zoom right in,
you see it's just so fast
and fluid bringing in
points of location.
I can pan around the map
to find a nice location,
maybe the Eiffel
Tower right here.
Let's go in to look
at that flyover data.
As we can see the Eiffel Tower,
we can go in to tilt it over,
that's the Eiffel
Tower right there.
The flyover data is just
beautiful and of course,
I can even rotate around Paris.
Look, you can even see through
the Eiffel Tower as it rotates
into the area of the city below.
The data is just gorgeous,
the new flyover data.
It's really amazing on
your big Mac display.
Of course, we support great
search for points of interest
so if I want to go
to lunch, maybe at --
I'm told this is Guy Savoy.
We'll go to Guy Savoy, they
have this great info cards
with reviews, photos.
I can add a site to my
Bookmarks just like this
and it's now synced
across all my devices
so this location is available
to me, of course, on my phone.
And because this is a
Mac, I can tear this off
so if I'm planning a trip,
I can set aside some
things of interest.
I can, of course,
get directions.
Let's do that here, directions
from the Eiffel Tower.
And when I'm ready to
go, I can send it right
to my phone like this.
And that's Maps.
[ Applause ]
Next, let's take a look
at the new Calendar.
It has continuous scrolling and
what's really amazing is even
without the stitching,
the Window still sticks
right there on the screen.
It doesn't fall off
without the stitching.
I don't know how we did it.
It's engineering.
It's really great for
creating events so if I go
and create an event like
this, let's say I'm going
to have lunch and I'm going to
type in what I want for lunch,
I'm going to say I want pizza.
And you notice, it suggests
all sorts of locations nearby
so I'm going to select
Tony's Pizza
and you notice I get a map.
I even get projected weather
for that location so I know
if I need to bring a jacket.
Now, I can select here
and actually ask it
to tell me what the
travel time is expected
from my last location
so I can decide
if I want to drive or walk.
I'm going to say I want to walk
and it actually adds the travel
time right to my Calendar
so I know not to
schedule anything there.
[ Applause ]
And I don't have to remember
because I can ask to be notified
when I need to leave and
I'll get a notification both
in my Mac and on my phone
as well so that is Maps.
[ Applause ]
Finally, let's take
a look at iBooks.
So, I have all my books here,
of course, I can browse my--
the collections I've arranged.
We have access to the Store
with all of its content.
Books of course ultimately about
reading so you can get in here
and read, move easily
between the pages.
You have access to all
the controls you'd expect.
Your Bookmark, search,
can adjust your type
and font and type size.
Go into a nice night mode that's
relaxing for the eyes but,
of course, I really love these
interactive iBooks Textbooks.
Let's open one of those up now.
So, I can scroll through
the pages in my book,
see all of this nice
interactives and videos.
I can pinch right into a
graphical table of contents,
scroll through the
pages of this chapter.
I can select another chapter,
scroll through just like this
on these fantastic interactives.
So, if I want to understand the
way the cellular structure works
for instance on this leaf,
I can just drill right in
and see all the way
through this.
It's just incredible, a
really great way to learn.
[ Applause ]
It's also a great
environment for taking notes,
just select some text, add
a note, ask the teacher
about this, take
a note like that.
Because it's a Mac, of
course, I can just stretch out
and get the sidebar where
I can see all my notes
in the sidebar just really
convenient just like this.
We also have a great
view with the Sidebar
to show all your notes.
You can use them to
navigate your book.
When it comes time to study,
you have this great study cards,
you can just flip through
them, use all your notes
to study, just like that.
[ Applause ]
And that is iBooks in Mavericks.
So, Mavericks continues making
your digital life follow you
easily from device to device.
So now, your books are available
on whatever device you choose
to read them on and it remembers
what page you're reading.
We now remember your password
so they're available to you
across all your devices,
even now,
your bookmark location
and travel routes.
Mavericks is a fantastic
release,
it's full of some great features
for power users, deep technology
to extend your battery life and
improve system responsiveness
and some great features
for everyone.
For those of you developers,
we have a preview
available for you today.
[ Applause ]
And for everyone else
from the general public,
you'll be getting the
final release this fall.
So that is Mavericks.
Next, I'm going to hand
it over to Phil Schiller
to tell you a little
bit more about the Mac.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Well, good morning everyone.
I'd like to talk to you
about the MacBook Air.
The MacBook Air answer
the question in this age
of the iPad, what is the
future of the notebook?
The MacBook Air really
gave us a direction
of where the notebook can go,
and it's really become
everyone's ultimate
everyday notebook.
And that's why we're really
pleased to tell you today
that we've updated an entirely
new line of MacBook Air.
And these new MacBook Airs
deliver the most important
feature we always want
in a portable device,
all day battery life.
Yes.
[ Applause ]
And the MacBook Air is based
on a new 4th Generation
Intel Core Processor,
otherwise known as Haswell ULT.
And if you don't know Haswell
ULT, it's a great processor
for incredible power savings.
There's more energy-efficient
CPUs,
there's twice the
graphics execution units
so we can run them actually
to slower clock speed
to save energy and still
deliver the 40 percent faster
graphics performance.
And the Apple engineers
have worked together
with the Intel engineers on
some great low power state
so we can do things
like wake in one second
or standby for up to 30 days.
But the biggest benefit
is battery life
so here is the current
generation MacBook Air,
11 inch and 13 inch.
The 11 inch is now going to go
from 5 hours of battery life
up to an incredible 9
hours of battery life.
And if you like that,
the 13 inch goes from 7
to 12 hours of battery life.
Yes, true, all day
battery life and it helps
across your entire system.
For example, if you like
watching movies from iTunes,
up to 10 hours, you can watch
almost the entire Trilogy
of Lord of the Rings,
it's amazing.
And of course, MacBook Air
is based entirely on Flash.
Flash is faster, up
to 45 percent faster
than the previous version
and Wi-Fi is faster too,
now 802.11ac Wi-Fi networking.
Now, ac gets you up to
three times the performance
of 802.11n at the same distance.
But the way to get that of
course is you want your MacBook
Air to talk to a Wi-Fi base
station that supports 802.11ac.
So, we're really happy to along
with MacBook Air announce some
new AirPort Base Stations,
entirely new designs, they're
actually a very small base,
just 4 inches square but
extruded 6 and a half inches
to get wider range
from those antennas.
So there's a new AirPort
Extreme that does 802.11ac.
There's also room in
there for a hard drive
so you have a new AirPort
Time Capsule as well
and these are great
base stations.
They're incredibly powerful,
they have a lot of
cool features.
I'll just point out one,
beamforming, it even
sounds cool.
Beamforming can send more energy
directly to an 802.11ac device
to enhance the throughput
and performance.
So, these are great
base stations.
The MacBook Air comes in
11 inch and 13 inches sizes
and the value is even
greater than before.
The 11 inch starts at 999
with 128 gigabytes
that's twice the storage
at the same price as before.
And the 13 inch with
128 gigs starts at 1099,
that's 100 dollars less
expensive than before.
And these new MacBook
Airs start shipping today.
[ Applause ]
As we have for a while
now, we're really proud
that we lead the industry
in the most environmentally
friendly products so we're going
to make sure everyone
knows how important this is
to have Energy Star 5.2,
most products don't.
EPEAT Gold, most on
arsenic-free display glass,
mercury-free displays, BFR-free,
PVC-free, and highly recyclable.
We lead at this and we're
going to continue to.
So, that's the new MacBook Air.
They're faster graphics, longer
battery life, better value,
faster Wi-Fi, incredible
notebooks.
Let me do something different.
We don't usually do this
but you're really an
important audience so we'd
like to give you a sneak peek
of something we're working on.
Would you like that?
>> Yeah.
[ Applause ]
>> Only because you're 6,000
of my most important friends.
[ Applause ]
Video editors, musicians,
photographers,
graphic designers count
on products like Mac Pro
to get their work done and our
most advanced users just want
to get their hands
on the fastest,
most expandable Mac we make.
And the Mac Pro is really
important to delivering on that.
We didn't want to just
make another version
of the same old desktop
idea that everyone has had.
Like with MacBook Air,
our engineering team has spent
quite a bit of time thinking
about the technology available
today and what could be possible
for the future of a Pro desktop.
What would be a new
formed factor, new design,
new capabilities for
another 10 years?
And the engineering
team has come
up with something truly
revolutionary, truly radical
and this product is so cool.
We'll, I'm going to go
a little over the top
and give it a grand introduction
that is unlike any introduction
we've ever had for a product.
So, I am really pleased to
give you our, closest friends,
the first glimpse of the
next generation of Mac Pro.
[ Pause ]
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
Can't innovate anymore, my ass.
This is--
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
This is a machine unlike
anything we've ever made both
the inside and out.
The processor, graphics,
memory storage are all built
around a new unified
thermal core.
That even sounds cool.
Inside is state-of-the-art
technology,
a new generation Intel Xeon
chip, up to 12 core configs,
256-bit-wide floating-point
PCI Express gen 3.
This is double the
CPU performance
of the previous generation.
The fastest memory we've ever
put in our product, ECC memory,
1,866 megahertz DDR3 on a
four-channel controller,
60 gigabyte per second
bandwidth.
That's double the performance
of the previous generation.
Internal storage
is based on flash.
Not any old flash,
new PCIe-based flash.
1.25 gigabytes per second reads
a gigabyte per second writes.
That's two and a
half times faster
than any flash we've ever built.
It's 10 times faster than
any hard drive we've put
in a Mac Pro before.
All expansion is external,
you can add storage arrays,
you can add expansion chassis
over the brand new announced
Thunderbolt 2, it's 20 gigabit
for seconds up to six
Thunderbolt 2 devices per port.
It's backwards compatible with
Thunderbolt 1 and FireWire
and it's double the performance
of the industry's standard
and industry of leading
Thunderbolt 1.
But the place where the team has
probably gone, the most crazy
and done something we've never
done before is in graphics.
This is the first Mac
ever that comes standard
with dual workstation GPUs,
AMD FirePro graphics in it.
You can configure it up to
4,096 screen processors,
528 gigabytes per seconds.
This is two and a half times
the graphics performance
in the last generation.
And for those of
you who use OpenCL
and you all know you should,
this delivers seven teraflops
of compute power to
your applications.
Of course, you want to hook on
the latest third party displays
and this supports 4K displays.
Yes, multiple streams
of 4K displays.
You can have up to
three 4K displays
on the built-in dual
workstation graphics.
The Final Cut Pro team is
hard at work in a version
of Final Cut Pro X that will
support all the performance
and graphics capabilities
of this Machine,
you can be this guy.
It is a Mac unlike
any we've ever made.
It delivers so much more
performance, capabilities
and expansion than
anything we've made
and here it is alongside
the previous generation.
[ Applause ]
The team has packed all
of its capability inside
one eighth the volume
of the previous generation.
The one thing everyone loved
about the old generation Mac
Pro is those handles on the top
so you can move it around
to get access to the I/O.
Well, the entire top of the new
generation Mac Pro is a handle.
Just put your hand in it,
you can spin it around,
get access to the I/O.
It's all organized
beautifully on the back for you.
There is audio, four USB 3,
six FireWire 2 being driven
by three FireWire 2
controllers and you guys
who use this stuff know
what I'm talking about.
It's gigabit Ethernet, HDMI
out and it has a motion sensor
so when you turn
it, it even lights
up to show you where the I/O is.
[ Applause ]
It is a stunning product.
This is without doubt the
future of the Pro desktop.
It is coming later this year.
I did say this is a sneak peek.
It is designed by brilliant
engineers in California
and assembled here in the USA.
[ Applause ]
And for all of you who are dying
to see it put towards places
and what it can do, we have
a special session tomorrow,
lunch time session for
all the developers here,
for our good friends at
Pixar along with developers
from The Foundry are going
to show you some amazing
character animation
in the upcoming movie
"Monsters U" running
on the new generation Mac Pro
and you want to check it out.
And that's the Mac
Pro, back to you, Tim.
[ Applause ]
>> You're going to love
the Mac Pro, it's killer.
Next, I'd like to
talk about iCloud.
We've now passed 300 million
iCloud accounts making iCloud
the fastest growing
Cloud service ever.
Now, by comparison, it
took Facebook five years
to reach this many accounts.
One of the most popular features
of iCloud is iTunes in the Cloud
which makes all of your
purchase content available
on all of your devices.
We now have 300 million users
of this feature and they read
out of their content
35 billion times.
Now, the back-end infrastructure
of iCloud allows us
to provide Cloud services
across many of our products
like Game Center, our
social gaming network now
with over 240 million users.
Sixty of the top 100 games
on the App Store integrate
Game Center support right
in their game.
iCloud is also --
has incredible scale
like sending 800
billion iMessages,
or a mind-boggling 7.4
trillion push notifications.
iCloud allows us to seamlessly
integrate Cloud services
into so many of our products
across Apple in both
OS X and iOS.
Today, we want to share with
you how we're deeply integrating
iCloud into the next
version of iWork.
And to do that, I'd like
to invite Roger Rosner
up to the stage.
Roger.
[ Applause ]
>> Hello. Hi, let me tell
you a little bit about iWork.
iWork is pages, numbers,
and keynote.
And we think it's the best way
to create beautiful documents,
spreadsheets and presentations.
Of course, iWork was born on
the Mac and it has full support
for the awesome feature set
of Mac OS X and Mac hardware.
We also have amazingly powerful
and fully multi-touch versions
of these apps on the
iPad and on the iPhone.
We think our multi-touch
apps are the most powerful
productivity apps ever
created for a mobile device.
And later this year, we're going
to have awesome new releases
of both our Mac and
our iOS suites.
But today, I want to
introduce the newest member
of the iWork family,
introducing iWork for iCloud.
iWork for iCloud lets you
create beautiful documents right
in a browser on a
Mac or on a PC.
And rather than talk about it,
let's just jump right
into a demo.
[ Applause ]
All right, I'm going to fire
up Safari on my Mac here
and go straight to
my iCloud homepage
where you see three new app
icons, and I click on Pages.
And here is all the documents
I've been working on, on my Mac
or my iPad and saved in iCloud.
I can create a new document by
clicking Plus and I have a bunch
of beautiful Apple-designed
templates.
But let's just open a
document we were working on.
And as you can see, it's a
beautiful Pages document,
great fonts, graphics,
images, page layouts.
This is all happening in
a web browser of course.
So I can just click
here and type.
And over here, I have all
the formatting controls
in our new context-sensitive
format panel.
So I'll just select some
text, go up to my Styles,
choose a text style, select
some more text, choose another.
I can click on some images.
And you see, my controls
now show me Image Controls.
I can click on a bunch of
styles, choose that one.
Now, of course, Pages has always
been great at handling graphics.
So, how do I add graphics?
Well, I drag one
in from my desktop,
drop it in there
and drag it around.
[ Applause ]
All right.
Now, we know we live
in a world full
of Microsoft Office documents,
so how do we work with Office?
Well I have a Word document
here, and I'm just going to drag
that in from my desktop and drop
that in the Pages
for iCloud window.
It uploads it.
I open it up.
[ Pause ]
And here I am editing a
Microsoft Word document
in Pages for iCloud.
[ Applause ]
All right, let's take
a look at numbers.
Back to my iCloud homepage,
click the Numbers icon.
Again, a bunch of
beautiful documents.
As you can see, this spreadsheet
has a bunch of different sheets
in it, great charts,
great tables and graphics.
Here on the last
sheet, we have a table
that hasn't been finished.
So I'm just going to click
in a cell, hit Equals.
We get help for the over
250 functions that we have.
But I'll just type SUM,
select this column,
and there you go,
my chart updates.
If I want to fill this
across the rest of the table,
I'll just drag it across,
a real spreadsheet.
Again, this is all
happening in a web browser.
[ Applause ]
All right, let's try Keynote.
I will open this
presentation here.
And it's a real keynote
presentation,
photographs, texts, fonts.
I can rearrange the
slides if I want to.
I can add a new slide.
I'll click the Plus button
down here, choose this layout.
Let's give it a title.
And let's try again imaging.
Move it around, get the
alignment guides we all love
from Keynote.
Double-click to go
into masking mode,
scale up that mask a
little, recenter it.
Let's give it a photo border,
let's make the border
a little thicker.
Let's rotate the image.
This is all happening in a
browser, it's pretty incredible.
[ Applause ]
How about animations?
Let's add a cube animation
here and click play.
[ Pause ]
And there, you see our
beautiful Keynote 3D animations
in a browser window.
[ Applause ]
All right.
I'm sure everyone wants to know
how does this work on Windows.
Well, here it is.
This is a Windows 8 desktop,
I have IE and Chrome here,
I'm just going to
fire up Chrome.
[ Laughter ]
And it's logged in as the
same user I was logged
into on the Mac.
So I'm going to open
that same document.
As you can see, it's the same,
there's the slide we just made.
Let's go in there and make
that mask a little bit tighter
and move it around a little.
And there we go.
I'm editing a Keynote
document on Windows 8.
[ Applause ]
All right.
That is iWork for iCloud.
Now, we know, in a lot of cases,
that the best user
experiences are made
with native app technologies.
But I think you can
see with iWork
for iCloud you can do some
pretty great stuff on the web.
As I mentioned, we
support IE or--
we support Safari
best I should say.
Like all websites, we
run best in Safari.
We also support IE and Chrome.
And now, you have iWork
on all of your devices.
You can create a document
on your Mac, you can edit
on your PC, and you can
present from your iPhone.
We're going to make this
available starting today
as a developer beta.
Just go to iCloud and
we'll expand that beta
to include all users of
iCloud later in the year.
Thank you very much.
Send us your feedback.
[ Applause ]
>> OK. Next, we'd like to
turn our attention to iOS.
[ Applause ]
iOS is the world's most
advanced mobile operating system
and powers the world's
best mobile devices.
iPad, iPhone, and iPod Touch.
We have now sold over
600 million iOS devices.
It's an incredible number.
[Applause]
But, it's extraordinary
and we're proud of it,
but it's not what drives us.
We want to make the best
products that people use more
and love more than
anyone else's.
And I'm really happy
to tell you,
people are using our
products substantially more
than anyone else's.
Let me show you.
This recent study from Experian
showed that iPhone users use
of iPhone 50 percent more than
Android users use their phone.
Now this is incredible
but may be not surprising.
And if you look at mobile web
share, it's not even close.
iOS is two and a
half times Android.
And if you look at iPads
compared to all other tablets,
it's not even comparable.
iPad is over four times more.
Now this shows up in
a variety of ways.
As an example, just like
iOS customers buy more
of your incredible apps,
they evidently also buy a lot
of everything else according
to a recent IBM survey.
Both iPhone and iPad
customers were responsible
for materially more
mobile shopping traffic
than all other Android
devices combined
on the most critical day
of shopping last year.
Now, it probably
doesn't surprise you
if people are using them
more, they love them more.
And this is what is
most important to us.
iPhone was named number one
in customer satisfaction
by J.D. Power.
Not just once, but
nine consecutive times.
The first time this
has ever been done.
[ Applause ]
And iOS satisfaction is
literally off the charts.
Change Wage [phonetic] recently
measured it at 97 percent.
And if you look at those
people that responded
that they're very satisfied
and really look at the detail
which I'm sometimes known to
do, you would see that iOS blows
out everyone else,
20 points better
than our closest competitor
and almost 25 points
better than Android.
[ Applause ]
One of the reasons for this is
that we provide amazing
software updates
that provide users
incredible new features.
And we do this easily
and make them available
to as many users as possible.
Let me show you.
Over 90 percent of iOS users are
using the latest version of iOS.
Now, that's in stark contrast
to the world of Android.
And by the way, this is the
most ideal state of Android.
It only includes us version
of Android which talk
to the Google Play store.
So it doesn't things
like Kindles and Nooks.
But even then, it's
a pretty bleak story.
More than a third of Android
users are using an operating
system that was released
in 2010.
And if you look at the customers
of each operating system
which are using the latest
version, it's not even close.
Now this isn't just
bad for users,
but this version
fragmentation is terrible
for developers as
many of you know.
In fact, if you do the
math, you would find
that iOS 6 is the world's most
popular mobile operating system
and in second place is
a version of Android
which was released in 2010.
Now this is why we get so
excited when we're working
on a new version of
iOS because we know
that we can positively
affect millions of developers
and hundreds of millions
of users.
And that is exactly
what we've been up to.
The team at Apple has been
working incredibly hard
on the latest version of iOS.
And today, it's of great
thrill that I announce iOS 7.
[ Applause ]
iOS 7 is the biggest
change to iOS
since the introduction
of iPhone.
It's packed with
amazing new features
and a stunning new
user interface.
We prepared a video to show you
our thinking behind the design
and I'd like to run
it for you now.
[Applause]
[ Music ]
>> We have always thought of
design as being so much more
than just the way
something looks.
It's the whole thing.
The way something actually works
on so many different levels.
Ultimately, of course,
design defines
so much about experience.
[ Music ]
I think there is a profound and
enduring beauty in simplicity,
in clarity, in efficiency.
True simplicity is
derived from so much more
than just the absence of
clutter and ornamentation.
It's about bringing
order to complexity.
[ Music ]
iOS 7 is a clear
representation of these goals.
It has a whole new
structure that is coherent
and it is applied
across the entire system.
[ Music ]
We've considered
the tiniest details,
like refining the
typography, to much larger ones
like redesigning all the icons,
and developing a grid
system allowed us
to achieve a much more
harmonious relationship
between individual elements.
We've also incorporated a
whole new palette of colors.
[ Music ]
Distinct, functional layers help
establish hierarchy and order.
[ Music ]
And the use of translucency
gives you a sense
of your context.
These planes, combined with
new approaches to animation
and motion, create a sense
of depth and vitality.
[ Music & Applause ]
The iPhone responding to your
movements drives the parallax
to create a whole new
experience of depth.
[ Music ]
In many ways, we tried
to create an interface
that is unobtrusive
and deferential.
One where the design
recedes and in doing
so actually elevates
your content.
Even the simple act of changing
your wallpaper has a very
noticeable effect on the way
your iPhone looks and feels
across the entire system.
[ Music ]
While iOS 7 is completely
new, it was important to us
to make it instantly familiar.
[ Music ]
We wanted to take an experience
to people know very well
and actually add to it
to make it more useful,
to make enjoyable.
To create it, we brought
together a broad range
of expertise from
design to engineering.
With what we've been able to
achieve together, we see iOS 7
as defining an important
new direction,
and in many ways, a beginning.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> You are going to
absolutely love iOS 7.
>> We love you!
[Laughter]
>> This-- thank you.
This major effort, this
major effort is only possible
because of the incredible
collaboration between Johnny
and his amazing design
team and Craig
and his incredible
engineering team.
Without further ado, I'd like
to invite Craig, back up,
to take you through iOS
7, the biggest change
to iOS since the iPhone.
Craig.
[ Applause ]
>> Well, on behalf of all of
the engineers and designers
who worked so hard to
make today a reality,
I'm absolutely thrilled at this
opportunity to show you iOS 7.
Let's take a look.
It's unbelievable.
It's just gorgeous.
From the typography on this
lock screen to the vitality
of the background of an
animation, to the home screen
with these icons, it looks so
great, it just look fantastic.
And, you know, a lot of us have
our own wallpaper, you know,
I mean like pictures
of our family there.
And now that liveliness
actually carries
through to the home screen,
because as you move the device
on your hand it actually
tracks your motion.
And as parallax that-- but you
can see the behind the icons.
It's really incredible
and it carries
over across the system,
this liveliness.
I mean just take a look
at something like weather,
with emotion conveys this
information and where the edge
to edge design just takes
advantage of every pixel
on that retina display.
It's so nice.
It's great for apps you use
everyday, like messages,
your calendar, your
email is gorgeous.
Your friends never
looked more attractive.
And Game Center, we
just completely ran
out of green felt.
[ Applause ]
And wood as well.
This has got to be good
for the environment.
The clocks look great.
And even apps like
Stocks and Compass,
but they just have this look of
precision, a sense of purpose.
The best way to appreciate
iOS 7 is to see it live.
I'd like to give you
a demo right now.
[ Applause ]
So let's take our first
live look at iOS 7.
Here it is.
You can see how the
device actually response
to the motion in my hand.
Just slide out the lock screen.
You see how it slides in.
And I want you now to look away
for a moment while I
type in my password.
OK, you can look again.
OK, don't tell anyone
about that.
All right.
So here we are on the
gorgeous new home screen.
Let's go into Weather.
You see in Weather, it's
a little cloudy today.
I can actually tap here, the
degrees get more information
like humidity and rain,
swipe through some locations,
clear in Sydney, kind
of hot in Phoenix.
Here in a big thunder mountain,
it's looking little rough.
We've got some thunder brewing.
Oh, yeah. [applause] Some heavy
snow here on the North Pole
and tropical storm here
in Gilligan's Island,
I hope they got off that island.
So, and it's no functional
than ever.
If you pinch, you get
this gorgeous overview
of all your cities.
Even with the time, so
it's a world clock as well.
Let's take a look
at the Calendar.
So clean, swipe from
days to day like this,
turn it into landscape,
see your whole week
at a glance, got
a big week ahead.
Zoom out. Scroll easily
through your months,
we even go all the
way out to the year.
Let's take a look at Messages.
You know, so we scroll,
we have this great sort
of playful motion.
The bubbles, spring
up the keyboard,
lets you slide contents
of the keyboard.
You see the layering in
transparency, it gives you
that sense of context.
There's this gesture now from
the left edge of the device,
it's great for using
the device at one hand.
If I want to just go back, I
can just swipe from the edge
of the display, pull back
like that, move in and out.
So clean and natural.
Let's take a look at folders,
and it go here into
my Games folder.
I can have multiple pages,
stored under these
items not folders.
It's awesome.
Take a look at Game Center.
Some of those good
looking friends.
Let's take a look at Mail.
And the type is just so clean
and you drill into a message.
Look at how you get
this full screen edge
to edge photos, it's
really great.
And that gesture from moving in
and out works here
too, of course.
Just move between
messages, just like this.
It's so great.
And if you just slide
across in any item,
you can get at the
Trash and More Options
as well right here in Mail.
Finally, let's take a look
at Notification Center.
Same as always, we can
just swipe out from the top
of the device, comes
down with a nice thud,
you can see all notifications,
just might miss once.
And we've just great
new Today view.
So you can see you friends'
birthdays current look
at the weather, your upcoming
invitations, your calendar,
your stocks, and even a
quickly look at tomorrow.
You know, it's really great
as for the first time ever
Notification Center is now
available from the
lock screen as well.
You don't even have
to unlock your device.
[applause] So that's
a quick look at iOS 7.
It's a comprehensive end-to-end
redesign of the user experience.
Installing iOS 7
on your phone is
like getting an entirely
new phone,
but when you already
know how to use,
when it's so much more beautiful
and functional than ever before.
But iOS 7 is actually
more than that.
It's also a major
feature release as well.
I have 10 features I want
to talk to you about today,
starting with Control Center.
Control Center is
something that's
so simple and yet so essential.
You have those switches
that you just want to get
to really quickly
from wherever you are.
Well, now, with Control Center,
swipe up from that bottom
of the device and
there they are.
[ Applause ]
Turn on Airplane Mode, adjust
your brightness, play a song,
even get at a flashlight,
and available from anywhere,
including your lock screen.
So if you wake up in the middle
of the night and you need
to find something, your
flashlight's right there.
And that's Control Center.
Next, let's talk
about Multitasking.
Now, iOS 7 has always been built
on the industrial strength
foundations of OS X.
It's had intrinsic powerful
multitasking capabilities.
But we had to be careful
about how we'd exposed these
to applications because we want
to preserve great battery life.
Now on iOS 4 we did add
support for select kinds
of applications to
do multitasking.
Things like plain music in the
background or receiving a voice
over IP call, or your
app is in the background.
Well, now, in iOS 7, I'm pleased
to announce that we're going
to have multitasking for all
apps with great battery life.
[ Applause ]
So, how does it work?
Well, imagine you have an app
that you're using
constantly throughout the day,
a social networking app or
something and you're checking
in all of the time, what iOS
7 has noticed is that pattern
of use and is going
to provide that app
with frequent background
activity to stay up to date.
And there's even other app you
used, maybe that you just check
in on in the morning or
breakfast, maybe at night
after work, well iOS
7 notices that too.
And it's going to give that
app background cycles just
in time to-- it's up to
date for when you need it.
Now, in addition to this
intelligence scheduling,
iOS 7 does opportunistic
updates.
The average user wakes their
device dozens of time a day
and those provide
great opportunities
when the system's
already powered
up to update apps
on the background.
It also adapts intelligently
the network conditions.
So if it's in-- you
have good coverage,
it's a great time to fetch.
And it coalesces updates
across multiple applications.
So once you have those
radios powered up,
lets multiple applications
take advantage of it
for their background updates.
And, finally, iOS 7 response to
push notifications as a trigger
to give that application
time in the background.
So when you follow
that notification,
the app will already
be up to date.
[ Applause ]
Now, iOS 7 also has a great
new user interface for moving
between all the things you
have going on on your phone.
Now, you could double click and
move into Notifications Center
and just swipe between
your running applications,
tap and move right in and
that is multitasking in iOS 7.
[ Applause ]
Next, let's talk about Safari.
Safari is the most popular
mobile browser in the world.
And in iOS 7 we're
making it even better.
Has a great new full
screen look,
really focused on your content.
If you pull down
or tap at the top,
you can now get a
smart search field.
From that search field, you can
get it one tap access to all
of your favorites as well
as do search and access URLs
and there's a great new
interface for your tabs.
In addition to all of this,
it has parental controls
and integration with the same
iCloud Keychain you saw earlier
with Mavericks.
I'd like to give you
a demo of Safari now.
Let's take a look.
[ Applause ]
OK, head on in to Safari.
So here we are in Safari.
I'm going to just
zoom in on this page.
I want you to watch as I scroll,
all the controls just recede
and now you have that full
screen for your content.
We've really improved the way
you navigate now in Safari.
I'm just going to tap in here
to link to a detailed story.
I mean you can even zoom
in of course on this page.
And that same gesture you saw
earlier for going back well
of course that works
in Safari as well.
So I just swiped in from
the edge of the display
and I can navigate
back and forth
through my browser
history just like that.
It's such a fantastic
way to browse.
Next, let's look at that
unified search field.
I'm just going to tap
up here at the top.
You see I have one tap
access to all my favorites.
It's really convenient
but I'm going to type
in this case so I'll type DIS.
And you notice, I have
a top URL hit as well
as Google Search suggestions as
well available all right here.
We've really improved
bookmarking as well.
I use this bookmark
control down at the bottom.
I see my bookmark
folders, all my bookmarks.
We also have shared links.
You can see stories posted by
people you follow on Twitter.
And my Reading List.
And, now, just like you
saw on Mavericks on iOS,
you can scroll continuously
from article to article
without coming back to the list.
It's really awesome.
Next, let's take a look at tabs.
I'm going to click here at the
bottom into tabs, unbelievable,
and you're no longer
limited to just eight.
[ Applause ]
And down at the bottom are
also all your iCloud tabs.
You can see what you left open
on your other devices as well.
And tabs, they're
really nice to use.
You can just tap,
sweep into a tab,
back out, back in, back out.
It's just fantastic.
If you want to reorder your
tabs, just tap and hold,
just rearrange them like this.
And if you're done with
the tab, just swipe it off
to the side and it goes away.
And that's the new Safari.
[ Applause ]
Let's take a look now
at Control Center.
So I'm just going to swipe up
from the bottom of my display
and up comes Control Center.
See how these great switches
at the top can turn on and off.
Do Not Disturb, for instance,
access my brightness,
you can even access a
flashlight, really useful
at night, play a song.
[background music] And of
course this is available
to me everywhere so if I'm
in Safari for instance.
Let's bring it up here.
You can turn off that music.
And you notice how its layering
and transparency take the
personality, the environment
where you bring it up.
That's Control Center.
[ Applause ]
Next up, Multitasking.
It's just a great way to get
across all the things
you're doing on your device
so if I just double click
here on my Home button,
jump into Multitasking.
I can just swipe across
everything I have running.
I want to move into one,
Messages, double tap, back out.
Move into Mail, back
out, just like this.
It's really, really nice.
That's multitasking in iOS 7.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
So of course there's much,
much more to iOS 7,
including AirDrop.
[ Applause ]
AirDrop is absolutely
the easiest way to share
with the people that
are right around you.
So now when you're in any app
that supports a Share Sheet,
you bring up the Share Sheet
and your friends that are all
around you just show
up right there.
You tap on one and they're
going to get a panel right
on their display and they
can accept what it is
that you shared.
They accept it.
They're taken right into the
app and you know if you want
to share with multiple people
you just tap, tap, tap.
No need to wander
around the room,
bumping your phone or whatever.
[ Applause ]
Now, this is system wide for
any app that's supports a Share
Sheet and of course it uses peer
to peer Wi-Fi for maximum speed
and all your transmissions
are securely encrypted
because it uses the latest
Wi-Fi hardware, it's supported
on the iPhone 5, the
fourth-generation iPad,
iPad mini and the
fifth-generation iPod Touch
and that is AirDrop.
Next, let's talk
about the camera.
So, now, your camera in iOS
7 is four cameras in one.
You just swipe from your video
camera to your photo camera,
to your square cropped
camera, to your pano camera.
And when you're taking
stills, you now have access
to live photo filters from
some gorgeous black and whites,
to some classic color
filters as well.
So with your great,
new camera we want
to give you a great new
way to manage your photos
and it's the new Photos app.
You know for many users this is
what their photo organization
looks like: an endless,
unorganized stream
of their camera roll.
We've all been there
but, you know,
it doesn't have to be this way.
There's great information
in those photos.
iOS knows where you took the
photos and when you took them
and that provides inherent
structure that we can use
to organize those photos.
And now in photos
in iOS 7, we do.
We organize them into moments.
And I'd like to give you
a demo of that right now.
[ Applause ]
So let's take a look
now at the Photos app.
So here you see some photos
that were taken in San Francisco
and you see nothing was done to
organize these photos explicitly
and yet they have these labels.
It's like the Palace
of Fine Arts,
Baker Beach, Lombard Street.
It provides this
natural organization
for appreciating the photos.
We can go up that more trips
at more times in San Francisco,
Golden Gate, to San
Francisco Fisherman's Wharf.
But then you see we have home.
We have photos taken at
home and photos taken
at the elementary school
and around that area.
And now if you want to
zoom back out to get a--
more of bird's eye view
of your collection,
we draw these moments
intelligently together
into collections.
So see here how that
multiple day trip
around San Francisco is
collected-- sorry about that,
I've got a little
excited there, into--
it's a very exciting interface
into a multi-day trip
in San Francisco.
And that time at home and
around the school, well,
that's one moment-- that's
one collection as well.
It's a really great way
to browse your photos.
You can even go all the
way out to the year level.
Look across your whole
photo collection.
[ Applause ]
And look how we pull out the
interesting places that you went
in that year like 2011 was
Colorado and Hawaii, 2012,
went to South America.
You may not remember
when you did it
but iOS does and
it's right there.
And, you know, with this retina
display you can even can make
out patterns of photos in
one different occasions
or in a course we found like
we had the urge that we wanted
to just tap in right from here.
And so now in fact you can.
You can just tap and scrub
and find the photo you're
looking for just like that.
It's really just amazing.
So I can just pick a photo
here whichever one I want.
It's kind of cute and
now we can edit it
because we have photo filters.
So I can go into
the filters here,
I can try different color
effects, and if I find one I
like maybe a nice
black and white,
you can do it just like that.
I'll apply it and
save that photo away.
We also have great new ways
to share your photos
in the Photos apps.
Let's bring up sharing.
We have AirDrop right here if
any of you were running iOS 7,
I'd see you, it looks
like it didn't leak,
so that's good you're not
in there right now,
but you have AirDrop.
You have access to other
photos, you can share them
from right here,
just really handy.
Great photo sharing option
is iCloud photo sharing,
I'm going to tap on that now.
It's going to iCloud
photo sharing.
And from here, I can
select the Photo Streams
that I want to share too.
So I'm on family photos now,
but I'm going to drill in
and I can see other Photo
Streams I've set up.
And now, other people can share
into my Photo Stream as well.
So these are shared
Photo Streams.
[ Applause ]
I'll just select a Photo Stream
here and type a little message.
We'll post that photo.
So it made it really
easy to share
and we've also made it a
really great experience
to experience the photos
you and others have shared
with this new shared
tab at the bottom.
So I'm going to go in here.
I could see my photo
with a comment.
I can see the comments
of other people
and the photos that
they've shared.
And now, we even support sharing
video via iCloud photo sharing.
And we have a great way to just
browse those shared photos.
I'll just tilt the
device into landscape.
I can scroll through
it like this.
And just look how
beautiful that is.
What a great way to
experience your photos.
So that's the new
photos App in iOS 7.
[ Applause ]
So integration with internet
services is a huge part
of the experience of iOS and
never more so than in iOS 7.
So to take you through
some of those features,
I'd like to bring up Eddy Cue.
Eddy. [Applause]
>> Great job, Craig.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks, it's great
to be here.
So let's talk about Siri.
The first thing is Siri has
a gorgeous new interface.
Now as I speak, you'll see a
sound wave across the bottom
and you get the result to a
beautiful, gorgeous, clean way.
But Siri is always been a lot
about your-- the voice of Siri.
And we've got an all new voice.
>> Hi, Eddy.
What can I do for you?
>> And you can also
choose a male voice.
>> Hi, Eddy.
What can I do for you?
>> And we've got high
quality-- thank you.
We've also got high
quality female
and male voices for French.
[Foreign Language]
As well as German.
And we're going
to be adding other
languages over time.
Now Siri is also getting a
lot smarter and knows how
to control more of your device.
So you could say, play my last
voice mail or turn on Bluetooth
or increase my brightness.
[ Applause ]
And it can answer a
lot more questions
because we've integrated some
new services like Twitter,
so you can see what people are
saying or what's happening.
We've integrated the
world's largest Encyclopedia
and Wikipedia.
And we've even integrated
web search results
from Bing right inside of Siri.
And it's great for photos too.
And that is some of the new
features of Siri in iOS 7.
Now Siri is also a big
part of our next feature.
iOS in the car.
[ Applause ]
Now 95 percent of the cars being
sold today have integrated music
playback and control
from an iOS device,
but we want to take
this integration
to a whole another level.
What if you could get iOS
on the screen that is built
into your car so that you can
make phone calls, play music,
go to maps, get your iMessages
right on the screen in your car
or Eyes Free using Siri.
So now, when you
make a phone call,
it's going to look something
like this, call John Appleseed,
or play get lucky, or go
to maps, get directions,
or even get your
iMessages read to you
and you can dictate a
response all Eyes Free.
[ Applause ]
Now, all of these car
manufacturers are introducing
iOS integration in 2014 and I
know which one I want to buy.
And that's iOS in the car.
Next, the App Store.
Now the App Store
looks beautiful.
It's way easier to find
Apps than ever before.
We've added a new feature where
you can look for apps based
on your age range,
kid's categories,
parents are going to love this.
And apps Near Me, you can find
the most popular apps based
on your current location.
So now, let's say I'm at
AT&T park in San Francisco
and here are the
apps I would see.
Or I'm at the Louvre in Paris.
Or I'm in Union Square Shopping.
It's that easy to
discover new apps.
It's really great.
The next feature, I know,
you're all going to love
because everyday, you
see something like this.
Well, no more because the
App Store updates your
apps automatically.
[ Applause ]
Next, let's talk about music.
The music app in iOS
7 is beyond doubt,
the best music player
we have ever done.
The first thing you'll
notice is we provide you
with beautiful artist images
right in your library.
And you just tap an artist
and you see the songs.
But it's not just the
songs on your device,
you see all of your
purchased music
from iCloud right
in your library.
And if you want to hear one
of the songs, you just tap
and you get our beautiful
Now Playing screen.
But it's not just your purchased
music, in the video apps,
you get all of your movies and
TV shows right from iCloud right
into your library, it's
really, really great.
[ Applause ]
If you turn the device
sideways, you see your albums.
You could just swipe
to see more,
and once you see one you like,
you tap and it zooms right in.
Now, the music app is the best
way to listen to your music.
But today, we're
introducing an amazing way
to discover new music and
we call it iTunes Radio.
[ Applause ]
And here's what it looks like.
It's built right
into the music app.
But rather than tell you about
it, I'd love to show it to you.
[ Pause ]
And we'll launch the music app.
And the first thing you'll
notice is we've got a set
of featured stations that our
programming team have created.
So you can see the
songs that are trending
on Twitter right now,
or even the songs
that you guys are all going
to hear this week at WWDC.
But I feel like summer songs.
So you just tap.
[ Pause ]
[ Music ]
[Background Music] And once
you have a station you love,
you could just tap the i and you
could share it with a friend,
or even create a new station
based on this artist or song.
I can easily skip to see
what's the next song.
[ Music ]
[Background Music] I'll
go back to stations.
But it's not just the featured
stations that we provide.
You can create your
own stations.
Here are some that I've
previously created.
But I feel like doing
something new.
Now, our music team is
providing you with hundreds
of stations based on
alternative, country,
classic rock, but I feel
like doing something a
little more specific.
[ Music ]
How about some Led Zeppelin?
[Background Music] First,
start off with a great
Led Zeppelin song.
Let's go and see what
else is on this station.
And a great thing is I can
always modify the station,
I can just tap the star, and
I could say play more songs
like this, or never play this
song, or add it to my wish list.
Now, I like this so let's play
some more songs like this.
Now, another great feature of
iTunes Radio is it keeps track
of all of the songs
that you're listening
to across all the
stations, all your devices.
And you can get to them
by just tapping History.
You can see them all here.
You can Preview, and
buy right from there.
And that's iTunes Radio.
[ Applause ]
So iTunes Radio is built into
iOS 7, it works on your iPhone,
your iPod touch, and your iPad.
It's also built into iTunes
on your Mac and PC and even
in your living room
built into Apple TV.
[ Applause ]
iTunes radio is free with ads.
And if you are an
iTunes Match subscriber,
it's completely ad-free.
[ Applause ]
We're starting in the US and
we'll be adding other countries
over time and that's the
new music app on iOS 7.
It is the best music
player we have ever done.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Eddy.
So 10 amazing features in iOS 7
and a comprehensive
end to end UI redesign.
And of course we're bringing
it all to iPad as well.
Now, there's more to iOS 7
than we had time to talk to you
about in depth here today.
Things like FaceTime audio
where you now can do audio
only high quality audio calls
over Wi-Fi on any iOS device.
Notification syncs so if
you dismissed a notification
on one device, you don't have to
deal with it over and over again
on your other devices.
Great feature for our users
in China with integration
to popular microblogging
website Tencent Weibo.
And for those of
you who have people
who just won't let go phone
FaceTime and message blocking.
Also for our enterprise
fee, customers per App VPN.
Now there's yeah, a
couple of enterprise people
in the audience are you?
So, in addition to all of these
is one feature I want to talk
about in a little bit more
detail which is activation lock.
So hundreds of millions of
us use to Find My iPhone
to find their phone when
it's just lost in the couch
or maybe left at Starbucks,
but also when it's been stolen.
And now, with activation
lock, if a thief tries
to turn off Find My iPhone
or if they even wipe the device
entirely, they will not be able
to reactivate it because they
don't know your iPod user
name activation.
[ Applause ]
We think this is going to be a
really powerful theft deterrent.
Now of course in addition
to be in a great release
for our users, iOS 7 is also
a fantastic and major release
for developers as well.
The SDK includes
over 1500 new APIs.
We can add AirDrop, integrate it
with third-party
game controllers.
New APIs for taking
advantage of multitasking,
iBeacons for Bluetooth
LE micro location,
Sprite Kit for super fast
power-efficient game animations
and UI dynamics to bring physics
to your UIView Animations.
So I-- yeah.
[ Applause ]
So iOS 7 is available
to you developers
in beta on the iPhone today.
[ Applause ]
We'll have betas for iPad
coming up in the near--
in the coming weeks and for
everyone else a final release
coming this fall.
So iOS 7 will be available
for iPhone 4 and later iPad 2
and later the iPad mini and the
fifth generation iPod touch.
That is iOS 7.
I hope you'll love it.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> What a morning, it seems
to be incredible products.
OS X Mavericks, our
latest release
of the world's most advanced
desktop operating system.
It's the best OS X yet.
With new incredible MacBook Airs
with unbelievable battery life
that continue to define the
future of the notebooks.
The next generation Mac Pro,
a revolutionary computer
designed especially
for our power users.
I work for iCloud, create
beautiful documents right
in your browser on
a Mac or a PC.
iOS 7, amazing new features and
a stunning new user interface,
it's the biggest change to iOS
since the introduction
of iPhone.
And iTunes Radio, the absolute
best way to discover new music.
We are incredibly proud
of all of these products.
They are great examples
of what Apple does best.
I'd like to thank everyone
at Apple that worked
so hard to create them.
I get to work with the most
talented and creative people
on earth and it's a
joy to serve with them.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
I'd like to close this morning
with the reminder, that our goal
at Apple is to make
amazing products
that our customers love,
really great products
that enrich people's lives.
The words you saw at the
beginning of the show are more
than just words to us.
They are the values we lived by.
They drive us.
You see them reflected in our
products over the years and just
as much in the products
this morning.
And you'll just continue
to see these reflected
in the products we
do in the future.
We've created an ad to help us
express just how deeply we feel
about this and I'd like
to share it with you now.
>> [Music] This is it.
This is what matters.
The experience of a product.
How will it make someone feel?
Will it make life better?
Does it deserve to exist?
We spend a lot of time
on a few great things
until every idea we touch
enhances each life it touches.
You may rarely look at it,
but you'll always feel it.
This is our signature.
And it means everything.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
>> I'm really glad
you liked that.
You'll begin to see it on
TV beginning this evening.
Those words have been
a great deal to us.
And I hope they mean
a lot to you as well.
Have a great conference.
Enjoy the week.
Thank you.
[ Applause & Music ]