I'm walking
oh thank you
hmm
thank you very much
it always thank you it always helps and
I appreciate it very much so we've got
an awesome morning together this morning
and thank you for coming so much we we
have over 5,200 attendees here today we
sold out within two hours I'm sorry this
is the biggest place we can get to have
this so I'm sorry for all those people
that couldn't make it and we wish we
could sell more tickets but we don't
know where to have it if we do so 5200
attendees over 120 sessions over a
hundred hands-on labs where you can take
your code in and get to help tuning it
and porting it to some of our newer
devices and there are over a hundred
Apple engineers here this week a
thousand sorry Apple engineers here this
week to help you so there's a lot of app
of folks floating around grab them make
use of them and we hope you have a great
week here at WWDC now we're going to
talk about three things today you know
if the if the hardware is the the brain
and sinew of our products the software
in them is their sole and today we are
going to talk about software we've got
some great stuff to talk about
OS 10 lion iOS 5 and some kind of
interesting new cloud stuff so let's
start with Lion tell us all about Lion
I'm going to ask to my colleagues Phil
Schiller and Craig federighi to take us
through line and give us some demos pill
okay proceed
oh good morning everyone how you doing
yeah come on energy in the room this is
the Developer Conference that's what I
liked it I am really honored to be the
first to present to you the first of our
new products today in this product is
all about the Mac and the Mac is doing
incredibly well our customer base
continues to grow at a tremendous pace
we now have over 54 million active Mac
users around the world and growing the
customers love the products and press
and analysts have really incredible
things to say about it things like this
from All Things D there's really no
other way to say this the Mac is kicking
ass now that's really nice but what did
John mean well this is what he means the
last quarter the PC market actually
shrank year-over-year one percent while
the math grew 28%
in my book that's an ass-kicking now ass
do you think this is an aberration the
Mac has outgrown the industry every
quarter for the past five years it is
going so strong and it's because the
products are incredible products like
the new MacBook Air it's beautiful its
thin its light its fast the whole PC
industry wants to copy it but as you
know we've been leading in notebooks for
a while we're the first to really drive
the majority of our PC business to a
notebook business and it's almost
three-quarters of the Mac's we've
shipped today but whether you want a
great new notebook or a killer desktop
with the new iMac these Macs are the
best that we have ever made in the
history of Apple and they're great not
just because of the hardware they run
but because of the software Mac os10 is
the heart of the Mac and if you're
keeping track you know we launched Mac
OS 10 ten years ago we built it on a
solid UNIX foundation we added to it the
ease-of-use and simplicity that we know
Apple is renowned for and we built into
it amazing technologies for all of our
great developers to make the world's
best applications to run on it and for
those of you who are around and remember
this this is what Mac OS 10 looked like
ten years ago when we launched it
it was a revolution in its day and over
the last 10 years it's evolved to become
more refined more powerful more
beautiful than ever before the Mac os10
is looking incredibly strong so where do
we take it next well next up in OS 10 is
lying a major release with over 250 new
features and if you'd like me to go
through every one of them today yes
while I'd love to I'm told I don't have
enough time to tell you about 10 key new
features so we'll really get into 10
awesome features first up right into it
number one multi-touch gestures one of
the great things about the mat in the
beginning was that it uh sure Dan era of
a graphic unit user interface with a
mouse and cooking and dragging but so
much has changed over the last 10 years
we now build multi-touch trackpads into
all of our notebooks and we offer them
on our desktops we've learned a lot from
iOS as well
so now lion can count on multi-touch
from the beginning you can have
beautiful fluid momentum based scrolling
you can have incredible multi-touch taps
to zoom in on stories or pictures you
can dynamically zoom with beautiful
fluid pinch motions you can swipe
through your photographs your slides
your web pages all with an incredible
physical realism that's never been
possible the PC operating system before
and this has implications across the
system and a lot of little important
areas here's a simple example the scroll
bar why do we have scroll bar scroll
bars were there so it could click with
the mouse and drag and scroll but now if
you're pushing your window with
multi-touch you don't need them they can
disappear and if a much more beautiful
reading environment but when you go to
scroll they magically appear give you a
sense of place and proportional size and
then disappear when you don't need them
so multi-touch is now built throughout
the system in a very powerful way number
two full screen applications we've had
some full screen applications before and
these are really important for notebooks
11 inch and 13 inch where you want to
get take advantage of every pixel on the
display but developers have had to work
hard to make their applications
hand-coded to do full screen
including apps like like iPhoto well now
with lying we've built in a standard
method for developers to create full
screen applications and it has a simple
system control in the top right so all
users know where to tap and then bring
their applications full screen but this
isn't full screen like it was before
because now you can keep your
application running full screen with a
simple swipe gesture get back to your
desktop get something you need go back
to application never having left full
screen in fact you can have more than
one full screen application running at
the same time so we've worked on a
number of our applications to bring them
into the new full-screen mode of Lion
system applications like Safari mail
iCal iLife applications iPhoto iMovie
GarageBand I work with keynote numbers
and pages and all these applications
going fullscreen to have a great
experience right out of the box here's
an example of how it looks this is now
running fullscreen in Safari you can
have a beautiful place for viewing your
documents and now there's a new feature
since we've got all this extra room on
the left-hand side called the reading
list keep track of things want to get to
later
here's iCal running fullscreen here's
preview showing you PDF documents
running fullscreen so you just have a
beautiful experience like we've never
had on a computer before with full
screen applications next feature for
many users this will be the best feature
of Lion it's called Mission Control now
we all like to run a lot of software the
Apple we've created many features to
help customers find just what they need
expose for finding a document dashboard
for getting at a quick widget spaces for
organizing your work environment but did
it all work together in one unified way
well now with line we've unified that
with a simple gesture to get into
Mission Control and this is a bird's-eye
view of everything going on in your
system on the main window well that's
the current desktop you're working on
with all the documents now organized by
what application is running on them and
you can tap on any document and bring it
to the front that's right there Center
for you to work on up above are all your
spaces so you can have multiple desktops
you can have multiple full screen apps
running get to anyone with a single tab
and on the left of those spaces is a new
special one just for your dashboard
widgets you can get to again with a
single tab
so that's Mission Control and what I
like to do now is before we move on have
Craig federighi come up and give you a
demo of these three new features all
working together
Craig hello good morning so
let's take a look at lion in action
we're going to start with gestures great
played it place to experience gestures
is here in Safari the first thing you'll
notice is apparently something funny is
that how simple this UI looks because
there are no scroll bars it's a really
clean look we don't need scroll bars
anymore because we can simply push the
content with our fingers we can flick
and get momentum get a nice little
bounce the page feels really alive
beneath your fingers you can also expand
your fingers and fluidly zoom just like
that zoom out and you get a nice little
bounce page goes right back into place
if I want to smart zoom I just double
tap with two fingers it's smart zooms in
double tap again smart zooms out now I
want to show you something really cool
with gestures and that's how it can
navigate in Safari I'm going to drill
into a story and then after I've read it
I want to actually get back to the
previous page well now I can just take
two fingers and swipe the page right off
to the side and return back to my
previous page I want to get back and
swipe right back really fantastic in
fact I can swipe through my entire
Safari browsing history just like that
really smooth next up I'd like to show
you full screen apps let me launch
iPhoto here and you can see that I
photos adopted Lions and standard new
full screen control so I'll just take
lion or take iPhoto fullscreen it's a
great way to look at my photo album if I
want to get back to my desktop take
three fingers and I can just swipe the
desktop swipe iPhoto away and back to my
desktop but I didn't have to leave
iPhoto take it out of full screen it's
actually right there take a peek at it
go back just like that we loved this so
much that we made gestures accessible in
exactly the same way swipe over to the
left and I have access to my dashboard
you can see Safari supports full screen
as well let's go take our Safari window
full screen so now we have our dashboard
over our desktop over here to the left
we have Safari and of course I photos
still the
full screen as well you'll notice how
Safari is making great use of all the
available space on the screen for my
content if I want to get at my bookmarks
bar my menu just go to the top you see
they slide right out like that really
nicely and when I want to exit full
screen I have a control right there in
the upper right animates right back out
let's take a look now at photobooth this
is an app absolutely
born to run in full screen you can see
I'm surrounded by the curtains of the
the photobooth and in here I can
experience some fantastic new face
detection at fast so notice as I move
the birds actually track
it's right it's the most important
feature in line and we can also use this
base tracking technology to perform some
targeted facial enhancements for
instance I can finally have those big
eyes that I've always hoped for so let's
make a picture of that so that's that's
pretty cool so playing around yeah
that's great stuff so you know you can
spend hours at this so fullscreen is
fantastic but of course Mac users love
to get do a lot of things at once and
that often means that they have a lot of
windows in fact my desktop often looks a
little bit more like this right I've got
a lot going on so how do I get across
all of those different activities well I
just take three fingers swipe up on the
trackpad and I'm in Mission Control from
here I can get at any window I want so
if I want to get it I Cal here I click
it comes forward sweet back into Mission
Control over to dictionary same thing
and across the top you see I have my
dashboard my desktop my full screen apps
so I want to get to iPhoto just click
comes forward from anywhere three
fingers up and I'm back in Mission
Control I can also quick look my windows
if I just hit spacebar here get a better
look at my calendar or take this pile of
preview windows and spread them apart
with a little gesture up but you know
what's really awesome is the way that
multiple desktop spaces are now
integrated right into Mission Control
just take my mouse up to the corner of
the screen and the little space pops up
I click I've just created a new space
and I can populate it by just dragging
the windows I want to work within that
space just like this I've set up a new
desk
really useful I can swipe through the
spaces of course here in admission
control go over to my desktop and if I
want to then take even an entire app and
all of its windows and create a new
space for that I can click on the
preview icon drag the whole pile to the
corner I've just created another space
and the spaces are just as easy to clean
up as they were to create I just click
they delete and they float windows fly
right back to my original desktop space
so that is Mission Control thank you
very much
Thank You Craig to see how these new
features now work seamlessly together to
create an incredible experience in OS 10
unlike anything we've had on a personal
computer before
next up the Mac App Store we launched
the Mac App Store this past January and
users have found out that it is the best
place to purchase and discover new
software applications now for years
there have been many software channels
to buy PC software and they all work
kind of the same way you hop in your car
you drive downtown you buy a DVD if they
happen to have it you drive back home
you load it up or you wait for it to
come mail-order will no more well now
with the Mac App Store you can get your
software right from the comfort of your
own home on your Mac and in the last six
months something incredible has happened
the last six months the Mac App Store
has now become the number one PC
software channel for buying software
that's incredible passing Best Buy and
Walmart and Office Depot and the
developers that have gotten on board
with the Mac App Store seen some great
success - for example Autodesk they
brought their SketchBook Pro application
to it and since they've put it on the
Mac App Store they've seen a million new
users on the Mac feral interactive has
brought a host of games including Mini
Ninjas hopefully you've all played it
doubling of overall revenue since they
brought into the Mac App Store and small
great developers like Pixelmator has
brought their amazing new image editing
application to the Mac App Store they've
seen a quadrupling of the revenue in
fact they made a million dollars in the
first 20 days so the Mac App Store has
been a big hit for large and small
developers so what's new in lying well
first its built right in you don't have
to go and download it and get it and
decide to use it it's built in for every
Mac user and there's a lot of great
features for you developers to take
advantage of some of them you're used to
from the iOS App Store like in-app
purchases you can now build those in
push notifications if you want to alert
users about important information you
can make your applications more secure
there's a built-in sandboxing method now
in the Mac App Store and for users
downloads will be even faster because
you can get these updates as Delta
updates so that's the Mac app so it's a
really important part of the whole
experience of line is you'll hear more
about number 5 a simple but powerful
idea
Launchpad would it be great if no matter
where you are in your system if you want
to get in an application and quickly
launch it you can with a simple gesture
well now you can with Launchpad you
simply make a simple gesture a pinch
motion and all your applications fly
onto your screen no matter where they
are in your system
Launchpad knows where they are you can
have multiple pages of applications that
you can organize any way you want when
you go and buy a new application on the
Mac App Store and downloads installs
right into your Launchpad and you can
make it look however you'd like you can
rearrange your icons you can create
folders just as we're used to from iOS
and now you can do that on your Mac as
well so that's Launchpad next resume
here's a simple idea from the beginning
with the computer you've had to run
applications sometimes you quit them you
go back and you're back at the starting
point you get you have no more windows
open your documents aren't open you
usually have to pick a template why
can't applications get you back to work
quickly well that's what resume does now
when you launch an application and lyan
it brings you right back to where you
were when you quit it remembers what
documents you were opened remembers the
text that was selected in the document
remembers where the palettes were in the
windows and everything just how you like
it
and resume doesn't work just on an
application it works system-wide so the
next time you have to shutdown and
restart your your math for a reason
maybe you've installed some new software
and it asks you to reboot get you like
everything just the way it is well don't
worry you get the new login window you
log in and line will bring you back to
the work environment as you left it when
you restarted all your applications
running all those spaces you set up all
just the way you like it
so that's resumed number seven autosave
from the beginning of using computers
we've all had to remember one really
important fact save save save all your
work as you're going whether it's file
save or command S on the Mac you better
keep saving it's the one time you might
forget to save what you're doing
something goes wrong and what are you
going to hear you should have saved what
you're doing why should you why can't
the computer help you well that's what
Lyon does as you're creating a document
Lyon can automatically save it in the
background without you having to do
anything but I was happy to see anything
your work is just being saved for you
this is a really powerful but simple
thing but but as we got into we found
there's more things we can do for you
since we're Auto saving so if you zoom
in on the title bar of your documents
you'll see the name of your document is
actually a menu now that you can tap on
and take advantage of the power of
autosave but for example let's say
you're doing work and you don't like the
work you did and you're worried it got
auto saved over what you liked that
you've done previously well now I can
just select revert to last open and get
back to where you were when you started
maybe you love the changes you've made
and they're exactly what you want you
don't want it to ever get auto saved
over it again because it's perfect the
way it is you can just select lock and
now your documents locked it's like a
template and nothing can ever change it
you can even right from within the
application select duplicate and create
a second document just like the first
one that you can start working on
another version so you have the power of
all of this right from the title bar of
your window so that's auto save now auto
save gave us a great idea to go even
further with the next feature and that's
called versions so you're working on a
document you're entering the text you're
formatting you're adding copy you're
adding graphics and all along autosave
is saving your document in fact it's
saving all these versions of your
document as you're working so we call
that versions it's automatic you don't
have to do anything we'll do it for you
with Lyon if you love something at a
split second you can of course take a
manual snapshot if you want and it's
very efficient we only store the
difference between the versions there
are
new documents and you don't have to
worry if you ever share your work with
someone else that they're going to get
all that back work that you won't don't
want them to get when you copy it off or
you send it an email we only send the
current version so how do you get it
take advantage of this power of autosave
inversions
well again go back to that menu on the
top and there's another choice there
that you may have noticed browse all
versions you tap on it and you get this
beautiful new interface it looks a lot
like time machine but rather than being
about your whole system it's about that
one document you're working on on the
left is the current version on the right
all the past versions and you have a
time scale on the right just like time
machine you can scroll back through them
and they're all live you can switch you
make any one the current one you can
even cut and paste between them so
that's versions what I like to do is ask
Craig to come back up and give another
demo so how this all works together
Craig again
alright well let's let's start with
Launchpad you see it's an icon right
here on my dock I click I get an instant
view of all of the applications on my
system no matter where they're installed
I can page through them really nicely
with gestures and when I want to launch
let's say like address book it's just a
single click to bring it up can also
gesture with a forefinger pinch to get
in as well so of course when I want to
add things to my Launchpad the best way
to do that is with the Mac App Store I'm
going to launch it right here you can
see on the Mac App Store we have great
featured applications top paid and free
apps categories we have also all of your
purchase tabs so then if you buy another
Mac or you buy on one Mac you want to
get the app on the other one you can
download them here at no additional
charge
and of course updates with just a click
you can bring all the apps you have
installed on your system from the App
Store up to date
well now let's try adding Twitter to our
Mac we're going to click here go to the
Twitter product page and with a click
you can buy the app actually lifts up
out of the App Store and flies right
into my Launchpad downloads and is ready
to use
from here I can just click and position
it wherever I want I can move it maybe
to the first page and as you see we have
folders like this productivity folder
works great I want to create my own
folder just pick something up drop it
and I've created a folder just like that
in Launchpad next I'd like to show you
just how fantastic the Mac is now with
Lion working with documents I'm going to
open the document that I've been working
on here on the history of guitars when I
start editing a document often I'll
position my windows just the way I like
them like this maybe open up some
inspectors position them the way I want
them and then I'll set down to editing
now this guitar this looks maybe a
little bit too metal for my target
audience so I'll delete that take take
this move it aside maybe change the font
here on this on this document so I'm
done with my edits for now and I'm going
to quit I want you to watch what happens
when I quit
absolutely nothing I wasn't prompted to
say I didn't need to be because Lyon was
actually saving for me all along but it
wasn't just saving my document it was
saving exactly the state of how I was
working so now when I go back and launch
pages again you see it brings back all
my inspectors just the way they were
brings back my window position where it
was and even has my text selection
highlighted just as I left it
perfect restore but we're not just
storing the latest version of the
document we're keeping a history of the
document as it's edited so if I want to
go back maybe I regret these edits I
want to get back to the previous version
I go right here and browse all versions
and I'm taken right into the star field
where I get a view of my current version
on the left and the history on the right
if I want this previous version to
become current I click restore it picks
up flies on top and becomes the current
version of my document and I'm restored
but you saw that was actually more
history than that I'll go back into the
star field here you can see I actually
have a full timeline here on the right I
can go back to the very beginning of
this document when it was just a few
paragraphs or step forward as I was
adding pages and so forth but when I
restore a document you know very often
I don't want really the whole old
version I like mostly what my new
document has become but often I want to
harvest maybe just an image or perhaps a
particular slide and bring it into the
current version with versions I can
because these two windows are actually
live here so if I have on my current
version maybe a page that could really
use an image to punch it up a little bit
I go back to this past version I see oh
look there's there's a guitar that would
be just perfect well I can just select
the guitar in the old version copy it
and then paste it right into the latest
version and like that I've created just
the document I was
looking for and that's version thanks
Thank You Craig next number nine well as
long as we've had computers we wanted to
share documents we have a new feature to
help you do that and make it easier than
ever it's called airdrop you've got your
computer your friends got their computer
and trying to get documents between them
has always been such a pain in fact the
easiest way to do this that no one's
done better than is good old sneakernet
copy it off of one walk over your
friend's computer copy it back on
Millian solves that with a new
technology airdrop that's a peer-to-peer
Wi-Fi based network so how does it work
when you go into the finder in line
you'll see on the sources on the left a
new choice called airdrop you tap it you
get a new display inside the finder what
you see is yourself Center bottom right
there and the people around you who are
also running airdrop at the same time
you see their pictures I'm going to drag
a document over to Shawna's computer I
just drag the document on top of her
picture and it asked me are you sure you
want to send this and I confirm I do now
in Shauna's computer because she's also
now running airdrop she sees pops up
over my picture I'm trying to send her a
document she confirms she wants to
receive it and it downloads right into a
Downloads folder and that's it that's
what it takes to now wirelessly share
files between line computers so it's a
peer-to-peer Wi-Fi based network there's
nothing to set up it's Auto discovery
Auto setup we have confirmation on both
ends just to be safe and your data is
protected over the air because it's
fully encrypted as it's transferred so
that's airdrop that brings us to number
[Applause]
number ten is mail a completely new
version of mail in Lyon it's beautiful
the layout on it is incredible it works
in a window it takes advantage of full
screen you can work in a two-column or
if you want to have access to your mail
sources a three column view right there
on the left and you see that the design
of it's really optimized around reading
your mail have a beautiful full height
message window on the left and the
message list you see snippets like we
used to from iOS now built into mail
across the top you have a favorites bar
sort of like a browser does now in mail
that can be favorite folders where you
like to keep things you want to get at
quickly probably the most one of the
most powerful features is searching with
searching now we have new search
suggestions so you start to type what
you're looking for and mail recognizes
whether that's a person or a subject and
prompts you with the choices you have
across your entire mail database what
you can find quickly when you select one
it becomes what we call a search token
that's an interactive search token where
you can set some parameters on it and
you can have more than one create
boolean searches if you want but
probably the best feature of the new
mail is something we call yes you can
love to add it's okay boolean search is
probably the best feature something we
call conversation view in mail today as
you've got a conversation going you've
got some messages we responded to or
replied and forwards you see the mail
gets longer and longer and they're
indented and color coded things stripped
out it gets more and more difficult to
follow the flow of this and appreciate
the messages that were sent well now in
line is a brand-new conversation view
that shows your messages just as they
were sent
you see the messages you see the people
who send them you see the attachments
still in line all there for you to view
it's completely compatible with doing
email with other people who don't have
line and can't get the same beautiful
view
so that's male and lion I'd like to
bring Craig up for one last demo to show
off male okay well I absolutely love the
new male in Lion let's let's take a look
so it's got this great full height
message list perfect for laptops just
like this I've got my message list on
the side with snippets makes it really
easy to find the message I'm looking for
with this new favorites bar across the
top so I can click through my mailboxes
really easily but if I want to get back
to my full list they're available right
here as well I really find the new
search to be just awesome because when I
search I'm often searching for a person
let's say like Bill I start typing pH
see it prompts me for people in my mail
right now that match so I go Phil
Schiller found messages from Phil just
like that I can use it can retarget the
search to specific inboxes or search all
and of course as Phil showed you I can
pick whether I'm searching for from two
or the entire message
well suggestions don't just apply to
searching for people they also work for
other things as well like let's say a
subject I'll search for trip you see
that it's actually prompting me do you
want to search for messages the contain
trip or where trip just appears in the
subject line or even suggest specific
subject lines that match so I can select
this and I've done a subject search on
trip what about dates I'm going to type
March start typing March
there you see it prompts me March 2011
like that I've searched for all my
messages in March but what's really
awesome is the way you can combine these
really quickly to pinpoint just the
search you're looking for so let's say
looking for a message about that Phil
sent me it's the subject was something
about reservation it was from Phil
Schiller and it was last month like that
drills down to exactly the message
it's really nice as awesome as that is
my favorite feature is conversations so
this beautiful view all the messages
that were sent in the conversation just
as they were sent with all the images
and so forth and you'll notice that all
of that extra forwarded reply text
that's redundant in the conversation is
stripped right out it's gone but if I
want to show it I want to see mail the
way it kind of looks in lessor mail
programs I can click like this it folds
right out yeah this is awesome
if I want to reply to a particular
message in a conversation I can hover we
get a reply control and watch this
animation loop so message hops right out
so that's great and finally when you
want to file a whole conversation away
you can just drag it all at once drag
all the messages put it your folder and
you're done
that's mail in Lion thank you
so those are the top ten features of
mail and there's some excuse me of Lyon
and there is so much more for you to
learn about and discover and Lyon
amazing features just to bring up a few
and don't windows users who want to
upgrade to a Mac deserve a migration
feature just like we Mac users have well
now there is in line when you upgrade
from Windows we can help you migrate and
get to a better computing experience
there's File Vault ooh yeah so for all
of you who want more security and
encryption in your hard drive you have
that facetimes built-in even servers all
new with Lion server isn't another
operating system it's just a bunch of
applications you can purchase to run on
top of Lion so amazing depth of features
for you and for all the developers out
here we have over 3,000 new API for you
to take advantage of the power of Lion
amazing stuff you can do all the things
we showed here you can have full screen
applications you can create versions you
can take advantage of autosave all of
that can easily be done with all these
new api's so line is an incredible new
new release so how are we going to get
it well in the past one thing every
version of Mac OS 10 is shared in common
is it came on an optical disk no more
now line.we available only in the Mac
App Store
[Applause]
and that allows us to make it the
easiest upgrade you have ever seen when
it's ready you'll go into the Mac App
Store and you'll see a page there where
you can read about it see screenshots
read reviews when you're ready click buy
and it downloads right onto your Mac and
starts the upgrade process right there
so it's on the Mac App Store will be
about four gigabytes in size about the
same size as a single HD movie that you
might download it installs right in
place no more rebooting from an optical
disk and because it's part of the Mac
apps from the Mac App Store rules it
follows the same rules when you purchase
it you can use it on all of your
personal authorized max you have to buy
multiple copies that's where I am I know
what you're thinking what should we
charge for this but what would you
charge on the past most major leases of
Mac OS 10 have been one hundred and
twenty nine dollars and I think there's
a lot here for $129 but we love it so
much that we want to make it available
to even more people so we're going to
price it at just $29.99
I was hoping you're going to like that
so when do you all get your hands on it
here at the conference we're going to
have a Developer Preview the latest
developer preview available today for
you to download and take advantage of
everything you've seen up here and for
customers one will be available in July
so very very soon coming in July so that
is Lian that's the first four new
products we wanted to tell you about
today
the next product we're going to talk
about is iOS 5 and to do that I'd like
to invite up Scott Forstall
welcome so I'm here to tell you about
iOS five before I get into the cool
stuff let me give you a quick update on
iOS as you know iOS powers the iPhone
the iPad and the iPod Touch and to date
we have sold wait for it over two
hundred million iOS devices and that
makes iOS the number one mobile
operating system with more than forty
four percent at forty four percent of
the market now the latest addition to
the iOS family is the iPad 2 which is an
incredible product even thinner and
lighter than the original it comes in
black and white it has cameras on the
front and back it is an amazing product
and our customers just couldn't wait to
get their hands on it or else they'd
actually did have to wait to get their
hands on it in the first fourteen months
we have already sold more than
twenty-five million iPads
we created a whole new category of
device with the iPad and have sold more
than 25 million with the iPad to joins
the iPhone and the iPod Touch for an
incredible lineup of iOS devices and
we've got some great stores to go along
with these as well like the iTunes music
store we've already sold more than 15
billion songs from the iTunes music
store this course makes it the number
one retailer of music in the world
next is the iBook store you know we
launched the iBook store just a little
more than a year ago already all six
major publishers have signed up and are
providing books to the bookstore our
customers love it our customers have
downloaded more than 130 million books
great and of course there's the App
Store now the size and momentum of the
App Store is really hard to fathom there
are currently more than 425 thousand
apps on the App Store and more than 90
thousand of these were made specifically
for the iPad they take full advantage of
the large touchscreen display and they
make the iPad a better product so we'd
like to thank our developers for these
great apps
now our customers love it our customers
have downloaded more than 14 billion
apps from the App Store and that's in
less than three years it's amazing now
our developers are being well rewarded
for this Apple so far has paid out more
than two and a half billion dollars to
developers building apps for the App
Store thank you
now these apps as you know cover every
genre imaginable there's great travel
apps like this walking tour from Lonely
Planet they're incredibly addictive
games I'd say even mind controlling the
addictive games like tiny wings great
entertainment titles like HBO GO which
lets you take HBO wherever you are and
you can watch it right on your iPad
they're deep apps like mobile mem which
allow physicians to look at CT scans and
PET scans right on their iPad and this
has been fda-approved this next one from
Jepsen's been FAA approved and it allows
pilots to look at the charts and the
maps for airports around the world right
on their iPad and there's great business
apps out there like WebEx which allows
you to have a multi-party video
conference and really hold a virtual
meeting so some great apps out there for
our stores we have more than 225 million
accounts all with credit cards and
one-click purchasing to make it really
easy for our customers to find what they
want purchase it and download it
directly to their device
these stores go with an incredible
lineup of iOS devices let's talk about
the future of iOS and that is iOS 5
iOS 5 is a major release this is
incredible for our developers and for
our customers
for developers there are more than 1500
new api's and some great enhancements to
our tools for our for our users there
are more than 200 new features let me go
ahead and walk you through ten now
number one notifications
I'm sure you're all familiar with
notifications you look something like
this it looks best when giants are on
top so you get scoring alerts you have
alerts to pop up they game to audio
they can also badge the home screen
icons well these have been massively
popular in fact we have already pushed
more than a hundred billion push
notifications is scaled beautifully
we've heard from our customers they're
receiving so money they'd like a better
UI to get them and we agree and so we
have built something that solves some of
the problems in the current one
currently when you get a notification it
interrupts you if you're playing a game
you get a modal alert you have to deal
with that mode alert before you can go
on also in the lock screen you get this
nice list of things that have happened
while your phone's been locked but when
you unlock it
that list isn't persistent there's no
way to get back to that list and go
through those notifications well we have
designed the solution that solves those
issues and goes far beyond it and we
call it notification center Notification
Center is a single place which combines
together all of your notifications you
can get to it at any time from anywhere
on your iPhone or iPad or iPod touch
just by swiping your finger down from
the top to reveal the Notification
Center
so we think it is beautiful it has your
missed calls and voicemails text
messages mail messages scoring alerts
Facebook updates any push notifications
that come from the App Store all end up
right here in Notification Center and
we've even added stocks and weather
right up top now we didn't stop there
notifications are no longer interrupting
so now if you're playing a game and
someone sends you say a text message get
a nice animation from the top it's right
there you can keep on playing your game
and it'll automatically dismiss itself
if you have just tapped on it it would
take you to that app but doesn't matter
because you can always get back to at
any time just by swiping your finger
down from the top we've also improved
the lock screen you can see more
information for notifications here
and one of my favorite features is for
any one of the notifications in the lock
screen you can just slide your finger
across it and it takes you directly to
the app that sent the notification let
me go ahead just show this to you now so
I've got a phone here running iOS 5 you
see more information there now I'm just
going to swipe my finger right across
that text message and it takes me
directly to the messages app and right
into the conversation it's really
convenient now to get to the
Notification Center just swipe my finger
down from the top and there it is
dismiss it by swiping up really nice
animation you can see that we're still
in winter here in San Francisco I get
all of my messages here so text messages
and scoring alerts down at the bottom
here I have some alerts from mlb.com at
bat if I tap on that X button I can just
go ahead and clear that out if I see
another notification like the Facebook
one I tap on it takes me directly to the
Facebook app so it's really convenient
and at anytime again
swipe down from the top and you get back
to Notification Center and that is
Notification Center
number two is newsstand you know I love
reading newspapers and magazines right
on my iphone my iPad and recently we
added subscriptions this makes it easier
for you get all the new issues without
missing anything already
most of the major publishers of
magazines and many of newspapers have
signed up to support subscriptions now
these are incredible titles things like
National Geographic and spin to great
music magazines and of course when you
read these on your iPad you get audio
and video in addition to all the
articles Vanity Fair science magazines
like Popular Mechanics and popular
science Esquire GQ fashion magazines
like Elle The Oprah Magazine tech
magazines like Wired and automobile
magazines and sports magazines The New
Yorker and newspapers new ones like the
daily but also the New York Times the
San Francisco Chronicle Daily Telegraph
and other international papers and we've
now created a single place right in the
app store that combines all of these
newspaper and magazines so you can find
them all in one place when you purchase
them they're automatically downloaded
and placed in the newsstand it's a new
place right on the home screen looks
like it's beautiful news rack in
addition to this we do background
downloads
so if a new issue comes out say of a
newspaper while you're sleeping when you
wake up and pick up your iPad that new
newspaper is already there ready for you
to read it and you can read it offline
on top of this we set the cover to be
the front page of the new newspaper and
we'll set it to be the cover of the new
magazine for magazines
so that is newsstand next is Twitter now
as I'm sure everyone's familiar Twitter
is an incredibly popular service people
send more than a billion tweets per week
and we hear from a lot of our customers
on iPhone and iPad and iPod touch that
they love Twitter and so we want to make
it even easier for all of our customers
to use Twitter on iOS products we're
doing a number of things for this first
we're adding single sign-on so now when
you go to the Settings app its built in
on the iPhone or iPad you can enter your
username and password and now you're
configured for Twitter for any app you
download off the App Store it'll just
say can I use your credentials when you
say yes you're logged in you don't need
to real aughh in every single time so
single sign-on
next we've integrated Twitter in with
many of our apps like camera and photos
so now if you're at a concert you take a
photo you want to tweet that photo just
tap on the action button it's a new
option tweet and it brings up this
beautiful tweet sheet gives you a nice
thumbnail of the photo give you a
countdown of how many characters you
have left to type and you can even
optionally add your location tap on that
and now you've tweeted the photo it's
that simple
in addition to tweeting from photos and
camera you can tweet articles from
Safari websites you can tweet videos
from YouTube and you can tweet about
businesses or locations for maps beyond
all of this we added integration with
contacts now you might have a lot of
contacts that don't have photos but
Twitter may have photos for those people
and so you can use Twitter to
automatically update the photos in your
contact list and even the at user name
for your friends that's Twitter
integration throughout the OS
next is Safari
you know Safari is the best mobile web
browser out there it's also the most
popular in fact nearly two-thirds of all
mobile web browsing is done on Safari
beyond this we took apples Safari engine
and open sourced it and it's the basis
of all web browsing on Android so Safari
engine is the basis of more than 90% of
all web browsing on mobile devices well
iOS 5 we're making Safari even better
we've got some great features the first
is reader Safari reader becomes
available up here as a new button when
you're reading a story on a website if
you just tap on that button we take the
story you're reading and make it front
and center we get rid of all the
distractions set the font size rights
and even if it's a multi-page story so
you'd have to tap through multiple web
pages normally to get to it we put in a
single scrolling story it's really
convenient
on top of that you can now email the
contents of the story before you could
just email the link but now when you
email you get the link plus the contents
in your compose window and all and all
of this works really well on the iPad it
works great on the iPhone as well it's a
perfect size for it sets the font size
right it's really nice to read stories
so that's the for a reader the second
one is reading lists reading lists is a
simple and convenient way for you to
quickly save a story to read it later
just put it in the reading list and when
you add an item to reading list it gets
added to the reading list on all of your
iOS devices and even the reading list on
Safari on Mac and Safari on Windows
so if you don't have time to finish it
here on the iPad you can finish reading
it later on your iPhone and the next
feature is tabbed browsing we have added
full tab browsing and Safari on the iPad
and you know let me just show it to you
alright so here I have my iPad running
iOS 5 I'll launch Safari here and the
first thing you'll see with tabbed
browsing is it is lightning fast to
switch between Windows now just tap on
it and you're there
great now I'm on the DP review site
which is a fantastic review site for
cameras and they have really extensive
reviews in fact you don't have to tap
through many many pages to read the
whole review if I look at this one here
it's a 20 pages long if I tap the reader
button here it loads the entire story up
and reader now I can just scroll through
it gets rid of all the distractions lets
me concentrate just in the content that
is reader
you even see that when it goes between
pages here where you would have had to
you know tap to say next page it
automatically gives you a little page
break so you know when it's going
through those pages now let's say if I
don't have time to finish the story
right now I can just tap the bookmarks
bar item and here I have reading list I
tap plus and now it's added this to my
reading list and again I can go finish
this on Mac on you know on Safari on my
Mac or any of my other iOS devices it's
great and if I really like this and I
want to tweet about it let me show you
the Twitter integration while we're here
by tap tweet brings up the tweet sheet
we do completions of a hit I have a
friend Gary done so I hit at G
automatically fills in the name tap that
and say you know I like this one and I
can optionally add my location tap send
and it's tweeted it's that easy so some
really great Safari enhancements and
Twitter integration throughout
all right next up these reminders you
know all of us are constantly creating
lists of things list of things to do
list of things to buy like a grocery
list some of them have a place
associated like don't forget to walk the
dog when I get home and some have a time
associated say buy concert tickets
Monday at 10:00 a.m. so that's when they
go on sale wouldn't be great if you get
rid of all these scraps of paper and
store all this on your phone but beyond
that if your phone actually reminded you
to do things as opposed to just
statically keeping a list of things well
that's exactly what the reminders app
does on the reminders app you can store
lists of things multiple lists of things
for a trip to San Francisco or birthday
party or a grocery list you can store
dates associated with these reminders so
you'll be reminded on that date you can
also sign location this is really cool I
could set up a reminder to say remind me
to call my wife when I leave the
convention today and it'll set a
geofence
up around Moscone Center and so when I
get in my car to leave it will pop up
and say call
it solves the problem of unliving right
now I promise call in the car you can of
course search through all your reminders
and reminders will sync with iCal on the
Mac using CalDAV and even without look
on Windows using exchange and that is
reminders
next this camera you know the iPhone 4
is widely regarded as having one of the
best cameras on a mobile phone it's also
one of the most popular in fact if you
look at cameras used to take photos and
then post them to Flickr now this is all
cameras not just cameras on phones you
see where the iPhone 4 is it is already
by far the most popular camera on a
phone to take photos and it very soon
will be the most popular camera overall
but we want to make using the camera
even better and that's what we're doing
the first thing we're doing is making it
way faster just get in and take a photo
so now it's there's some moment
happening your kids doing something
really cute you want to capture it you
double-click that home button you get a
new camera icon when you tap on that
camera icon you're brought directly and
immediately to the camera and you're
ready to take a photo now
what's really cool about this is even if
you have a passcode set will take you
right into take a new photo will protect
it and you can't see any previous photos
you've taken or anything else in the
phone without typing your passcode
you can start taking a passcode a
picture immediately and you can even use
the volume up button now to click
and that sound I think people say use
the shutter button to turn your volume
up so in addition to this we've added
optional gridlines so you can use the
rule of thirds to compose your photo or
line it up you can now pinch to zoom
right within the camera and if you hold
your finger over part of the scene now
we'll set the auto exposure and auto
focus lock you can even move it around
you know stick to that
now this is a really advanced feature
when we brought it to the iPhone and
we've made it really easy for everyone
to use
now next once you've taken your great
photos you can now edit them right on
your iPhone and your iPad you do things
like crop and rotate redeye reduction so
if you've taken the photo at left where
the flash has caused a redeye you can
automatically remove that redeye
right on your iPhone or iPad and we even
brought over the one-click enhance that
we pioneered in iPhoto on the Mac and it
brought that to iOS so you can see when
you applied one tap enhance to the right
how the color tones look so much nicer
how it pulls detail out of shadow it's
really nice so some great photo editing
features and really nice camera
enhancements
next is male now male is one of the most
used applications on both the iPhone
iPod and iPod Touch iPad and iPod Touch
and we're making it even better in iOS 5
we're adding rich text formatting so you
can set things as bold italic and
underline you can control the
indentation so you're forwarding
something you can uh ninten it's or
further indent it you can now drag the
addresses between two CC and BCC don't
have to retype them again we've added
support for flagging so you can flag and
unplug this next one has been a
incredibly popular request in addition
to searching from two and subject you
can search the entire contents of all
your messages both the messages on your
phone and all the messages back on the
mail server so search the entire
contents of your messages for the iPad
we added a really nice swipe to inbox
gesture so it makes it really nice to
use this in portrait so you swipe it on
tap on something swipe it off and with
every release of iowa's fought or is we
continue to add more support for our
enterprise customers and one example of
that in iOS 5 is we added support for
s/mime so now I think we've done a
really nice job of this so now if you
have the certificate of someone else you
automatically get this lock icon right
in the addressing field just to show you
this will be encrypted
when sent to the other person let me
just go ahead and give you a demo a few
of these features now alright so first I
can show a simple gesture I just pull on
the inbox right from there so anywhere
you are when your portrait just pull it
on you have to go hunt up and find the
right button for it you can see we're
flagging here so I can tap on that
flagged message a one other feature
we've added is a built in dictionary
throughout the OS as a service now so
before we had a dictionary in the iBooks
app but we now brought that
to the entire OS so all apps from the
App Store can use it so here if I press
down let's say an lychees I don't know
what that is let's say I get a defined
addition to copy tap define there it is
built-in dictionary it's great if I say
respond to this message again I can grab
one of these addresses now just drag it
to BCC dragged it to and rearrange it
it's really nice and easy as one more
feature I want to show you and it's
actually a system-wide feature having do
with a keyboard when we released the
original iPhone we revolutionized the
way people would type on multi-touch
displays and we keep on challenging
ourselves to make that even better we
have a new variant of the keyboard in
iOS 5 for the iPad which we think people
who like to type with their thumbs while
holding it are really going to like in
the bottom right you see the keyboard
button and now it has some grab handles
if I just take those and drag it up it
splits it into two so what it does this
moves the keys closer to your thumbs on
the side so you can you can put it
wherever you want it's really nice and
it's persistent for every app in the
system it just stays where you put it we
want to put it back down just press and
hold the dock and merge it goes back
down to the bottom so even a split
keyboard that's nail number 8 PC free
so we felt these incredible devices the
iPhone the iPad and people get them home
they open up their box and I see this I
said what now we're living in a post PC
world in fact especially with the iPad
we're offering in the post PC world we
have a lot of customers coming to us and
saying I want to buy an iPad is my only
device I don't own a computer I want to
buy an iPhone is my only device my only
actually internet access for I live will
be my iPhone we know we're selling into
a lot of places where the households
just don't have computers and they want
to buy and iOS devices their only device
and that's exactly what we're going to
support an iOS 5 now you take your
iPhone out of the box instead of seeing
this you're going to see this
you can now set up and activate your
device right on the device and you are
ready to go it's that easy
of course there's some other things we
had to do to make this possible software
updates are now over-the-air
so you no longer need to go and plug
into a computer just to update your
software and of course they're now Delta
updates so instead of downloading the
entire OS you just download what's
changed now the next thing we did is we
we looked at all of the apps in the
iPhone iPad iPod Touch and asked
ourselves what are the reasons that
people go back to a computer today and
let's add that functionality right to
iOS so for instance you have to go back
to a computer to create calendars or
delete calendars you can now create and
delete calendars right from iOS you saw
four photos we've added really
significant editing functionality in
there so you can crop rotate one tap
enhance redeye reduction right from
within your iOS device even in mail now
you can create mailboxes and delete
mailboxes right from iOS so we looked at
all of the apps in the I phone and the
iPad added that functionality so now if
you want to cut the cord you can
next is gamecenter iOS is the most
popular gaming platform on the planet
there are more than a hundred thousand
game and entertainment titles in the App
Store and so about nine months ago we
launched Game Center and we did it to
make it even easier for people to find
players to play games against and also
to make it easy for you to compare how
you're doing against your friends well
in just nine months we have 50 million
Game Center users now to put that into
perspective Xbox Live has been around
for about eight years and they have
around 30 million users so Game Center
is very popular and we're making it even
better in iOS 5 to make it more fun and
social we're adding photos so you can
see photos of your friends change your
photos you can now compare yourself
against your friends using achievement
points per game you can see friends of
friends as well you also will get
recommended friends that might be great
people to play some of the games that
you like we've also added game
recommendations so there might be some
really great games out there maybe
they're new that you don't know about
and will help you discover those once
you've discovered a game you like you
can purchase and download it directly
from Game Center now this is great both
for our customers and for our developers
another thing we've done for our
developers is we've added support for
turn-based games right in to the OS
there are some great turn-based games
out there like Scrabble but the
developer had to do all the work for
that and now that's supported right out
of the box in iOS 5 so some really nice
enhancements to Game Center next is
iMessage now I believe we have the best
messaging client out there on the iPhone
it works tremendously well to send text
messages and photos and videos and our
customers love it our iPhone customers
but what about our iPad customers and
our iPod Touch customers they've been
asking us for a messaging solution and
so in iOS 5 we're launching a new
messaging service between all iOS 5
customers
and we call it iMessage so I message
supports the iPhone the iPad and the
iPod touch it does everything you've
come to expect from our messaging app on
the iPhone so you can send text messages
photos videos send contacts do group
messaging everything you come to expect
and we've added some really nice new
features things like delivery receipts
so you can see if it's been delivered to
the other person's device optional read
receipts so you can see if it's been
read this is why I favor a typing
indication so you can tell now if
someone starts typing and they're
responding to you you know you're about
to get that message I messages are
pushed to all your devices so if you
start a conversation on your iPad and
later pick up your iPhone you can pick
up right where you left off with all the
context of that conversation to date is
supported over both 3G and Wi-Fi and
everything is sent encrypted over the
where over the over the air and I like
to just give you a demo of iMessage now
to do so I also like to invite up jaws
vice president of product marketing to
help me hey da Scott thanks for having
me
absolutely we don't mind on the play
game though playing the game okay try
not the bottom right here frolic
marketing so he's on the iPhone on the
Left I'm on my iPad on the right hand
side I go ahead and launch messages here
so here I have a conversation go with
jaws normally we don't stand next to
each other we have these conversations
so most I've talked to you all week
let's grab lunch after the show no okay
so when I send this to them you'll
notice as he plays the game it comes in
right at the top and you can keep on
playing the game so it's not
interrupting him does his lovely job
playing I'm on a roll don't bother man
but at anytime he can get right back to
that message Oh at any time I think this
might be good time so it just by pulling
down town that takes him right to this
now as he starts typing see on my side
where there's the three dots of the
balloon that lets me know he's currently
responding well check maybe some other
messages while he's doing so so then
when he sends the message you see where
it says he gets a little delivered it
already knows it's been delivered right
to my device and when I tap on his
message it sends a read receipt saying
rad 11:15 a.m. he knows I've read it so
read restates three
we can also send high-quality photos and
videos let me go ahead and choose a
photo here alright maybe we have a
picnic by the bridge that's so sweet
[Music]
send it a little picture again you can
tell from the dots and his side that I'm
composing it right now send it off and
again we go over Wi-Fi as well as 3G
sends it over again he gets it nice high
quality and the entire transmission is
encrypted over-the-air and again I'm on
my iPad so it supports iPad iPod Touch
and iPhone thanks jealous can't wait for
lunch
so I message and we're actually building
this on the push notification system
we've built so we know how to scale this
we have incredible features here in iOS
5 notification system which is just
really nice newsstand makes it even
better to read your newspapers and
magazines right on your iPad or iPhone
great Twitter integration a new
reminders app you can be PC free if you
want and the new iMessage application
and these are just ten of the more than
200 new user features there's really
something for everyone in iOS 5 there's
other things like airplay mirroring you
can now mirror your entire iPad to write
to your television wirelessly using
Apple TV
Wi-Fi sync to iTunes before you had
exactly before before you had to go back
and plug into your computer to sync and
now when you are charging at night let's
say your iOS device will automatically
find iTunes over Wi-Fi and sync with it
and before it sinks it'll back itself up
so you automatically get backed up every
single day there's also some really nice
new multitasking gestures so you can
just flick right between your apps it's
really nice we're not only is there's
something for every one of our customers
there's something for every one of our
developers some great new development
tools including significant enhancements
to xcode instruments in the simulator
even core image we brought over the
powerful core image framework from Mac
OS 10 to iOS this allows developers to
do complex image operations like redeye
reduction face detection right from
within their apps so you're asking
yourself when are you getting it and the
answer is we are giving a developer seed
to you today
this is going to be great for the
conference as you learn about all the
new api's than all the sessions this
week you can go and use those api's
immediately using your seed and iOS five
will ship to all of our customers this
fall
iOS 5 will support the same devices that
we supported with our last software
update so that's the iPhone 3GS and
iPhone 4 all the iPads iPad and iPad 2
and the third and fourth generation iPod
Touch and that is iOS 5
and that is the second of the software
products we want to tell you about today
to tell you about the third I like to
turn it back over to Steve
so you like everything so far well I'll
try not to blow it so I get to talk
about iCloud we've been working on this
for some time now and we're really
excited about it about ten years ago we
had one of our most important insights
and that was that the PC was going to
become the digital hub for your digital
life what does that mean well it meant
that that's where you were going to put
your digital photos where else were you
going to put them your digital video off
your digital camcorder and of course
your music right you were going to
acquire it in the device or potentially
on your Mac and you were going to
basically sync it to the Mac and
everything was going to work fine and it
did for the better part of 10 years but
it's broken down in the last few years
why well because the devices have
changed they now all have music they now
all have photos they now all have video
and so if I acquire a song I buy it
right on my iPhone I want to get that to
my other devices right I pick up my iPad
it doesn't have that song on it so I
have to sync my iphone to my Mac then I
have to sync my other devices to the Mac
to get that song but then they've
deposited some photos on the Mac so I
have to sync the iPhone again with the
Mac to get those photos and keeping
these devices in sync is driving us
crazy
so we got a great solution for this
problem
and we think this solution is our next
big insight which is we're going to
demote the PC in the Mac to just be a
device just like an iPhone an iPad or
iPod touch and we're going to move the
digital hub the center of your digital
life into the cloud because all these
new devices have communications built
into them they can all talk to the cloud
whenever they want and so now if I get
something on my iPhone it sent up to the
cloud immediately let's say I take some
pictures with it
those pictures are in the cloud and they
are now pushed down to my devices
completely automatically and now
everything is in sync with me not even
having to think about it I don't even
have to take the devices out of my
pocket I don't have to be near my Mac or
PC now some people think the cloud is
just a hard disk in the sky right and
you take a bunch of stuff and you put it
in your Dropbox or your I disk or
whatever and it transfers it up to the
cloud and stores and then you drag
whatever you want back out on your other
devices we think it's way more than that
and we call it iCloud now iCloud stores
your content in the cloud and wirelessly
pushes it to all your devices so it
automatically uploads it stores it and
automatically pushes it to all your
other devices but also it's completely
integrated with your apps and so
everything happens automatically and
there's nothing new to learn it just all
works it just works
now you might ask why should I believe
them they're the ones that brought me
MobileMe it wasn't our finest hour let
me just say that but we learned a lot
now the three core apps in MobileMe were
contacts calendar and mail three things
we'd obviously like kept up to date
we've thrown them away we've reacted and
rewritten them from the ground up to be
iCloud apps and we've put them on all of
our devices so as an example in contacts
when I make a new contact on my iPhone
it's automatically brought up to the
cloud where it's stored on the cloud
right the truth is on the cloud and then
it's automatically pushed down to my
other devices so they're all in sync
it's that easy
I just update a contact on my iPhone and
don't even think about it and that
contact is updated on all my other
devices and if I change it on any device
it's updated on all devices wirelessly
automatically without me doing a thing
so that's contacts here's calendars
works much the same way I make a new
calendar event for my iPhone it's stored
in the cloud and it's pushed to my other
devices pretty cool
we've also added calendar sharing so as
an example if I'm sharing a few
calendars with my wife school and soccer
calendars let's say right and I add a
new calendar for a teacher parent
conference on my phone it's again
automatically pushed up to the cloud and
automatically push to my wife's iPhone
if she adds
the key adds an appointment for a soccer
game again goes up to the cloud and back
to my iPhone it's that simple
and so calendars has it stores your
calendars in the cloud changes on any
device or push to all your devices and
we have shared calendars we think you're
going to love the new calendars it just
works and then we have mail mail was in
the best shape of all but it's even
better now we give you a mail account it
at me calm your new messages again are
pushed to all your devices and like we
use through your inbox and folders are
all kept up to date on all devices
so that's mail and no ads
we build products that we want for
ourselves too and we just don't want to
ads so we can't get there so these are
the three apps that form the core of
mobile me we used to sell them for a
subscription price of $99 annually as of
today this product ceases to exist and
those three apps are out of the food
but we didn't stop there we've got three
more apps that we've brought into the
iCloud universe the first is of course
the App Store the App Store you've
bought a lot of apps so far and you can
buy them of course directly on your
devices
maybe the app you want isn't on the
device you've got with you so for all
your purchase history now you can see it
on all your devices even if the apps not
there and we've added this button here
which is download from the cloud and if
you want that app on that device you
just push that button and that app is
automatically sent to that device right
and there's no extra charge
no extra charge now we've done that for
your purchase history what about four
devices you buy in the future well four
devices when you buy them in the future
you want to buy Yelp let's say the cloud
downloads it to all your devices again
at no extra charge all automatically
so that's what we're doing with the App
Store iBooks same thing you've got your
purchase history of all the books you've
bought on any device you want to get it
on your iPhone se just push the button
it downloads to that device when you buy
a new iBook let's say you want to buy
this book here the wave it downloads it
to all your devices now and if you're
reading it on one device let's say
you're reading it on your iPad and
you've just got to run you get to a page
you bookmark that page that bookmark is
sent up to the cloud and stored and
again push to all your other devices so
maybe you can read another the rest of
the chapter as an example on the train
to work it all just works
and now back up we talked about being PC
free Scott talked about how you can
wirelessly backup your devices daily to
your PC or your Mac but let's do it to
the cloud as well for those people that
want to be completely PC free so we've
added wireless backup to the cloud and
basically once daily we're going to
backup a lot of your important contents
to the cloud if you ever get a new phone
and have to replace a phone you
literally type in your Apple ID and
password and everything will be loaded
onto that phone automatically in wires
so we automatically do daily backups to
iCloud over Wi-Fi
we backup your purchased music apps and
books we backup your camera roll with
your photos and videos we backup your
device settings and we backup your app
data all to the cloud so that is backup
and those are three other apps that come
with iCloud but we couldn't stop there
and so we have a final three apps that
are amazing
the most inventive part of iCloud I
think and I'd love to tell you about the
first one is documents in the cloud so
if I'm on my iPad and I create a Pages
document right I create a Pages document
and it automatically uploads it and
stores it in the cloud when I close that
document completely automatically and it
then pushes it to all the devices that I
have pages on so I can get the document
between my devices and we have put that
into Pages Numbers and Keynote as a
matter of fact the versions we just
released last week have this in there
and to demonstrate what this is like
with I work I'd love to invite Roger
Rosner who's our VP of I work up to give
us a quick demo
thank you Steve alright let's take a
look at how I work and iCloud will work
together let's say you're working on a
keynote presentation on your iPad making
a beautiful presentation with all those
awesome keynote graphic effects and
animations but you're away from home you
didn't bring your iPad with you and you
run into somebody who wants to see your
presentation well the good news is last
week we shipped I work for iPhone and
even better for anybody who bought and
iWork app for your iPad you can download
that app for your iPhone at no
additional charge so let's fire up
keynote on this phone this is the first
time we've run it here so it's going to
say hi then it's going to say do you
want to use iCloud we say yes and
immediately it sees all your keynote
presentations that you've been working
on in the cloud and starts to download
them in the background to your iPhone so
I'll open this one we were just looking
at and as you can see it's all there and
even remembered what slide we were
looking at and if I want to I can just
hit play play it right on my iPhone and
I put exactly zero effort into getting
that file over here pretty neat
of course all the iWork apps use iCloud
so let's take a look at pages and you
know imagine you're out and you you're
inspired to make some changes to a
document you've been working on so I'm
going to move this graphic over here
maybe I just took a photograph that I
think would be great to spruce up my
cover page so I'll go to my camera roll
I'd serve my graphic use alignment
guides to place it and I'm done and I
stick the phone in my pocket and I
forget about it and in the background
iCloud is grabbing all those changes and
then immediately pushing them back down
to my iPad so when I get home pick up
the iPad fire up pages you can see in
the upper left my document thumbnails
already been updated
and there are all my edits absolutely no
effort on my part and that is how I work
works with iCloud I think you're going
to like it
thank you thanks Roger
and documents in the cloud really
completes our iOS document storage story
- in other words a lot of us have been
working for 10 years to get rid of the
file system so the user didn't have to
worry about it when you try to teach
teach somebody how to use a Mac the
easiest of all computers to use
everything's going along fine until you
hit the file system and then difficulty
is staggering for most people so we've
made it on the iOS devices to where you
don't ever have to think about it the
app manages the presentation of its own
documents just like mail manages the
presentation of its own messages but the
piece that we weren't finished with was
how do we move those documents around to
different devices and documents in the
cloud solves that problem for us apps
can store documents in iCloud iCloud
pushes those documents to a user's
devices automatically
the documents update on all devices when
changed on any device and we are
releasing
[Applause]
it's really easy to tie your apps into
iCloud's storage system and again you
can have complex documents apps like
pages or we've got another storage
facility for key value data so as an
example if you've got an app that just
track stocks you can just update the key
value pairs and we'll store that in the
cloud as well so documents and key value
data works across all iOS devices and
Macs and PCs to
so we think this is going to be pretty
big and that is documents in the cloud
this next one is maybe my favorite one
and it's called Photo Stream and it's
going to bring the cloud to photos how
many times have we taken photos on our
iPhone maybe of our kids in the
afternoon and wanted when we got home to
share them on an iPad and have to go
through the process of moving them over
wouldn't it be great if by the time I
got home they were already there on the
iPad well that's what Photo Stream is
going to do for us across all of our
devices so again I take photos on any
device puts it in the camera roll and
that will be automatically uploaded to
the cloud where it's stored and
automatically downloaded to all my other
devices including in this case a Mac and
so I've got my photos on my iPad just
waiting for me when I get home now in
addition I can import photos right into
iPhoto as an example on the Mac it'll
upload those to the cloud and do exactly
the same thing with them by pushing them
down to all my other devices so it's
apps that I its photos that I take or
photos that I import and we built this
right into the apps I hope you've seen
that as we've gone through this we've
built this right into the app so there's
nothing new to learn
so photo stream on the iPads photo app
we've built it right in right next to
albums we have a button called Photo
Stream you push it and you're looking at
the photo stream it's that simple
there's not a separate app that you have
to go learn it's right there in your
Photos app it's right there in your
Photos app on your iPhone it's just
right there with all your other albums
there you go
Photo Stream
on the map on the map we built it right
into iPhoto and so it's right there on
the side your photo stream and on a PC
they don't have a Photos app so we use
the pictures folder right in addition to
that we even built it in to Apple TV so
Apple TV Apple TV talks directly over
the internet directly to the photo
stream servers doesn't even go through
your PC talks directly the photo stream
servers so you can watch the photos
right on your Apple TV so one of the
problems we faced was it will photos are
large and will use up all the memory on
your devices there are also large
they'll consume vast amounts of storage
in our server farms so we've came up
with a great scheme we're going to store
photos on your devices we're going to
store the last thousand photos right
let's store the last thousand and any
photos you want to keep permanently just
move them into an album and they'll stay
forever but they'll be parading by you
the last thousand photographs on your
Mac or PC because we have more storage
will store all of them you can get rid
of them by just deleting them but we'll
store all of them and on the server will
store them for 30 days which is more
than enough time for all your devices to
connect and automatically download those
photos so we think we've got a great
system here that's going to move our
photos around among all of our devices
even Apple TV so that when I take a
photo anywhere I can view it on all my
other devices we think this is going to
be really exciting to demonstrate this
I've asked Eddy Cue or VP of Internet
services to come out and give us a demo
of photo stream
thank you yep
so I want to take some photos to start
with now I love cars and I happen to
have brought one of my favorite ones
with me here today and here it is and
we're going to go to our my iPhone and
launch the camera app Lightning McQueen
is looking good
I love the headlights and now these
photos are on my iPhone but let's go
look at my iPad now we've built Photo
Stream right into the Photos app so
right next to albums this photo stream
and there is the pictures I just
I didn't have to learn anything new at
all and if I want to save them
permanently on my iPad I can just select
them and move them to an existing album
or even create a new album that's it
now these photos aren't just on my iPad
they're on all of my devices let's move
over to the Mac where I've got iPhoto
running and we've built again Photo
Stream right in and there are the photos
I just took so now when I take a photo
on one of my devices they automatically
appear on all of my devices without
having to do anything at all it's that
simple
and that's Photo Stream
okay okay not awesome
so photos you tape or import upload to
iCloud iCloud pushes them to all your
devices works over Wi-Fi its iCloud
stores each photo for 30 days which is
plenty enough time for all the devices
to be connected devices store the last
thousand photos and again you can just
drag them to an album they stay forever
and Macs and PCs store all photos so
we're really really pleased with Photo
Stream we think you're going to like it
a lot last but not least is iTunes in
the cloud
you know it's the same old story right
about I buy something on my iPhone right
wolf and and it's not on my other
devices
I grab my ipod and I go to listen to
that song I bought yesterday my iPhone
it ain't there well the first thing
we've done again is for the songs you've
already bought we've added a purchase
button that shows you your entire
purchase history of all the iTunes songs
you bought on any device you can look at
it by all songs or recent songs or you
can look at it by artist so I'm going to
pick Bob Dylan here and I can download
any of these albums that I've bought on
iTunes to this device just by pushing
that cloud download button or I could go
in to one of them and just download
whatever songs I want to this device so
anything I bought I can now download to
any of my devices at no additional
charge which is
this is the first time we've seen this
in the music industry no charge for
multiple downloads two different devices
and for the future I flick one switch to
on and now any song I buy on any device
again will automatically be downloaded
to all my devices so when I want to buy
a song in this case in a Dell song it
will push it to all of my devices so to
give us a demo of that again I'd like to
invite idiot thank you thanks Steve so
I'm on my iphone and I want to listen to
a song I'd previously purchased on
iTunes but it's not in the music library
on this device well now I can easily
just go to the iTunes Music Store
there's a new purchase tab right on the
bottom and now I'm seeing all of the
purchases I've ever done on iTunes I can
even look at them the songs that I had
that are not on this device that I
previously purchased by just tapping
that button now I'm going to look for a
Foo Fighters song I think it's called
the walk
and there it is and what just tapping
the iCloud button it downloads to my
iPhone again because I'd previously
purchased this song it's downloading at
no additional cost let's go ahead and
play it
just finishing downloading
now that's great but I think's in the
cloud is even better let's see what
happens when I purchase a new song and
if we can bring up my iPad I'm going to
go ahead and launch our new music player
in iOS 5 and on my iPhone I'm going to
go back to the iTunes store I want to
buy a new song and I want to look at the
Bruno Mars's new album I know he has a
hit song I think it's called the lazy
lazy song that's it
we can preview it that's definitely it
now I'm going to buy it but before I do
notice on my iPad I don't have any Bruno
Mars songs at all so we're going to go
and buy and it's now downloading to my
iPhone and in addition there's the Bruno
Mars song
and of course what so now when I buy a
song on one of my devices it
automatically downloads to all of my
devices without having to sync or do any
work at all and that's iTunes in the
cloud
thank you very much is this awesome
so music purchase from iTunes high
quality 256 kilobits AAC and you can
have up to 10 devices downloading your
music to all of them every time you buy
it on any device iTunes in the cloud so
these 9 apps constitute iCloud and they
are all free we want we want every user
to take advantage of these and we know
if we make them free that they'll they
will and we want people to see what
these devices can really do and what the
software can really do so we're making
it free and we're very excited about it
so that's iCloud it stores your content
and wirelessly pushes it to all your
devices and it's integrated with your
apps so everything happens automatically
so a competitor that doesn't own the
apps or doesn't have great developers to
integrate with their apps they can never
do this they can never make it so it
just works and that's what we've done
here so how do you get it well when you
upgrade your phone or buy a new phone
with iOS 5 on it all you have to do is
type in your Apple ID and password and
that's it and you'll go to switch that's
iCloud you can turn it off if you'd like
it would be turned on by default and
you're up and running we're also going
to give everybody five gigabytes of free
storage for mail documents and backup
and that's even more than it sounds like
because we're not counting purchase
music apps or books towards that five
gigabytes
nor are we counting photostream
towards that five gigabytes so when can
you get your hands on this today we're
going to get you all a developer beta
today and also today we're going to make
something available to end-users which
is the iTunes in the cloud portion and
it runs on iOS 4.3 it will run on all
the supported platforms when we ship it
this fall but today we're going to put
it out for 4.3 as a beta and everyone
can get their hands on it and run it on
their existing existing iPhone 4s so we
think this is going to be really
exciting and of course we ship iCloud
concurrent with shipping iOS 5 this fall
so that is iCloud
now there's one more thing small thing
it pertains to iTunes in the cloud as
you recall iTunes in the cloud is just
for the music that you've purchased from
the iTunes Store now at 14 billion songs
15 billion excuse me that's a lot of
songs out there
they've been purchased from iTunes Music
Store but you may have some that you
ripped yourself and there's 3 ways you
can deal with that one
you can sync your new devices over Wi-Fi
or cable cable and you only have to sync
them once just to get that music on them
and then you can rely on iCloud to take
care of getting all your new purchases
off iTunes onto that device or if it's
just a few songs you love you don't
leave behind you can buy those songs
that you'll miss on iTunes we're going
to offer a third way which is called
iTunes Match what is iTunes Match well
iTunes Match uses the fact that we've
got 18 million songs now in the iTunes
music store and the chances are awfully
good that we've got the songs in our
store that you've ripped and so we wrote
software to scan those CDs the rip scene
on iTunes music and match it up with
those songs we have in the store right
and so we can give that music the same
benefits as music purchase from iTunes
and it takes just minutes not weeks if
you have to upload your whole library
into some Lockland the sky that
literally takes weeks this takes minutes
because we're scanning and matching your
library so we don't need to upload that
that large part of your library and the
few songs that remain well we'll upload
them but with 18 million songs are most
likely to have what's your back
in addition iTunes Match will upgrade
those songs that match the 256 kilobits
AAC
I
and iTunes Match cost just $24.99 a year
so if you've got a bunch of music if
you've got a bunch of music that you
didn't buy from iTunes you can get all
the benefits of the cloud service and
more in terms of upgrading your music
for $24.99 a year now if you look and
compare that to some competitors let's
just look at Apple and Amazon and Google
your kind of get surprised because again
the library in the cloud we scan and
match the other guys you've got to
upload your whole music library again
it's going to take weeks music apps on
your Mac and PC well you're stuck with a
web app instead of iTunes upgrade to 256
kilobits per second the other guys
aren't upgrading you at all the annual
price for 5,000 songs we're $24.99
Amazon charges you $50 for the storage
and google hasn't announced their
pricing yet even at 20,000 songs we
charge one flat price Amazon is up to
$200 for the storage and Google has an
announcer present
most of our customers won't need this
because they bought a lot of their music
on iTunes but for those that do
it's an industry-leading offering let's
put it that way
so that's iTunes Match and it goes along
with free iTunes in the cloud
and that's what it is
now if you don't think we're serious
about this you're wrong this is our
third data center that we just completed
it's in Maidan North Carolina this is
what it looks like it's rather large
[Music]
it's as eco-friendly as you can make a
data center with modern technology and
we're pretty proud of it just to give
you a feel for its size see those two
little dots on the roof those are two
people right there so it's a pretty
large place and and it's a full of stuff
a little expensive stuff and we are
ready we think for for our customers to
start using iCloud and we can't wait to
get it in their hands so I cloud is the
third thing we want to talk about today
I hope you like all the three things
that we've unveiled this morning and
again we've got a great week plan for
you with 5200 attendees over 120
sessions over 100 hands-on labs and over
a thousand Apple engineers here all week
so please ask us for any help you need
that's why we're here so go at it have a
great week and thank you very much for
coming
[Applause]
you