With the introduction
of the revolutionary iPhone X
and Apple TV 4K,
the video experience
is taken to a whole new level
with the addition of support
for high dynamic range video.
With HD, you only see
16 million colors.
But with HDR,
you see one billion colors.
HDR allows content creators
to use a much richer
and vibrant color palette,
which results in unbelievable
and stunning image quality.
To better understand
how HDR works,
let's first take a look
at the evolution
in color capabilities.
Here is a representation
of the visible color spectrum.
With the introduction
of HD in 1990,
the color space was defined in
ITU Rec 709
and covered about 36 percent
of the visible spectrum.
But, a lot has changed
since 1990,
and since then, the P3
color space was introduced.
This color space is widely
supported across our platforms
for all types of app content.
Then in 2012,
Recommendation 2020
was introduced
to define the color space
for Ultra High-Definition
television,
which offers a much wider
color space
that covers more than 75 percent
of the visible spectrum.
Video content can now be
delivered to supported devices
in any of these
three color spaces,
enabling far more realistic
and rich color reproduction.
But, the color space itself
isn't the whole story.
The luminance range and settings
of the target display
is also extremely important
and impacts how a given color
is going to be perceived.
This combination of color space
and luminance range
is often described
as the color volume,
with the luminance values
on a logarithmic scale.
With standard
dynamic range content,
it is assumed that displays
offer a peak luminance
of 100 nits,
yielding a relatively modest
color volume.
However, HDR formats
are designed to support displays
capable of up to 10,000 nits of
peak luminance,
yielding a much richer
color volume
for content creators
to work with.
To further understand
the impact of luminance,
let's take a look
at a 100 percent red square
in the P3 color space.
If the brightness setting of the
display is at about 50 percent,
the red square
might look something like this.
However, if the brightness
of the display is turned up,
the very same RGB value
looks quite different
and more intense.
Similarly, if the brightness
is turned down,
it looks much more dull.
As you can see
in this illustration,
simply utilizing the RGB values
without having control
or context of the luminance
of the display
leads to vastly different
color perception by the viewer.
This also doesn't
take into account
other influencing factors
such as the ambient light level
or the color temperature
of the ambient light.
Another key goal of HDR
is to help improve
consistency in playback
across different displays.
In SDR video, the target display
is assumed to be capable
of up to approximately
100 nits of peak brightness.
However, the actual capabilities
of modern displays
far exceeds this value,
and so each display
then attempts
to interpolate the appropriate
brightness levels
to match its own
luminance range.
This leads to
all kinds of variance
in the appearance
of a given video
across different displays,
and in many cases,
a very loose interpretation
of the original artistic intent.
Now that you have
a basic understanding
of the key elements
of color and luminance,
and some of the goals of HDR,
let's dig into the types
of HDR video that we support.
We support two HDR standards:
Dolby Vision and HDR10.
These two formats share
some common principles,
but also differ in many ways.
One of the commonalities
between the formats
is how the luminance values
are encoded.
Because the human eye
is more sensitive
in dark ranges
than light ranges,
the luminance values
are encoded on a curve,
so that greater detail in darks
can be encoded using
the limited bits available.
In SDR, the gamma curve
was relatively shallow,
but this was sufficient
for the assumed peak target
display luminance of 100 nits.
For HDR, a new
luminance encoding curve
has been introduced.
Known as
the Perceptual Quantizer,
it can better map these
perceptible luminance changes
across the broader,
10,000 nit range.
This curve,
described in SMPTE ST 2084,
allows for even
smoother gradation
of dark luminance values,
yielding a far better experience
for the viewer.
This curve is utilized
by both Dolby Vision and HDR10.
In HDR10,
a static set of metadata
is included in the video stream.
This metadata includes
information about the display
on which the content
was originally mastered,
such as its effective
color gamut, white point,
and luminance range.
It also includes information
about the content itself,
namely the peak
and average luminance levels.
This metadata can then
be used by the target display
to tone map the content
to the output capabilities
of the display.
With HDR10,
the metadata is applied
to the entire length
of the program.
Dolby Vision gives you
even more control,
allowing for metadata to
be conveyed dynamically
on a scene-by-scene,
or even frame-by-frame basis.
This way, the available
luminance range of the display
can be optimized
throughout a program
that might include both very
dark and very bright scenes.
The format also carries
a much broader metadata set,
further enabling
the target display
to perform much more detailed
tone mapping
and detail management.
Finally, Dolby operates
a certification program
to ensure that each Dolby Vision
capable display is consistent,
so content will always
be displayed as intended.
For more information
on authoring your HDR content
for delivery
to supported devices,
please visit our HTTP
Live Streaming developer page