iPhone X's super retina display
gives you more space
to display content
and create
deeply immersive experiences.
This video will help you
get started
designing apps and games
that look and feel great
across all iOS devices.
First, let's review
some key aspects
of the new display.
iPhone X 's display
has a 3x image scale factor.
When producing and delivering
image assets,
we recommend using PDFs because
they're resolution-independent
and may significantly reduce
the size of your app.
When rasterized images
are needed,
be sure to include
both 2x and 3x resolutions
in your app's asset catalog.
To streamline
your production process,
we suggest using
the templates included
in the Apple UI Design
Resources.
They're available to download
on the Resources page
of the Apple Human
Interface Guidelines.
The iPhone X's
display dimensions
are 375 points wide
by 812 points tall.
On a 3x display,
this equals 1125 by 2436 pixels.
375 points is the same width
as the 4.7 inch displays
of iPhone 6,
iPhone 7 and iPhone 8.
So there shouldn't
be any difference
in the amount
of information presented
along the narrower dimension
of these devices.
The 812 point height
is 145 points taller
than a 4.7 inch display.
This additional height
provides about 20 percent
more space for content.
Of course,
the most notable feature
of the super retina display
is its shape.
The display follows
the design of the product
around all four rounded corners
for a symmetrical look.
Updating your app to work
on the new display
involves extending
visual elements
to fill the display's view port,
while also keeping controls
and critical information
from getting clipped
in the corners
or covered
by the sensor housing.
On iPhone X,
people access the app switcher
and the Home screen
by swiping up anywhere
along the bottom edge
of the display.
An indicator
at the bottom of the screen
offers a hint
about this interaction.
This indicator is displayed
over your app's interface.
You'll need to account for this
when designing your app.
If your app uses UIKit controls
and auto-layout,
designing and developing
for iPhone X
and our other devices
should be straightforward.
Standard UIKit elements
such as navigation bars,
tables, and collection views,
automatically adjust
when viewed on iPhone X.
Navigation bars,
tab bars, and toolbars
are positioned
and scaled appropriately
on all iOS devices.
The navigation bar's
background material
is extended
to the display's top edge,
and the background material
of the tab bar and toolbar
is extended to the bottom,
while the elements they contain
are positioned
to prevent underlapping
or clipping
by other elements.
In landscape orientation,
table views will span
the full width of the display,
while the table cell's
content view is inset.
If your app uses auto-layout,
views can automatically adapt
to the iPhone X's
larger display size.
For iOS 11, a new layout guide
was added to auto-layout
called a Safe Area layout
guide.
The Safe Area layout guide
helps avoid
underlapping system UI elements
when positioning content
and controls.
On iPhone 8,
the Safe Area
is the same size as the viewport
if no bars are visible.
If a status bar is visible,
the safe area's top edge
is lowered
to account for
the status bar's height.
The Safe Area is further inset
to accommodate a navigation bar
and toolbar or tab bar.
On iPhone X,
the Safe Area layout guide
provides an additional benefit.
It's inset from the top
and bottom of the screen edges
in portrait orientation,
even when no bars
are visible on screen.
This helps you to prevent
interface elements
fromgetting clipped or covered
by positioning them away
from the sensor housing,
the display's
rounded corners,
and the Home indicator.
In landscape orientation,
the Safe Area is inset
from the sides of the screen
and the Home indicator
for the same reason.
So, for example,
the width of the content view
in these table row cells
is constrained by the Safe Area
to keep them from underlapping
the sensor housing
or getting clipped
by the display's
rounded corners.
And the table's top edge
has been inset
to avoid underlapping
the navigation bar.
On iPhone 8, where occlusion
and clipping is not an issue,
the Safe Area width
matches the display's width
and the table is allowed to run
edge-to-edge.
You'll notice
that text and controls
are actually inset
from the safe area.
This inset is achieved
using another layout guide
called a layout margin.
Layout margins provide
consistent content margins
across apps
and help you to align content
to other controls
like navigation bar buttons.
Even if you're not using
auto-layout,
UIView provides
the Safe Area insets
and layout margin values
as properties.
Now, one final note
about auto-layout.
iPhone 6, 7, 8, and X
all belong in
the compact width size class.
This essentially means
that your app's layout
should be consistent
on all these devices.
If your app
has custom controls
or non-standard layouts,
you may need to make
slight alterations
to your app's interface
to work well on iPhone X.
There are two aspects to this.
First, your app or game
should always fill the display
that it runs on.
Placing black bars at the top
or bottom of the screen
makes your app
feel small, cramped,
and inconsistent
with other apps on iPhone X.
When designing
background graphics,
or rendering background scenes,
keep in mind
that iPhone X's display
has a different aspect ratio
than a 4.7 inch display.
Background graphics designed
for iPhone 8's 16:9 aspect ratio
will be cropped along the left
and right edges on iPhone X
if they're scaled to fill,
or letter-boxed
if scaled to fit.
Similarly, background graphics
designed for iPhone X,
will either be cropped
along the top and bottom edges
on iPhone 8
or pillar-boxed.
It's best compose images
so that critical visual
information remains visible
regardless of the display's
aspect ratio.
The second part of updating
your layout involves insetting,
or repositioning interactive
elements and key information.
Any element that's positioned
too close to the viewport's
edges or corners
may get clipped
by the display's rounded corners
or covered
by the sensor housing.
So be sure to inset controls
and other elements
to avoid this.
Again, Safe Area layout
guides and layout margins
should be used for determining
proper inset values.
It's also worth noting
that controls placed
along a device's edge
could be more difficult to reach
depending on how
the device is held.
Insetting controls can make
interacting with them faster
and more comfortable.
Visual elements
that appear tucked into corners
or under screen edges
may need to be revised
since insetting them
probably won't look right.
In some cases,
a different visual treatment
may be necessary.
Please also note
that status bars are taller
on iPhone X.
Content views
that have been inset
by a fixed point value
will have their top edges
covered by the status bar.
On iPhone X, the status bar
no longer changes height
when background tasks,
like a phone call
or location tracking,
are running.
This helps create a more
consistent user experience
regardless
of the status bar style.
On iPhone X, the status bar
occupies an area of the screen
that your app
probably won't fully utilize.
If you have hidden
the status bar
to claim more space
for your app's interface,
you may want to reconsider
if that's still necessary.
Now, one quick note
about landscape orientation.
Most apps look and function best
when controls and visual
information are centered.
Asymmetrical layouts
that shift around
based on how
the device is rotated
will lead to an inconsistent
user experience
and can undermine
people's ability
to build muscle memory.
Finally,
a few key considerations
related to the indicator
that let's people know
they can swipe up
to access the app switcher
and Home Screen.
Because this interaction
is core to the experience
of using an iOS device,
the indicator should always
be clearly visible.
To help accomplish this,
iOS dynamically adjusts
the indicator's appearance
to maintain sufficient contrast
relative to the background.
The indicator appears dark
against lighter backgrounds,
and light
against darker backgrounds.
When designing
your app's interface
to work well
with the Home indicator,
it's best to avoid
placing interface elements
in close proximity
to the indicator.
Simply leave some negative
space around the indicator
by placing all non-scrollable
content within the safe area.
It's also not desirable
to draw special attention
to the indicator
through visual adornments
such as brackets,
bezels, or other means.
As mentioned earlier,
people will access
the app switcher and Home screen
by swiping upward
from the bottom edge
of the display.
In most cases,
swipe gestures tend to occur
in the center of the display,
so this interaction
is unlikely to conflict
with interactions in your app.
However, if your app or game
encourages people
to swipe along the very
bottom of the display,
you may want
to turn on edge protection
for the bottom edge
of the display.
This will give the indicator
a more subtle appearance
and change it's behavior
so that two swipes
are required to exit your app.
The first swipe, or drag,
lifts the indicator
and enables the control.
While swiping a second time
allows people
to exit your app or game.
Because edge protection leads to
an inconsistent user experience,
it should be used only
when it's absolutely necessary.
Unlike swipes,
tapping the bottom edge
of the display
will only affect
your app or game.
For example,
tapping a table row cell
has the same result
whether or not
it's behind the indicator.
Vertically scrollable views,
such as tables
or collection views,
should extend all the way
to the bottom of the display
rather than being constrained
by the Safe Area.
Lastly, you can enable
an auto-hide behavior
when presenting
full screen visual content.
Auto-hide causes
the indicator to fade out
if the display hasn't been
touched for a few seconds
and fade back in
when the display is touched.
Use auto-hide sparingly
and only for passive experiences
where people are unlikely
to touch the display frequently.
OK, for more iPhone X
design guidance,
please visit the
Apple Human Interface Guidelines
at developer.apple.com/design.
And while you're there,
download the latest version
of the iOS Apple UI
Design Resources.
We've updated the Sketch
and Photoshop templates
for iPhone X,