As an app developer,
it's critical that
you know exactly
what your app
is storing on disk,
where everything
is being stored,
and why it's needed.
The best way to stay
on top of these details
is to take inventory of
what your app actually stores.
To get started, build and
run your app on a device,
then exercise all the features
that will store things on disk.
Once you've done this,
it's time to look at what
actually got stored, and where.
Use the Devices and Simulators
window in Xcode
to extract your app's container
so that we can see what's in it.
Select your device
in the column on the left,
then select your app
in the Installed Apps list.
And using the gear icon,
choose Download Container,
and save it on your Mac.
In the Finder,
Control-click on the xcappdata
file that was downloaded.
Choose Show Package Contents,
and go into the App Data folder
and start taking inventory.
Look through the directories
to see what got stored
in each one.
For each file, make sure
you can identify what it is,
and why it's being stored.
If you're not sure
why something is there,
you may be able
to get rid of it.
You want to verify that
you're putting the right files
in the appropriate directories,
and also consider whether
the file should be included
in iTunes and iCloud backups.
Only you can answer
the first two questions,
since they relate
to your app's functionality.
I'll focus on
the last two questions
and start with
where files should be stored.
iCloud Drive is the best
place to put documents
because they become available
on all of the user's devices.
Because the contents of your
app's folder on iCloud Drive
is visible, it's important that
you only put documents in there
that people will recognize
and access directly.
Your app reads and writes
the content locally,
and then the operating
system will automatically upload
those files when
the network is available.
Since multiple devices may
be accessing the files
in iCloud Drive
at the same time,
you do need to use
file coordination
to avoid any conflicts.
So be sure to read
the documentation
for more details.
For locally stored files,
the Documents directory
is available
in your app's container.
Like with iCloud Drive,
you should only store
user-visible documents here.
Once you have verified
that your Documents directory
only contains files
that should be exposed,
the Files app can show them
in the On My iPhone
or On My iPad location.
To do this, your app
should support Open in Place
and indicate that
file sharing is enabled,
both of which are configured
in your Info.plist file.
In addition to seeing
their files in the Files app,
people can find
their files in Spotlight,
and on iPad, drag and drop them
to other apps.
Another great
benefit of exposing
your Documents directory
is that people will see their
files in the Storage Settings UI
and can individually
remove items.
This makes it much easier
to manage disk space,
and will reduce the likelihood
that your entire app is deleted
when space is low.
But remember, the only
things that should be going
into the Documents directory
are files that will make sense
to people using your app.
The critical question
you should ask is,
"Should my users
be able to see this file?"
If the answer is yes,
then that's fine.
But if the answer is no,
move it out of
the Documents directory
and into one
of the following locations.
The Application Support
directory
is a good place to store files
that might be in your
Documents directory
but that shouldn't
be seen by users.
For example,
a database that your app needs
but that the user would
never open manually.
You can store files
at the top level,
or you can create directories
if that helps
keep things organized.
The directory is
completely under your control,
and it's persistent.
The contents are included
in backups by default,
but you can opt files out
if they don't need
to be backed up.
And finally, the disk space used
in the Application Support
directory
is reported in
the Storage Settings UI
under your app's
Documents & Data total.
The next location
available to your app
is the Caches directory.
You can store files here
that can be discarded
if space is low.
This is a good location
for any content
that can be
re-downloaded when needed.
The contents of
the Caches directory
is not included in backups.
When a device
is low on disk space,
iOS can help by clearing caches.
Files will never be removed
from your caches directory
if your app is running,
and the operating system
will start by clearing caches
for apps that haven't
been used in a while.
As a bonus to you,
files in your caches directory
are not reported
as part of your app's
Documents & Data total.
Although they are included
in the overall space
taken up by apps.
And finally, you can put
files that you won't need
for any extended period of time
in the Temporary directory.
Even though the operating
system will periodically
remove these files
when your app is not running,
it's best to remove them
when you're done with them.
Like the Caches directory,
the Temporary directory
is not backed up
and is not reported in your
app's Documents & Data total.
These are all
the common locations
that your app
can store files in.
Use iCloud Drive
and the Documents directory
for files that should be
accessible in the Files app,
while application support,
caches,
and temporary directories
are all for use
by your app privately.
Be sure to review
where you're storing things
and use the right directory.
Lastly, a couple
best practice tips.
If you have files
that don't need to be included
in iTunes or iCloud backups,
use the NSFileManager APIs
to set the
"IsExcludedFromBackupKey".
You also want to
be resilient to files
that might be restored from
an older version of your app.
For example, if you had
a 32-bit version of your app
and its files were backed up,
then for a 64-bit version
of your app,
those older files
might get restored
and you need to be able
to handle that situation.
It's best to use a versioning
scheme on your files
so that you can provide
robust compatibility
across multiple versions
of your app.
And be sure that you're only
storing files in one location.
For example,
if you put files into
your local Documents directory,
don't duplicate
those in iCloud Drive.
Choose one place
and stick to it.
For user documents,
I suggest preferring
a cloud storage location
unless you have
a specific reason
to store files only
local to a device.
And finally, some new
volume capacity details
are available in iOS 11
to help in knowing
if it's a good time
for your app to take up
more disk space.
The first key,
Available Capacity
For Important Usage,
indicates the amount of space
that can be made available
for things that the user
has explicitly requested
in your app's UI.
For example, if they have
chosen to download a video
or a new level in a game.
If the space you need is
greater than what's available,
you should let them
know that their request
cannot be fulfilled.
The second key,
Available Capacity
For Opportunistic Usage,
indicates the amount
of space available
for things that
the user is likely to want,
but hasn't explicitly requested.
This could be something
like the next episode
in a series of videos
that they are watching,
or recently updated
documents on a server
that they might
be likely to open.
For these types of files,
you might store them initially
in the Caches directory
until they are actually used,
at which point
you could move them
to the Application Support
or Documents directory.
After taking inventory
and identifying what your app
stored,
if you found something
that wasn't in the right place,
then update your code to put it
in the appropriate directory.
And don't forget to add
any necessary migration code
to move the files
from one place to another.
If you don't do this,
you might inadvertently
leave abandoned files behind.
By cleaning up
your on-disk storage,
you can open up your
Documents directory
to people in the Files app
and they can be even more
productive with your app.
You can find
more information at
developer.apple.com
or on our Developer Forums.