[ Background Noise ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning, everyone.
Sorry about the technical
difficulties, but we're ready.
[laughing] All right, so I'm
Sarah Roddy and welcome to
Localizing with Xcode 9 session.
And today, with my colleagues Ia
and Chris, who would like to
talk to you about some exciting
new improvements we made to the
localization process in Xcode 9.
So let's get started.
Around the world, you have so
many people who are looking to
access and use your great
applications, but they can't do
that if you don't give them the
ability to use your apps in
their native language.
And your app can easily access
this global audience by
following some simple steps and
best practices.
And, in today's session, we will
talk about how Xcode makes it so
easy for you to add new
languages to make your app look
and feel local, which will allow
you to go global.
So there are three main topics
we will be covering today.
First, we will start with how to
make your code world ready, then
we will walk you through the
localization process in Xcode
and introduce new features we
added in Xcode 9.
Finally, and through the
presentation, we will talk about
testing and give you some best
practices to make sure that your
app works and looks great in all
languages that you support.
So let's start with
internationalization.
So internationalization is the
process of designing your
software so it can be adapted to
different languages and regions
without making code changes
every single time you are adding
a new language to your app.
So the point here is it
shouldn't matter which language
your app is running in.
If the language has short text
or long text or tall text or
even text or layout that flows
from right to left, your app
should be able to adapt
dynamically to all these
scenarios.
And the first step in
internationalization is managing
your strings.
Your app will be localized by
translators who would be working
with your strings and in this
localized string is there to
make it easier for you to create
localizable content for your
translators as well as
displaying the right text at the
right time.
So if your strings are coming
from a storyboard or a zip file
they're localizable by default,
so we don't need to worry about
those.
But sometimes you might have
some strings that are defined in
your source code that will be
displayed to the user, like
error messages or notifications;
if you would like to notify your
users about something.
And you want to make sure that
this translator is also
localizable.
And to do that you just need to
wrap those strings with NS
Localized String.
In addition to that you can use
NS Localized String as a format
string with localized language
format to get a localized and a
formatted string.
So here let's go through a quick
example together.
So here they have a label.
When I set its text to a string
called population.
So again, my string is hardcoded
and is not localizable.
To make it localizable, you just
need to wrap it with NS
Localized String.
And as you can see here on the
screen, NS Localized String
takes two arguments, your string
and a comment.
Comments here are really, really
important to provide to your
translators so they have context
about the string they are
translating.
And I would say most of the time
you just need to use NS
Localized String, but in some
cases when you're working on a
framework or a shared component
you might want to use NS
Localized String from table
where you specify the table name
where your strings are coming
from.
And as I mentioned before, you
can also combine NS Localized
String with Localized String
with Format, where NS Localized
String is a format string.
And in this case it's really,
really critical that you provide
those comments for your
translators so they have context
about the string they are
translating.
Then at run time NS Localized
String will determine the
preferred language of the user
and find the corresponding
localizable string files.
As you can see here, this is an
example of a localizable string
files coming from the French
localization projects and it
contains all your localizable
strings, the one that you
wrapped with NS Localized String
as well as the comments that you
provided.
And this is the information that
will be provided to your
translator.
And if you're using Objective
Senior App you can run the
static analyzer to find
localizability problems in your
code, like if you forgot to make
a string localizable or if you
forgot to add a comment to a
localizable string you can run
the static analyzer and you get
warnings that will show you what
these problems are and you can
fix them right on your code.
If you'd like to learn more
about the static analyzer please
check out this talk from last
year.
Another thing that your app
should handle well when it comes
to localization is working with
different visual representations
of date, time, numbers, et
cetera.
For example, 12-hour time format
is a standard format we use here
in the US, but you want to make
sure that a user who's using
your app in France, for example,
is getting 24-hour time
formatting set because this is
the default format used there.
And we provide a variety of very
powerful formatters that will
let you handle the complexity of
data formatting and regions, but
just to give you an example on
how formatters work, let's take
a look at a date formatter
example.
So here let's say you want to
display a full date format in
your app.
So instead of setting a date
format string that is specific
to a region or a country that
has a specific order, we
recommend that you use date
style.
This formatter has different
styles that you can choose from,
but since here we want to
display a full date format I'm
setting my date style to full.
So with that you are making sure
that your date is formatted
correctly in all regions in the
world.
As you can see on the screen,
there are differences between
the date format in the US and
the date format in France, like
the French date does not have
any commas, the month name is
not capitalized, the day of the
month comes before the month
itself, and this would not be
achievable if you have pasted in
a date format instead of a date
style.
In addition to date formatter,
we have a series of formatters
for common data types available
in foundation.
If you'd like to learn more
about formatters please check
out these two great talks from
last year.
Finally, you want to make sure
that your user interface is
flexible and looks nice and
beautiful in all languages that
you support and to do that the
process is really simple.
We just need to use base
internationalization and auto
layout.
So let's talk about base
internationalization for a
moment.
So by enabling base
internationalization in your
project, Xcode modifies your
projects for Destructor and
separates your UI from your
strings, which means any file
that is related to your user
interface, like a zip file or a
storyboard file, will be stored
in base [inaudible].
While your strings, either if
they are coming from a
storyboard file or if they are
in your code that you wrapped
with NS Localized String, they
will be stored in the specific
language folders so that way you
only have one set of user
interface instead of duplicating
your UI every single time you
are creating a new language in
your app.
And base internationalization is
enabled by default since Xcode
5.
So if you have an older project
that you want to localize,
please make sure that you enable
it there.
And you might be already
familiar with auto layout or
you're already using it to
support different presentations
of your app or different screen
sizes, but auto layout is also a
critical technology to use for
localization.
So by using auto layout you are
making sure that your app is
flexible and it can adapt to
different string lengths and
different configurations of your
app.
And new in Xcode 9 we are
introducing new interface
builder localization warnings to
validate your constraints for
localization, which means when
you are working on your UI and
your storyboard file or your zip
file and you're setting up these
constraints and they are not
localization friendly you will
get this warning as well as
suggestions on how to fix them.
And new interface builder
warnings will be available in
the future seat.
Additionally we are introducing
an Xcode -- 9 used to the
localization options for you to
simulate a localized
environment.
So instead of having a real
strings, translated strings, to
see how they look like in your
app you can just use one of
these pseudo localization
options that we are providing.
So, in Xcode 9, we have new
options for accented Latin
strings for a fixed strings and
new options for right to left
languages.
And with that I would like to
call Ia on stage to give you a
demo about how to prepare your
app for localization.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Sarah.
Hi. I'm Ia and today I want to
show you this really cool app
I've been working on called
International Effects.
As you see on the screen, my UI
consists mostly of this table
view and a user can go and
select a country or territory
from this list and they'll see
some information about it like
the flag, the population, and
even the language population.
So I made sure my app looks
beautiful in English and I'm
happy with the way it looks, but
now I want to internationalize
it so it can be ready for my
first localization.
And to do that I'm going to
follow the steps that Sarah just
showed us in her slides.
So the first thing I want to do
is my strings management.
I'm loading all of these strings
in my table cells in code.
So I'm going to open my Xcode
project.
And in my table view controller,
in my cell for wrote indexpath
function I want to make sure I
don't have any hardcoded strings
that I'm loading into my UI.
And instead I want to replace
them with a call to NS Localized
String.
And I'll pass in my English
string and I'll also give a
helpful comment.
So; "Label preceding the
selected territory."
And then I also went ahead and
made sure I'm calling NS
Localized String for all the
other text I'm loading in code.
So the next thing I want to do
is I also want to make sure I'm
displaying and representing data
correctly for different locales.
So in this case my data are
mostly these numbers that you're
seeing on the right side.
And numbers are displayed
differently in different
countries.
So to format them correctly I'm
going to use a number formatter.
Number formatter is similar to
date formatter that Sarah showed
us earlier, except, of course,
it's used to format numbers
instead of dates.
So for population I can simply
set my formatter's number style
to decimal and I set "uses
grouping separator" to "true,"
which makes it easier to read by
separating the number by the
thousands, and that's because
population tends to be a large
number.
For GDP I can also use a number
formatter, except this time I
would set the number style to
currency and the currency code
to US dollars because our data
is in US dollars.
And finally, for the literacy
percentage cell, as well as my
language population, I set the
number style to percent and I
give it a maximum and minimum
fraction digits to make sure it
looks consistent.
So now that my strings are
localizable and I'm displaying
my numbers -- and I'm formatting
my numbers correctly, the next
thing I want to do is make sure
my user interface is also ready.
And to do that I'm going to open
my main storyboard and I want to
show you how you can use pseudo
languages in Interface Builder
Preview to test your app for
localization.
So first I'll click on the top
right corner on the Assistant
Editor icon.
And then under this dropdown I
want to choose "preview" and
basically it's showing me a
preview of my storyboard.
And on the bottom, right corner
I get a language chooser and if
I had any localizations on my
project I would see those here,
but in this case it's showing me
all the pseudo language options
I can use in the preview.
So new in Xcode 9 we've
introduced a fixed pseudo
language.
So I'm going to select that to
see what it does.
As you can see it simply added
those square brackets and the
pound symbol before and after
each string.
And that makes it really easy to
spot if something is clipping or
not fitting in my UI because
those symbols would be missing.
So in this case it looks like my
button on the bottom doesn't
have the pound symbol and that's
the first thing I saw, but if
you take a closer look, even --
the y is clipping in "play."
So I'm going to go back to my
storyboard and see why that is.
And it looks like I have a fixed
width constraint, which in this
case is not necessary and
generally fixed width
constraints on text controls are
a bad idea for localization.
So if I get rid of it you'll see
that my pseudo language looks
exactly as expected and now I
know that I'm not going to be
clipping anything.
So these interface builder
previews are even more helpful
if you have more of your UI
defined in your storyboard.
In my case, a lot of my UI is
loaded in my table view
controller.
So I also want to show how I can
use pseudo languages at runtime
to test that.
So if I select -- if I click on
my scheme and select "edit
scheme" -- and make sure you
have "run" selected in the
sidebar -- under "application
language" you get a list of
languages you can choose from,
but over at the bottom you have
a list of all the available
pseudo languages you can use as
well -- at runtime.
Another pseudo language we've
added in Xcode 9 is the accented
Latin pseudo language.
And if I go ahead and play that
--
My app will launch with accents
above and below each of my
localizable strings.
And what this really helps with
is it gives me a preview of what
my app -- how my app would
handle languages that use a lot
of accents, diacritics, or even
languages where the scripted
self is generally taller than
English -- like Thai for
example.
So I can quickly scan this and
make sure that everything's
fitting vertically and I'm not
seeing any clippings.
And everything looks good here.
And then finally one more pseudo
language I'd like to show you at
runtime is the new right to left
pseudo language with right to
left strings.
And this pseudo language is very
helpful in testing whether your
app is ready for right to left
languages like Arabic and Hebrew
where the text itself is written
from right to left.
So as you can see, my UI
controls are already adjusted
and mirrored to look the way
they would look in a right to
left localization.
And what we also do is we
display the localizable strings
from right to left.
So the letters themselves have
flipped order and that really
helps give you an idea -- or put
you in the mindset of somebody
who reads their text from right
to left.
So these are some of the pseudo
languages.
I highly encourage you to try
them all.
They're very helpful to test
your app before you even add
localization.
And to summarize the
internationalization process;
first make sure you're using
standard APIs to load
localizable strings as well as
to format your data, like dates
and numbers.
And make sure your app is using
base internationalization to
separate your UI from your
localizable content.
And, of course, use auto layout
in your UI to make sure that the
app itself is flexible and can
adapt to different translations.
And, finally, we showed a lot of
tools that can validate your
internationalization, like the
new pseudo languages we've added
and the auto layout warnings
that are coming soon in the
future seat.
So my app is internationalized
now and I'm ready to add my
first localization.
So I'm going to call Sarah back
up on stage to show us how to do
that since she's the expert on
the topic.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Ia.
So now that you're done with the
steps that Ia showed us earlier
in her demo, you are ready to
add new languages to your app.
And you can do that right from
Xcode from your project info and
you have over 100 languages to
choose from.
So now that you've added these
languages that you want to
support in your app, so to
generate the localizable content
for your translators Xcode will
find all the localizable
resources that you have in your
project, then when you export
your projects for localization
Xcode will extract the strings
from this localizable resources
and generate XLIFF files for
every single language that you
have added.
And XLIFF file is simply a
standard XML localization file
format that is standard in the
localization industry.
So if you send your XLIFF files
to one of the localizers they
will be already familiar with
the formats and how to work with
it.
So once your XLIFF files are
translated you can import them
back and Xcode will integrate
automatically your localized
text back into your project.
And that's the localization
process in Xcode.
It's very simple and
straightforward.
And new in Xcode 9 we are adding
support for exporting and
importing string dics file
formats.
So string dics is the powerful
tool that lets you handle
plurals and adaptive strings in
your app.
In Xcode 9 you can now add and
create string dictionaries right
from the file template list in
Xcode and that will generate an
editor for you where you can add
and edit your keys and values.
So now let's talk more in detail
about what can you do with
strings dictionaries and why
they are helpful.
So first strings dictionaries
can help you handle the
complexity of plural forms
without writing any code in your
app.
So let's assume I have this
logic in my code to handle
plural variants.
So here I have an array.
The name of my array here it is popular languages
where I check it's count
If the count of my array is one
I set my string to one popular
language.
Else if the count of my array is
more than one I set my string
here to something like person d
popular languages where person d
is a format string that will
replace the runtime with the
count of my array.
So this logic might work -- well
it would work for a language
like English where there are
only two plural forms; one
singular and one plural.
But this would be a complete
disaster for a language like
Russian where there are more
plural variants.
So Russian has four different
plural variants and your
translators need to think about
work arounds and ways on how to
translate all these variants
with the one generic plural that
you provided -- the one you are
using for English, which will
make basically your translations
sound robotic and not very
natural for a native speaker.
So this example here sounds like
something; "popular languages
column one, popular languages
column two," and you don't want
that in your app.
So to solve this kind of
problem, when we're done writing
any code you can just use
strings dictionaries.
So all you need to do in your
strings dics file -- so you need
to add your localized format
key.
In this example my localized
format key is "languages."
Then you need to add the plural
variants that are relevant for
your development language.
So since here my development
language is English, I only care
about two plural variants, one
and other.
So one is for the singular case
and other is for the plural
case.
Then by wrapping your plural
string with NS Localized String,
as you will do with any other
string that you have in your
code, when you export your
projects for localization, Xcode
will generate automatically for
you the plural keys for other
languages that you support.
So the variance for other
languages will be included in
your XK files and your
translators when they are
translating the strings they
will find the plural variants
that are relevant for the
language.
And now our translation will be
correct and your users will have
more grammatically correct
translations.
So this is Strings Dics support
for Plural Variants in Xcode 9.
Another thing you can do with
strings dictionaries in Xcode 9
is support for adaptive strings.
So if we take this example from
Ia's app earlier, she had a
string here called "Gross
Domestic Products in Billions,"
which is kind of long, but it
fits fine on an iPad because
there is enough space for it.
If we run the app again in a
smaller device like an iPhone 7
-- so this string does not fit
anymore.
As you can see on the screen,
the number on the right side now
shrinks and you can only read
the three first characters,
which is kind of wrong because
we are given the wrong
information to the user.
So you can take advantage of
strings dictionaries again to
solve these kinds of problems
and provide different string
variants for your app.
So here I have three different
keys; 20, 25, and 50.
They correspond to different
screen sizes.
And then I have the strings that
I want to show for every screen
size.
So if you call NS Localized
Strings on the key within your
strings dics file.
So you enable -- we pick the
right value for you at runtime
based on the space available on
the screen.
So if you are not using UI label
and you are using a custom
control of your own, you can
still take advantage of the
functionality by calling
variance fit in presentation
with API, where you pass in one
of the keys that you have
defined in your strings dics
file and then at runtime this
will choose the right value for
you that corresponds to that
key.
And we will be providing the
keys and the corresponding
screen sizes in the
documentation if you would like
to check out that later.
So now if we run again the app
on the iPad, still using the
full string, and if we run it
again in a smaller device like
an iPhone 7 now we pick the
right variant that will fit
nicely on the screen size.
And thus without erasing a
single line of code your app
looks nice and beautiful in all
different screen sizes and
configurations of your app.
And adaptive strings are really
helpful if you are supporting
localizations in your app
because you might have some
languages that are longer or
shorter than others and you want
to give this flexibility to your
translators to provide like
adaptive strings for the
language.
So now that you're done with
supporting plural support as
well as adaptive strings you are
ready to localize your app.
And the first step in
localization is exporting your
project.
So when you export your projects
for localization -- so Xcode
will ask you which languages you
want to localize first.
So once you pick the language
you want Xcode will generate
XLIFF files for you to send to
your translators.
So once your XLIFF files are
translated you can import them
back in your project and Xcode
will show you this nice diff
with what was changed by your
translators.
And after that Xcode will just
integrate your localized text
back into your project and your
strings will be localized.
So now that your strings are
localized, what about other
resources that are not string
based that you want -- probably
you want to localize, like
images or audio files?
So you might have something like
this, an image that has text on
it, and you want to provide an
alternative image for other
languages.
So you can localize other
resources in Xcode easily by
clicking the "localize" button
in the "file inspector."
Again Xcode will ask you which
language you want to localize
this asset for.
You can pick from the list of
your languages and Xcode will
move this asset to the specific
language folder where you can
replace it with the image or the
asset that you want to show for
that language.
So this is the localization
workflow in Xcode 9.
So we saw how to support plurals
as well as adaptive strings and
how to localize other resources.
And with that I would like to
call Chris on stage to give you
a demo.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Sarah.
>> Yeah.
[ Applause ]
>> So earlier we saw Ia validate
that her app as
internationalized using both our
framework and tools features.
So let's get started on actually
localizing it.
First though, I really
appreciated Sarah's discussion
of plurals and adaptive width
strings.
So I've added a strings dict
file to our project here.
Oops. [laughs]
And I've added that GDP adaptive
width string with all of the
different variants for our
different device widths; 20, 25,
and 50.
And I've also created a plural
variant, just like Sarah showed,
for the number of popular
languages.
Now though, I'm ready to
localize my application into
Russian.
So what I'm going to do is go to
the project editor and right
under my localizations, where it
tells me that English is my
development language, I have
this plus button.
I can choose that and just go
about halfway down and choose
Russian.
And Xcode will ask me which of
my resources I want to take and
make Russian placeholders for.
Since I want to localize
everything I'm just going to
tell Xcode to finish.
And you can see that in addition
to my main storyboard file I now
have a placeholder for my
Russian strings.
Still in the project editor, I'm
going to go to the "editor" menu
now and I'm going to export my
project for localization.
And I'm just going to save this
file -- actually this folder --
on the desktop and Xcode is
going to read through all of my
source code, all of my
resources, and it's going to
generate that XLIFF file.
So let's take a look at what it
looks like.
Here you can see that the file
is named "ru.xliff" where ru is
the ISO language code for the
Russian language.
And if I double click this we
have a little tool that we've
written so that we can see all
of this localization data in
sort of a tabular form so that
we don't have to wade through a
whole bunch of XML angle
brackets just to show you.
And up at the top here you can
see a bunch of strings that came
directly from our storyboard
file.
And you can see in our
translation column everything is
in red because we haven't
actually put any translations in
this XLIFF file yet.
Here in the next section we have
file -- we have elements that
will go into our localized
strings -- our
localizable.stringsdict file.
And you can see that there are
more variants of the percent d
popular languages string than we
had in our original
localizable.stringsdict.
And this is because Xcode knows
that we're exporting to Russian
and creates placeholders for all
of the Russian variants for you
automatically.
We also have our adaptive width
string variants for the gross
domestic product and we have a
couple other things like our
application name and our
info.plist and the strings from
our source code that will then
show up in a Russian
localizable.strings file upon
import.
Now let's say I have a
translator who worked really
fast and I have a translated
version of this XLIFF ready to
go.
I could just go to the project
editor in Xcode and choose
"import localizations" and just
choose that file and export --
Xcode will read your project,
read the file, and then show you
how what that file is importing
differs from your project.
Here I'm just getting a warning
that I didn't actually localize
the name of my app in English
yet, but I do have a
localization now in Russian.
And I can also see in the files
view here exactly what files
will be affected by this import.
And this is all what I expect.
Now I tell Xcode to import it
and it'll write out these new
resource files for me.
And you can see that where we
didn't have a
localizable.strings file before,
now we have one.
And if I choose it we have a
localizable.strings file with a
whole bunch of Russian text.
Now if I run our application --
it looks like I've hit a little
bug here, that's okay.
Oops. I'll just quit and
relaunch Xcode.
Now if I run our application
we're building and Xcode is
integrating all of our
localizable strings that we just
imported.
There is one step that I missed
though, sorry about that.
I want to run my application in
Russian so I can see those
translations.
So I'm just going to open the
scheme editor and I'm going to
switch from that right to left
pseudo language that I was using
to the Russian language.
And now if I run our application
it'll build the storyboard, copy
in the swift standard libraries,
and launch.
And we can see our application
is running in Russian.
And not only are all the
formatters and everything
correct for all of our dates and
our numbers, but we also have
all of that Russian text that we
just imported.
So, to summarize, strings dicts
are really powerful and you can
use them for pluralization and
for adaptive width strings in
your applications to ensure that
they look right not only based
on the user's language, but also
based on their device width.
It's easy to export an XLIFF
from your Xcode application for
your localization process and to
import your translated strings
via XLIFF back into your
application's Xcode project.
And Sarah showed us how you can
also localize non-string
resources in Xcode.
And now Ia is going to show us
how you can test your
localization.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Chris.
I can't believe that my app is
already localized into its first
language and the steps were
really simple and easy to
follow.
So now that I do have my
localization, let's talk about
some things that we could do to
test it.
New in Xcode 9 we've introduced
the ability to specify the
application language and region
that you would like to run your
tests in.
And you can do this in the test
scheme editor right in Xcode.
And today I want to talk about
UI testing with XC test.
So UI testing is a great way for
you to validate both your
application's UI as well as its
functionality.
Let's take this line of code on
the screen for example.
This is what you would write to
simulate tapping on a table cell
that has the text territory in
it.
Now that's not going to work for
localization because that text
is going to be translated into
each language that you run your
test in.
And additionally, if you decide
to go and change the wording in
your app, even in your
development language -- like
let's say I want to call it
"region" now instead of
"territory," you don't really
want to go back and update every
single test that you've written
just so that it can start
succeeding again.
So instead, what we recommend
you do is use accessibility
identifiers.
These identifiers are unique to
every element on your screen and
you can use them to find these
elements without really knowing
what strings are loaded into
them.
So to set the accessibility
identifier, you can simply set
the property on your UI control
when create it, or your NS
control.
Or if you're loading your UI
from a storyboard or a zip file
you can set it in the identity
inspector in interface builder.
So now that your tests are
localization friendly and
they're succeeding in all the
languages that you support,
there's even more that you can
do to take advantage of that.
We're introducing -- this year
we're introducing XCT attachment
APIs, which allow you to attach
screen shots as well as any
other data you collect during
your test and it'll attach it to
your test report at the end.
What this empowers you to do is
get a full coverage of your UI.
So every screen in your app, in
every localization that you
support, as well as every device
that you support.
And you can do all that while
writing only one test -- well,
one test for each thing you want
to test.
[laughing] To find out more
about XCT attachment and what
else is new in testing please
see those related sessions
throughout the week.
And now I want to show you a
test that I've written for my
international facts app.
Okay. So in my Xcode project
I've already created this UI
test target and I wrote my first
test, called Test Some
Territories.
So let's run it to see what it
does exactly.
Now Xcode will launch my test
runner, which in turn launches
my app.
And in this specific test we
select a different territory, in
this case Belgium, and then the
test succeeds.
So now let's try running my test
in Russian.
And to do that I'll go into my
scheme and instead of "run" this
time we want to select "test"
and under language I'm going to
choose "Russian" so I can test
the new localization that Chris
added to my project.
Now again my test runner
launches, which launches my app.
And this time my app is launched
in Russian, but it looks like my
test failed.
So let's see what's going on.
And it looks like my test can't
find a cell that has "territory"
in it, which is what we just
talked about.
Silly me. So -- oops, sorry.
So in my project I'm going to go
back to my main table view
controller and make sure that
I'm setting an accessibility
identifier for my territory
picker cell so I can actually
select it.
So when I create my cell I also
want to give it an identifier.
So territory picker cell.
And I want to use the same
identifier in my test.
So where it's failing, instead
of using static text I'll simply
replace it with this identifier
that I just created.
And now I'll try to run my test
again in Russian using the
identifiers.
As you can see, my app launches
in Russian again, but this time
it actually got further and it
chose Belgium as the country and
the text succeeded.
So I just want to show you what
my test does exactly.
First, I want to validate some
of -- some functionality.
So I have this XCT assert equal
to make sure that my app
initially launches with the US
selected and then I use the XCT
attachment APIs to collect
screen shots.
So my first screen shot is a
screen shot of the US page.
And I add it to my test case and
then I collect more screen shots
later when I open the territory
list and after I've selected
Belgium.
And now finally if I want to see
these attachments I can simply
go to the "reports" navigator in
the sidebar and select my most
recent test that I've run.
And then if I expand my test
some territories test case,
you'll see that some of these
lines have the attachment icon
on them.
And these are the attachments
that I've created.
So as I've mentioned, they're
all screen shots in this case.
And there's so much that I can
do with these attachments.
I can bundle them up and send
them to somebody to ensure the
quality of my translations,
somebody who actually speaks
these different localizations --
and to make sure the UI looks
good and the formatters are
correct.
And I can even use these screen
shots in my app store preview
when I want to launch my app in
all these different storefronts
around the world so that users
can get a preview of what your
app will look like in their
language.
So, I show you how with one test
you can test every single
localization that you add in
your apps.
And to summarize what we talked
about today, we covered the
localization process for an app.
First, you need to prepare your
code for localization, and
that's the internationalization
steps.
And then we showed you ways you
can validate your apps readiness
including the static analyzer
and auto layout warnings and the
new pseudo languages.
And then you can export your --
all your localizable content
into a single XLIFF.
And now that includes string
dict files, which are really
powerful for handling plurals
and adaptive strings.
And finally, when your XLIFF is
translated you can import it
back into your project and that
integrates the translations into
all the different pieces of your
app.
And then you can take advantage
of your existing tests to run
them in all your supported
localizations.
And you can take advantage of
the new XCT attachments to do a
lot more than test your app's
functionality.
For more information, our
session is 401, and you can
visit our page on
developer.apple.com.
We highly recommend that you
attend, or at least watch, these
related sessions throughout the
week.
Thank you and enjoy the rest of
the conference.
[ Applause ]