my desk is on the seventh floor if you
need anything you can call me make sure
to keep your ID with you because you're
going to need to badge in every time you
reenter cafeterias on the fourth floor
and we generally take lunch about 12:30
this is where I'm sitting for now yeah
with the big move coming up it's kind of
crazy around here I promise it's only
temporary
all right thank you
Oh
[Music]
come on let us see we need healthy until
there's not in there maybe where are we
man solid city
[Music]
world leaders are declaring a global
state of emergency and so the app
situation can be resolved okay group us
to go first
[Music]
it's like
do you think we should have gone with
the puck you see I just made this whole
piece of myself
hashtag do delicious to share disperse
back beat the emoji farm bill - right
here y'all as I get the Buddhist Bryan
livable bride first activate I wanna
fight
Oh
[Applause]
[Music]
good morning I'm so glad that really
can't happen
welcome to WWDC it's great to be back in
San Jose the heart of Silicon Valley and
right down the street from Apple in our
new campus it's been 15 years since we
held a developer conference in San Jose
and an awful lot has changed but the one
thing that hasn't changed is our
commitment to the developer community
and our ability to do amazing things
together this is going to be the best
and biggest WWDC ever
[Applause]
every year we post WWDC to bring Apple
engineers and our amazing developers
together on our collective mission to
change the world and I'm pleased to tell
you the Apple Developer community has
never been more vibrant
we now have 16 million registered
developers in the program around the
world and we added 3 million last year
alone we've got 5300 developers here
this morning our largest group ever
we have attendees this morning from 75
countries across the world it's truly a
worldwide conference and we have the
most student developers with us this
morning ever
[Applause]
in fact one of our youngest is here this
morning is his name is Juma Soriano he's
from Australia and he's just 10 years
old he started coding when he was sick
and he already has five apps on the app
store
I met Yuma yesterday and I can't wait to
see what he's going to accomplish next
and while we've got some great
up-and-coming developers like Yuma we
got some that got a bit of a later start
motsek Oh Massa Co waka Mia is just 82
years old
and she's from Japan and she published
her first app earlier this year so so if
you haven't published yet there is still
time let's give them a big round of
applause
[Applause]
now let's turn our attention to our four
incredible platforms of course as you
know each of them stem from the same
core technology but each is uniquely
expressed and designed for the best
experience for where they work we keep
pushing these platforms forward giving
you the developers powerful tools and
opportunities to change the world
that's why this developer conference is
so important now we have a lot to talk
about today and I do mean a lot so I'm
dispensing with the updates other than
to tell you apples doing gray
[Applause]
we have six important announcements to
share with you this morning so let's get
right into it and I'll start with TV OS
we recently introduced the TV app on
Apple TV I phone and iPad to create the
easiest way to discover and enjoy your
TV content from across your video
channels all in one convenient place we
launched it with support from just a
handful of video channels but now we
have 50 partners integrated into the TV
app and today we're really thrilled to
announce that Amazon is coming Amazon is
coming to the TV app and Apple and all
Apple TVs later this year with Amazon
Prime video and of course as you know
Prime video provides a wealth of great
content thousands of TV shows and movies
and some great original content like
transparent Mozart in the jungle man in
the high castle and so much more we are
so pleased to welcome Amazon to Apple TV
[Applause]
that's TV OS you will be hearing a lot
more about TV OS later this year number
two let's talk about Apple watch Apple
watch has had incredible growth this
past year in fact it's the number one
selling SmartWatch by far and what's
most important to us is that it's number
one in customer satisfaction again by
far Apple watch is designed to help you
live a healthier life and people are
absolutely loving the fitness
capabilities the health capabilities the
quick access to information and even the
ability to swim with it we've got some
exciting updates to the watch OS and to
take you through them I'd like to invite
Kevin Lynch up Kevin
thank you too so watch os is moving
forward really quickly and I'm very
excited to introduce watch OS for today
this furthers the areas that people love
and also introduces new ways to make the
watch more personal to you let's start
with watch faces now Apple watch is
great for quickly glancing at
information and many people are using a
watch face like this today now you need
to choose what information shows up here
so for example weather calendar and
workouts or maybe you'd like to look at
the date and reminders and sunset the
information that you'd like to see
actually varies based on time and your
location and your routine what if we
could actually show you a selection of
information that you might need
automatically well Siri is becoming more
and more a proactive assistant knowing
what information you need when you need
it and we've created a new watch face
which is powered by Siri intelligence
this is the new Siri watch face now it
automatically displays the information
that's most relevant to you it can also
access Siri just by tapping on the new
complication on the top left and it
automatically displays this information
with the same type of intelligence we've
applied on iOS we're using machine
learning to adapt automatically based on
your routines and the apps that you use
when you use them so in the morning I
might see for example commute time and
my first meeting and if I rotate the
crown I can see more information from
Siri for example reminders or even photo
memories from the same time last year or
maybe from this location and throughout
the day whenever you raise your wrist
the face will dynamically update with
information for you so for example at
noon I might see a reminder to make a
call and I might get a pass to a flight
that I'm taking that afternoon so
relevant passes in wallet can appear
here right in the face
including from third-party apps now at
the end of the day I might see what time
the sun's going to set and also I can
get access to controls I tend to use in
the home app at night this is an
intelligent proactive assistant right on
your wrist and this is the new Siri face
on Apple watch
now sometimes you might like kind of
less information and more graphics and
that's the soul of a new kaleidoscope
face it displays a beautiful symmetrical
pattern it slowly changes throughout the
day and you can rotate the crown and
give this kind of trippy effect whenever
you want and there's multiple styles you
can choose from so for example if you
use a photo like this you can create a
variety of kaleidoscope styles this is
the new kaleidoscope face now making it
mini have been a big hit on Apple watch
and more characters have been working to
find their way in and I'm really excited
to welcome woody and Jessie and buzz
they're going to be right at home inside
the watch and they're so much fun and
whenever you raise your watch with the
Toy Story phase you're going to see a
variety of vignettes kind of like this a
lot of hijinks going on in there so
these are three really lively new faces
in watch OS series face
kaleidoscope and Toy Story now let's
talk about xfinity Apple watch has
already been helping many people improve
their health and fitness and activity is
one of the most frequently used apps on
the watch and watch OS for activity
notifications are more personalized to
you to help you closure rings more often
so you might start off each day with
some inspiration by receiving an update
like this this lets you know if you're
close to accomplishing an achievement or
what you can do to match yesterday's
goals and these are all personalized to
you and as part of the smarter coaching
we're also introducing monthly
challenges these challenges are designed
to help you either
beat or repeat something that you
accomplished or came close to doing and
they're all achievable because they're
based on your real history and like
every great coach we want to celebrate
your success so we've added a little bit
more fun when you close your rings or
earn an achievement you get smaller
celebrations for everyday successes and
bigger celebrations for harder to reach
milestones now we've also enhanced the
workout app to be even easier to use and
more powerful starting with the new UI
where click starts right up front you
can just tap and go it's much easier
customers have really loved the new
swimming capabilities in series two and
we're now enhancing the pool swim
workout with Auto sets so just by taking
a rest at the edge of the pool will
automatically mark each set of swimming
that you're doing and at the end you'll
even get your distance for each stroke
type and your pace for each set that
you're doing and we also are creating
it's great the full swim thing is very
popular also created some custom motion
and heartrate algorithms for a new
workout type called high-intensity
interval training now this is one of the
most popular workouts in the world so we
know it's going to be a favorite for a
lot of you when you start using it now
if you like to do more than one workout
in a row it's now super easy to just
swipe over during a current workout and
then add another one by pressing the
plus button use press plus and I can
continue with another workout for
example I might do some outdoor cycling
here I just tap and I continue super
easy now to do multiple workouts in a
single session now many people are doing
the workouts indoors at a gym and when
you use gym equipment it has data the
Apple watch doesn't have and the watch
has data the gym equipment doesn't have
so you end up with numbers like calories
and distance that don't quite match so
in watch OS 4 we come up with a great
solution to this we're enabling for the
first time to eight data exchange in
real time with gym equipment so you'll
be able to simply tap your Apple watch
an FC reader on the gym equipment your
watch will automatically launch the
workout app and you can connect and then
your heart rate is read by the watch and
sent to the equipment and data like
incline and speed is sent from the
equipment to your watch and when you
start and stop the workout in your gym
machine it does the same thing on your
watch so now all the information matches
it's much easier and it's a lot more
accurate now this is being supported by
the largest gym manufacturers in the
world provide about 80% of equipment in
gyms today an Apple watch enabled
equipment will be rolling out starting
this fall
let's talk about music Apple watch
paired with air pods has really become a
magical combination and we're
redesigning the music app on watch make
this a really great experience with the
new music app we're going to
automatically sync music for you based
on what you love to listen to so for
example will automatically get your
Apple music mixes like new music and
favorites freshly updated on your watch
and the app simply presents the
beautiful album art and playlist images
and you can just navigate by rotating
the digital crown and he gets the album
you like you can just tap and play so
you can easily play your music now and
we support multiple playlists and music
on the watch now so your music that you
love is going to be ready when you are
in making apple watch and ear pods a
truly magical listening experience
that's the new music app now let's take
a look at this to give you a quick demo
of watching us for please welcome beer a
car from the watch and health
engineering team thank you Kevin
good morning I'm so excited to be here
the first thing I want to show you is
the new dock I can now vertically scroll
through my recently used apps like the
new music app using the dock makes
finding the apps I'm looking for easier
than ever
next let's look at the new intelligence
Siri watch face here the warm morning I
could see things like the weather for
today and my upcoming events later today
I'm heading back to San Francisco to see
my parents and in the afternoon the Siri
face will proactively update to tell me
how long it'll take me to get there
tonight we're going to see the new alien
movie which I'm super excited about
no one's spoiler for me for any content
in this series face I could tap directly
into the app for more details here for
example the series face has my tickets
so tonight I can just raise my wrist and
with one tap they'll be ready the Siri
face also shows me timely content like
photo memories and news here's a news
headline picked for me by the brand new
news app now available on Apple watch in
the app I can view stunning photos
glanced at top news stories throughout
the day
and save them for later to be read on my
phone we've also integrated our new
activity coaching notifications directly
into the Siri face now this near the end
of your day are you close to closing
your rings or coaching algorithms will
tell you how much you need to walk to
hit your move goal I did a lot of
nervous pacing before this so now I just
need to take a 16 minute walk let's
close those rings we've added something
new here and workout that's really cool
music instantly gets me motivated and
now in watch OS 4 I can pick a playlist
that automatically starts with my
workout let's do it
[Music]
and when I'm going to workout I can
quickly swipe the left and control my
music right here these are only a few of
the new features and watch our s4 I
can't wait for you to try it out back to
Kevin to tell you more terrific Shelby
oh thank you there's a lot more coming
and watch us for including for example a
new flashlight in the control center
which you can also use as a blinking
safety light when you're doing an
evening run there's a lot more happening
here now we of course have a number of
updates that enable great apps by
developers in watch os including more
support for apps running in the
background
faster app responsiveness and some new
UI capabilities and we're also now
supporting native core bluetooth on the
watch which is going to enable
experiences for apps that work with
small devices around you so for example
continuous glucose monitoring directly
from Dexcom sensor to your watch where's
app tennis which connects to a sensor on
your racket for real-time swing analysis
when you're playing we're denser which
connects your watch to your surfboard so
you can actually see the height of the
waves you're doing and how many calories
you're burning while you're still in the
water so lots of new possibilities here
for watch OS
developer preview is available today so
you can get going and there's a free
upgrade for everyone across all watches
this fall and that's just some of what's
coming and watch us for please welcome
Tim back to the stage thank you
watch OS 4 is a great update now let's
talk about a product that in many ways
is the heart and soul of Apple and of
course I'm talking about the Mac there's
never been a computer quite like the Mac
the Mac is so important in fueling the
world's passion and creativity it's a
computer all of us love to use and no
one can match the Mac's deep integration
of hardware and software and of course
at the heart of the Mac experience is
Mac OS and to tell you about what's next
with Mac OS please welcome Craig
federighi Craig thank you
hey good morning so let's talk about Mac
OS now our current release of Mac OS
course is Mac OS Sierra now Sierra
brought Siri and Apple pay to the Mac
let you put your documents and your
desktop in the cloud
even let you unlock your Mac
automatically using the watch on your
wrist
now people are loving Sierra and we love
it too so we wanted to spend this year
perfecting it of course the question is
what do we call it
so we enlisted once again our crack
marketing team they were giddy to hop in
their minibus and this time venture east
deep into the Sierras but this time
ascending its highest peaks and when
they finally came back they had a name
they said felt really really good and
it's my privilege to announce for you
today Mac OS hi Sierra
now we talked to the guys and we said
there might be this time you
misconstrued but they assured us this
name is fully baked
so now high sierra is all about deep
technologies that provide a powerful
platform for future innovations on the
mac but we couldn't help ourselves we
also added some refinements and it
starts with Safari now Safari is known
for its efficiency and it's a legendary
battery life but Safari is also
incredibly fast
in fact we benchmark Safari on the same
hardware running Mac OS and Windows with
all the popular browsers and Safari
smokes them in benchmark after benchmark
jet streams speedometer motion mark
Safari tops them all that's right Safari
is the world fastest desktop browser
with high sierra and safaris domination
continues with the new modern version of
javascript Eknath scripts 5 we can see
Safari delivers 80% faster performance
than Chrome now in addition to being
tremendously fast Safari also helps give
you a serene browsing experience now you
know sometimes you go to read an article
and instead of finding something to read
you get this
just some loud audio and video that Otto
plays and disrupts your whole reading
vibe well now don't worry about it
because we have autoplay blocking and
Safari Safari detects a site that
shouldn't be playing video and puts you
in control you can always push play
now Safari is also key and respecting
your privacy now if you ever have this
experience where you go to buy something
on the web you even complete the
purchase and it seems like everywhere
you go on the web it just follows you
around it kind of feels like you're
being tracked and that's because you are
no longer because Safari has intelligent
tracking prevention
safari uses machine learning to identify
trackers segregate the cross site
scripting data put it away so now your
privacy your browsing history is your
own it's not about blocking ads the web
behaves as it always did but your
privacy is protected next I want to talk
about some refinements to mail and it
starts with search so in addition to
providing searches based on recency
search in mail is now using spotlight to
identify your top hit so the message
you're looking for is almost always
right there at the top and if you're
into using mail in full screen well now
we support split view for your compose
window it's a great way to compose mail
and mail is more efficient than ever it
actually uses 35% less disk space for
storing your mail now probably our
biggest area of refinement in high
sierra is in photos yeah photos had some
great new organization and editing tools
there's a persistent sidebar and a new
view that has all your imports in
chronological order and in any view up
here in the upper right you can filter
by your keywords by your favorites by
just media types like video so it's
really easy to get to just what you're
looking for we've also improved faces it
recognizes far more faces automatically
using advanced convolutional neural
networks and when you put effort into
categorizing and naming people well
that's now synchronized automatically
across all your devices
now we also have some great enhancements
to editing inside of photos you can see
here on the right hand side all of your
editing tools are right in there a bunch
of great new ones including curves which
allows you to fine-tune the color and
contrast in your image and selective
color did you modify color in a
selective range I think you're going to
like this one because if you like to do
edits in a pro tool like Pixelmator or
Photoshop well now when you punch out to
that other editing tool all of your
edits automatically synchronize right
back to your photo library now Apple
pioneered printed books based on
projects you construct right inside of
the photo application and now we're
opening this up to third parties they're
going to offer some amazing new printing
services full-frame wall-mounted of
photos and even publishing websites all
based on projects right inside of photos
so those are some quick refinements but
I want to return to the main story now
and that's technology these because
we've gone deep on the fundamentals data
video and graphics and when it comes to
data the fundamentals are in the file
system
now the Mac file system has its roots
actually HFS from 30 years ago well a
lot has changed since then we have a lot
of flash drives or storage is a billion
times larger and it's time for a more
modern file system so I'm pleased to
announce that we're bringing the Apple
file system to Mac OS is our new default
now a PFS is a thoroughly modern
filesystem 64-bit top to bottom it's
safe and secure with built-in crash
protection and native encryption and
it's ultra responsive with modern
features like instant file and directory
cloning and high-performance
parallelized metadata operations now
what does that really mean in practice
well let's take a look at a simple file
duplication inside of cear so we're
going to go up to the file menu select
duplicate on these very large video
files and it's going to copy and just
like you'd expect there's a lot of data
to be copied here so it takes a little
while just about done there we go now
let's watch that in high sierra well
we're going to go up to the file menu
we're going to sub duplicate and we're
done
next up video now the current standard
in video is h.264 in fact h.264 has
really enabled the revolution of
streaming HD video on the internet but
of course the game is moved from HD to
4k and 4k high dynamic range video and
there's a new standard to support this
it's h.265 or HEV c you want your video
to look great
preserve all the detail and color and
heb c does it while saving up to 40%
that our compression than h.264 now
we're building in software encoder
support into high sierra for all macs
and hardware acceleration of HEV c for
the newest macs and we're also building
it into pro tools like final cut motion
and compressor now i want to return to
our main story which is graphics and
graphics are all about the GPU the GPU
has been the performance superstar of
the last decade they're living
incredible gains in computational
performance now our api for
high-performance graphics is metal and
developers have taken amazing advantage
to metal this is Dawn of War 3 from
feral interactive incredible graphics
this is DaVinci Resolve from black magic
which can accelerate many editing
operations and of course we even use
metal inside of photos for doing machine
learning and identifying your photos but
we've learned a lot working with
developers on their adoption of metal
and we have a new version to announce
today you'll never guess what we called
it it's metal to
now Edel 2 is tremendously fast in fact
it has great optimizations and new AP is
that when adopted deliver another 10
times improvement and draw call
throughput now some of you remember when
metal first came out it itself had a 10
times improvement over OpenGL you can
multiply those numbers together that's a
hundred times improvement now we've also
provided better sorry
debugging and performance analysis tools
for you to optimize your app for metal
and we're so excited about the advances
in metal 2 that we've taken the Mac
Windows server and put it on top of
metal accelerating things like Mission
Control and some of our most challenging
system animations are now buttery smooth
all the time now metal is not just about
graphics we're also using it for machine
learning to now accelerate yes we have
metal performance shaders accelerate all
kinds of deep learning algorithms now
another piece of metal news today is
metal for external graphics so you know
our mac books have this tremendous
balance of Portability and power but
sometimes for some workflows you need
even more power you want to take
advantage of the incredible Thunderbolt
IO on your MacBook Pros to access
external graphics so we're going to be
making this possible in metal too now
we're starting with the develop
developer kit that will be available
today you can actually order a
Thunderbolt 3 enclosure with a
high-performance AMD GPU and tune your
apps for high-performance external
graphics and then we'll be rolling out
support to all of our customers in the
months to come
now with this graphics power we're
really doubling down on our focus on pro
content creation and that's increasingly
about VR content creation and so we're
bringing metal for VR to high sierra
the metal is delivering a br optimized
display pipeline that provides extremely
high performance and optimizing our pro
apps like final cuts for doing things
like editing spiracle video right inside
the VR environment we're also working
with valve they're bringing the steamvr
SDK to the Mac and we work with unity
and unreal to bring their engines for VR
to the Mac it's really cool and you
might just be seeing a little bit more
from us later today on this topic so
that's a quick look at Mac OS some great
technologies with the Apple file system
HEV C video and incredible graphics with
metal to support for external graphics
and VR support on the maket and of
course a bunch of fantastic refinements
now Mac OS hi Sierra is available for
all of you today as the developer beta
and if you sign up at beta Apple comm
will also have a public beta available
later this month
and of course it's shipping to everyone
as a free upgrade this fall on all
systems that support Sierra now that's
your update on Mac OS hi Sierra and I'm
going to turn it over to our
vice-president of hardware engineering
John Ternes to tell you more about the
Mac thank you
[Applause]
Thank You Craig so we have some great
updates to talk about today that span
much of the Mac product line and let's
begin with the iMac now the iMac has
been the gold standard of desktops for
many years but we're going to raise the
bar once again and as always on the iMac
it starts with the display because the
4k and 5k retina iMac displays with
their high resolution excellent
brightness and petrie color gamut are
the best displays on any desktop but
we're going to make them even better so
these new displays are now going to be
500 nits that's 43% brighter than a
previous generation and for the first
time we're going to support 10 bit
dithering which means these displays can
reproduce up to a billion colors so your
content is going to look more true to
life than ever before now in addition
we've got some great internal updates
for these IMAX so we'll start with the
CPU because the whole line is moving to
Intel seventh generation Core processor
also known as KB Lake now KB Lake gets
this better base in turbo frequencies
for more performance as well as hardware
base 10 bit HEV C decode which is great
for playing back high quality video in
addition these eye mechs are getting a
boost when it comes to memory capacity
so the 21.5 inch systems can now be
configured with up to 32 gigs of memory
and the 27-inch can go all the way up to
64 gigabytes of memory both of those are
twice what the previous generation could
do now fast storage has always been a
key part of the iMac and so we're going
to now make our fusion drive standard on
all 27-inch configs and it's also going
to be standard on the high-end 21.5 inch
config as well in addition our SSD
options are going to be up to 50% faster
and now available up to 2 terabytes and
the IMAX are getting an i/o upgrade as
well because we're giving them two USB C
connectors which support Thunderbolt 3
and we think our customers especially
our pro users are really going to love
this because you can do some cool things
like hook up a high performance raid
array and an external 5k display at the
same time so now let's talk about
graphics and as you heard earlier we're
investing heavily in graphic software
technologies like metal 2
we're also investing in graphics
hardware and every configuration in this
new iMac line is going to get a big bump
in its graphics performance so we'll
start with the entry-level iMac now this
system gets a boost and it's integrated
GPU by way of Intel's iris plus graphics
which now has 64 megabytes of video ram
and the performance that we're getting
out of this is pretty amazing because
the system is up to eighty percent
faster in graphics than the previous
generation now next up is the 21.5 inch
iMac with retina 4k display and the big
news here is that we're going to be
moving to discrete graphics and making
it standard on all 4k IMAX and that's
going to come there you go and that's
going to come in this Radeon Pro Series
GPUs with up to 4 gigabytes of vram and
again this moved to discrete graphic
fields a pretty spectacular performance
increase because this new system is up
to three times faster than the previous
generations of graphics now lastly we
have our 27-inch iMac and this is our
most popular desktop for our pro
customers so obviously it's going to get
a bump in graphics today as well so it's
going to have these Radeon Pro 500
series GPUs with up to 8 gigabytes of
vram and again we get a great
performance uplift in fact this 27-inch
iMac can now deliver up to
five-and-a-half teraflops of graphics
confus which makes it a great platform
for VR content creation in fact we've
seated some developers with this new
iMac and High Sierra so that we could
see what they can do with Virtual
Reality on the Mac and I'm really
excited that we can give you a demo of
some of this amazing work right now so
I'd like to invite up on the stage here
from Industrial Light and Magic
it's Academy award-winning visual
effects artist and chief creative
officer John Knoll John
package on at lucasfilm's ilm xlab story
concept design and technical development
are all intertwined to come together for
us to create immersive experiences for
people to enjoy at home in cinemas and
at theme parks now I've always done my
art and development on a Mac so I'm
really excited about these new iMacs I
truly love the platform so I'm
especially especially excited to be able
to share some of our VR content created
on these new iMacs in epics Unreal
Engine I'm joined by Lauren Ridge and
epic programmer will be backstage
driving our demo we working together we
can work in real time to create an
immersive experience as we step inside
the Star Wars universe now Lauren's
backstage so we can show you the
environment around her and now we're
going to show you from my perspective
here we are on the planet Mustafar
thanks to the native VR support in Mac
OS hi Sierra I can use unreal engines
editor's to create content inside the VR
experience and for the first time it's
all powered by my map on my left motion
controller I have my radial menu which
acts as my artist palette and on the
right I have the laser I use to interact
with the world
have some fire here so let's try that
out all right very nice let's do some
set dressing what do you have let's see
let me open my content browser it has
all the assets
I need to dress my scene I think I saw a
good landing spot for an imperial
shuttle over here let's bring one of
those in
we've actually set up these smartass
estimator exactly want to come into
their landing great all right ask you go
wide sure I can grab off so over two
hands and yeah myself up I can also use
this to rotate the world around me over
tool I have a TIE fighter here too so
let's bring one of those in thanks for
more than five-and-a-half teraflops of
GPU performance manipulating objects is
super smooth and really intuitive great
alright can we have a squadron of those
flying overhead okay what about from
over there on the horizon - over there
by the castle right perfect okay alright
let me teleport back down
oh hey seeing the castle back there
reminds me we're missing one important
element right how could I forget all
right nice boy looks really good so that
it against the sky back there can we go
in closer
sure thing it's really cool huh metal -
I'm lost on wheels advanced rendering
features set on a mat Wow yeah really
nice all right let's play this scene
from here okay
oh he's upset that's the third one this
week
[Music]
Oh
God he didn't see me there wouldn't be
so sure about that
alright actually let's stop it right
there
that was a close one
but it's really nice to see an iMac
rendering this level of graphics in VR
mode at a smooth 90 frames a second
really great all right Thank You Lauren
metal - and unreal our epics Unreal
Engine will it enable the next
generation of storytellers we use this
technology in our filmmaking everyday
for virtual set scouting for art
direction and shot design and that means
that this immersive content can be made
by the same people that bring you the
film's that's incredibly powerful at
Lucasfilm and ILM xlab we're looking
forward to using our max to create new
experiences as we invite people
everywhere to step inside our stories
thank you thank you
thank you John and Lauren that was
awesome so that is our update to the
iMac line and to recap they have the
best Mac displays we've ever made faster
processors higher memory capacity
superfast storage Thunderbolt 3 and as
you saw incredible graphics performance
so here's the line and but there's one
more change because we're going to bring
even more value to the iMac product line
for the first time ever we're going to
have a 4k iMac that starts at just
$12.99
but the updates don't stop with just the
iMac because we're refreshing our
notebooks today as well and together the
MacBook and MacBook Pro make up the
strongest line of notebooks we've ever
had but we're going to make them even
better because we're moving to KB Lake
here as well and we're bringing faster
SSD to our macbook and faster standard
graphics to the 15-inch MacBook Pro so a
great performance bump across the board
so here's that lineup but just like the
iMac we're going to bring more value
here as well because we're going to have
a new configuration of the 13-inch
MacBook Pro that also starts at just
$12.99
so there you have it we've updated seven
of our most popular Mac and the MacBook
Air is going to get a bump in maker mid
megahertz as well and even better
they're all shipping today
now we care deeply about the environment
and so as with all their products we've
been working really hard to ensure that
these new Mac are free of harmful
chemicals very energy efficient and
highly recyclable so that's everything
we're updating today but it's not
actually everything we want to show you
today now the iMac line has incredible
breadth it spans from an entry-level
system that's perfect for use at home or
in a school all the way up through that
powerhouse 27-inch model which allows
professional customers to create amazing
things every day but that said there's
another class of pro users who would
love to be able to take advantage of the
IMAX display and design but they need
workstation class performance that can't
possibly fit into an all-in-one well we
wanted to challenge that assumption and
so we've been working really hard to see
just how far we can push the iMac now
this isn't going to be shipping until
the end of the year but I'm really
excited to be able to give you a sneak
peek at what we've been up to and here
it is
[Music]
cool so that is the new iMacs row now
the first thing you'll notice it
features the same great design as our
27-inch iMac but it's in this seriously
badass space gray finish and with that
stunning new color and gorgeous 5k
display this is without a doubt the most
beautiful iMac we've ever made but it's
also going to be by far the most
powerful iMac we've ever made in fact
this will be the most powerful Mac we've
ever made because because we actually
are going to put workstation class
performance into our incredible 5k iMac
design now to do that the team had to
completely rethink the thermal
architecture and they came up with this
really efficient dual centrifugal fan
solution which generates significantly
more airflow than a traditional iMac
in fact the iMac pro has a greater than
80 percent increase in cooling capacity
so that means we can deliver
unbelievable performance while still
maintaining the quiet operation you'd
expect from an iMac so let's talk about
what's inside and I want to start with
the CPU because we wanted to go really
big here so the iMac pro is going to
ship with an 8 core xeon processor but
it's also going to ship with a 10 core
xeon processor and then we thought you
know we've gotten this far let's get
really nutty so we're going to offer it
with up to 18 or
that is a ton of compute power but we
didn't want to stop there because we
wanted to go really big on graphics as
well so the iMac Pro is going to use
AMD's Radeon Vega graphics this is their
brand new workstation class graphics
architecture it features a completely
new GPU core and high bandwidth on
package memory it's going to be
available with up to 16 gigabytes of
vram and over 400 gigabytes per second
of memory bandwidth and we aren't going
to use an entry-level configuration here
because our implementation is going to
offer up to 11 teraflops of single
precision compute power that's three
times more than the best GPU and a Mac
Pro but it actually gets even better
because this Radeon Vega GPU can also do
half precision compute so that means the
iMac pro can deliver up to 22 teraflop
of passes and computations this is a
really big deal for things like machine
learning development so the iMac Pro as
you can see is going to be a monster
when it comes to graphics but we didn't
want to stop there either so we're going
to let you configure it with up to 128
gigabytes of ECC memory that's twice
what you can do in a standard 27-inch
iMac and up to 4 terabytes of 3 gigabyte
per second SSD now the iMac Pro is also
going to be a full complement of high
performance IO including 4 Thunderbolt 3
ports and for the first time ever in any
Mac built in 10 Gigabit Ethernet
and with all that cutting edge IO you
can do some pretty amazing things that
you can hook up to 5k displays into high
performance raid arrays no iMac before
could ever do that and when you combine
that with the internal display that
means the iMac Pro can drive up to 44
million pixels there's so much more we
don't have time to get into things like
a 1080p FaceTime camera a user
configurable VESA mount option two times
wider AVX instructions and even a UHS 2
SD card slot so with all the type
performance technologies in our
incredible 5k display this iMac pro is
going to be an awesome workstation for
things like real-time 3d rendering high
frame rate immersive VR machine learning
development and with all those cores in
all that memory super fast code
compiling now speaking of workstations
we wanted to compare the starting
configuration of the iMac Pro to what's
on the market and so if you were to go
out and build a comparably spec system
today it would cost over $7,000 and keep
in mind that's a system that doesn't
have our best-in-class 5k display
doesn't have the iMac pros incredible
all-in-one design and obviously doesn't
run Mac OS well this is the starting
configuration of the iMac pro and we're
going to price it at just 49.99
and it's going to be available in
December so that's a sneak peek at the
iMac Pro attacks workstation class
performance into our incredible 27-inch
iMac design with its gorgeous 5k display
and it is going to be the most powerful
Mac we have ever made so that is all of
our Mac news today now back to Tim all
right so many great things happening
with the Mac and John I agree that I Mac
Pro is really badass alright next up
let's talk about iOS the world's best
and most advanced mobile operating
system our customers love the latest
version iOS 10 which has an
industry-leading 96% customer
satisfaction and it's absolutely
incredible that 86% of our customers are
running iOS 10 and taking advantages of
its capabilities this blows away the
other platforms that suffer from
horrible fragmentation with with iOS
developers can always target the latest
capabilities and features of our latest
operating system and be confident that
there's customers there for them today
we're going to take the world's best and
most advanced mobile operating system
and turn it up to 11
and I'd like to invite Craig back to
take you through it Craig
Thank You Kim hello again let's talk
about iOS 11 it's a big one now with a
big focus on technologies in iOS 11 but
also some really big features we have a
lot to talk about we're going to start
with messages now you all know in iOS 10
we add an iMessage apps and stickers
people had a lot of fun with these and
now in Iowa at 11 we're making them more
discoverable and ever with this we
designed app drawer you can see you have
your apps accessible right there at the
bottom of the screen with just a tap can
bring them up scroll through them and
tap into any app so really easy it's
going to make it a lot of fun for you to
use your apps and stickers now the big
story with messages though is messages
in iCloud because now with your I
messages in iCloud when you sign in to
another new device well all of your
conversations are automatically
synchronized
and in fact they stay in sync so if you
want to delete an embarrassing message
that you don't want in your transcript
well it goes away everywhere which is
kind of nice so this course allows us to
optimize your device storage because
with your messages in the cloud we only
need to keep your most recent messages
cached on the device and so that makes
for smaller and faster backups that is
available for iOS and the Mac and of
course your messages remain end-to-end
encrypted next Apple pay so we love
using Apple pay to buy things at retail
in fact Apple pay is the number one
contactless contactless payment hub
service on mobile devices and by the end
of the year it'll be available in more
than 50% of retailers here in the US but
in addition to paying at retail we use
Apple pay and apps we use it in the web
there was one final frontier we wanted
to conquer and that's Apple pay for
person-to-person payments
now it's super simple because it's
integrated right in two messages as an
iMessage app you can send and receive
money right in your transcript of course
when you send it you authenticate
securely with touch ID and if you
received money with iMessage it goes to
your Apple pay cash card and from there
where you can send it on to friends and
family if you're charitable you can make
Apple pay purchases at retail or on the
web and of course you can pull it out
and transfer it to your bank and it's
available across all these iOS devices
and Apple watch too
so next let's turn to Siri now Siri is
used monthly for more than 375 million
devices absolutely huge and it's
available in more languages and more
countries than any other assistant 21
languages in 36 countries so for iOS 11
we're making a big upgrade to your
primary interface and dealing with Siri
that series voice we've used deep
learning now to create a really natural
and expressive voice for Syrian I'd like
you to hear it
here's the forecast for the next gen a
son honey honey three different ways to
say sunny very powerful now Siri also
has a male voice and it sounds fantastic
- I love machine learning especially
since I'm a machine learning so Syria is
a great new visual interface as well and
it's able to provide you with follow-up
questions and answers with just a tap
and multiple results when you make a
query it's really handy now Siri also
has a new capability just translation so
you can now ask something like how do
you say one of the most popular dishes
in your restaurant in Chinese and Siri
can say even attention Yana here's how
to show when you totally
now translation initiative will support
translation from English to Chinese
French German Italian and Spanish and
will have more language combinations
coming in the months to come now when it
comes to using Siri to access your other
applications we have Siri kit and
sirikit can now do more than ever in iOS
11 so now you can do task management by
using Siri to make tasks and OmniFocus
or things take notes and Evernote do
banking and City mobile or even bring up
a QR code in WeChat now Sirius is just a
voice assistant because with Siri
intelligence Siri not only understands
your voice it understands the context it
understands your interests and
understands how you use your device this
allows it to ultimately understand what
you want next now we've all experienced
this where Siri can help us predict what
apps we might want to use next give us a
time to leave notification based on our
calendar and where we are help us
respond to a text message when iOS 11
Siri uses on device learning to
understand more about topics of interest
to us so it can actually suggest topics
we might be interested in learning about
in news can help us respond with our
location for getting to an appointment
to someone in messages and even help us
make a calendar appointment based on
something we've just booked inside of
Safari on the web and what Siri learns
about you on device it's now kept synced
across all of your devices so you're
dealing with one theory but of course
this is kept completely private readable
only by you and your devices
[Applause]
next let's talk about the camera
people love the fantastic cameras in the
iPhone 7 and 7 plus and in fact our
customers now take a trillion photos per
year it's absolutely amazing and they
take a lot of video too and today they
do it in h.264 but now with our latest
iPhones and iOS 7 they get we're using
h-e-b C which is giving us up to two
times better compression for camera
captured videos which means less storage
space used on your device and less space
used in the cloud and we're applying
these same techniques to replace JPEG
capture with what we call hei F high
efficiency image format is based on HEV
C and it also provides awesome quality
images at half the size on your device
and of course you can still share
completely compatibly with others now
with the iPhone 7 plus we love taking
these beautiful portrait photos and now
with iOS 11 we can take a low-light
photographs using optical image
stabilization true tone flash HDR
delivers incredible image quality and
we're taking the depth information that
we can capture with two cameras and
exposing it to developers with a new
depth API which has allowed them to do
incredibly fun and artistic photos like
this using using the depth API now when
you're done taking your photos you go to
enjoy them in the Photos app and one of
the ways I love enjoying them is with
the memories feature because memories is
able to scan my library and find all
kinds of fun events and now it can do
more than ever it uses machine learning
to identify things like sporting events
even weddings anniversaries memories of
your babies it's really great and when
you go to play those back you can see
them not just in normal landscape
orientation but now watch them in
portrait taking full advantage of the
height of your display now when it comes
to live photos we have some great
enhancements as well so you can now trim
your live photos the video around the
still you can mark any part of the video
is your key photo and so much more so
these are some of the big features in
iOS 11 there's one other which is a
major redesign to Control Center rather
than showing slides how about we do a
demo
alright let's take our first live look
no I don't want to do that let's take
our first live look at IO s11 I'm going
to just bring up control center as
always and what you'll notice is control
center is now a single page packed all
the features into a single page now of
course it has simple switches I'll just
do an orientation lock it's got a
beautiful little animation there for the
orientation lock it has sliders
available so you can adjust volume like
this but it provides greater depth
because with 3d touch pretty touching on
slider like this and get access to more
controls and this allows us to pack lots
of capabilities really easily into the
design so you see we have our wireless
control so I could just tap on airplane
mode but if I 3d touch on the platter I
get access to even more features this is
really great with your music because you
can operate them here or jump in for
even more information so it's a really
great new control center I think you're
really going to love it
now we've also taken this opportunity to
redesign lock screen and Notification
Center by making them one so now when
I'm on my lock screen if i unlock the
device just like that I can actually now
swipe back down I'm actually on my lock
screen seeing those notifications but I
can get it all my other notifications
just by scrolling up like that it's a
really great unification and you still
have access of course to your widgets on
the left and your camera on the right
now let's take a look at photos these
beautiful portrait photos but also these
great live photos and you know live
photos capture still but then also a
bunch of video automatically captured
around it and sometimes the best shot
wasn't the still well now we can go into
edit mode we could trim this video if we
want but we also can capture just the
frame we want and make that our key
photo now we can do other really fun
things with live photos now here's one
great shot this girl blowing a bubble
but would it be greater great if she
could just keep blowing that bubble well
now she can we actually use computer
vision to compute a seamless loop around
this live photo it's really fun and we
have another great effect
so here's fun jump in the pool but
wouldn't it be better if it balanced
there it is now we can really get some
artistic things with live photos as well
so you see this is a shot we have still
landscape but then this movement in the
water now if you wanted to capture this
kind of motion traditionally you'd have
to get a tripod and figure out how to
configure a long exposure on your
high-end camera but now you can actually
just go into the effects here and select
long exposure and check it out it's
really gorgeous yeah let's take a quick
look at memories because you see
memories can now capture things like
activities like scuba diving can spot
your anniversaries these really touching
memories of your children growing up and
most importantly your pets let's play a
movie about these pets and what we'll
see is that we play them of course
traditionally here in landscape which is
a great way to watch video of course
memories is using computer vision to
actually identify photos of your pet and
pick the best scenes now it's great if I
can also rotate my phone now into
portrait and it automatically reformat
to take full advantage of the height of
the display
that's a quick look at memories now with
memories we're using machine learning to
help learn more about you and what
you're interested in by looking at your
photo library but now in iOS 11 Siri
does so much more in learning how you're
using your device so for instance if I'm
in Safari here and I'm reading about
Iceland maybe I'm considering taking a
trip there there's a reykjavik is a nice
location
well now Siri actually on my device
spots my interest so when I go let's say
into news Siri automatically surfaces
for me a recommendation that I might be
interested in news about Iceland could
just tap in and heart this one like this
and if I tap into a particular article
we can see it mentions certain locations
in Iceland I think this one is called
Naples anise I hope it's okay with
anyone to speak speaks Icelandic what's
great is now serious learning this
vocabulary knows it might be something
I'm going to use in my communication in
the future so when I go into messages
and start typing a message and let's say
I start typing Reykjavik we'll check it
out it learns that Reykjavik is probably
a word I might type and what about there
it is
knife Alanis pretty awesome now let's
take a look at stickers because you
notice now right on the bottom of the
display we have access to all my sticker
packs I can tap in on the bottom here to
my Star Wars sticker pack can tap and
slide say select music and we now have
Apple pay right here as a messages app
but what's so cool is if I receive a
message saying that I owe someone money
will you notice the quicktype keyboard
automatically surfaces Apple pay as an
option and picks the amount out is what
I might want to pay I can just tap the
pay button send and authenticate my
fingerprint and just like that I paid
with Apple pay and that the quick demo
file at 11
but wait there is more
start with maps now in iOS 10 maps
brought beautiful new clarity to
navigation and we're now giving you
enhanced information for when you get
there to the mall so we have detailed
floor plans now of malls with place
cards directory and search and we let
you browse by for we're gonna be
supporting
malls in all of these cities out the
gate and hundreds more per month
thereafter we're also bringing the
support to air major airports you can
see where security is so you can plan
now will be supporting all of these
airports to start and again building out
more over time and of course we have
more improvements to navigation so now
in the upper left you can even see your
speed limit I hope you're paying
attention to that and Lane Guidance so
you know which lane to be in to make
your next move when navigating no we
know in addition of navigation people
like to do more with their phones
sometimes while driving and our safest
solution for doing this is carplay let
you keep your eyes on the road while
you're doing things like asking Siri to
play music well we wanted to bring this
same level of safety to everyone who
maybe doesn't have one of the 200 models
of car that currently support car play
and we're building on do not disturb
with a new feature we call do not
disturb while driving and it's all about
keeping your eyes on the road when
you're driving you don't need to be
responding to these kinds of messages in
fact you don't need to see them so now
when you install iOS 11 we're going to
use bluetooth to understand if you're
connected to a car even if you don't
have Bluetooth we're going to use Wi-Fi
Doppler effect to measure that you're
moving in a car and when you finish that
first drive we're going to suggest hey
how about we activate do not disturb
while driving and when we do instead of
seeing all those notifications we have
this new user interface for you
now if you're tempted and you try to
turn on your phone you're actually going
to receive this little reminder that
you're not receiving notifications while
you're driving but of course you might
be sitting in the backseat which case
you can tell us I'm not driving you can
get through but what if you are driving
and someone sends you a message well
they can now get an automatic response
saying I'll see your message when I get
where I'm going and you can also enable
select people to break through if it's
especially urgent you get the peace of
mind that you can get contacted they can
reply urgent in that message we'll go
through we think this is going to be a
real important step in safety in the car
next up home kid so home kit provides a
secure and private way to automate all
of your devices your home accessories
and you can do it right inside the home
app and control them here and also of
course use your voice with Siri now
almost all the major accessory makers
are providing great home kit accessories
across all of these categories some
security cameras and door locks to
lights and fans but there's one category
really close to our heart that we wanted
to add to home kit and that's speakers
you'll now be able to configure your
speaker's inside of home kit and access
them via our new airplay to protocol it
builds multi-room audio in throughout
iOS so you can play music to select
speakers throughout your home right from
the music app and with Apple music we
have a new feature called shared up next
so if you have a friend over and you
have a playlist going maybe your friend
wants to contribute to that playlist
well they can do that without
interrupting the music you all can pile
into that party playlist now beat all
these speaker makers announce upcoming
support for airplay - but of course many
of us already own a great airplay
compatible speaker and those are the
ones connected to our Apple TV because
now your Apple TV can be played too from
your iPhone or iOS device and Mac
anywhere in the home and of course if
you turn on your Apple TV it can control
playback home wide including using Siri
and we're providing a great developer
API so third-party audio apps and iOS
can all get in on the multi-room audio
fun next is Apple music now last fall we
introduced - all new design for Apple
music which brought greater clarity and
simplicity to the Apple music experience
we now have 27 million customers who are
really enjoying the curation as well as
the personalization of Apple music but
of course a lot of the way we discover
music is to ask one of our friends what
have you been listening to late
so now in Apple music you'll be able to
find out right inside the application
for all the music served up and for you
you'll see indicators if this is music
your friends are listening to they can
configure their profile either puck to
be public or private and control what
playlist they share or whether all the
music they share they want to make
available to their other friends now for
developers we're also providing a new
API music kit for Apple music this
allows apps full access to the Apple
music service both on device and from
your cloud service and you can do a
tremendous amount with this now Nike has
done great exercise playlist using the
full Apple music catalog with Anchor
anyone can be a DJ using all 40 million
songs and should them can automatically
add songs to your collection that it
identifies you know one of the biggest
stories today for iOS 11 is about the
App Store now to give you the big news
with the App Store I'd like to hand it
off to Phil Schiller
thank you Thank You Craig
good morning everyone a tariff on the
way back come on good morning everyone I
am so excited to be able to talk to you
this morning about the App Store the App
Store is turning nine years old and it
is going so well there are five hundred
million weekly visitors to the App Store
who come to see your amazing apps and to
download them they have now downloaded
over 180 billion apps to date that's
incredible that does not include Auto
read downloads and updates amazing
and just recently we passed seventy
billion dollars paid out to developers
today 30% of that in the last year alone
the apps are incredible and customers
are doing things with them that none of
us had ever imagined like this these are
people in Hong Kong playing Pokemon go
Pokemon goes from Niantic it was one of
the big hits from last year and they've
been a lot of big hits last year from
big developers and indie developers
alike and together the developers at
Apple we've made this the best app
platform in the world so thank you
yes thank you for the incredible apps
you make that we and our customers all
love it's not by chance that the app
stores become such a great place from
the beginning we've had two very
important goals to make the app store a
trusted and safe place for users and to
make it a great opportunity for all
developers we continue to work really
hard at that over the last year the team
has done a lot of great things to make
the App Store even better store for all
of us there's many things we can talk
about but I think one stands head and
shoulders above the rest
faster app review times I'm sure you're
well aware that the majority of apps are
all now reviewed in under 24 hours many
in just one to two hours the team is
going to keep working hard at that and
we have a lot more coming for the
remainder of the year I've highlighted a
bunch of things here I'll just point out
one of them you can read some of your
favorite things up there of big requests
and developers is called phased releases
that when you suggest roof or phrase
releases climb phase releases mean when
you submit an app you can choose if you
want it to be phased over time so it
doesn't hit your infrastructure all at
once and you can see how customers are
responding to that update so it's really
great feature for you to take advantage
of and there are a lot of things coming
this year but there is there is one that
is incredibly gigantic and that is we're
going to do something that we've never
done before in the nine years of the app
store we're going to completely redesign
it a brand new app store it is
absolutely beautiful
the App Store starts with a brand new
tab called today did you remember that
the first time you started downloading
apps when you use the App Store and it
was so much fun to go in every single
day and discover the new apps that were
appearing and that's an amazing feeling
and we're bringing that back again with
this brand new tab called today a whole
new way to discover apps it's a place
where we can feature the apps we all
love and the stories about the
developers who created them it's going
to be such a great place for customers
to discover your apps every single day
there's another new tab games games the
biggest area the App Store has its own
dedicated space now so for all of us who
love gaming and finding the best feature
games of the day and seeing charts of
all gaming this is now a place to go to
experience all the top Nealon games and
not only can we feature games but for
the first time the App Store we can
feature in app purchases as well a big
part of your business is now they're in
the App Store so the next time if a
brand new level if a brand new character
customers can see them right in the App
Store and click on them and start the
process to get them right away
and since games have their own tab now
apps have their own tab this is
everything that we love about apps
besides games with dedicated features
and charts all there for customers to
enjoy and every app in every game of
course has its own product page in the
store these are more beautiful than ever
more engaging with incredible videos
you're going to love all the features on
your product pages and the sessions here
at WWC to learn how to take advantage of
all those great new app page features
these are just some of the new things in
the all new app store the new today tab
the games tab new apps tab and would
love to show it to you live for the very
first time
so please welcome anti product marketing
manager for the App Store to the stage
and
thanks Bill I'm so excited to show you
the new app door so let's get to it I'm
going to open the store and I land right
here on The Today tab the new front of
the app store that updates every day the
first thing I see is our top story the
world premiere of Monument Valley - is
finally here let's check it out by
tapping on the card
this opens a story view where we can
learn more about the game and what makes
it so great looks like this is going to
be even more beautiful than the first
I can watch videos that show me what the
gameplay is like and here's a cool quote
from Dan gray at us two games about what
inspired them I can share the story with
a friend and what's incredible is that
we can actually all download this today
only on the App Store let's see what
else is happening today what have we got
here oh here's a how-to guide about
visco I use this app all the time let's
check it out this is packed full of
useful tips so even if you have an app
already you still might learn something
new like I didn't know you could use it
to make animated gif or Jif anyway you
can make them I just scroll back up and
pull down on the card and I'm back in
the feed every day there's a new app of
the day and a new game of the day and
the daily list these are great because
they're focused on a theme or a goal
like meditation I've actually been
trying some of these out to get ready
for this and it's totally working
if I'm busy and miss a day I can scroll
down and see stories from earlier in the
week so that's the today tab if I only
want to see games now I can go to the
new games tab this is huge let's check
it out up at the top I can see the
biggest new releases or just let the
game editors are playing this week I
scroll down I can watch a whole bunch of
game videos and it's not just previews
but also tips and gameplay videos by
editors too if I scroll down I can see
charts that only feature games so it's
really easy to see what the most popular
games are separate from app and now I
can browse by game categories too this
page is just packed full of
recommendations this artsy game looks
fun let's check it out I'm going to tap
on the icon and it opens up a redesigned
app page it's more beautiful and more
useful I can watch more videos that show
me how fun this is
and this badge at the top tells me it
was named editor's choice if I scroll
down I can see ratings and reviews front
and center so I can see what other
customers think before making a choice
like this review it tells me this game
is great for killing time thanks furious
potato-faced for all the incredible apps
on the store there's a new tab to the
apps tab let's go there it shares the
same great design as the games tab but
with a focus just on app so that was
just the first day on the new App Store
now you can see why we're so excited to
have a beautiful new place to share apps
and games we love with you back to you
Phil
[Music]
thank you n so that's her first glimpse
of an entirely new app store we hope you
love it
he'll customers love it they visit it
every single day to download your
incredible apps and that's it for the
App Store back to you Craig Thank You
Phil the app store looks just fantastic
so those are some of the big features in
iOS 11 but of course it's also core
technologies now metal 2 and HEV C
coming to iOS as well but there's more
and it starts with machine learning now
you've seen the way we've used machine
learning throughout the experience as an
Apple watch for instance in the
predictive Siri watch face we use it on
the iPad for palm rejection when you're
writing with Apple pencil of course we
use it to extend your battery life by
predicting how you're going to use your
device and you've seen it throughout
photos with memories and face
recognition well now for all of you
developers we want to make powerful
machine learning easy for you to
incorporate in your apps and we're doing
it via a set of new api's starts with a
vision API which provides face tracking
face detection landmarks all of these
core features we use inside of our apps
and the natural language API that
provides capabilities like tokenization
and named entity recognition now these
are all built on core ml and core ml
provides high performance
implementations of deep neural networks
for current neural networks
convolutional neural network support
vector machines and they allow you to
take models that you've built with any
of these popular third-party tools and
using our machine learning model
converter execute them with tremendous
performance on device because you all
the data privacy benefits and all of the
carefully tuned compatibility with all
of our platforms and the performance
really is incredible you look at this
benchmarks called inception v3 it's a
popular photo recognition benchmark
iPhone is six times faster than Google
pixel and the Samsung
sh using 4ml next I'd like to turn to a
are now with multi-touch we've really
changed the way that you interact with
the world on the screen of your iPhone
and with the camera it allows you to
capture the world around you but when
you bring these things together the
results can actually be quite profound
now it's called augmented reality and we
have a new core technology called AR kit
to bring it to all of you and I'd like
to show it to you and a demo now so
we've all seen a lot of carefully edited
vision videos on this topic recently but
in this case I'd like to show you
something for real so what we see here
is an iPhone that's look using its
camera but using the computer vision
it's actually able to identify surfaces
such as this table and I can actually
just add an object this is a developer
application a test application that
you'll all be getting code for that
allows you to do these things now this
is a virtual object on this table now
get them some steam in there coming off
the cup now I can add other objects to
the scene and these things can actually
interact let's add a lamp and I want you
to watch when I turn the lamp off on the
dynamic shadows here I'm going to move
the cup and watch how the shadow moves
in relationship to the light here it's
really pretty incredible now I can add
additional objects puts out a vase to
this to this scene I mean isn't that
just incredible you guys are actually in
the shot here with these objects all in
augmented reality so it gives you a
little bit of an idea of the technology
involved it's really pretty incredible
now how do we do it we're a Ark it
provides fast and stable motion tracking
and it uses all of the sensors and the
camera and your device to do this it
actually binds planes like floors and
tables it's able to estimate ambient
light which helps us with the rendering
and also helps with scale you notice
that cup hits the table looking the size
of a cup and not the size of an elephant
and we provide integration to all kinds
of third-party frameworks to help you
with your rendering but the
implementation is possible because we're
able to take advantage of the awesome
hardware and iOS devices the cameras the
high-performance CPU and GPU and the
motion sensors when you bring the
software together with these devices we
actually have hundreds and of millions
of iPhones and iPads that are going to
be capable of a are in fact that's going
to make overnight a arc it the largest
AR platform in the world
we've had some third parties in to take
a look at AR kit and they are totally
excited and we are just blown away by
what they may been able to accomplish
IKEA of course is placing furniture
everywhere and its really super awesome
but check this out what you can do with
Batman Lego I mean how fun is this right
on the table a Lego with a live Lego
Batman and you can explode the Lego like
you like you can never do in the real
world pan around it and interact with
Batman right there it's really awesome
and then Pokemon go we've all seen it
before but check it out with a our kid
the Pokemon is so real he's right there
on the ground as the ball bounces it
actually bounces right there in the real
environment it's AR like you've never
seen it before now
there's there's one of these that I
think you just really need to see see
live now wing nut AR is director Peter
Jackson's new production company it's
dedicated to producing a our content we
all know Peter Jackson from his
incredible cinematic work on movies like
the Lord of the Rings series but he's
now really excited about AR and to show
you what he has in the works I'm
thrilled to introduce wingnut ARS
creative director alistair cool
Alistair thanks Craner we're really
excited to share an exclusive sneak peek
it's something we've been working on
with ar kit you don't need any special
equipment or tracking markers it just
works
dance here with me for weena AR so let's
take a look here we're using AR kit to
detect play no table estimated size and
locker content on the surface and since
this is augmented reality you folks are
all in the shop
this is all rendered in real time using
the power of Unreal Engine 4 we're at a
remote outpost on a desolate world for
supplies are scarce airships come here
to refuel get repairs and to trade these
are our town smoke they're expecting to
visitors soon so they're all starting
get ready for their arrival except this
guy died here apparently new heart hip
that's our airships arriving there and
what's really cool here is that with the
ark it's tracking you can get really
close and choose how to view the action
it's like you're the director of your
own experience Oh looks like some
Raiders are attacking
[Music]
whoa I guess that takes care that guy
one of the cool to bear ship battles
like this in your own living rooms
oh I think the dirt road rash hacking
this Airport and another one down
and we got them
Oh
these well that didn't end well for
anyone but our heroes are limping away
to fight another day
so that's one of the things we've up to
wing Nighy our and the fact that our kid
[Applause]
thank you the fact the ark enabled and
millions of people to jaian says like
this opens up so many possibilities I
think it's a real game-changer look out
for any are experience from us in the
App Store later this year thank you so
what do you think so those are some of
the major features in iOS 11 of course
there's much more than we have time to
talk about today but I want to highlight
some features of special interests to
our customers in China like QR code
support integrated right into the main
camera accessible from the lockscreen
super usable yes super useful for
customers in China so that's our update
for iOS 11 I'm going to turn it back to
Tim thank you
iOS the lovin is absolutely jam-packed
with great features and I can't wait for
you to get your hands on the new app
store and a arquette number-5 an
important part of the iOS story is the
course iPad iPad has completely changed
the way we work play teach learn and
create it's truly a magical piece of
glass that transforms into anything you
want we've been pushing the boundaries
on iPad and today we're going to push
them further than ever before and to
tell you all about it I'd like to invite
up jaws job
thank you Tim and good morning everybody
I'm so excited to talk to you today
about iPad pro when we first introduced
iPad pro just eighteen months ago it
completely redefined what you can do
with your iPad along with your
incredible apps that allowed our users
to do really amazing things from
professional design and illustration to
fashion to architecture engineering and
so much more we're really excited about
what can be real in your world today
with iPad pro well as you know there's
two models the iPad pro today there's a
13 inch and a nine point seven inch and
the nine point seven inch is our most
popular model it has a screen large
enough to get your work done but it's in
a thin and light enough package allows
you to take it with you everywhere you
go
well today we're going to introduce an
all-new iPad pro is going to take
everything you love about the nine point
seven inch and give you a whole lot more
to love let's take a look this the new
iPad pro
it's the first iPad pro with a larger
ten and a half inch Retina display
now why ten and a half inch well for one
it's a lot larger its 20% larger than a
nine point seven inch but we were able
to reduce the borders by nearly 40
percent which allows us submitted in
this incredibly compact design that
still weighs just one pound and of
course ten point five inch also allows
us to do some other things it's the
perfect size to allow us to display a
full size on-screen keyboard it's also
the perfect size to allow us to have a
full size smart keyboard as well and
when we deliver the smart Keyboard we're
going to have support for more than 30
languages at launch including Chinese
and for the very first time a Japanese
Jaya keyboard now iPad pro has always
had the best displays in the industry
and both sizes are going to get really
incredible new displays today they're
the best displays that we've ever made
they're packed with incredible features
like true tone for automatic white
balance p3 wide color gamut for the best
color ultra low reflectivity the best in
the industry and a 50% brighter with 600
nits and this extra brightness in the p3
wide color gamut means that with iOS 11
you'll be able to display HDR video for
the first time in an iPad for a really
immersive cinematic experience they're
truly awesome displays but our biggest
breakthrough is a feature we call
promotion so what is promotion well we
were able to take our unique hardware
and software capabilities and
dramatically improve our display
performance now typically up until today
mobile displays have refreshed at 60
Hertz means they update their content 60
times every second while on the new iPad
pro we've doubled that maximum refresh
rate to an incredible 120 Hertz
so what does that mean to you it means
that all of your motion content on your
screen is going to be smoother crisper
more responsive now this is something
you have to really touch and feel
yourself to appreciate because our
projection systems just aren't capable
of doing those type of refresh rates but
I'll tell you the difference is dramatic
and when you scroll it's buttery smooth
now the higher refresh rate also means
it works even better with the Apple
pencil we already have the
industry-leading performance for drawing
and writing with the Apple pencil but
with pro motion it gets even better it's
more responsive and it reduces our
latency to an industry best 20
milliseconds so drawing is incredibly
fluid and even more natural you're going
to love using the Apple pencil with the
new iPad pro another breakthrough
promotion is that deep become the first
mobile displays to be able to
dynamically adjust the refresh rate
depending on what you're looking at this
is a really big breakthrough for both
display quality as well as for power
savings so would you have fast moving
content they can update quickly but they
can also update slower when you don't
need that type of refresh rate for
example a still image this allows us to
save a lot of energy and give you a
better battery life so hopefully you see
why these are not just the best displays
that we've ever made but we think
they're the most advanced displays on
the planet next let's talk about
performance iPad is already
best-in-class for performance but we're
not resting on our laurels these are the
fastest we've ever created inside them
they're powered by the a 10x fusion chip
the a 10x has a six core CPU three
high-performance course three high
efficiency cores all automatically
managed by the Apple performance
controller it also has a 12 core GPU
this is a powerhouse and it delivers 30%
faster CPU performance overall already
industry-leading a9x and 40% faster
graphics performance
our chip team has done just an amazing
job over the years with the performance
improvements that the results have been
staggering they're delivering an
industry-leading graphics performance
that's more than 500 times the original
iPad from just a few years ago but of
course numbers only tell part of the
story to demonstrate the real-world
performance of the a 10x in the new iPad
pro I'd like to invite Ashe Hewson of
Sarah to give you a demo of their new
Profoto editing app called affinity
photo at thank you so I'm thrilled today
to be able to show you the iPad version
of affinity photo this is a truly
high-end professional photo editing tool
and on this latest iPad pro we can
achieve levels of performance which is
simply unattainable on any other device
and I'm going to try and show you that
today by creating a movie poster I've
already setup a few layers I've kind of
got this great background some stormy
sky I've got a turbulent sea and this
ship now the first thing you'll notice
when you're using this is as you'll kind
move your layers around rotating them or
even just sort of panning and zooming
around your work I'm seeing all of this
now at 120 frames a second so it just
feels incredibly smooth but when you
come to edit layers because of metal we
can achieve performance more than four
times an i7 quad-core desktop PC and
I'll show you what that means on this C
I'm going to apply a twelve filter and
look just through my finger I can kind
of push this C around I can even just
like flick a wave right over the side of
the ship is a totally new way to kind of
interact with your designs and actually
everything is this fast so let's say I
wanted to set this ship on fire
for example I've got this fireball here
I can move this over the back of the
ship but to make that look more
realistic I need to apply blend mode now
normally blend modes are something that
takes a lot of trial and error but now
look at this I can just scrub down here
and I get an instant preview of all the
different blend modes so it makes it
really really easy to select the right
blend mode that I want now of course
everything I've done so far I've done
using touch but with iPad pro
we have the best stylist that's ever
been made and we can do some great stuff
with Apple pencil too
a really good example of that is our
lighting filter so here are choose
lighting make that a bit bigger and look
I can actually control now the angle and
the tilt of that light using Apple
pencil
there's no latency whatsoever so it's a
really immersive way to work now I said
at the start I was creating a movie
poster and in fact what I'm actually
doing is creating a pirate movie poster
so now I need a pirate and I've got
Captain Jack Sparrow here but at the
moment of course he's on the wrong
background so what I need to do is cut
him out and I'm going to use some
selection tools to do that so to start
with I'm just going to do and you can
see how quick it is to do a really quick
selection with pencil to sort of snap
around the edges but of course with
selections what often happens is you
need to do much more accurate selection
around here and to do that we're going
to do a selection of Fineman this is
something that takes a huge amount of
CPU power but on this latest iPad it's
twice as fast as ever before
and you can see pretty much instantly I
get a selection down to individual
strands of hair
[Applause]
and that's it that's my poster
completely professional-looking poster
created on a design on a device that I
can hold in my hands it's really
incredible I really think that iPad pro
alongside affinity photo is a truly
game-changing experience for
professional photo editing and the best
thing of all is that you can now
experience it now because I'm delighted
to announce that affinity photo for iPad
is available on the App Store from today
thank you wow thanks thank you ask
that's amazing performance again
especially for a device that's still
thin in light in a simple 1 pound
package you could take with you
everywhere you go and what's also cools
despite all is the form to new iPad pro
still delivers the same all-day 10 hour
battery life their iPad users love next
to talk about cameras the new iPad pro
features the latest camera system from
our iPhone 7 that means the same high
performance 12 megapixel sensor with
optical image stabilization and it has
the ability to even capture and of
course edit 4k video on the go
so absolutely fantastic cameras the
front-facing cameras from the iPhone 7
as well with all this great features
like wide color gamut capture auto image
stabilization and the entire display can
light up to become the world's brightest
and largest retina flash
we have great accessories as well the
iPad pro supports USB 3 which means that
you're going to get faster transfers
with eur/usd and SD camera adapters and
this also so we also support fast
charging means any of our USB C charge
adaptors will now allow you to charge at
half the time and we have great new
smart covers we have available in
polyurethane and then we're bringing
back the popular leather as well and
then we've designed an all new leather
sleeve with a built-in storage for your
Apple pencil steps the new iPad pro
family a lineup with the world's most
advanced displays including a brand new
10 and 1/2 inch size and incredibly
compact design powerful new a 10x fusion
chip and
new cameras and of course as you would
expect we make all these in incredibly
environmentally friendly ways we're also
going to double the amount of memory
that comes at the beginning of these
configurations both both sizes will now
start with 64 gigabytes of memory and a
ten and a half inch with 64 gigs will
now be at 6:49 and it's just 150 dollars
more to move up to the bigger display at
$7.99 we're also going to have
configurations in 256 and 512 gigabytes
half a terabyte of storage in an iPad
and as always you can get any of these
models with LTE as well so this is the
new iPad pro you can order them today
they'll start shipping next week and of
course because they're shipping now
they're going to ship with iOS 10 which
will be able to easily update to iOS 11
it's a free update this fall but you
haven't heard the full iOS 11 story yet
as relates to iPad so I'd like to invite
Craig back to the stage to tell you
about some incredible iPad features
coming in iOS 11 okay thank you hey
everybody
yes there is more I owe s11
if you love iPad like I do will buckle
up for a while you're in for a wild ride
we are taking iOS to the next level this
is the largest iOS release for iPad
we've ever done now it starts with the
dock and we all know that dock hovering
down there at the bottom of the screen
it is more powerful than ever you can
fill it with app on the right there's a
predictive area figures out what you're
going to use next including your
continuity apps and now you can summon
the dock from anywhere right from the
bottom of the screen and use it for
switching apps just like that and what's
incredible is how it's used for
multitasking so now if you're in an app
and you swipe up we can pull an app out
just like that in the slide over
now of course you can snap your apps
into split view but what's really cool
is the new app switcher because it
preserves all of your spaces with your
app pairings it's really great now the
iPad of course is the ultimate multi
handed multi-touch device and so we're
so excited to bring drag and drop to
iPad you can drag images you can drag
text you can drag URLs you can
multi-select and multi hand drag it's a
drag fest now incredibly productive but
of course sometimes you have to type and
so we made the keyboard even more
productive as well
you can now flick on keys to access
punctuation and numbers all without
switching planes it's super fast and
super easy
now we have a new app to introduce to
you today and it's called files files
brings together all your files on your
iPad it supports everything you'd expect
nested folders spring loading list view
favorites search tags and it has this
beautiful recent view that pulls it all
together across all of your sources
because it supports not only iCloud
it also supports third-party storage
providers like box Dropbox onedrive and
Google Drive and they're all right here
in your sidebar you know what let's do a
demo let's take our first look at i/o
s11 on iPad so here we have our new dock
at the bottom now I can easily drag
right into the dock just like this it's
a great way to launch apps as always but
now it's also a great way to switch apps
just tap like that now if I want to
multitask check this out drag it out
it's right there now I can slide it off
the screen I can out slide it over here
both these views are completely live I
can go into split view just like this
but I want you to check out the new app
switcher I'm just going to swipe for up
from the bottom and keep swiping goes
back like that let's do that again that
is so great so that easy
now you notice my spaces are preserved
so over here on the left I had mail and
Safari and splitview I can just tap
those open like this let's try some
drag-and-drop so I'm going to drag a URL
from the top of Safari here right into
this mail message drag it and drop it
now I can drag it yepp let's drag an
image yep
just like that now I want to focus just
on mail because I'm going to show you
dragging across spaces so let's go into
photos I have some great photos here of
some potential drone protection options
for the new campus so I'm going to start
a drag but watch this with my other hand
I'm going to tap I can add to this
selection just like that and I can even
swipe up with my other hand into
multitasking move over to mail and drop
now I want to show you files I can bring
up files of course right from the dock
in split view just like this and it's a
great way to deal with attachments
because I can take this attachment and
this mail message pick it up and just
drop it right into this folder of
top-secret projects now let's dive all
the way in and take a closer look at the
files app we see it has this gorgeous
grid view but it also has a ListView
that provides me all the details about
my files I can sort them by size or
let's sort by date now I can create new
folders let's say I want to create an R
and D folder right here I'm going to
take some of my top-secret prospective
projects and I can do multi select just
like this drop them in now I can also
take the folder drag it right in to my
favorite so these are synced across all
of my devices and if I want to tag a
file of course I just drag it right on
there and make that one important and
you notice in addition to iCloud here on
the Left I've accessed all my cloud
providers like box so you can see I have
files here I'm using folders that I'm
using for collaboration and that
includes this drone defense proposal
right here presentation I want to show
you when I go into the recent view from
the tab at the bottom notice I get a
view across everything including that
one inside a box I'm going to tap into
that keynote presentation and for my
final act I want to show you how can use
files directly from the dock just swipe
up by tap and hold I get access to my
recent assets I can just pick this up
drop it down just like that and that is
a quick demo of our productivity
features on iPad
now next or talk about Apple pencil
because Apple pencil has really created
a whole new way of working on iPad and
with iOS 11 we've integrated it deeply
into the system now it starts with
markup because you can markup anything
you can quick look you can take Safari
content we create it into a continuous
scrolling view that you can markup you
can actually do this with any app that
supports printing because we have a
create PDF option that will create a
markup PDF it's a really great way to
mark up anything and share it we know a
lot of people do like to share with
screenshots and so now when you take a
screenshot we'll create a thumbnail down
on the bottom of the screen if you tap
it you go instantly into markup you can
mark it up right there and share it now
we've all it's really cool now we've
also integrated pencil deeply into nodes
so if you're working on a note later
you're at the lock screen you want to
get back just a tap of the pencil the
lock screen and you're right back into
your note and we've made your note
handwritten text searchable so we can
now search handwriting we use deep
learning to recognize what you write and
if you're doing primarily typed notes
you can now also do inline draw in line
drawings right there it's very handy
now of course sometimes we still have to
deal with paper so notes now has a built
in document scanner it can correct
perspective and contrast and when you
bring the note in you can mark it up
right with your pencil and we've
integrated markup in the mail as well so
you can personalize your mail messages
with inline drawings now for a look at
all of these great new pencil features
I'd like to introduce the man who heads
iPad software engineering for us tobe
Patterson for a live demo Coby good
morning well the first thing I want to
show you is a quick way of getting to
your notes using your Apple pencil you
just tap on the lock screen like this
and it slides up to reveal your notes
beneath it now you can see here I've got
a handwritten note and I want to show
you how easy it is to create one of
these watch at the top of the note here
as I edit the title just by putting a
pencil down and writing like this after
the 2017 keynote it's as natural as
putting pencil to paper
now something paper can't help you with
is finding your notes again later we're
using machine learning to recognize your
handwriting and index it in spotlight
let's switch into spotlight now and
we'll search for that text that I just
wrote how you can see here I've got the
new flick keyboard which makes it really
easy to enter numbers just by swiping
down on the keys like this and you can
see there it's already found my note as
the top hit even with my atrocious
handwriting we'll just tap on that and
we're back at the note
now I'm going to switch to a different
note now because I want to show you how
you can mix drawing with tight text and
tables and all of notes as other great
features this is a note that my young
daughter shared with me as part of a
school assignment where she had to work
with her parents to develop an idea for
a new app now she asked me how many
copies of our app I thought I might sale
we might sell and so I want to quickly
draw a graph to give her some idea of
that I'm just going to press down here
with the pencil to make some space for
my drawing and we can take that little
grabber and open up some more room now I
am really bad at drawing but I just love
doing it and what's great about drawing
on the iPad is it works the same way as
it does with paper and that means it's
really easy for me to draw really badly
right here watch I'm just gonna put the
pencil down and just like that it's so
simple and I think you're going to have
a lot of fun rediscovering the joy of
drawing but let's move on now
so my daughter's learnt a few things
from me about how Apple works and before
I left this morning she gave me an NDA
to sign I'm going to use the new
document scanner and notes my pencil to
take care of that in a snap we'll just
tap the plus button here to bring up the
document scanner and all I need to do is
point the camera at the piece of paper
notes will take the picture
automatically even straighten the page
up we'll open it up full screen here and
now I just fill in the blanks with my
pencil and just like that I've got a
signed copy of the NDA saved away in my
notes now I see my daughter sent me a
message and it must be pretty important
if she's interrupts to my demo so if
you'll excuse me I'm just going to tap
on that see what she has to say Wow
an offer for a hundred million dollars
is really pretty thrilling I need to
send this to my wife right away I'm
going to take a screenshot of this and
then we'll tap on the thumbnail here to
open up our new screenshot editing UI
from here I can
drop it down to just a part of the image
that I want to send I can scribble a
quick note with my pencil and then I can
bring up the share sheet to send it off
to my wife right away so these are just
a few of the ways you can use your
pencil with your iPad in iOS 11 back to
you now Craig thank you it is so great
when your grade school child gets a
hundred million dollars of funding they
just they do grow up so fast these days
well so these are some of the great new
features for the iPad and of course
they're joined by all of these other
features you heard from earlier today
we're really excited about what we're
doing with iPad this year and really
excited about iOS 11 now iOS 11 is
available to all of you developers today
if you sign up at Beta Apple comm and
get a beta at the end of the month and
we're making it available as a free
upgrade to everyone in the fall supports
all of these devices that is your update
for iOS 11 I'm going to turn it back
over to Tim thank you
thank you iOS 11 really takes iPad to a
whole new level people are going to be
able to do more in more places than ever
before we're so excited about the
marriage of iOS 11 and the new iPad pro
that we made a video and I'd love to run
it for you
[Music]
you keep my hands on my stuff because up
the bottom back up on the Shelf little
David girl isn't me we can find a waffle
[Music]
I hope you're as excited about the new
iPad pro and iOS 11 as we are now we've
got one last thing to talk to you about
let's turn our attention to music music
has always been a part of Apple's DNA we
first revolutionized the music industry
with iTunes then we forever change the
way people listen to music on the go
with the iPod and today iPhone has
become the best portable music player in
the world and it's even better when it's
paired with Apple music you now have 40
million songs in your pocket and when
you add air pod it brings an absolutely
magical experience to wireless audio now
so we have such a great portable music
experience but what about our homes we
think we can do a lot to make this
experience much better just like we did
with portable music we want to reinvent
home music and I'd like to invite Phil
up to tell you all about it
thank you this is really exciting the
chance to reinvent the way we enjoy
music in the home can't think of
anything that matters more to so many of
us why hasn't this happen yet there
certainly are a lot of companies hard at
work making products to enjoy music in
our home but none of them have quite
nailed it yet some have worked hard to
make Wireless music sound good around
our homes but these aren't smart
speakers others have worked to make
smart speakers so you can talk to the
down sound so great when you listen to
music we want to combine all this and
the product can really deliver a
breakthrough spear Ian's
and our team has been hard at work for
many years now on a breakthrough home
speaker and it has to do a few things
really great if it's going to be a great
breakthrough speaker first needs to rock
the house right we need to enjoy our
music whatever genre you love really low
we're really loud free from distortion
second it needs to be spatially aware
it's going to fit in different rooms in
our house and it needs to be smart
enough to know what to do to make the
music sound great third has to be really
fun to use it has to have a built-in
musicologist an expert on music who can
help us to hear the music we'd love or
discover music we're going to love now
we're working on this speaker for later
this year but we want to give you 6,000
of our closest friends a sneak peek at
it this morning and here it is
[Music]
[Applause]
it is absolute beautiful and we call it
home pod just like iPod reinvented music
in our pockets home pod is going to
reinvent music in our homes so let's
talk about these features first rock the
house the home pod is just under 7
inches tall it's covered in a seamless
3d mesh fabric that has incredible
acoustic properties and it hides within
it amazing audio technology for example
along the bottom is a 7 array being
formed tweeter pack that's packed with
seven tweeters each with their own
individual driver their precision
acoustic horns that drive the audio from
within and they're not along the bottom
with tremendous directional control and
that'll become really clear in a bit as
we talk about how it works it has a
really big Wooper 4 inch woofer
upward-facing with a large motor to move
a lot of air that's automatic base
equalization and dynamic software
modeling so that as we turn the volume
up it's free from distortion and all of
this is controlled by an Apple a8 chip
yes the same chip that powers the inside
of our iPhone is inside home pod it's
perhaps the biggest brain ever in a
speaker it does some incredible thing
it does real-time acoustic modeling
audio beamforming and multi-channel echo
cancellation you have to know what any
of that is just know that it sounds
incredible next talk about this spatial
awareness what does that mean well you
plug in your home pod AC and it gets it
to music wirelessly and it's compact
enough you can put it most anywhere in
your house you can put it on a table on
a shelf against the wall in a corner and
then intelligently and automatically
detects the space that's within and it
uses that information to adjust the
audio to balance it and take full
advantage of the environment and create
a very spacious sound now we want to
give you a sense of what that experience
is like so we want to play some music in
this room and show you a visual
simulation to give you an understanding
of some of the technologies that's using
and how it's adapting them to make an
incredible sound of this compact speaker
so going to start by playing an audio
track and it'll be a full mix and then
we're going to break it down into some
of the components that the home pod
controls
[Music]
so that's a full Rix audio mix but
within it home pod detects the center
vocal and can use beamforming to direct
that gives incredible clarity precision
and then it can detect something called
direct energy with the instrumentation
and direct out in the room as well in
addition to that direct energy there's
something that's usually missing in
music Andy and audio the backing vocals
and reverb home pod can direct all of
this and pull it together to a full rich
mix that fills up your room
[Music]
[Applause]
it's a really remarkable experience to
hear this kind of a spacious sound come
from such a compact speaker if you loved
one you should see what it's like when
you set up two they automatically work
together to give this incredible
spacious sound that really is the power
to rock your house next a musicologist
this intelligent helper to help us
discover the music we love home pod has
incredible speaker system that works
together with our Apple music
subscription from the beginning it's
designed to work with that now Apple
music as you know provides music in the
cloud and the speaker can get it
directly from the cloud you can get 40
million tracks 2 million artists tens of
thousands of playlists but not just any
music library this is your music library
it knows the playlist you've setup it
knows the artists you love and all of
them stream directly to your home pod it
works with an array of six microphones
around the middle so as you talk to it
and you say those magic words hey Siri
you see a waveform light up on top and
now can respond to your commands and
help serve up the music you want to hear
the Siri team has worked very hard to
adapt the domain of music and Siri to be
even greater and understand more of the
questions we're going to ask about music
simple things obviously like play beats
1 radio we all want to do that or play
unhoppy check it out if you don't know
what that's about
play something new who's singing on this
track something I ask outside was
playing drums on this track the complex
questions like what was the top song on
May 5th 2016 we just play more like that
or I like that song is a free-form Siri
doesn't need a specific list of commands
that can interpret what you're saying
and help you discover the music you love
and even better you don't have to just
sit next to the home pod to talk to it
it can be across the room
and speak to the home pod even while
loud music is playing and if speaker ray
and the microphones can can pick it up
and hear what you're saying so home pod
there's the power to rock the house it's
spacial awareness so that understands
the rooms we place it within and is the
fun interactivity of Siri becoming a
musicologist and helping us to listen to
the music we love and since series
built-in there and you can speak to it
where the team's also worked hard to
make it a great and helpful home
assistant as well we said the domain of
music is something Cyrano's really well
in home pod there are other domains as
well we've worked hard to pick the first
ones that we think matter most in a
product like home pods of course and
play your podcast but it can also do
things like give you news give you
weather traffic sports you can ask it to
set a reminder set a timer catch someone
with messages and if you have home kids
devices set up your home you can speak
to your home pod and control your home
kit devices so for example for the home
pod setup you can say when do the Red
Sox play next can beat the Yankees trust
me two to NPR instead flip a coin remind
you to bring snacks to a party you can
set up reminders check all these sports
news and weather all directly with your
voice talk to a home pod to gets the
information directly from the cloud and
if you have homekit devices set up you
can say simple things like are the
lights on turn the heat up turn on the
air conditioning bring the shades down
halfway turn off the lights in the
bedroom and if you've set up themes in
home kick you can control those as well
you can say I'm home it's movie time
I'm leaving now and the whole scene can
automatically happen just by talking to
your home pod and because there is a
home pod base a home kid base built into
home pod that means anywhere in the
world once you've set up your first home
pod you control your home kit devices
remotely using the built-in home app on
your iPhone or iPad now setting up a
home pod and it's microphone array
in your home you probably have a
question that we've worked really hard
to deal with which is privacy our team
cares deeply about your privacy so for
example there's that magic phrase hey
Siri until you say it nothing's being
sent to Apple it recognizes when you do
say it and from that point it sends an
anonymous Siri ID in order to help you
with the command you're looking for and
of course that communication is all
encrypted so this is the home pod to
break through home speaker typically
Wi-Fi speakers if they're good quality
or 300 to 500 dollars they're smart
speaker might cost you 100 to 200
dollars so it's not unreasonable for a
home pod to be priced in the range of
400 to 700 dollars so we're really
excited to tell you that home pod is
going to be priced for 349 dollars
comes in white space gray they'll start
shipping this December first in the US
UK and Australia and then next year
we'll start bringing it around the world
so that's home pod back to you Tim thank
you
it is so cool we really believe it's
going to take your home music experience
to the next level now it's been an
incredible morning we've shared with you
lots of things this morning and all of
them are shipping this year some now
some in the fall and others at the end
of the year we got started with watch OS
more intuitive and intelligent than ever
before
incredible new features to help us live
a healthier life Mac OS hi Sierra
great refinements and technology that
will push the Mac OS experience forward
updates the MacBook MacBook Pro and IMAX
faster and more capable than ever before
an iOS 11 a major update of the world's
best and most advanced mobile operating
system absolutely jam-packed with new
features including a completely new app
store peer-to-peer payments and Apple
pay and with a arkyd iOS 11 becomes the
world's largest augmented reality
platform overnight iPad taken to a whole
new level with incredible iPad features
in iOS 11 it's the biggest release for
iPad ever of course a new lineup of iPad
pro with an all-new perfect 10.5 inch
size would advanced displays powerful
new features that enable people to do
more with their iPads than ever before
and we gave you two sneak peeks
I Mac Pro an entirely new workstation
class of products that we designed
specifically for our pro users and the
home pod a breakthrough home speaker
with amazing sound in incredible
intelligence it will reinvent home audio
now we have a hands-on area for the
press set up to it to attend immediately
after the keynote and for all developers
we welcome you to come by from 4 to 7
p.m. this evening we've got over a
hundred sessions planned for you this
week and over a thousand Apple engineers
here to spend time with you so take
advantage of the time tomorrow we've got
a special fireside chat planned in the
morning in this room and someone will be
joining us that's devoted her entire
career to highlighting and encouraging
young people women and doers I'm very
excited to tell you that Michelle Obama
will join
[Applause]
he'll be joining us for the open session
in this room tomorrow and she'll be
talking about empowering people from all
walks of life to change the world this
is a very special treat and I encourage
everyone to come I hope everyone here
has a fantastic week
thank you thank you
[Applause]