>> My desk is on the seventh
floor, if you need anything, you
can call me.
Make sure to keep your ID with
you because you're going to need
to badge in every time you
reenter.
The cafeteria is on the fourth
floor and we generally take
lunch about 12:30.
>> Cool. This is where I'm
sitting?
>> For now, yeah.
With the big move coming up,
it's kind of crazy around here.
I promise it's only temporary.
>> All right, thank you.
>> Mm-hmm.
[ Music ]
[ Foreign Language ]
[ Baby Crying ]
[ Music ]
>> Come let us in, we need
Airbnb.
>> This is not an Airbnb.
>> Where are we, man?
>> I don't know.
I don't even know what city
we're in.
>> Look out!
[ Music and Noise ]
>> World leaders are declaring a
global state of emergency until
the app situation can be
resolved.
>> Selfies, anybody?
Selfies, selfies!
>> The apocalypse is nigh!
The apocalypse is nigh!
>> OK. Who wants to go first?
[ Screams ]
[ Music ]
>> iTunes, get your iTunes.
>> Do you think we should have
gone with the puppy face?
>> I just ate this whole pizza
by myself.
Hashtag too delicious to share.
Hashtag pizza emoji.
>> Farm Ville 2 right here, yo.
>> Hashtag eat the food.
>> Brian, looking for Brian.
>> Hashtag does anybody want a
slice?
[ Music ]
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Good morning.
I'm so glad that really can't
happen.
Welcome to WWDC.
It's great to be back in San
Jose, the heart of Silicon
Valley and right down the street
from Apple and our new campus.
It's been 15 years since we held
the developer conference in San
Jose and an awful lot has
changed.
But the one thing that hasn't
changed is our commitment to the
developer community and our
ability to do amazing things
together.
This is going to be the best and
biggest WWDC ever.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Every year, we host WWDC to
bring Apple engineers and our
amazing developers together on
our collective mission to change
the world.
And I'm pleased to tell you, the
Apple Developer community has
never been more vibrant.
We now have 16 million
registered developers in the
program around the world.
And we added three million last
year alone.
We've got 5300 developers here
this morning, our largest group
ever.
We have attendees this morning
from 75 countries across the
world.
It's truly a worldwide
conference.
And we have the most student
developers with us this morning
ever.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
In fact, one of our youngest is
here this morning.
His, his name is Yuma Sorianto.
He's from Australia and he's
just 10 years old.
He started coding when he was
six and he already has five apps
on the App Store.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
I met Yuma yesterday and I can't
wait to see what he's going to
accomplish next.
And while we've got some great
up and coming developers like
Yuma, we got some that got a bit
of a later start, Masako.
Masako Wakamiya is just 82 years
old and she's from Japan and she
published her first app earlier
this year.
So--
[ Applause and Cheering ]
So, if you haven't published
yet, there is still time.
Let's give them a big round of
applause.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now, let's turn our attention to
our four incredible platforms.
Of course as you know each of
them stem from the same core
technology, but each is uniquely
expressed and designed for the
best experience for where they
work.
We keep pushing these platforms
forward giving you, the
developers, powerful tools and
opportunities to change the
world.
That's why this developer
conference is so important.
Now, we have a lot to talk about
today.
And I do mean a lot.
So, I'm dispensing with the
updates other than to tell you,
Apple is doing great.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
We have six important
announcements to share with you
this morning.
So, let's get right into it and
I'll start with tvOS.
We recently introduced the TV
app on Apple TV, iPhone and iPad
to create the easiest way to
discover and enjoy your TV
content from across your video
channels all in one convenient
place.
We launched it with support from
just a handful of video channels
but now, we have 50 partners
integrated into the TV app.
And today, we're really thrilled
to announce that Amazon is
coming--
[ Applause and Cheering ]
-- Amazon is coming to the TV
app and Apple-- and all Apple
TVs later this year with Amazon
Prime Video.
And, of course, as you know,
Prime Video provides a wealth of
great content, thousands of TV
shows and movies and some great
original content like
"Transparent", "Mozart in the
Jungle", "Man in the High
Castle" and so much more.
We are so pleased to welcome
Amazon to Apple TV.
[ Applause ]
So that's tvOS.
You'll be hearing a lot more
about tvOS later this year.
Number two, let's talk about
Apple Watch.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Apple Watch has had incredible
growth this past year.
In fact it's the number one
selling smartwatch by far.
And what's most important to us
is that it's number one in
customer satisfaction again by
far.
Apple Watch is designed to help
you live a healthier life.
And people are absolutely loving
the fitness capabilities, the
health capabilities, the quick
access to information and even
the ability to swim with it.
We've got some exciting updates
to the watchOS and to take you
through them, I'd like to invite
Kevin Lynch up.
Kevin?
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thank you, Tim.
>> So watchOS is moving forward
really quickly.
And I'm very excited to
introduce watchOS 4 today.
This furthers the areas that
people love.
It also introduces new ways to
make the watch more personal to
you.
Let's start with watch faces.
Now, Apple Watch is great for
quickly glancing at information.
And many people are using a
watch face like this today.
And now, you need to choose what
information shows up here.
So for example weather, calendar
and workouts, or maybe you'd
like to look at the date and
reminders and sunset.
The information that you like to
see actually varies based on
time and your location and your
routines.
What if we could actually show
you a selection of information
that you might need
automatically?
Well, Siri is becoming more and
more a proactive assistant
knowing what information you
need when you need it.
And we've created a new watch
face, which is powered by Siri
intelligence.
This is the new Siri watch face.
Now, it automatically displays
the information that's most
relevant to you.
And it can also access Siri by
tapping on the new complication
on the top left.
And it automatically displays
this information with the same
type of intelligence we've
applied on iOS.
We're using machine learning to
adapt automatically based on
your routines and the apps that
you use when you use them.
So in the morning, I might see
for example, can you time in my
first meeting.
And if I rotate the Crown, I can
see more information from Siri.
For example, reminders or even
photo memories from the same
time last year or maybe from
this location.
And throughout the day, whenever
you raise your wrist, the face
will dynamically update with the
information for you.
So for example at noon, I might
see a reminder to make a call
and I might get a pass to a
flight that I'm taking that
afternoon.
So, relevant passes in Wallet
can appear here right in the
face including from third party
apps.
Now, at the end of the day, I
might see what time the sun is
going to set and also, I can get
access to controls I tend to use
in the home app at night.
So this is an intelligent
proactive assistant right on
your wrist.
And this is the new Siri face on
Apple Watch.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now, sometimes you might like
kind of less information and
more graphics.
And that's the soul of the new
Kaleidoscope face.
It displays a beautiful
symmetrical pattern that slowly
changes throughout the day.
And you can rotate the Crown and
you can get this kind of trippy
effect whenever you want.
And there's multiple styles you
can choose from.
So for example if you use a
photo like this, you can create
a variety of Kaleidoscope
styles.
This is the new Kaleidoscope
face.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now, Mickey and Minnie have been
a big hit on Apple Watch and
more characters have been
working to find their way in.
And I'm really excited to
welcome Woody, and Jessie and
Buzz.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
They're going to be right at
home inside the watch and
there's so much fun.
And whenever you raise your
watch with the Toy Story Face,
you're going to see a variety of
vignettes kind of like this.
[ Laughter ]
There's a lot of hijinks going
on in there.
So these are three really lively
new faces in watchOS, Siri face,
Kaleidoscope and Toy Story.
[ Applause ]
Now, let's talk about Activity.
Apple Watch has already been
helping many people improve
their health and fitness.
And Activity is one of the most
frequently used apps on the
watch.
In watchOS 4, Activity
notifications are more
personalized to you.
There'll be "Close Your Rings"
more often.
So you might start off each day
with some inspiration by
receiving an update like this.
This lets you know if you're
close to accomplishing an
achievement or what you can do
to match yesterday's goals.
And these are all personalized
to you.
And as part of the smarter
coaching, we're also introducing
monthly challenges.
And these challenges are
designed to help you either beat
or repeat something that you
accomplish or came close to
doing and they're all achievable
because they're based on your
real history.
And like every great coach, we
want to celebrate your success
so we've added a little bit more
fun when you close your rings or
earn an achievement.
[ Applause ]
So you get smaller celebrations
for everyday successes and
bigger celebrations for harder
to reach milestones.
Now, we've also enhanced the
Workout App to be even easier to
use and more powerful.
Starting with the new UI where
quick start is right up front,
you can just tap and go.
It's much easier.
And customers have really loved
the new swimming capabilities in
Siris too.
And we're now enhancing the pool
swim workout with auto-sets.
So just by taking a rest at the
edge of the pool, it'll
automatically mark each set of
swimming that you're doing.
And at the end, you'll even get
your distance for each stroke
type and your pace for each set
that you're doing.
We also are creating-- It's
great, pool swim thing is very
popular.
We've also created some custom
motion and heart rate algorithms
for a new workout type called
High Intensity Interval
Training.
Now, this is one of the most
popular workouts in the world.
So we know it's going to be a
favorite for a lot of you when
you start using it.
Now, if you like to do more than
one workout in a row, it's now
super easy to just swipe over
during a current workout and
then add another one by pressing
the plus button.
You just press plus and I can
continue with another workout.
For example, I might do outdoor
cycling here.
I just tap and I continue, super
easy now to do multiple workouts
in a single session.
[ Applause ]
Now, many people are doing the
workouts indoors at a gym.
And when you use gym equipment,
it has data the Apple Watch
doesn't have and the watch has
data the gym equipment doesn't
have.
So you end up with numbers like
calories and distance that don't
quite match.
So in watchOS 4, we've come up
with a great solution to this.
We're enabling for the first
time two-way data exchange in
real-time with gym equipment.
So you'll be able to simply tap
your Apple Watch, on an NFC
reader on the gym equipment.
Your watch will automatically
launch the Workout App and you
can connect.
And then your heart rate is read
by the watch and sent to the
equipment.
And data like incline and speed
is sent from the equipment to
your watch.
And when you start and stop the
workout in your gym machine, it
does the same thing on your
watch.
So now, all the information
matches, it's much easier and
it's a lot more accurate.
Now, this is being supported by
the largest gym manufacturers in
the world, provided about 80% of
equipment in gyms today.
And Apple Watch-enabled
equipment will be rolling out
starting this fall.
[ Applause ]
Now let's talk about music.
Apple Watch paired with AirPods
has really become a magical
combination.
And where redesigning the music
app and watch makes this a
really great experience.
With the new music app, we're
going to automatically sync
music for you based on what you
love to listen to.
So for example, it'll
automatically get your Apple
Music mixes like new music and
favorites freshly updated on
your watch.
And the app simply presents some
beautiful album art and playlist
images and you can just navigate
by rotating the Digital Crown.
When you get the album you like,
you can just tap and play.
So you can easily play your
music now and we support
multiple playlist and music on
the watch now.
So your music that you love is
going to be ready when you are
and making Apple Watch and
AirPods a truly magical
listening experience.
That's the new music app.
[ Applause ]
Now, let's take a look at this.
To give you a quick demo of
watchOS 4, please welcome Vera
Carr from the Watch and Health
Engineering team.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thank you, Kevin.
Good morning.
I'm so excited to be here.
The first thing I want to show
you is the new doc.
I can now vertically scroll
through my recently used apps
like the new music app.
Using the doc makes finding the
apps I'm looking for easier than
ever.
Next, let's look at the new
intelligent Siri watch face.
Here in the morning, I could see
things like the weather for
today and my upcoming events.
Later today, I'm heading back to
San Francisco to see my parents.
And in the afternoon, the Siri
face will proactively update to
tell me how long it will take me
to get there.
Tonight, we're going to see the
new "Alien" movie, which I'm
super excited about.
No one spoil it for me.
For any content in the Siri
face, I could tap directly into
the app for more details.
Here for example, the Siri face
has my ticket so tonight, I can
just raise my wrist and with one
tap, they'll be ready.
The Siri face also shows me
timely content like photo
memories and news.
Here's a news headline picked
for me by the brand new news app
now available on Apple Watch.
In the app, I can view stunning
photos, glance at top news
stories throughout the day and
save them for later to be read
on my phone.
We've also integrated our new
Activity coaching notifications
directly into the Siri face.
Now, when it's near the end of
your day or you're close to
closing your rings, our coach
algorithms will tell you how
much you need to walk to get
your move goal.
I did a lot of nervous pacing
before this so now, I just need
to take a 16-minute walk.
Let's close those rings.
We've added something new here
in Workout that's really cool.
Music instantly gets me
motivated and now in watchOS 4,
I can pick a playlist that
automatically starts with my
workout.
Let's do it.
[ Music ]
And when I'm in a workout, I can
quickly swipe to the left and
control my music right here.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
These are only a few of the new
features in watchOS 4.
I can't wait for you to try it
out.
Back to Kevin to tell you more.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Terrific job, Vera.
Thank you.
There's a lot more coming in
watchOS 4 including, for
example, a new flashlight in the
control center, which you can
also use as a blinking safety
light when you're doing an
evening run.
So, a lot, lot more happening
here.
Now, we of course have a number
of updates that enable great
apps by developers in watchOS
including more support for apps
running in the background,
faster app responsiveness and
some new UI capabilities.
And we're also now supporting
native Core Bluetooth on the
watch, which is going to enable
experiences for apps that work
with small devices around you.
So for example, continuous
glucose monitoring, directly
from Dexcom sensor to your
watch, or a Zepp Tennis, which
connects to a sensor on your
racket for real-time swing
analysis when you're playing, or
a sensor which connects your
watch to your surfboard so you
can actually see the height of
the waves you're doing and how
many calories you're burning
while you're still on the water.
So, lots of new possibilities
here for watchOS.
[ Applause ]
Developer preview is available
today so you can get going.
And there's a free upgrade for
everyone across all watches this
fall.
And that's just some of what's
coming in watchOS 4.
Please welcome Tim back to the
stage.
Thank you.
>> Thanks, Kevin.
[ Cheering Applause ]
WatchOS 4 is a great update.
Now, let's talk about a product
that in many ways is the heart
and soul of Apple.
And, of course, I'm talking
about the Mac.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
There's never been a computer
quite like the Mac.
The Mac is so important in
fueling the world's passion and
creativity.
It's a computer all of us love
to use and no one can match the
Mac's deep integration of
hardware and software.
And, of course, at the heart of
the Mac experience is macOS.
And to tell you about what's
next with macOS, please welcome
Craig Federighi, Craig.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thank you.
Thank you, Tim.
Hey, good morning.
Well, let's talk about macOS.
Now, our current release of
macOS, of course, is macOS
Sierra.
Now, Sierra brought Siri and
Apple Pay to the Mac let you put
your documents and your desktop
in the cloud and even let you
unlock your Mac automatically
using the watch on your wrist.
Now, people are loving Sierra
and we love it too.
So, we wanted to spend this year
perfecting it.
Of course, the question is, what
do we call it?
[ Laughter ]
So we enlisted once again our
crack marketing team.
They were giddy to hop in their
mini bus and this time, venture
east, deep into the Sierras but
this time, ascending its highest
peaks.
And when they finally came back,
they had a name they said felt
really, really good.
And it's my privilege to
announce for you today, macOS
High Sierra.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now, we talked to the guys and
we said there might be-- this
might be misconstrued but they
assured us this name is fully
baked.
So--
[ Laughter ]
Now, High Sierra is all about
deep technologies that provide a
powerful platform for future
innovations on the Mac.
But we couldn't help ourselves,
we also added some refinements.
And it starts with Safari.
Now, Safari is known for its
efficiency and it's a legendary
battery life but safari is also
incredibly fast.
In fact, we benchmarked Safari
on the same hardware running
macOS and Windows with all the
popular browsers and Safari
smokes them in benchmark after
benchmark, JetStream,
Speedometer, MotionMark.
Safari tops them all.
That's right, Safari is the
world's fastest desktop browser
with High Sierra.
[ Applause ]
And Safari's domination
continues with the new modern
version of JavaScript,
ECMAScript 5.
We can see Safari delivers 80%
faster performance than Chrome.
Now, in addition to being
tremendously fast, Safari also
helps give you a serene browsing
experience.
Now, you know, sometimes you go
to read an article and instead
of finding something to read,
you get this.
[ Music ]
Just some loud audio and video
that autoplays and disrupts your
whole reading vibe.
Well, now, don't worry about it
because we have autoplay
blocking in Safari.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Safari detects the sites that
shouldn't be playing video and
puts you in control.
You can always push play.
Now, Safari is also key in
respecting your privacy.
Now, have you ever had this
experience where you go to buy
something on the web and you
even complete the purchase.
And it seems like everywhere you
go on the web, it just follows
you around.
It kind of feels like you're
being tracked and that's because
you are.
[ Laughter ]
No longer, because Safari has
Intelligent Tracking Prevention.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Safari uses machine learning to
identify trackers, segregate the
cross-site scripting data, put
it away, so now, your privacy,
your browsing history is your
own.
It's not about blocking ads, the
web behaves as it always did,
but your privacy is protected.
Next, I want to talk about some
refinements to Mail and it
starts with search.
So in addition to providing
searches based on recency,
search in Mail is now using
Spotlight to identify your top
hits.
So the message you're looking
for is almost always right there
at the top.
And if you're into using Mail in
full-screen, well now, we
support Split View for your
compose window.
It's a great way to compose
mail.
[ Applause ]
And Mail is more efficient than
ever.
It actually uses 35% less disk
space for storing your mail.
Now, probably our biggest area
of refinement in High Sierra is
in photos.
Now-- Yeah, photos has some
great new organization and
editing tools.
There's a persistent sidebar and
a new view that has all your
imports in chronological order.
And in any view up here on the
upper right, you can filter by
your keywords, by your
favorites, by just media types
like video so it's really easy
to get to just what you're
looking for.
We've also improved faces.
It recognizes far more faces
automatically using advanced
convolutional neural networks.
And when you put effort into
categorizing and naming people,
well, that's now synchronized
automatically across all your
devices.
[ Applause ]
Now, we also have some great
enhancements to editing inside a
photo.
So you can see here on the
right-hand side, all of your
editing tools array.
And there are bunch of great new
ones, including Curves which
allows you to fine-tune the
color and contrast in your
image.
And Selective Color will teach
you modify color in a selective
range.
And I think you're going to like
this one because if you like to
do edits in a ProTool like
Pixelmator or Photoshop, well
now, when you punch out to that
other editing tool, all of your
edits automatically synchronize
right back to your photo
library.
[ Applause ]
Now, Apple pioneered printed
books.
Based on projects, you construct
right inside of the photo
application.
And now, we're opening this up
to third parties.
They're going to offer some
amazing new printing services,
full-framed wall, mounted
photos, and even publishing
websites, all based on projects
right inside of photos.
So those are some quick
refinements but I want to return
to the main story now and that's
technology, this-- because we've
gone deep on the fundamentals,
data, video and graphics.
And when it comes to data, the
fundamentals are in the file
system.
Now, the Mac File System has its
roots actually, HFS from 30
years ago.
Well, a lot has changed since
then.
We have a lot of flash drives or
storage is a billion times
larger and it's time for more
modern file system.
So, I'm pleased to announce that
we're bringing the Apple File
System to macOS as our new
default.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now, APFS is a thoroughly modern
file system, 64-bit top to
bottom.
It's safe and secure with
built-in crash protection and
native encryption.
And it's ultra responsive with
modern features like instant
file and directory cloning and
high performance parallellized
metadata operations.
Now, what does that really mean
in practice?
Well, let's take a look at a
simple file duplication inside
of Sierra.
So we're going to go up to the
File menu.
It's like duplicate on this very
large video files.
And it's going to copy.
And just like you'd expect,
there's a lot of data to be
copied here so it takes a little
while, just about done, there we
go.
Now, let's watch that in High
Sierra.
Well, we're going to go up to
the File menu, we're going to
subduplicate, and we're done.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Next up, video.
Now, the current standard in
video is H.264.
In fact, H.264 has really
enabled the revolution of
streaming HD video on the
Internet.
But, of course, the game is
moved from HD to 4K and 4K high
dynamic range video.
And there's a new standard to
support this, it's H.265 or
HEVC.
And you want your video to look
great, preserve all the detail
and color, and HEVC does it
while saving up to 40% better
compression than H.264.
Now, we're building in software
encoder support in the High
Sierra for all Macs and hardware
acceleration of HEVC for the
newest Macs.
And we're also building it into
ProTools, like Final Cut,
Motion, and Compressor.
Now, I want to return to our
main story which is graphics and
graphics are all about the GPU.
The GPU has been the performance
superstar of the last decade
delivering incredible gains in
computational performance.
Now, our API for
high-performance graphics is
Metal.
And developers have taken
amazing advantage of Metal.
This is Dawn of War III from
Feral Interactive, incredible
graphics.
This is DaVinci Resolve from
Blackmagic which can accelerate
many editing operations.
And, of course, we even use
Metal inside of photos for doing
machine learning in identifying
your photos.
But we've learned a lot working
with developers and their
adoption of Metal and we have a
new version to announce today.
And you'll never guess what we
called it.
It's Metal 2.
[ Laughter ]
Now, Metal 2 is tremendously
fast.
In fact, it has great
optimizations and new APIs that
when adopted, deliver another 10
times improvement in draw call
throughput.
Now, some of you remember when
Metal first came out, it itself
had a 10 times improvement over
OpenGL.
You can multiply those numbers
together.
That's a hundred times
improvement.
Now, we've also provided
better-- sorry, debugging and
performance analysis tools for
you to optimize your app for
Metal.
And we're so excited about the
advances in Metal 2 that we've
taken the Mac Window Server and
put it on top of Metal,
accelerating things like Mission
Control.
And some of our most challenging
system animations are now
buttery smooth all the time.
Now, Metal is not just about
graphics.
We're also using it for machine
learning.
It can now accelerate-- yes, we
have Metal performance shaders
to accelerate all kinds of deep
learning algorithms.
Another piece of Metal news
today is Metal for external
graphics.
So, you know our MacBooks have
this tremendous balance of
portability and power.
But sometimes for some
workflows, you need even more
power.
You want to take advantage of
the incredible Thunderbolt IO on
your MacBook Pros to access
external graphics.
So we're going to be making this
possible in Metal 2.
Now, we're starting with the
Developer Kit that will be
available today.
You can actually order a
Thunderbolt 3 enclosure with a
high-performance AMD GPU and
tune your apps for
high-performance external
graphics.
And then we'll be rolling out
support to all of our customers
in the months to come.
Now, with these graphics power,
we're really doubling down on
our focus on Pro content
creation.
And that's increasingly about VR
content creation.
And so, we're bringing Metal for
VR to High Sierra.
[ Applause ]
Now Metal is delivering a
VR-optimized display pipeline
that provides extremely high
performance.
And we're optimizing our Pro
apps like Final Cut for doing
things like editing spherical
video right inside the VR
environment.
We're also working with Valve.
They're bringing the SteamVR,
SVK to the Mac.
And we work with Unity and
Unreal to bring their engines
for VR to the Mac.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
It's really cool and you might
just be seeing a little bit more
from us later today on this
topic.
So that's a quick look at macOS.
Some great technologies with the
Apple File System, HEVC Video
and incredible graphics with
Metal 2 support for external
graphics and VR support of the
Mac and, of course, a bunch of
fantastic refinements.
Now, macOS High Sierra is
available for all of you today
as a developer beta.
And if you sign up at
beta.apple.com, we'll also have
a public beta available later at
this month and, of course, it's
shipping to everyone as a free
upgrade this fall on all systems
that support Sierra.
Now, that's your update on macOS
High Sierra and I'm going to
turn it over to our vice
president of Hardware
Engineering, John Ternus, to
tell you more about the Mac.
Thank you.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thank you, Craig.
So, we have some great updates
to talk about today that span
much of the Mac product line.
And let's begin with the iMac.
Now, the iMac has been the gold
standard of desktops for many
years but we're going to raise
the bar once again.
And as always on the iMac, it
starts with the display.
Because the 4K and 5K Retina
iMac displays with their high
resolution, excellent brightness
and P3 color gamut, are the best
displays on any desktop.
But we're going to make them
even better.
So these new displays are now
going to be 500 nits.
That's 43% brighter than the
previous generation.
And for the first time, we're
going to support 10-bit
dithering, which means these
displays can reproduce up to a
billion colors.
So, your content is going to
look more true to life than ever
before.
Now, in addition, we've got some
great internal updates for these
iMacs.
So we'll start with the CPU
because the whole line is moving
to Intel's 7th-generation Core
Processor, also known as Kaby
Lake.
Now, Kaby Lake gets this better
base and turbo frequencies for
more performance as well as
hardware-based 10-bit HEVC
decode which is great for
playing back high quality video.
In addition, these iMacs are
getting a boost when it comes to
memory capacity.
So the 21.5-inch systems can now
be configured with up to 32 gigs
of memory.
And the 27-inch can go all the
way up to 64 gigabytes of
memory.
Both of those are twice what the
previous generation can do.
Now, fast storage has always
been a key part of the iMac.
And so, we're going to now make
our Fusion Drive standard on all
27-inch configs.
And it's also going to be
standard on the high-end
21.5-inch config as well.
In addition, our SSD options are
going to be up to 50% faster and
now available up to 2 terabytes.
And the iMacs are getting an IO
upgrade as well because we're
giving them two USB-C connectors
which support Thunderbolt 3.
And we think our customers
especially our Pro users are
really going to love this
because you can do some cool
things like hook up a
high-performance RAID array and
an external 5K display at the
same time.
So now, let's talk about
graphics.
And as you heard earlier, we're
investing heavily in graphic
software technologies like Metal
2.
Well, we're also investing in
graphics hardware.
And every configuration in this
new iMac line is going to get a
big bump in its graphics
performance.
So we'll start with the
entry-level iMac.
Now this system gets a boost in
its integrated GPU by way of
Intel's Iris Plus Graphics which
now has 64 megabytes of eDRAM.
And the performance that we're
getting out of this is pretty
amazing because this system is
up to 80% faster in graphics
than the previous generation.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now next up is the 21.5-inch
iMac with Retina 4K display.
And the big news here is that
we're going to be moving to
discrete graphics and making it
standard on all 4K iMacs.
And that's going to come-- There
you go.
And that's going to come in this
Radeon Pro series GPUs with up
to 4 gigabytes of VRAM.
And again, this move to discrete
graphics yield to pretty
spectacular performance increase
because this new system is up to
three times faster than the
previous generation for
graphics.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now, lastly, we have our 27-inch
iMAc.
And this is our most popular
desktop for our Pro customers.
So obviously, it's going to get
a bump in graphics today as
well.
So it's going to have this
Radeon Pro 500 series GPUs with
up to 8 gigabytes of VRAM.
And again, we get a great
performance uplift.
In fact, this 27-inch iMac can
now deliver up to 5.5 teraflops
of graphics to you.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Which makes it a great platform
for VR content creation.
In fact, we've seated some
developers with this new iMac in
High Sierra so that we could see
what they can do with virtual
reality on the Mac.
And I'm really excited that we
can give you a demo of some of
this amazing work right now.
So, I'd like to invite up on the
stage, here from Industrial
Light & Magic is academy-award
winning visual effects artist
and Chief Creative Officer John
Knoll.
John.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thank you, John.
At Lucasfilm's ILMxLab, story,
concept design and technical
development are all intertwined.
They come together for us to
create immersive experiences for
people to enjoy at home, in
cinemas and at theme parks.
Now, I've always done my art and
development on the Mac so I'm
really excited about these new
iMacs.
I truly love the platform so I'm
especially excited to be able to
share some of our VR content
created on these new iMacs and
Epic's Unreal Engine.
I'm joined by Lauren Ridge, an
Epic programmer who will be at
backstage driving our demo.
Working together, we can work in
real-time to create an immersive
experience as we step inside the
"Star Wars" universe.
Now, Lauren's backstage so we
can show you the environment
around her.
>> And now, we're going to show
you from my perspective.
Here, we are in the planet
Mustafar.
Thanks to the native VR support
in macOS High Sierra, I can use
Unreal Engine's editor to create
content inside the VR
experience.
And for the first time, it's all
powered by my Mac.
On my left motion controller, I
have my Radial Menu, which
accesses my artist palette.
Now on the right, I have the
laser I use to interact with the
world and some fire here.
So, let's try that out.
>> All right.
Very nice.
Let's do some set dressing.
What do you have?
>> Let's see.
Let me open my content browser.
It has all the assets I need to
dress my scene.
I think I saw that landing spot
for an imperial shuttle over
here so let's bring one of those
in.
We've actually set up the smart
assets so they know exactly
where to come in for their
landing.
>> Great, all right.
Can we go wide?
>> Sure. I can grab on to them
with two hands and scale myself
up.
I can also use this to rotate
the world around me.
>> Very cool.
>> I have a TIE fighter here too
so let's bring one of those in.
Thanks to the more than five and
a half teraflops of GPU
performance, manipulating
objects is super smooth and
really intuitive.
>> Great, all right.
Can we have a squadron of those
flying overhead?
>> OK, what about from over
there on the horizon.
So, over there by the castle.
>> Right. Perfect, OK.
>> Right, let me teleport back
down.
>> Hey, seeing the castle back
there reminds me, we're missing
one important element.
>> Right, how could I forget?
>> All right.
Nice. All right, that's really
good.
Saw that against the sky back
there.
Can we go in closer?
>> Sure thing.
It's really cool how Metal 2
unlocks Unreal's advanced
rendering feature set on the
map.
>> Wow, yeah, really nice.
All right, now let's play the
scene from here.
>> OK.
[ Sound Effects ]
[ Music ]
>> Oh he's upset.
That's the third one this week.
[ Sound Effects ]
>> Whoa, I'm glad he didn't see
me there.
>> Wouldn't be so sure about
that.
[ Music ]
All right, actually, let's stop
it right there.
>> That was a close one.
[ Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
>> Well, it's really nice to see
in iMac rendering this level of
graphics in VR mode at a smooth
90 frames a second.
Really great.
All right, thank you, Lauren.
[ Applause ]
Metal 2 and Unreal's-- or Epic's
Unreal Engine would enable the
next generation of storytellers.
We use this technology in our
filmmaking every day for virtual
set scouting, for art direction
and shot design.
And that means that this
immersive content can be made by
the same people that bring you
the films.
That's incredibly powerful.
At Lucasfilm and ILMxLab, we're
looking forward to using our
Macs to create new experiences
as we invite people everywhere
to step inside our stories.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
Well, thank you.
Thank you, John and Lauren.
That was awesome.
So that is our update to the
iMac line.
And to recap, they have the best
Mac displays we've ever made,
faster processors, higher memory
capacity, super fast storage,
Thunderbolt 3, and as you saw,
incredible graphics performance.
So, here is the line and-- but
there's one more change because
we're going to bring even more
value to the iMac product line.
For the first time ever, we're
going to have a 4K iMac that
starts at just $1299.
[ Applause ]
But the updates don't stop with
just the iMac because we're
refreshing our notebooks today
as well.
And together, the MacBook and
MacBook Pro make up the
strongest line of notebooks
we've ever had.
But we're going to make them
even better because we're moving
to Kaby Lake here as well.
And we're bringing faster SSDs
to our MacBook and faster
standard graphics to the 15-inch
MacBook Pro.
So a great performance bump
across the board.
So here is that lineup.
But just like the iMac, we're
going to bring more value here
as well because we're going to
have a new configuration of the
13-inch MacBook Pro that also
starts at just $1299.
[ Applause ]
So there you'd have it.
We've updated seven of our most
popular Macs and the MacBook Air
is going to get a bump in
megahertz as well.
And even better, they're all
shipping today.
[ Applause ]
Now, we care deeply about the
environment.
And so as with all our products,
we've been working really hard
to ensure that these new Macs
are free of harmful chemicals,
very energy efficient and highly
recyclable.
So that's everything we're
updating today.
But, it's not actually
everything we want to show you
today.
Now the iMac line has incredible
breadth.
It spans from an entry level
system that's perfect for use at
home or in a school, all the way
up through that powerhouse
27-inch model which allows
professional customers to create
amazing things every day.
But that said, there's another
class of Pro users who would
love to be able to take
advantage of the iMac's display
and design, but they need
workstation class performance
that can't possibly fit into an
all-in-one.
Well, we wanted to challenge
that assumption, and so we've
been working really hard to see
just how far we can push the
iMac.
Now, this isn't going to be
shipping until the end of the
year but I'm really excited to
be able to give you a sneak peek
of what we've been up to, and
here it is.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
Cool. So that is the new iMac
Pro.
Now, the first thing you'll
notice, it features the same
great design as our 27-inch iMac
but it's in this seriously
badass space gray finish.
And with that stunning new color
and gorgeous 5K display, this is
without a doubt the most
beautiful iMac we've ever made.
But it's also going to be by far
the most powerful iMac we've
ever made.
In fact, this would be the most
powerful Mac we've ever made
because--
[ Applause ]
Because we actually are going to
put workstation class
performance into our incredible
5K iMac design.
Now to do that, the team had to
completely rethink the thermal
architecture, and they came up
with this really efficient dual
centrifugal fan solution which
generates significantly more
airflow than a traditional iMac.
In fact, the iMac Pro has a
greater than 80% increase in
cooling capacity.
So that means we can deliver
unbelievable performance while
still maintaining the quiet
operation you'd expect from an
iMac.
So let's talk about what's
inside and I want to start with
the CPU because we wanted to go
really big here.
So the iMac Pro is going to ship
with an 8-core Xeon processor.
[ Applause ]
But it's also going to ship with
a 10-core Xeon processor.
[ Applause ]
And then we thought, you know,
we've gone this far, let's get
really nutty.
So we're going to offer it with
up to 18-core.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
That is a ton of compute power.
But we didn't want to stop there
because we wanted to go really
big on graphics as well.
So the iMac Pro is going to use
AMD's Radeon Vega graphics.
This is a brand new workstation
class graphics architecture.
It features a completely new GPU
core and high bandwidth on
packaged memory.
It's going to be available with
up to 16 gigabytes of VRAM and
over 400 gigabytes per second of
memory bandwidth.
And we aren't going to use an
entry level configuration here
because our implementation is
going to offer up to 11
teraflops of single precision
compute power.
That's three times more than the
best GPU in the Mac Pro.
But it actually gets even better
because this Radeon Vega GPU can
also do half precision compute.
So that means the iMac Pro can
deliver up to 22 teraflops of
half precision computation.
This is a really big deal for
things like machine learning
development.
So the iMac Pro as you can see
is going to be a monster when it
comes to graphics, but we didn't
want to stop there either.
So we're going to let you
configure it with up to 128
gigabytes of ECC memory.
That's twice what you can do on
a standard 27-inch iMac.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
And up to 4 terabytes of 3
gigabyte per second SSD.
Now, the iMac Pro is also going
to have a full complement of
high performance I/O including
four Thunderbolt 3 ports and for
the first time ever in any Mac,
built-in 10 gigabit Ethernet.
[ Applause ]
And with all that cutting edge
I/O, you can do some pretty
amazing things.
So you can hook up two 5K
displays in two high-performance
RAID arrays, no iMac before
could ever do that.
And when you combine that with
the internal display, that means
the iMac Pro can drive up to 44
million pixels.
There's so much more.
We don't even have time to get
into things like a 1080p
FaceTime camera, a user
configurable VESA mount option,
two times wider AVX instructions
and even a UHS-II SD card slot.
So with all these
high-performance technologies
and our incredible 5K display,
this iMac Pro is going to be an
awesome workstation for things
like real-time 3D rendering,
high frame rate, immersive VR,
machine learning development,
and with all those cores and all
that memory, super fast code
compiling.
Now speaking of workstations, we
wanted to compare the starting
configuration of the iMac Pro to
what's on the market.
And so, if you were to go out
and build a comparably spec
system today, it will cost over
$7000.
And keep in mind, that's a
system that doesn't have our
best in class 5K display.
It doesn't have the iMac Pro's
incredible all-in-one design.
And then obviously doesn't run
Mac OS.
Well, this is the starting
configuration of the iMac Pro
and we're going to price it at
just $4999.
[ Applause ]
And it's going to be available
in December.
So that's a sneak peek at the
iMac Pro.
It packs workstation class
performance into our incredible
27-inch iMac design with its
gorgeous 5K display.
And it is going to be the most
powerful Mac we have ever made.
So that is all of our Mac news
today.
Now, back to Tim.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thanks John.
All right.
So many great things happening
with the Mac.
And John, I agree that iMac Pro
is really badass.
All right, next up.
Let's talk about iOS.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
The world's best and most
advanced mobile operating
system.
Our customers love the latest
version, iOS 10, which has an
industry leading 96% customer
satisfaction.
And it's absolutely incredible
that 86% of our customers are
running iOS 10 and taking
advantages of its capabilities.
This blows away the other
platforms that suffer from
horrible fragmentation.
[ Applause ]
With iOS, developers can always
target the latest capabilities
and features of our latest
operating system and be
confident that there's customers
there for them.
Now today, we're going to take
the world's best and most
advanced mobile operating system
and turn it up to 11.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
And I'd like to invite Craig
back to take you through it.
Craig?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Tim.
Hello again.
Let's talk about iOS 11.
It's a big one.
Now, we have a big focus on
technologies in iOS 11 but also
some really big features.
We have a lot to talk about.
We're going to start with
Messages.
Now, you all know in iOS 10, we
had iMessage apps and stickers.
People had a lot of fun with
these.
And now in iOS 11, we're making
them more discoverable and ever
with this redesigned app drawer.
You can see you have your apps
accessible right there at the
bottom of the screen with just a
tap, you can bring them up,
scroll through them and tap into
any app.
It's really easy.
It's going to make it a lot of
fun for you to use your apps and
stickers.
Now, the big story with messages
though is messages in iCloud.
Because now with your iMessages
and iCloud, when you sign in to
another new device, well all of
your conversations are
automatically synchronized.
[ Applause ]
In fact, they stay in sync.
So if you want to delete an
embarrassing message that you
don't want in your transcript,
well it goes away everywhere,
which is kind of nice.
So, this, of course, allows us
to optimize your device storage
because with your messages in
the cloud, we only need to keep
your most recent messages cached
on the device and so that makes
for smaller and faster backups
that is available for iOS and
the Mac.
And, of course, your messages
remain end-to-end encrypted.
Next, Apple Pay.
So we love using Apple Pay to
buy things at retail.
In fact, Apple Pay is the number
one contactless payment service
on mobile devices.
And by the end of the year, it
will be available in more than
50% of retailers here in the US.
Yeah.
[ Applause ]
But in addition of paying at
retail, we use Apple Pay in
apps, we use it in the web.
There was one final frontier we
wanted to conquer and that's
Apple Pay for person to person
payments.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now, it's super simple because
it's integrated right in to
messages as an iMessage App.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
So you can send and receive
money right in your transcript.
Of course, when you send it, you
authenticate securely with Touch
ID.
And if you receive money with
iMessage, it goes to your Apple
Pay cash card.
And from there, well you can
send it on to friends and
family, if you are charitable,
you can make Apple Pay purchases
at retail or on the web.
And, of course, you can pull it
out and transfer it to your
bank.
And it's available across all
these iOS devices and Apple
Watch too.
Thank you.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
So next, let's turn to Siri.
Now, Siri is used monthly for
more than 375 million devices.
It's absolutely huge.
And it's available in more
languages, in more countries
than any other system, 21
languages and 36 countries.
So for iOS 11, we're making a
big upgrade to your primary
interface in dealing with Siri,
not Siri's voice.
We've used deep learning now to
create a really natural and
expressive voice for Siri and
I'd like you to hear it.
>> Here's the forecast for the
next 10 days.
Sunny, sunny, and sunny.
>> Three different ways to say
sunny.
Very powerful.
Now, Siri also has a male voice
and it sounds fantastic too.
>> I love machine learning
especially since I'm a machine,
learning.
[ Laughter ]
>> So, Siri is a great new
visual interface as well.
And it's able to provide you
with followup questions and
answers with just a tap and
multiple results.
When you make a query, it's
really handy.
Now, Siri also has a new
capability, just translation.
So, you can now ask something
like, how do you say what are
the most popular dishes in your
restaurant in Chinese?
And Siri can say,
[ Foreign Language ]
Totally.
[ Applause ]
Now, translation initially will
support translation from English
to Chinese, French, German,
Italian, and Spanish and we'll
have more language combinations
coming in the months to come.
Now, when it comes to using Siri
to access your other
applications, we have SiriKit.
And SiriKit can now do more than
ever in iOS 11.
So now, you can do task
management by using Siri to make
tasks and OmniFocus your things,
take notes in Evernote, do
banking in Citi Mobile or even
bring up a QR code in WeChat.
Now, Siri isn't just a voice
assistant, because with Siri
Intelligence, Siri not only
understands your voice, it
understands the context.
It understands your interest.
It understands how you use your
device.
And this allows it to ultimately
understand what you want next.
Now, we've all experienced this
where Siri can help us predict
what apps we might want to use
next, give us a time to leave
notification based on our
calendar and where we are, help
us respond to a text message.
In iOS 11, Siri uses on-device
learning to understand more
about topics of interest to us.
So it can actually suggest
topics we might be interested in
learning about in news.
It can help us respond with our
location for getting to an
appointment to someone in
messages.
And even help us make a calendar
appointment based on something
we've just booked inside of
Safari on the web.
And what Siri learns about you
on device is now kept synced
across all of your devices.
So you're dealing with one Siri
but of course this is kept
completely private, readable
only by you and your devices.
[ Applause ]
Next, let's talk about the
camera.
People love the fantastic
cameras in the iPhone 7 and 7
Plus.
And in fact, our customers now
take a trillion photos per year.
It's absolutely amazing.
And they take a lot of video
too.
And today, they do it in H.264.
But now with our latest iPhones
in iOS 7, they get or using
HEVC, which is giving us up to
two times better compression for
camera-captured videos, which
means less storage space used on
your device and less space used
in the cloud.
And we're applying these same
techniques to replace JPEG
capture with what we call HEIF,
High Efficiency Image Format.
It's based on HEVC and it also
provides awesome quality images
at half the size on your device.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
And, of course, you can still
share completely compatibly with
others.
Now, with the iPhone 7 Plus, we
love taking these beautiful
portrait photos.
And now, with iOS 11, we can
take low light photographs using
optical image stabilization,
True Tone Flash, HDR delivers
incredible image quality.
And we're taking the depth
information that we can capture
with two cameras and exposing it
to developers with a new Depth
API which has allowed them to do
incredibly fun and artistic
photos, like this, using the
Depth API.
Now, when you're done taking
your photos, you go to enjoy
them in the Photos app.
And one of the ways I love
enjoying them is with the
Memories feature because
Memories is able to scan my
library and find all kinds of
fun events.
And now, it can do more than
ever.
It uses a machine learning to
identify things like sporting
events, even weddings,
anniversaries, memories of your
babies.
It's really great.
And when you go to play those
back, you can see them not just
in normal landscape orientation
but now watch them in portrait
taking full advantage of the
height of your display.
Now, when it comes to live
photos, we have some great
enhancements as well.
So, you can now trim your live
photos, the video around the
still.
You can mark any part of the
video as your key photo and so
much more.
So, these are some of the big
features in the iOS 11.
There's one other which is a
major redesign, the Control
Center.
Rather than show in slides, how
about we do a demo?
[ Applause and Cheering ]
All right, let's take our first
live look.
No, I don't want to do that.
Let's take our first live look
at iOS 11.
Now, I'm going to just bring up
Control Center as always and
what you'll notice is Control
Center is now a single page.
It packs all the features into a
single page.
Now, of course, it has simple
switches, I'll just do an
orientation lock.
It's got a beautiful little
animation there for the
orientation lock.
It has sliders available so you
can adjust volume like this.
But it provides greater depth
because with 3D Touch, 3D Touch
on slider like this and get
access to more controls.
And this allows us to pack lots
of capabilities really easily
into the design.
So you see, we have our wireless
control so I could just tap on
Airplane Mode.
But if I 3D Touch on the
platter, I get access to even
more features.
And this is really great with
your music because you can
operate them here or jump in for
even more information.
So it's a really great new
Control Center and I think
you're really going to love it.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now, we've also taken this
opportunity to redesign lock
screen and notification center
by making them one.
So now, when I'm on my lock
screen, if I unlock the device,
just like that, I can actually
now swipe back down.
I'm actually on my lock screen
seeing those notifications, but
I can get at all my other
notifications just by scrolling
up, like that.
It's a really great unification
and you still have access, of
course, to your widgets on the
left and your camera on the
right.
Now, let's take a look at
photos, this beautiful portrait
photos but also these great live
photos.
And, you know, live photos
capture a still, but then also a
bunch of video automatically
captured around it and sometimes
the best shot wasn't the still.
Well, now, we can go in to Edit
Mode, we could trim this video
if we want but we also can
capture just the frame we want
and make that our key photo.
[ Applause ]
Now, we can do other really fun
things with live photos.
Now, here is one great shot,
this girl blowing a bubble.
But would it be greater-- great
if she could just keep blowing
that bubble?
Well, now, she can.
We actually use computer vision
to compute a seamless loop
around this live photo.
It's really fun.
[ Applause ]
And we have another great
effect.
So here's a fun jump in the
pool.
But wouldn't it be better if it
bounced?
There it is.
[ Applause ]
Now, we can really do some
artistic things with live photos
as well.
So, you see, this is a shot
where we have a still landscape
but then there's movement in the
water.
Now, if you wanted to capture
this kind of motion,
traditionally you'd have to get
a tripod and figure out how to
configure a long exposure on
your high-end camera.
But now, you can actually just
go into the effects here and
select Long Exposure.
And check it out.
[ Applause ]
It's really gorgeous.
Now, let's take a quick look at
Memories.
Because you see, memories can
now capture things like
activities, like scuba diving.
It can spot your anniversaries,
these really touching memories
of your children growing up, and
most importantly, your pets.
Let's play a movie about, you
know, these pets.
And what we'll see is that we
play them of course
traditionally here in landscape
which is a great way to watch
video.
And, of course, Memories is
using computer vision to
actually identify photos of your
pet and pick the best scenes.
Now, what's great is I can also
rotate my phone now into
portrait and it automatically
reformats to take full advantage
of the height of the display.
[ Music ]
And that's a quick look at
Memories.
[ Applause ]
Now, with Memories, we're using
machine learning to help learn
more about you and what you're
interested in by looking at your
photo library.
But now in iOS 11, Siri does so
much more in learning how you're
using your device.
So for instance if I'm in Safari
here and I'm reading about
Iceland, maybe I'm considering
taking a trip there.
Here's Reykjavik as a nice
location.
Well, now, Siri actually on my
device spots my interest.
So when I go let's say into
News, Siri automatically
surfaces for me a recommendation
that I might be interested in
news about Iceland.
I could just tap in and heart
this one like this.
And if I tap into a particular
article, we can see it mentions
certain locations in Iceland.
I think this one is called
Snaefellsnes.
I hope it's OK with anyone who
speaks Icelandic.
But what's great is now Siri is
learning this vocabulary.
It knows it might be something
I'm going to use in my
communication in the future.
So when I go into messages and
start typing a message and let's
say I start typing Reykjavik,
well check it out.
It learns that Reykjavik is
probably a word I might type.
And what about-- there it is,
Snaefellsnes.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Pretty awesome.
[ Applause ]
Now, let's take a look at
stickers.
Because you notice now, right on
the bottom of the display, we
have access to all my sticker
packs.
I can tap in in the bottom here
to my Star Wars sticker pack, I
can tap and slide and say select
Music.
And we now have Apple Pay right
here as a messages app.
But what's so cool is if I
receive a message saying that I
owe someone money, well you
notice the quick type keyboard
automatically surfaces Apple Pay
as an option and picks the
amount out as what I might want
to pay.
I can just tap the Pay button,
send, and authenticate with my
finger print.
And just like that, I've paid
with Apple Pay.
And that is a quick demo of iOS
11.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
But wait, there is more.
It starts with maps.
Now, in iOS 10, maps brought
beautiful new clarity to
navigation.
And we're now giving you
enhanced information for when
you get there to the mall.
So, we have detailed floor plans
now of malls with place cards,
directory and search.
And we let you browse by floor.
And we're going to be supporting
malls and all of these cities
out the gate and hundreds more
per month thereafter.
And we're also bringing the
support to major airports.
You can see where security is so
you can plan.
[ Applause ]
Now, we'll be supporting all of
these airports to start, and
again building out more over
time.
And, of course, we have more
improvements to navigation.
So now on the upper left, you
can even see your speed limit, I
hope you're paying attention to
that, and lane guidance so you
know which lane to be in to make
your next move when navigating.
[ Applause ]
Now, we know in addition to
navigation, people like to do
more with their phones sometimes
while driving.
And our safest solution for
doing this is CarPlay, lets you
keep your eyes on the road while
you're doing things like asking
Siri to play music.
Well, we wanted to bring this
same level of safety to everyone
who maybe doesn't have one of
the 200 models of cars that
currently support CarPlay.
And we're building on "Do Not
Disturb" with a new feature we
call "Do Not Disturb While
Driving".
And it's all about keeping your
eyes on the road.
When you're driving, you don't
need to be responding to these
kinds of messages.
In fact, you don't need to see
them.
So now, when you install iOS 11,
we're going to use Bluetooth to
understand if you're connected
to a car.
Or even if you don't have
Bluetooth, we're going to use
WiFi Doppler effect to measure
that you're moving in a car.
And when you finish that first
drive, we're going to suggest,
hey how about we activate "Do
Not Disturb While Driving".
And when we do, instead of
seeing all those notifications,
we have this new user interface
for you.
[ Applause ]
Now, if you're tempted and you
try to turn on your phone,
you're actually going to receive
this, a little reminder that
you're not receiving
notifications while you're
driving.
But, of course, you might be
sitting in the back seat in
which case, you can tell us,
"I'm not driving and you could
get through."
But what if you are driving and
someone sent you a message?
Well, they can now get an
automatic response saying, "I'll
see your message when I get
where I'm going."
And you can also enable Select
People to break through if it's
especially urgent.
You can have the peace of mind
that you can get contacted and
they can reply urgent and that
message will go through.
We think this is going to be a
real important step in safety in
the car.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Next up, HomeKit.
So HomeKit provides a secure and
private way to automate all of
your devices, your home
accessories and you can do it
right inside the home map and
control them here.
And also, of course, use your
voice with Siri.
Now, almost all of the major
accessory makers are providing
great HomeKit accessories across
all of these categories, from
security cameras and door locks
to lights and fans.
But there's one category really
close to our heart that we
wanted to add to HomeKit.
And that's Speakers.
[ Applause ]
You'll now be able to configure
your speakers inside of HomeKit
and access them via our new
AirPlay 2 protocol.
It builds multi-room audio in
throughout iOS.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
So, you can play music to select
speakers throughout your home
right from the Music app.
And with Apple Music, we have a
new feature called Shared Up
Next.
So if you have a friend over and
you have a playlist going and
maybe your friend wants to
contribute to that playlist,
well they can do that without
interrupting the music.
You all compile into that party
playlist.
Now, the-- all these speaker
makers have announced upcoming
support for AirPlay 2, but, of
course, many of us already own a
great AirPlay 2 compatible
speaker and those are the ones
connected to our Apple TV.
Because now, your Apple TV can
be played to from your iPhone or
iOS device in Mac anywhere in
the home.
And, of course, if you turn on
your Apple TV, it can control
playback homewide including
using Siri.
And we're providing a great
developer API, so third party
audio apps in iOS can all get in
on the multi-room audio fun.
Next is Apple Music.
Now, last fall, we introduced
the all new design for Apple
Music which brought greater
clarity and simplicity to the
Apple Music experience.
We now have 27 million customers
who are really enjoying the
curation as well as the
personalization of Apple Music.
But, of course, a lot of the way
we discover music is to ask one
of our friends, "What have you
been listening to lately?"
So now, in Apple Music, you'll
be able to find out right inside
the application.
[ Applause ]
For all the music served up and
for you, you'll see indicators
if this is the music your
friends are listening to and
they can configure their profile
either to be public or private
and control what playlists they
share or what are all the music
they share they want to make
available to their other
friends.
Now for developers, we're also
providing a new API MusicKit for
Apple Music.
This allows apps full access to
the Apple Music service, both on
device and from your cloud
service.
And you can do a tremendous
amount with this.
Now, Nike has done great
exercise playlists using the
full Apple Music catalog.
With Anchor, anyone can be a DJ
using all 40 million songs.
And Shazam can automatically add
songs to your collection that it
identifies.
But, you know, one of the
biggest stories today for iOS 11
is about the App Store.
Now, to give you the big news
with the App Store, I'd like to
hand it off to Phil Schiller.
Thank you.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thank you, Craig.
Well, good morning everyone.
Let's hear it from the way back
of the room.
Come on. Good morning, everyone.
[ Cheering ]
Yes. I am so excited to be able
to talk to you this morning
about the App Store.
The App Store is turning nine
years old and it is going so
well.
There are 500 million weekly
visitors to the App Store who
come to see your amazing apps
and to download them.
They have now downloaded over
180 billion apps to date.
That's incredible.
That does not include auto
re-downloads and updates.
Amazing. And just recently, we
passed $70 billion paid out to
developers today.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Yes. Thirty percent of that in
the last year alone, the apps
are incredible.
And customers are doing things
with them that none of us have
ever imagined.
Like this.
These are people in Hong Kong
playing Pokemon Go.
Pokemon Go is from Niantic.
It was one of the big hits from
last year and there have been a
lot of big hits last year from
big developers and indie
developers alike.
And together, the developers at
Apple, we've made this the best
app platform in the world.
So thank you.
[ Applause ]
Yes. Thank you for the
incredible apps you make that we
and our customers all love.
It's not by chance that the App
Store has become such a great
place.
From the beginning, we've had
two very important goals, to
make the App Store a trusted and
safe place for users and to make
it a great opportunity for all
developers.
We continue to work really hard
at that.
Over the last year, the team has
done a lot of great things to
make the App Store an even
better store for all of us.
There's many things we can talk
about but I think one stands
head and shoulders above the
rest, faster app review times.
[ Applause ]
Yes. I'm sure you're well aware
that the majority of apps are
all now reviewed in under 24
hours, many in just one to two
hours.
The team is going to keep
working hard at that.
And we have a lot more coming
for the remainder of the year.
I've highlighted a bunch of
things here.
I'll just point out one of them.
You can read some of your
favorite things up there.
A big request in developers is
called phased releases.
Now when you--
>> Woo!
>> Yes, woo for phased releases,
come on.
Phased releases means, when you
submit an app, you can choose if
you want it to be phased over
time so it doesn't hit your
infrastructure all at once and
you can see how customers are
responding to that update.
So it's really great feature for
you to take advantage of.
And there are a lot of things
coming this year but there is
one that is incredibly gigantic.
And that is we're going to do
something that we've never done
before in the nine years of the
App Store.
We're going to completely
redesign it, a brand new App
Store.
[ Applause ]
It is absolutely beautiful.
The App Store starts with a
brand new tab called Today.
Did you remember back the first
time you started downloading
apps when you use the App Store
and it was so much fun to go in
every single day and discover
the new apps that were
appearing?
I mean, that's an amazing
feeling.
And we're bringing that back
again with this brand new tab
called Today, a whole new way to
discover apps.
It's a place where we can
feature the apps we all love and
the stories about the developers
who created them.
It's going to be such a great
place for customers to discover
your apps every single day.
There's another new tab, Games.
Games, the biggest area of the
App Store has its own dedicated
space now.
So for all of us who loves
gaming and finding the best
featured games of the day and
seeing charts about gaming, this
is now a place to go to
experience all that's happening
with games.
And not only can we feature
games, but for the first time in
the App Store, we can feature
in-app purchases as well.
A big part of your business is
now there in the App Store so
the next time you have a brand
new level, you have a brand new
character, customers can see
them right in the App Store and
click on them and start the
process to get them right away.
And since Games have their own
tab, now Apps have their own
tab.
This is everything that we love
about apps besides games with
dedicated features and charts
all there for customers to
enjoy.
And every app and every game, of
course, has its own product page
in the store.
These are more beautiful than
ever, more engaging with
incredible videos.
You're going to love all the
features on your product pages
and there're sessions here at
WWDC to learn how to take
advantage of all those great new
app page features.
These are just some of the new
things in the all new App Store,
the new Today tab, new Games
tab, new Apps tab.
And we'd love to show it to you
live for the very first time.
So please welcome Ann Thai,
Product Marketing Manager for
the App Store to the stage.
Ann.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thanks Phil.
I'm so excited to show you the
new App Store.
So let's get to it.
I'm going to open the store and
I land right here on the Today
tab, the new front of the App
Store that updates every day.
The first thing I see is our top
story, the world premiere of
Monument Valley 2 is finally
here.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Let's check it out by tapping on
the card.
This opens a story view where we
can learn more about the game
and what makes it so great.
It looks like this is going to
be even more beautiful than the
first.
I can watch videos that show me
what the game play is like.
And here's a cool quote from Dan
Gray at Ustwo Games about what
inspired them.
I can share the story with a
friend and what's incredible is
that we can actually all
download this today, only on the
App Store.
[ Applause ]
Let's see what else is happening
today.
What have we got here?
Here's a how to guide about
VSCO.
I use this app all the time.
Let's check it out.
This is packed full of useful
tips.
So even if you have an app
already, you still might learn
something new like I didn't know
you could use it to make
animated GIFs or GIFs.
Anyway, you can make them.
I just scroll back up and pull
down on the card and I'm back in
the feed.
Every day there's a new app of
the day and a new game of the
day and the daily list.
These are great because they're
focused on a theme or a goal
like meditation.
I've actually been trying some
of these out to get ready for
this and it's totally working.
If I'm busy and miss a day, I
can scroll down and see stories
from earlier in the week.
So that's the Today tab.
If I only want to see games, now
I can go to the New Games tab.
This is huge.
Let's check it out.
Up at the top I can see the
biggest new releases or just
what the game editors are
playing this week.
If I scroll down I can watch a
whole bunch of game videos.
And it's not just previews but
also tips and gameplay videos by
editors too.
If I scroll down, I can see
charts that only feature games.
So it's really easy to see what
the most popular games are
separate from apps.
And now I can browse by game
categories too.
This page is just packed full of
recommendations.
This artsy game looks fun.
Let's check it out.
I'm going to tap on the icon and
it opens up a redesigned app
page.
It's more beautiful and more
useful.
I can watch more videos that
show me how fun this is.
And this badge at the top tells
me it was named editor's choice.
If I scroll down, I can see
ratings and reviews front and
center so I can see what other
customers think before making a
choice.
Like this review, it tells me
this game is great for killing
time.
Thanks, FuriousPotatoFace.
For all the incredible apps on
the store there's a new tab too,
the Apps tab.
Let's go there.
It shares the same great design
as the Games tab but with a
focus just on apps.
So that was just the first day
on the new App Store.
Now you can see why we're so
excited to have a beautiful new
place to share apps and games we
love with you.
Back to you, Phil.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Ann.
So that's your first glimpse of
an entirely new App Store.
We hope you love it.
We hope customers love it and
visit it every single day to
download your incredible apps.
And that's it for the App Store.
Back to you, Craig.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Phil.
The App Store looks just
fantastic.
So those are some of the big
features in iOS 11.
But of course, there's also core
technologies.
Now, Metal 2 and HEVC coming to
iOS as well, but there's more
and it starts with machine
learning.
Now, you've seen the way we've
used machine leaning throughout
the experiences on Apple Watch,
for instance, and the predictive
Siri watch face.
We use it on the iPad for palm
rejection when you're writing
with Apple Pencil.
Of course, we use it to extend
your battery life by predicting
how you're going to use your
device.
And you've seen it throughout
photos with memories and face
recognition.
Well now, for all of you
developers, we want to make
powerful machine learning easy
for you to incorporate in your
apps.
And we're doing it via set of
new APIs.
Starts with the vision API which
provides face tracking, face
detection, landmarks, all of
these core features we use
inside of our apps.
And the natural language API
that provides capabilities like
tokenization and named entity
recognition.
Now, these are all built on Core
ML.
And Core ML provides high
performance implementations of
deep neural networks, recurrent
neural networks, convolution
neural networks, support vector
machines.
And they allow you to take
models that you've built with
any of these popular third party
tools.
And using our machine leaning
model converter, execute them
with tremendous performance on
device to give you all the data
privacy benefits and all of the
carefully tuned compatibility
with all of our platforms, and
the performance really is
incredible.
You look at this benchmark
called Inception v3.
It's a popular photo recognition
benchmark.
iPhone is six times faster than
Google Pixel and the Samsung S8
using Core ML.
[ Applause ]
Next, I'd like to turn to AR.
Now, with Multi-Touch, it really
changed the way that you
interact with the world on the
screen of your iPhone.
And with the camera, it allowed
you to capture the world around
you.
But when you bring these things
together, the results can
actually be quite profound.
Now it's called the augmented
reality and we have a new core
technology called ARKit to bring
it to all of you.
And I'd like to show it to you
in a demo now.
[ Applause ]
So, we've all seen a lot of
carefully edited vision videos
on this topic recently, but in
this case I'd like to show you
something for real.
So, what we see here is an
iPhone that's-- look, using its
camera but using computer vision
it's actually able to identify
surfaces such as this table and
I can actually just add an
object.
This is a developer application,
a test application that you'll
all be getting code for that
allows you to do these things.
Now, this is a virtual object on
this table.
Now--
[ Applause ]
Get some steam in there coming
off the cup.
Now I can add other objects to
the scene and these things can
actually interact.
Let's add a lamp and I want you
to watch when I turn the lamp up
on the dynamic shadows here.
I'm going to move the cup and
watch how the shadow moves in
relationship to the light here.
It's really pretty incredible.
Now, I can add additional
objects.
Let's add a vase to the scene.
I mean, isn't that just
incredible?
Well, you guys are actually in
the shot here with these objects
all in augment reality.
So it gives you a little bit of
an idea of the technology
involved.
It's really pretty incredible.
Now, how do we do it?
[ Applause ]
Well, ARKit provides fast and
stable motion tracking and it
uses all of the sensors and the
camera in your device to do
this.
It actually finds planes like
floors and tables.
It's able to estimate ambient
light which helps us with the
rendering and also helps with
scale.
You notice that cup hit the
table looking the size of a cup,
not the size of an elephant.
And we've brought integration to
all kinds of third party
frameworks to help you with your
rendering.
The implementation is possible
because we're able to take
advantage of the awesome
hardware in iOS devices, the
cameras, the high performance
CPU and GPU, and the motion
sensors.
And when you bring the software
together with these devices, we
actually have hundreds of
millions of iPhones and iPads
that are going to be capable of
AR.
And, in fact, that's going to
make overnight ARKit the largest
AR platform in the world.
[ Applause ]
We've had some third parties in
to take a look at ARKit and they
are totally excited and we are
just blown away by what they've
been able to accomplish.
IKEA, of course, is placing
furniture everywhere and it's
really super awesome, but check
this out.
What you can do with Batman
Lego, I mean how fun is this?
Right on the table a Lego with a
live-- Lego Batman, and you can
explode the Lego like you can
never do in the real world, pan
around it and interact with
Batman right there.
It's really awesome.
And then Pokemon GO, we've all
seen it before but check it out
with ARKit.
The Pokemon is so real, he's
right there on the ground.
As the ball bounces, it actually
bounces right there in the real
environment.
It's AR like you've never seen
it before.
Now--
[ Applause ]
There's one of these that I
think you just really need to
see, see live.
Now, Wingnut AR is Director
Peter Jackson's new production
company.
It's dedicated to producing AR
content.
We all know Peter Jackson from
his incredible cinematic work on
movies like The Lord of the
Rings series.
But he's now really excited
about AR.
And to show you what he has in
the works, I'm thrilled to
introduce Wingnut AR's creative
director, Alasdair Coull.
Alasdair.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Craig.
We're really excited to share an
exclusive sneak peek of
something we've been working on.
With the ARKit, you don't need
any special equipment or
tracking markers, it just works.
Dan is here with me for Wingnut
AR, so let's take a look.
Here we're using ARKit to detect
the plane of the table, estimate
its size and lock our content on
the surface.
And since this is augmented
reality, you folks are all in
the shop table.
[ Applause ]
This is all rendered in
real-time using the power of
Unreal Engine 4.
We're in a remote air post in a
desolate world where supplies
are scarce.
Airships come here to refuel,
get repairs and to trade.
These are our townsfolk.
They're expecting some visitors
soon so they're all starting to
get ready for their arrival.
Except for this guy down here
apparently.
Who hired him?
[ Sound Effects ]
That's our airships arriving
now.
And what's really cool here is
that with the ARKit's tracking,
you can get on really close and
choose how to view the action.
It's like you're the director of
your own experience.
Looks like some raiders are
attacking.
[ Sound Effects ]
[ Gunshots ]
[ Music and Noise ]
Oh, I guess that takes care of
that guy.
[ Music and Noise ]
Wouldn't it be cool to have
airship battles like this in
your own living room?
Oh, I think they're going to
regret attacking this air post.
[ Music and Noise ]
And another one down.
And we got him.
Oh, geez. Well, that didn't end
well for anyone.
But our heroes are limping away
to fight another day.
So that's one of the things
we've been up to, Wingnut AR.
And the fact that ARKit-- Thank
you.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
The fact that ARKit enables
hundreds and millions of people
to enjoy experiences like this
opens up so many possibilities.
I think it's a real game
changer.
Look out for an AR experience
from us in the App Store later
this year.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> So what do you think?
[ Applause and Cheering ]
So those are some of the major
features in iOS 11.
Of course, there's much more
than we have time to talk about
today, but I want to highlight
some features of special
interest to our customers in
China, like QR codes that are
integrated right into the main
camera, accessible from the lock
screen, super use-- Yes, super
useful for customers in China.
So that's our update for iOS 11.
I'm going to turn it back to
Tim.
Thank you.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> That's right.
iOS 11 is absolutely jam-packed
with great features and I can't
wait for you to get your hands
on the new App Store and ARKit.
Number five.
An important part of the iOS
story is, of course, iPad.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
iPad has completely changed the
way we work, play, teach, learn
and create.
It's truly a magical piece of
glass that transforms into
anything you want.
We've been pushing the
boundaries on iPad.
And today, we're going to push
them further than ever before.
And to tell you all about it,
I'd like to invite up Joz.
Joz
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thank you, Tim.
And good morning, everybody.
I'm so excited to talk to you
today about iPad Pro.
When we first introduced iPad
Pro just 18 months ago, it
completely redefined what you
could do with your iPad.
Along with your incredible apps,
it allowed our users to do
really amazing things, from
professional design and
illustration to fashion, to
architecture, to engineering and
so much more.
We're really excited about what
can be real in your world today
with iPad Pro.
Well, as you know, there's two
models to iPad Pro today.
There's a 13-inch and a
9.7-inch.
And the 9.7-inch is our most
popular model.
It has a screen large enough to
get your work done, but it's in
a thin and light enough package
that allows you to take it with
you everywhere you go.
Well, today, we're going to
introduce an all new iPad Pro.
It's going to take everything
you love about the 9.7-inch and
give you a whole lot more to
love.
Let's take a look.
This is the new iPad Pro.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
It's the first iPad Pro with a
larger 10 and a half inch Retina
display.
Now, why 10 and a half inch?
Well, for one, it's a lot
larger.
It's 20% larger than a 9.7-inch.
But we are able to reduce the
borders by nearly 40% which
allows us to submit it in this
incredibly compact design that
still weighs just one pound.
And of course, 10.5-inch also
allows us to do some other
things.
It's the perfect size to allow
us to display a full-size
on-screen keyboard.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
It's also the perfect size to
allow us to have a full-size
Smart keyboard as well.
And when we deliver the Smart
keyboard, we're going to have
support for more than 30
languages at launch including
Chinese, and for the very first
time, a Japanese JIS keyboard.
[ Applause ]
Now, iPad Pro has always had the
best displays in the industry.
And both sizes are going to get
really incredible new displays
today.
They're the best displays that
we've ever made.
They're packed with incredible
features like True Tone for
automatic white balance, P3 wide
color gamut for the best color,
ultralow reflectivity, the best
in the industry.
And they're 50% brighter with
600 nits.
And this extra brightness and
the P3 wide color gamut means
that with iOS 11, you'll be able
to display HDR video for the
first time in an iPad for really
immersive cinematic experience.
They're truly awesome displays.
But our biggest breakthrough is
a feature we call ProMotion.
So what is ProMotion?
Well, we were able to take our
unique hardware and software
capabilities and dramatically
improve our display performance.
Now, typically, up until today,
mobile displays have refresh at
60 hertz, means they update the
content 60 times every second.
Well, on the new iPad Pro, we've
doubled that maximum refresh
rate to an incredible 120 hertz.
[ Applause ]
So what does that mean to you?
It means that all of your motion
content on your screen is going
to be smoother, crisper, more
responsive.
Now, this is something you have
to really touch and feel
yourself to appreciate because
our projection systems just
aren't capable of doing those
type of refresh rates.
But I'll tell you the difference
is dramatic.
And when you scroll, it's
buttery smooth.
Now, the higher refresh rate
also means it works even better
with the Apple Pencil.
We already have the
industry-leading performance for
drawing and writing with the
Apple Pencil, but with
ProMotion, it gets even better.
It's more responsive and it
reduces our latency to an
industry best 20 milliseconds.
[ Applause ]
So drawing is incredibly fluid
and even more natural, you're
going to love using the Apple
Pencil of the new iPad Pro.
Another breakthrough of
ProMotion is that these become
the first mobile displays to be
able to dynamically adjust the
refresh rate, depending on what
you're looking at.
This is a really big
breakthrough for both display
quality, as well as for power
savings.
So when you have dash-moving
content, they can update
quickly.
But they can also update slower
when you don't need that type of
refresh rate.
For example, a still image, this
allows us to save a lot of
energy and give you better
battery life.
So, hopefully you see why these
are not just the best displays
that we've ever made, but we
think they're the most advanced
displays in the planet.
Next, let's talk about
performance.
iPad is already best in class
for performance.
But we're not resting on our
laurels.
These are the fastest we've ever
created.
Inside them, they're powered by
the A10X Fusion chip.
The A10X has a six-core CPU,
three high-performance cores,
three high-efficiency cores, all
automatically managed by the
Apple performance controller.
It also has a 12-core GPU.
This is a powerhouse.
And it delivers 30% faster CPU
performance over our already
industry leading A9X and 40%
faster graphics performance.
[ Applause ]
Our chip team has done just an
amazing job over the years with
the performance improvements and
results have been staggering.
They're delivering an
industry-leading graphics
performance that's more than 500
times the original iPad from
just a few years ago.
But of course, numbers only tell
part of the story.
To demonstrate the real-world
performance of the A10X in the
new iPad Pro, I'd like to invite
Ash Hewson of Serif to give you
a demo of their new Pro photo
editing app called Affinity
Photo.
Ash.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Joz.
So I'm thrilled today to be able
to show you the iPad version of
Affinity Photo.
This is a truly high-end
professional photo editing tool.
And on this latest iPad Pro, we
can achieve levels of
performance which is simply
unattainable on any other
device.
And I'm going to try and show
you that today by creating a
movie poster.
I've already set up a few
layers.
I've kind of got this great
background of some stormy sky.
I've got a turbulent sea and
this ship.
Now, the first thing you'll
notice when you're using this is
as you're kind of moving layers
around, rotating them or even
just sort of panning and zooming
around your work, I'm seeing all
of these now at 120 frames a
second.
So it just feels incredibly
smooth.
But when you come to edit
layers, because of Metal, we can
achieve performance more than
four times than i7 quad core
desktop PC.
And I'll show you what that
means.
On this sea, I'm going to apply
a 12 filter.
And look, just with my finger, I
can kind of push this sea
around, or I can even just like
flick away right over the side
of the ship.
It's a totally new way to kind
of interact with your designs.
And actually, everything is this
fast.
So let's-- So I wanted to set
this ship on fire, for example.
I've got this fire up all here.
I can move this over the back of
the ship.
But to make that look more
realistic, I need to apply blend
mode.
Now normally, blend modes is
something that takes a lot of
trial and error.
But now, look at this.
So I can just scrub down here
and I'll get an instant preview
of all the different blend
modes.
So it makes it really, really
easy to select the right blend
modes that I want.
Now of course, everything I've
done so far, I've done using
touch.
But with iPad Pro, we have the
best stylus that's ever been
made.
And we can do some great stuff
with Apple Pencil, too.
A really good example of that is
our lighting filter.
So here, I'll choose lighting,
and make that a bit bigger.
And look, I can actually control
now the angle and the tilt of
that light using Apple Pencil.
There's no latency, whatsoever.
So it's a really immersive way
to work.
Now, I said at the start, I was
creating a movie poster.
And in fact, what I'm actually
doing is creating a pirate movie
poster.
So now, I need a pirate.
And I've got Captain Jack
Sparrow here.
But at the moment, of course,
he's on the wrong background.
So what I need to do is cut him
out.
And I'm going to use some
selection tool to do that.
So, to start with, I'm just
going to do-- and you can see
how quick it is to do a really
quick selection with pencil to
sort of snap around the edges.
But of course, with selections,
what often happens is you need
to do a much more accurate
selection around hair.
And to do that, we're going to
do a selection refinement.
This is something that takes a
huge amount of CPU power, but on
this latest iPad, it's twice as
fast as ever before.
And you can see pretty much
instantly, I'll get a selection
down to individual strands of
hair.
[ Applause ]
And that's it, that's my poster
complete, a professional looking
poster created on a device that
I can hold in my hands.
It's really incredible.
I really think that iPad Pro,
alongside Affinity Photo, is a
truly game-changing experience
for professional photo editing.
And the best thing of all is
that you can now experience it
now, because I'm delighted to
announce that Affinity Photo for
iPad is available on the App
Store from today.
Thank you.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Wow. Thank you, Ash.
That's amazing performance,
again, especially for a device
that's so thin and light in a
simple one-pound package you
could take with you everywhere
you go.
And what's also cool is despite
all this performance to new,
iPad Pro still delivers the same
all day 10-hour battery life
that our iPad users love.
Next, let's talk about cameras.
The new iPad Pro features the
latest camera system from our
iPhone 7.
That means the same high
performance 12 megapixel sensor
with optical image
stabilization.
And it has the ability to even
capture and, of course, edit 4K
video on the go.
They're absolutely fantastic
cameras.
The front-facing cameras from
the iPhone 7 as well got all
these great features, like wide
color gamut capture, auto image
stabilization and the entire
display can light up to become
the world's brightest and
largest Retina flash.
We have great accessories as
well.
The iPad Pro supports USB 3,
which means that you're going to
get faster transfers with your
USB and SD camera adapters.
And this also-- We also support
fast charging, means any of our
USB-C charge adapters will now
allow you to charge at half the
time.
And we have great new Smart
covers we have available in
polyurethane and then we're
bringing back the popular
leather as well.
And then we've designed an all
new leather sleeve with a
built-in storage for your Apple
Pencil.
So that's the new iPad Pro
family, a line-up with the
world's most advanced displays
including a brand new 10 and a
half inch size and incredibly
compact design, powerful new
A10X Fusion chip, incredible new
cameras.
And of course as you would
expect, we make all this in
incredibly environmentally
friendly ways.
We're also going to double the
amount of memory that comes at
the beginning of these
configurations.
Both sizes will now start with
64 gigabytes of memory.
[ Applause ]
And the 10 and a half inch with
64 gigs will now be at $649 and
it's just $150 more to move up
to the bigger display at $799.
We're also going to have
configurations in 256 and 512
gigabytes, half a terabyte of
storage in an iPad.
And as always, you can get any
of these models with LTE as
well.
So this is the new iPad Pro.
You can order them today.
They'll start shipping next
week.
And of course because they're
shipping now, they're going to
ship with iOS 10 but you'll be
able to easily update to iOS 11
as a free update this fall.
But you haven't heard the full
iOS 11 story yet as relates to
iPad.
So I'd like to invite Craig back
to the stage to tell you about
some incredible iPad features
coming on iOS 11.
>> Thank you.
Hey, everybody.
[ Applause ]
Yes, there is more iOS 11.
If you love iPad like I do,
well, buckle up for -- You're in
for a wild ride.
We are taking iOS to the next
level.
This is the largest iOS release
for iPad we've ever done.
Now, it starts with the dock.
Now we all know that dock
hovering down there at the
bottom of the screen, it is more
powerful than ever.
You can fill it with apps.
On the right there's a
predictive area, figures out
what you're going to use next
including your continuity apps.
And now you can summon the dock
from anywhere right from the
bottom of the screen and use it
for switching apps just like
that.
And what's incredible is how
it's used for multitasking.
So now if you're in an app and
you swipe up, we can pull an app
out just like that into Slide
Over.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now of course you can snap your
apps into Split View, but what's
really cool is the new app
switcher, because it preserves
all of your spaces with your app
pairings.
It's really great.
Now, the iPad of course is the
ultimate multi-handed,
multi-touch device and so we're
so excited to bring drag and
drop to iPad.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
You can drag images, you can
drag text, you can drag URLs,
you can multi-select and
multi-hand drag, it's a drag
fast.
Now, it's incredibly productive.
But of course sometimes you have
to type and so we made the
keyboard even more productive as
well.
You can now flick on keys to
access punctuation and numbers
all without switching planes.
It's super fast and super easy.
[ Applause ]
Now, we have a new app to
introduce to you today, and it's
called Files.
[ Applause ]
Files brings together all your
files in your iPad.
It supports everything you'd
expect, nested folders,
spring-loading, list view,
favorites, search, tags and it
has this beautiful Recents view
that pulls it all together
across all of your sources.
Because it supports not only
iCloud, it also supports third
party storage providers like
Box, Dropbox, OneDrive and
Google Drive.
And they're all right here in
your sidebar.
You know what, let's do a demo.
>> All right.
[ Applause ]
Let's take our first look at iOS
11 on iPad.
So here we have our new dock at
the bottom.
Now I can easily drag right into
the dock just like this.
It's a great way to launch apps
as always.
But now it's also a great way to
switch apps.
Just tap like that.
Now, if I want to multitask,
check this out, drag it out,
it's right there.
Now I can slide it off the
screen.
I can now slide it over here.
Both these views are completely
live.
I can go into Split View just
like this.
But I want you to check out the
new app switcher.
I'm just going to swipe for up
from the bottom and keep
swiping, goes back like that.
Let's do that again, that is so
great.
It's that easy.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now you notice my spaces are
preserved.
So over here on the left I have
mail in Safari.
In Split View I can just tap
those open like this.
Let's try some drag and drop.
So I'm going to drag the URL
from the top of Safari here
right into this mail message.
Drag it and drop it.
Now I can drag it, yup.
Let's drag an image.
Yup, just like that.
Now, I want to focus just on
mail, because I'm going to show
you dragging across spaces.
So let's go in to Photos.
I have some great photos here of
some potential drone protection
options for the new campus.
So I'm going to start to drag.
But watch this, with my other
hand I'm going to tap.
I can add to this selection just
like that.
And I can even swipe up with my
other hand in the multitasking,
move over to mail and drop.
[ Applause ]
Now I want to show you files.
I can bring up files of course
right from the dock and Split
View just like this.
And it's a great way to deal
with attachments because I can
take this attachment and this
mail message, pick it up and
just drop it right into this
folder of top secret projects.
[ Applause ]
Now let's dive all the way in
and take a closer look at the
Files app.
We see it has this gorgeous grid
view but it also has a list view
that provides me all the details
about my files.
I can sort them by size or let's
sort by date.
Now I can create new folders.
So let's say I want to create an
R&D folder right here.
I'm going to take some of my top
secret perspective projects and
I can do multi-select just like
this, drop them in.
Now I can also take the folder,
drag it right in to my
Favorites.
And these are synced across all
of my devices.
And if I want to tag a file, of
course I just drag it right on
there and make that one
important.
And you notice in addition to
iCloud here on the left, I have
access to all my cloud providers
like Box, so you can see I have
files here I'm using and folders
that I'm using for
collaboration.
And that includes this drone
defense proposal right here,
presentation.
And I want to show you when I go
into the Recents view from the
tab at the bottom, notice again
I view across everything
including that one inside the
Box.
I'm going to tap into that
keynote presentation and for my
final act, I want to show you
how I can use files directly
from the dock, just swipe up.
If I tap and hold, I get access
to my recent assets.
I can just pick this up, drop it
down just like that.
And that is a quick demo of our
productivity features on iPad.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Now, next I want to talk about
Apple Pencil, because Apple
Pencil has really created a
whole new way of working on
iPad.
And with iOS 11, we've
integrated it deeply into the
system.
Now it starts with markup,
because you can mark up anything
you can Quick Look.
You can take Safari content,
recreate it into a continuous
scrolling view that you can mark
up.
And you can actually do this
with any app that supports
printing, because we have a
create PDF option that will
create a markup PDF, it's a
really great way to mark up
anything and share it.
We know, a lot of people do like
to share with screenshots, and
so now when you take a
screenshot, we'll create a
thumbnail down in the bottom of
the screen.
If you tap it, you go instantly
in the markup, you can mark it
up right there and share it.
Now, we've all-- It's really
cool.
[ Applause ]
Now, we've also integrated
Pencil deeply into Notes.
So if you're working on a note
and later you're at the lock
screen, you want to get back,
just a tap of the pencil to lock
screen and your right back into
your note.
And we've made your note
handwritten text searchable.
So we can now search handwriting
and we use deep learning to
recognize what you write.
And if you're doing primarily
typed notes, you can now also do
inline drawings, right there.
It's very handy.
[ Applause ]
Now of course, sometimes we
still have to deal with paper,
so Notes now has a built-in
document scanner.
It can correct perspective and
contrast.
And when you bring the note in,
you can mark it up, write with
your pencil.
[ Applause ]
And we've integrated markup in
the mail as well so you can
personalize your mail messages
with the inline drawings.
Now, for a look at all of these
great new Pencil features, I'd
like to introduce the man who
heads iPad software engineering
for us, Toby Paterson, for a
live demo.
Toby.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Good morning.
[ Applause ]
Well, the first thing I want to
show you is a quick way of
getting to your notes using your
Apple Pencil.
You just tap on the lock screen
like this and it slides up to
reveal your notes beneath it.
Now you can see here I've got a
handwritten note and I want to
show you how easy it is to
create one of these.
Watch at the top of the note
here as I edit the title.
Just by putting the pencil down
and writing like this, after the
2017 keynote.
It's as natural as putting
pencil to paper.
Now something paper can't help
you with is finding your notes
again later.
We're using machine learning to
recognize your handwriting and
index it in Spotlight.
Let's switch into Spotlight now
and we'll search for that text
that I just wrote down.
You can see here I've got the
new flick keyboard which makes
it really easy to enter numbers
just by swiping down on the keys
like this.
And you can see there it's
already found my note as the top
hit even with my atrocious
handwriting.
We'll just tap on that and we're
back with the note.
[ Applause ]
Now, I'm going to switch to a
different note now, because I
want to show you how you can mix
drawing with typed text and
tables and all of the notes'
other great features.
This is a note that my young
daughter shared with me as part
of a school assignment where she
had to work with her parents to
develop an idea for a new app.
Now, she asked me how many
copies of our app I thought I
might sell-- We might sell.
And so, I want to quickly draw a
graph to give her some idea of
that.
I'm just going to press down
here with the pencil to make
some space for my drawing and
then we can take that little
grabber and open up some more
room.
Now, I am really bad at drawing
but I just love doing it.
And what's great about drawing
on the iPad is it works the same
way as it does with paper.
And that means it's really easy
for me to draw really badly
right here.
Watch. I'm just going to put the
pencil down and just like that,
zoom.
It's so simple, and I think
you're going to have a lot of
fun rediscovering the joy of
drawing.
But let's move on now.
So, my daughter's learned a few
things from me about how Apple
works.
And before I left this morning,
she gave me an NDA to sign.
I'm going to use the new
document scanner notes and my
pencil to take care of that in a
snap.
We'll just tap the plus button
here to bring up the document
scanner and all I need to do is
point the camera at the piece of
paper.
Notes will take the picture
automatically, even straighten
the page up.
We'll open it up full screen
here and I just fill in the
blanks with my pencil.
And just like that, I've got a
signed copy of the NDA saved
away in my notes.
Now I see my daughter sent me a
message and it must be pretty
important if she's interrupting
my demo.
So if you'll excuse me, I'm just
going to tap on that and see
what she has to say.
Wow, an offer for $100 million
is really pretty thrilling.
I need to send this to my wife
right away.
I'm going to take a screenshot
of this and then we'll tap on
the thumbnail here to open up
our new screenshot editing UI.
From here, I can crop it down to
just the part of the image that
I want to send.
I can scribble a quick note with
my pencil, and then I can bring
up the share sheet to send it
off to my wife right away.
So these are just a few of the
ways you can use your pencil
with your iPad in iOS 11.
Back to you now, Craig.
Thank you.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> It is so great when your
grade school child gets $100
million of funding.
They just-- They do grow up so
fast these days.
Well, so these are some of the
great new features for the iPad
and of course they're joined by
all of these other features you
heard from earlier today.
We're really excited about what
we're doing with iPad this year,
and really excited about iOS 11.
Now iOS 11 is available to all
of you, developers, today.
And if you sign up at
beta.apple.com, you can get a
beta at the end of the month and
we're making it available as a
free upgrade to everyone in the
fall, supports all of these
devices.
That is your update for iOS 11.
I'm going to turn it back over
to Tim.
Thank you.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> That's right.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
iOS 11 really takes iPad to a
whole new level.
People are going to be able to
do more in more places than ever
before.
We are so excited about the
marriage of iOS 11 and the new
iPad Pro that we made a video
and I'd love to run it for you.
[ Alarm Ringing ]
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
I hope you're as excited about
the new iPad Pro and iOS 11 as
we are.
Now, we've got one last thing to
talk to you about.
Let's turn our attention to
music.
Music has always been a part of
Apple's DNA.
We first revolutionized the
music industry with iTunes.
Then we forever changed the way
people listen to music on the go
with the iPod.
And today, iPhone has become the
best portable music player in
the world and it's even better
when it's paired with Apple
Music.
You now have 40 million songs in
your pocket.
And when you add AirPods, it
brings an absolutely magical
experience to wireless audio.
Now, so we have such a great
portable music experience.
But what about our homes?
We think we can do a lot to make
this experience much better.
Just like we did with portable
music, we want to reinvent home
music.
And I'd like to invite Phil up
to tell you all about it.
Phil.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thank you.
This is really exciting, the
chance to reinvent the way we
enjoy music in the home.
I can't think of anything that
matters more to so many of us.
Why hasn't this happened yet?
There certainly are a lot of
companies hard at work making
products to enjoy music in our
home.
But none of them have quite
nailed it yet.
Some have worked hard to make
wireless music sound good around
our homes, but these aren't
smart speakers.
Others have worked to make smart
speakers that you can talk to,
but they don't sound so great
when you listen to music.
We want to combine all these in
a product that can really
deliver a breakthrough
experience.
And our team has been hard at
work for many years now on a
breakthrough home speaker.
And it has to do a few things
really great if it's going to be
a great breakthrough speaker.
First, it needs to rock the
house, right?
We need to enjoy our music,
whatever genre you love, really
low or really loud, free from
distortion.
Second, it needs to be spatially
aware.
It's going to fit in different
rooms in our house and it needs
to be smart enough to know what
to do to make the music sound
great.
Third, it has to be really fun
to use.
It has to have a built-in
musicologist, an expert on music
who can help us to hear the
music we love or discover music
we're going to love.
Now we're working on this
speaker for later this year, but
we want to give you, 6000 of our
closest friends, a sneak peek at
it this morning.
And here it is.
[ Music ]
[ Applause and Cheering ]
It is absolutely beautiful and
we call it HomePod.
Yes.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
Just like iPod reinvented music
in our pockets, HomePod is going
to reinvent music in our homes.
So let's talk about these
features.
First, rock the house.
The HomePod is just under 7
inches tall.
It's covered in a seamless 3D
mesh fabric that has incredible
acoustic properties, and it
hides within it amazing audio
technology.
For example, along the bottom is
a 7 array beam-formed tweeter
pack that's packed with seven
tweeters, each with their own
individual driver.
They're precision acoustic horns
that drive the audio from within
and then out along the bottom
with tremendous directional
control.
And that will become really
clear in a bit as we talk about
how it works.
It has a really big woofer,
4-inch woofer upward facing with
a large motor to move a lot of
air.
It has automatic bass
equalization and dynamic
software modeling so that as we
turn the volume up, it's free
from distortion.
And all of this is controlled by
an Apple A8 chip.
Yes, the same chip that powers
the inside of our iPhone is
inside HomePod.
It's perhaps the biggest brain
ever in a speaker, and it does
some incredible things.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
It has real-time acoustic
modeling, audio beam-forming,
and multi-channel echo
cancellation.
You don't have to know any of
that, is just know that it
sounds incredible.
Next, we talk about this spatial
awareness.
Well, what does that mean?
Well, you plug in your HomePod
to AC and it gets its music
wirelessly.
And it's compact enough that you
can put it mostly anywhere in
your house.
You can put it on a table, on a
shelf, against the wall, in a
corner and it intelligently and
automatically detects the spaces
within.
And it uses that information to
adjust the audio, to balance it,
and take full advantage of the
environment and create a very
spacious sound.
Now, we want to give you a sense
of what that experience is like.
So we want to play some music in
this room and show you a visual
simulation to give you an
understanding of some of the
technologies it's using and how
it's adopting them to make
incredible sound, on this
compact speaker.
So I'm going to start by playing
an audio track and it will be a
full mix and then I'm going to
break it down to some of the
components that the HomePod
controls.
[ Music ]
So that's a full rich audio mix
but within it, HomePod detects
the center vocals and can use
beam-forming to direct that.
[ Music ]
It gives incredible clarity and
precision.
And then it can detect something
called direct energy with the
instrumentation and direct that
in the room as well.
[ Music ]
In addition to that direct
energy, there's something that's
usually missing in music,
ambient audio, the backing
vocals and reverb.
[ Music ]
HomePod can direct all of these
and pull it together to a full
rich mix that fills up your
room.
[ Music ]
[ Applause and Cheering ]
It's a really remarkable
experience to hear this kind of
a spacious sound come from such
a compact speaker.
And if you love one, you should
see what it's like when you set
up two and they automatically
work together to give this
incredible spacious sound that
really has the power to rock
your house.
Next, a musicologist.
This intelligent helper to help
us discover the music we love.
HomePod has an incredible
speaker system that works
together with our Apple Music
subscription.
From the beginning, it's
designed to work with that.
Now, Apple Music as you know
provides music in the cloud and
if the speaker can get it
directly from the cloud, it can
get 40 million tracks, two
million artists, tens of
thousands of playlists.
But not just any music library,
this is your music library.
It knows the playlists you've
set up, it knows the artist you
love and all of them stream
directly to your HomePod.
It works with an array of six
microphones around the middle,
so as you talk to it and you say
those magic words, "Hey Siri,"
you see a waveform light up on
top and now it can respond to
your commands and help serve up
the music you want to hear.
The Siri team has worked very
hard to adapt the domain of
music in Siri to be even greater
and understand more of the
questions we're going to ask
about music.
Simple things obviously like
Play Beats 1 Radio.
We all want to do that.
Or play "I'm Poppy".
Check it out if you don't know
what that's about.
Play something new.
Who's singing on this track?
Something I ask all the time.
Who's playing drums on this
track?
To complex questions like, what
was the top song on May 5th,
2016.
You just play more like that or
I like that song.
It's a free form.
Siri doesn't need a specific
list of commands.
It can interpret what you're
saying and help you discover the
music you love.
And even better, you don't have
to just sit next to the HomePod
to talk to it.
It can be across the room and
speak to the HomePod even while
loud music is playing and the
speaker array and the
microphones can pick it up and
hear what you're saying.
So HomePod, it has the power to
rock the house in a spatial
awareness so that it understands
the rooms we place it within.
And it has the fun interactivity
of Siri becoming a musicologist
and helping us to listen to the
music we love.
And since Siri is built in there
and you can speak to it, well,
the team has also worked hard to
make it a great and helpful home
assistant as well.
We said the domain of music is
something Siri knows really well
in HomePod.
There are other domains as well.
We've worked hard to pick the
first ones that we think matter
most in a product like HomePod,
so of course, it can play your
podcasts.
But it can also do things like
give you news, give you weather,
traffic, sports.
You can ask it to set a
reminder, set a timer, text
someone with messages.
And if you have HomeKit devices
set up in your home, you can
speak to your HomePod and
control your HomeKit devices.
So for example, for the HomePod
set up, you can say, "When do
the Red Sox play next?"
They're going to beat the
Yankees, trust me.
Tune to NPR instead, flip a
coin, remind me to bring snacks
to a party.
You can set up reminders, check
all the sports news and weather,
all directly with your voice,
talk to a HomePod that gets the
information directly from the
cloud.
And if you have HomeKit devices
set up, you can say simple
things like, are the lights on,
turn the heat up, turn on the
air conditioning, bring the
shades down halfway, turn off
the lights in the bedroom.
And if you've set up scenes in
HomeKit you can control those as
well.
You can say, "I'm home.
It's movie time.
I'm leaving now."
And the whole scene can
automatically happen just by
talking to your HomePod.
And because there is a HomePod
base-- the HomeKit base built
into HomePod, that means
anywhere in the world, once you
set up your first HomePod, you
control your HomeKit devices
remotely using the built-in Home
app on your iPhone or iPad.
Now, setting up a HomePod and
its microphone array in your
home, you probably have a
question that we've worked
really hard to deal with, which
is privacy.
Our team cares deeply about your
privacy.
So for example, it has that
magic phrase, hey Siri.
Until you say it, nothing is
being sent to Apple.
It recognizes when you do say it
and from that point it sends an
anonymous Siri ID in order to
help you with the command you're
looking for.
And of course that communication
is all encrypted.
So this is the HomePod.
It's a breakthrough home
speaker.
Typically Wi-Fi speakers, if
they're a good quality, of $300
to $500.
And a smart speaker might cost
you $100 to $200.
So it's not unreasonable for a
HomePod to be priced in the
range of $400 to $700.
So we're really excited to tell
you that HomePod is going to be
priced for $349.
[ Applause ]
It comes in white and space
gray.
It'll start shipping this
December, first in the US, UK,
and Australia.
And then next year we'll start
bringing it around the world.
So that's HomePod.
Back to you, Tim.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
>> Thank you.
It is so cool.
We really believe it's going to
take your home music experience
to the next level.
Now, it's been an incredible
morning.
We've shared with you lots of
things this morning and all of
them are shipping this year,
some now, some in the fall, and
others at the end of the year.
We got started with watchOS,
more intuitive and intelligent
than ever before, incredible new
features to help us live a
healthier life.
macOS High Sierra, great
refinements in technology that
will push the macOS experience
forward.
Updates to MacBook, MacBook Pro
and iMac, faster and more
capable than ever before.
And iOS 11, a major update of
the world's best and most
advanced mobile operating
system, absolutely jam-packed
with new features including a
completely new App Store,
peer-to-peer payments in Apple
Pay.
And with ARKit, iOS 11 becomes
the world's largest augmented
reality platform overnight.
iPad is taken to a whole new
level with incredible iPad
features in iOS 11.
It's the biggest release for
iPad ever.
And of course a new line up of
iPad Pro with an all new perfect
10.5-inch size with advanced
displays, powerful new features
that enable people to do more
with their iPads than ever
before.
And we gave you two sneak peaks,
iMac Pro, an entirely new
workstation class of products
that we design specifically for
our Pro users.
And the HomePod, a breakthrough
home speaker with amazing sound
and incredible intelligence.
It will reinvent home audio.
Now, we have a hands-on area for
the press set up to attend
immediately after the keynote.
And for all developers, we
welcome you to come by from 4 to
7 p.m. this evening.
We've got over a hundred
sessions planned for you this
week, and over a thousand Apple
engineers here to spend time
with you, so take advantage of
the time.
Tomorrow we've got a special
fireside chat planned in the
morning in this room.
And someone will be joining us
that's devoted her entire career
to highlighting and encouraging
young people, women and doers.
I'm very excited to tell you
that Michelle Obama will join
us.
[ Applause ]
She'll be joining us for the
open session in this room
tomorrow and she'll be talking
about empowering people from all
walks of life to change the
world.
This is a very special treat and
I encourage everyone to come.
I hope everyone here has a
fantastic week.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]