The ClockKit
framework allows you to display
your app’s data
on the watch face.
These areas are called
complications.
Complications are a great way
to connect people
to their favorite apps
with every wrist raise
and keep them informed
throughout their day.
Complications can also be tapped
for quick access into the app.
With Apple Watch Series 4,
we’re adding new complication
capabilities to ClockKit,
which allow you to create
engaging,
full-color complications
for the new Infograph
and Infograph Modular
watch faces.
On the Infograph watch face,
these new complications
can extend
into the corners
of the incredible new display.
On the Infograph Modular
watch face,
you can now present
even more of your app’s
information in full-color,
right in the middle
of the watch face.
Complications are divided
into families.
These determine how information
is presented onscreen.
On Apple Watch Series 4,
we’ve added four new families:
Graphic Corner,
Graphic Circular,
Graphic Bezel,
and Graphic Rectangular.
Each complication family uses
system-defined templates
to determine how the information
is laid out,
like the Graphic Circular family
seen here.
There are many templates
for you to choose from
to display your data.
The complication family
templates each consist
of different combinations
of data provider classes
from the ClockKit framework,
from text to images
to the all-new gauges.
For the Infograph and Infograph
Modular watch faces,
we’ve added
a new full-color image provider
and a new gauge provider.
Let’s learn about these.
First is the all-new
gauge provider.
Gauge providers allow you
to show progress completed
or a value within a range
to the user in different ways,
depending on the complication
template family you are using.
You can also use
a time interval gauge
to automatically animate
the values as they change,
as you see here
with the timer complication.
With gauge providers,
you can provide a single color
or you can provide a gradient,
specifying the gradient colors
along the gauge.
You can also specify
whether the color or gradient
will fill the gauge
as the data progresses
or if it’s a range and uses
a ring to indicate the value.
Next, we have image providers.
Image providers allow you
to display a tintable image
or a one-color image for use
on existing watch faces,
and now on the Infograph and
Infograph Modular watch faces,
full color images.
Finally, we have text providers,
which allow you to use text
throughout the various
templates.
They can be used
to display text,
dates, time, time ranges,
and even automatic countdowns
or count-ups between two dates
or times.
In a handful of complication
family templates,
you can also now use multiple
text providers together,
each with their own tint color,
to make one
multi-purpose string.
This can be really useful
if your app has
specific branding
for different pieces of data.
Now that you’re familiar
with the gauge,
image, and text providers,
let’s look at the new graphic
complication family templates
available on the Infograph and
Infograph Modular watch faces
and learn how to combine
providers to display your data
in different ways.
The first new complication
family template
is the Graphic Corner.
This is available for use
on the Infograph watch face.
This template curves along
the corner of the display
to allow for more content
like never before.
The Graphic Corner templates
have a handful
of different combinations
of providers to use.
You can use a gauge provider
with text,
a gauge provider with an image,
a set of text providers,
a text provider with an image.
And finally, you can use
a full-color image by itself.
Now, for consistency
with other corner complications,
it’s recommended
that you use providers
that will curve
around the display.
OK, let’s look at a code example
of how to create
a graphic corner complication
that uses a gauge provider
with text.
Let’s make something similar
to the Weather app.
First, we’ll need to work
with our designer
to get some values
for the text tint colors.
In this example,
we have text showing our high,
low, and current temperatures.
We will also need an array
of values
for which colors
will make up the gradient.
Here, we’re going to use
three colors.
One for the low,
one for the middle of the range,
and one for the high.
watchOS will take care
of the gradient between colors,
so the only additional
information we need to provide
is an array of values to express
where each color should
be located along the gauge.
Now that we have
all of our values,
we need to create our graphic
corner complication template.
We’re going to create
a corner complication
with a gauge provider
and text provider,
so we create an instance of the
GraphicCornerGaugeText template.
Once we’ve created
our template instance,
we need to create
the providers for it,
starting with
the gauge provider.
Here we’re using
CLKSimpleGaugeProvider.
The style can be a ring,
which displays a ring
around the value in the gauge,
or a fill, if you’re wanting
to fill the progress
within the gauge.
Here we’ll use the ring style.
Next, we set our gauge colors
to the gradient colors
we created earlier,
as well as the gauge color
locations,
which will define where
the colors are along our gauge.
Finally, we need to set
the fill fraction.
This sets the current value
for the gauge
and should be dynamic,
depending on your data.
Next, we set the gauge provider
property of the corner template
and set the various
text providers for the template,
which we created earlier in code
with tint colors for each.
All that’s left is to pass in
the completed template
to create a timeline entry.
This looks great.
You can see our gradient
between colors
is handled by the system,
and our ring-style
gauge provider
centers in the ring
on our current value.
Next, let’s look at
the graphic circular
complication family templates
available on both the Infograph
and Infograph Modular
watch faces.
The Graphic Circular templates
provide the ability
to combine gauge providers
with text providers
to show an open gauge
with values
at the end of a range.
You can also create a template
with text
below the center text value
with an open gauge,
as well as use a full-color
image provider
below the center text
with an open gauge.
Using a closed gauge,
you can provide
a full-color image
inside of the gauge or text.
And finally, you can use
a full-color image
to represent the entire area
of the complication.
In our previous example,
we created a graphic
corner complication
representing weather data.
Now, let’s take that same data
and create a graphic
circular complication
using an open gauge
with text.
The text providers,
gradient colors,
and gradient color locations
we're going to use
are the same as we used
in the graphic
corner complication.
The main difference
is that we need to instantiate
the graphic circular open gauge
range text template.
We will create the gauge
provider as we did last time.
One additional change
is that we will set
the center text provider
property for the template,
where on the graphic
circular template,
this was an outer text provider.
And that’s all.
Now we have our graphic
circular complication.
But there’s more that we can do
with a graphic circular
complication.
On the Infograph watch face,
there is another family called
Graphic Bezel.
This utilizes a graphic
circular complication
and adds a text provider to it
to wrap the text
within the time bezel.
First, we start by creating
a graphic circular template.
In this example,
we’ll use the one
we just created
in our last example.
Once the graphic circular
template is configured,
we create an instance of
the GraphicBezelCircularText
template.
This takes a configured
graphic circular template
and a text provider
for the bezel text.
Here, we’re just hardcoding
some values for the example.
Finally, you need to pass
in the configured bezel template
for the complication
timeline entry.
Here’s our completed
Graphic Bezel complication.
The text will automatically
curve along the bezel
and display as uppercase.
The bezel text can fill
nearly 180 degrees
of the bezel
before it is truncated.
The final addition
to our complication families
is the Graphic Rectangular,
which is available on the
Infograph Modular watch face.
This family has templates
allowing you to create
a full-color image that fills
the middle of the watch face.
This template also includes
a text provider.
This image should be
highly visual
and not rely on text
to convey the information shown.
The graphic rectangular
templates also allow
for a more traditional
configuration,
utilizing multiple
text providers.
Additionally, an image can be
used beside the header text
and you can also use a template
that displays a gauge provider
instead of a third line of text.
This is great
to communicate progress.
Let’s create a graphic
rectangular complication
that provides a header text
and a big full-color image
below it.
First, we need to instantiate
our graphic rectangular
large image template.
The next step is to create
a text provider
with our header text.
Again, this can be
a text provider
that is made up
of multiple text providers.
Finally, we create
a full-color image provider
with an image of our data.
Some key points to keep in mind
as you create complications
for the new Infograph and
Infograph Modular watch faces
are that the update
opportunities remain the same.
You have 50 guaranteed
complication push updates
every 24 hours,
as well as the possibility
of an update each hour
if your app is taking advantage
of background app refresh
or is in the most
recently used apps
on the person’s Apple Watch.
As you take advantage
of the graphic circular
and graphic
rectangular families,
be aware that there are
potential CPU
and update time thresholds
while you get your data,
process it,
and render images,
so do this work quickly.
For full-color image providers,
use the accessibility
label property to provide
meaningful information
to people using VoiceOver.
This is especially important
for graphic circular templates
using only an image,
as there will be
no accompanying text,
as well as for
the graphic rectangular
large image template,
which allows for a lot of data
to be represented.
For more information
on creating
the new graphic complications
using the ClockKit framework,
please visit the Apple developer
documentation
at developer.apple.com.
The watchOS Sketch
and Photoshop resources
in the Human Interface
Guidelines
have also been updated
for Apple Watch Series 4
and watchOS 5.
In addition,
the size specifications
for each of the templates
in the Graphic complication
families are shown here
and can also be found in
the Human Interface Guidelines
at developer.apple.com.