Hello, my name is Michael Ford
and I'm an engineer
on the CloudKit team.
Today we're going to talk
about GDPR and CloudKit.
GDPR stands for General Data
Protection Regulation.
It's a European Union regulation
that went into effect
on May 25th, 2018.
The regulation focuses on
giving users visibility into,
and control over,
their personal data
and how companies use it.
At Apple, we value user privacy,
and we want to make sure
that developers
have the tools they need
to build great applications
while protecting
their user's privacy.
During this talk, we'll discuss
new and existing CloudKit APIs
that you can use
to fulfill user requests
related to GDPR
or other regulations.
If you're interested in
a broader privacy discussion,
take a look at the "Better Apps
through Better Privacy" session
from WWDC 2018.
Now, you might ask,
"Why are we only talking
about CloudKit APIs?"
Let's talk through some
of the iCloud syncing services
that are available
for developers to use,
and you will soon see why.
As a developer, you can save
user data to iCloud
using iCloud Backup,
Key Value Store,
iCloud Drive, and CloudKit.
Let's talk through
their data isolation,
data interaction,
and API availabilities.
For Backup, Key Value,
and iCloud Drive,
data is always stored
for a single user.
CloudKit offers developers
a more flexible API,
where you can share data
between users,
or make data available
to all users.
When a user initiates
an iCloud Backup restore,
application data that was saved
is automatically restored.
Application data saved to
Key Value Store and iCloud Drive
are automatically synced
between all of the devices
where the user is signed in
to their iCloud account.
In contrast, data that your
application saves to CloudKit
is not automatically mirrored
to another device.
You can use the
Fetch Changes APIs or Query APIs
to access all or part of
the data stored in CloudKit.
Backup, Key Value,
and Drive APIs
are only available on device.
You can use Objective-C
or Swift versions
of the CloudKit APIs on device,
or you can use
the CloudKit web services
to access CloudKit data
from a browser.
As you can see,
CloudKit is unique.
It's more flexible and there are
more ways to interact with it.
When fulfilling GDPR requests
for data saved to iCloud Backup,
Key Value Store,
or iCloud Drive,
you can treat the data
like other data
that your application
has stored locally.
However, with CloudKit,
you may need to interact
with the server to complete
the GDPR request.
Now, as we talk
about GDPR more,
I want you to remember that
I am an engineer, not a lawyer.
If you have questions
about GDPR compliance,
you should consult a lawyer.
That said, let's get into
some of the user rights
guaranteed by GDPR.
GDPR guarantees users
the right to know
what data is stored about them
and how it is being used.
A user has the right to access
data stored about them.
They have the right
to export data.
A user can request that
processing of their data
be paused.
They can request that
their data be deleted.
This is commonly known as
the right to be forgotten.
If the data about
a user is incorrect,
the user should be able
to update it.
Users can also object
to how their data is used.
Examples include
objecting to direct marketing,
or objecting to processing
a user's data
for scientific research.
Finally, a user should have
access to human intervention
if automated decision making
may legally or materially
impact the user.
Now, that's quite a list.
Today, we're going to focus
on those rights
that are broadly applicable
to developers using CloudKit.
This will not be a comprehensive
talk about GDPR compliance.
Instead, we'll focus
on how to use new and existing
CloudKit APIs
to fulfill user requests
related to GDPR
or other regulations.
Let's first review some of
the concepts inside of CloudKit.
At the highest level
is a CloudKit container.
You can have multiple
applications interact
with the same
CloudKit container.
Inside of a CloudKit container,
there are three types
of databases.
A private database,
a shared database,
and a public database.
There is one public database
per container.
By default, all users
can read and write data
in the public database.
Every user has their own private
and shared database
in a container.
Data in the private database
belongs to that user.
If your application
supports sharing,
when a user accepts
a sharing invitation,
data becomes visible
in their shared database.
This is a reference back
to the owner's private database,
where the actual data resides.
Inside of a given database,
you can have multiple zones.
In a private database
and a public database,
there is always
a default zone.
And in a private database,
you can create
multiple custom zones.
In the shared database,
zones show up as you accept
a sharing invitation.
Inside of a zone are records.
This is where you store
the actual data.
To summarize the conceptual
hierarchy of CloudKit,
you first have a container.
Then, there are three
different types of databases.
In a database, you can have
one or more zones,
depending on the type
of database.
Finally, records are where
the data is stored.
Now that we've reviewed
those core CloudKit concepts,
we're ready to focus on
the individual GDPR rights.
We'll look at access
and portability together.
To fulfill these rights,
you'll need to fetch data
from CloudKit.
For deletion, you'll need
to delete data from CloudKit.
And for restriction,
you will apply a restriction
to an account in your
CloudKit contianer.
For access and portability
requests,
you should provide
visibility into the data
that is saved inside of CloudKit
for the user.
You should also provide
a way to export the user's data
in a standard format.
If you are exporting an image,
it would make sense to use
a JPEG file format.
For general structured data,
use either JSON or CSV,
depending on the type
and amount of data.
You've just exported data.
While there's no requirement
to import data,
you may gain some users
if you do.
If you have already synced
all of the data locally,
you can just fulfill the GDPR
access or portability request
from the data
you've saved locally.
In case you haven't,
you'll need to fetch the data
from the CloudKit server.
So how do you fetch
all of the data from CloudKit?
Inside of
the CloudKit hierarchy,
for every container,
for every database,
you should fetch all zones,
and then query for all records.
Let's review some of the code
for how you would do that.
First, let's set up
our container
and database variables.
In this case, we'll focus on
the private database.
Next, we'll fetch all of the
zones inside of the database.
We'll iterate through
all of those zones
and set up a query.
You'll notice that this query is
only for a single record type,
so you may need to run
multiple queries.
You could loop through all of
the record types that you have,
or enumerate them individually.
We'll pass an NSPredicate to
the query that is always true,
so that we get
all of the records
of a given record type.
Then we'll actually perform
the query in the database.
Finally, once the query returns,
you should display the records,
or save them for export.
I just showed you code
to query for all of the records
in the private database.
Shared databases and public
databases are more complex.
For a participant, a shared
database is a partial view
into the owner's
private database.
Remember that the data
belongs to the owner,
so you should only
return the data
if it relates
to the participant.
The same is true
of the public database.
By default, any user
can read or write data
into the public database.
Again, you should only return
data that relates to the user
making the GDPR request.
Deletion is forever.
You should make sure
that the user
really wants to delete
their data en masse.
You may want to offer
a restriction as an alternative.
If the user confirms that
they want to delete their data,
you'll need to delete all of
the user's data from CloudKit.
Let's look at the code
for that now.
Once again,
we'll set up the container
and database variables.
We'll focus on
the private database.
Again, we'll fetch all of the
zones inside of the database.
Now, we're going to pull
the zoneID
from the individual zones
and use them
to create a deletion operation.
This deletion operation passes
in the record zoneIDs
that you want to delete.
Finally, we perform the deletion
operation against the database.
We just saw code to delete
all of the zones
inside of the private database.
Once again, if your
application supports sharing,
be selective, but this time
be selective in what you delete.
Deleting records in the shared
database deletes them
for the owner and all other
participants in the share.
If there is data that should be
expunged in this way,
perform the record deletions
before deleting the zones.
Once that's complete,
delete all of the zones in
the user's shared database.
In contrast to deleting
individual records,
this will not delete the data
for the owner,
or the other participants
in the share.
In fact, a zone deletion
in the shared database
changes the user from being
a participant in the share
to being in
an invited state.
This means that
they no longer see the zones
in the shared database.
Finally, in the public database,
you'll need to review the data
that you're storing
related to a given user
and determine which data
is appropriate to delete.
Finally, let's talk about
restriction.
In effect, this is a way
to pause or un-pause processing
on a user's data.
Under GDPR, you may need
to pause processing
when the user invokes
another right.
Or in some cases,
the user may request
that you restrict their data
rather than delete it.
We've exposed two new web
service APIs that you can use
to restrict or un-restrict
an account.
You can invoke these web service
APIs from any version of iOS,
provided you have
the appropriate credentials.
Let's talk through the code
to restrict a user now.
First, you'll need to generate
an API token
in the CloudKit dashboard.
Once you have the API token,
you can create
a fetchAuthorization operation.
The fetchAuthorization API
was first released in iOS 9.2.
With both the apiToken
and the webToken,
you have everything you need
to make
the web service restrict call.
We've wrapped that in
a restrict helper function,
and we'll take a look
at that now.
First, you'll need
to URL encode the webToken.
Create the full web service URL
by combining a baseURL,
apiPath, and query parameters.
Once you've done that,
you should actually
send the request
as an HTTP post
to the CloudKit server.
We won't go through
the code for that now,
but you can find it in our
linked documentation.
Once you restrict a user,
any operation against
that container will result in
a managedAccountRestricted
error.
You will also see this error
if the user has
restricted their iCloud
account through Apple.
Apple will stop processing
the user's data
and will return this error
for any CloudKit request,
so be sure to handle
this error in your code.
To review,
for access and portability,
return all data inside
of the user's private database.
For shared databases
and the public databases,
be discerning
when determining
which data
to return to the user.
To respond to
a user deletion request,
you can delete all of the data
inside of user's
private database.
You can also delete
shared zones,
which removes the user
as a participant.
For the public database,
be discerning when determing
which data to delete.
Finally, we introduced
new web service APIs
to restrict
or un-restrict accounts.
You will see a
managedAccountRestricted error
if you restrict the user,
or if the user has requested
that Apple restrict processing
across their iCloud account.
With these tools, we know
that you can build great privacy
into your apps.
For more information, please
visit developer.apple.com,
and feel free to email
cloudkit@apple.com
with any questions
or feedback you may have.